<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-03-23">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
March 23, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               
               
               
               
               
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 7</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">March 23–June 9, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1991</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">6-9</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">279-280</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">200-201</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jw">Joseph Whitehouse</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 11</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of Joseph Whitehouse, May 14, 1804–April 2, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1997</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">430-433</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
         <geoDecl datum="WGS" xml:id="lc.geo.1806-03-23.01">
            <placeName/>
            <geo>46.1811 -123.7395</geo>
            <note>Camped just below the mouth of John Day River, the captains' Kekemarque Creek, Clatsop County, OR.</note>
         </geoDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Journal Entries</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-09-23</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1806-03-23">March 23, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-03-23.01" n="lc.geo.1806-03-23.01">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Sunday March 23rd 1806.</hi>
                     <ref target="n31032301" n="1"/>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
Half after 9 A. M. <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name> arrived, having killed one Elk but so distant that we could not send for the meat and get arround <name type="place" key="Tongue Point (Point William)">Point William</name>
                  <ref target="n31032302" n="2"/> today, we therefore prefered seting out and depending on <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name> and the hunters<ref target="n31032303" n="3"/> we have sent forward for meat.    the wind is pretty high but it seems to be the common opinion that we can pass <name type="place" key="Tongue Point (Point William)">point William</name>.    we accordingly distributed the baggage and directed the canoes to be launched and loaded for our departure.—    at 1 P.M. we bid a final adieu to <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name>.    we had not proceeded more than a mile before we met <name type="person" key="Delashelwilt">Delashelwilt</name> and a party of 20 <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinnooks</name> men and women.<ref target="n31032304" n="4"/>    this Cheif leaning that we were in want of a canoe some days past, had brought us one for sale, but being already supplyed we did not purchase it.<ref target="n31032305" n="5"/>    I obtained one Sea Otter<ref target="n31032306" n="6"/> skin from this party.    at a ¼ before three we had passed <name type="person" key="Youngs (Meriwether's) Bay">Meriwethers bay</name>
                  <ref target="n31032307" n="7"/> and commenced coasting the difficult shore; at ½ after five we doubled <name type="place" key="Tongue Point (Point William)">point William</name>, and at 7 arrived in the mouth of a small creek<ref target="n31032308" n="8"/> where we found our hunters.    they had killed 2 Elk,<ref target="n31032309" n="9"/> at the distance of a mile &amp; ½.    it was too late to send after it this evening.    we therefore encamped on the Stard side of the Creek.    the wind was not very hard.—
</p>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <p>The Expedition's Route, March 23–June 9, 1806</p>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-03-23.02" n="lc.geo.1806-03-23.01">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Sunday 23rd March 1806</hi>
                     <ref target="n31032310" n="10"/>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
This morning proved So raney and uncertain that we were undeturmined for Some time whether we had best Set out &amp; risque the [river?] which appeared to be riseing or not.    <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Jo. Colter</name> returned haveing killed an Elk about 3 miles towards <name type="place" key="Point Adams">Point Adams</name>.    the rained Seased and it became fair about Meridean, at which time we loaded our Canoes &amp; at 1 P. M. left <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name> on our homeward bound journey.    at this place we had wintered and remained from the 7th of Decr. 1805 to this day and have lived as well as we had any right to expect, and we can Say that we were never one day without 3 meals of Some kind a day either pore Elk meat or roots, not withstanding the repeeted fall of rain which has fallen almost Constantly Since we passed the <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">long narrows</name> on the [<hi rend="italic">blank</hi>] of Novr. last<ref target="n31032311" n="11"/>    indeed w[e] have had only [<hi rend="italic">blank</hi>] days fair weather since that time. Soon after we had Set out from <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name> we were met by <name type="person" key="Delashelwilt">De lash el wilt</name> &amp; 8 men of the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinnooks</name>, and <name type="person" key="Delashelwilt">Delashelwilt</name>s wife the old boud and his Six Girls, they had, a Canoe, a Sea otter Skin, Dried fish and hats for Sale, we purchased a Sea otter Skin, and proceeded on, thro' <name type="place" key="Youngs (Meriwether's) Bay">Meriwethers Bay</name>, there was a Stiff breese from the S. W. which raised Considerable Swells around <name type="place" key="Smith Point">Meriwethers point</name>
                  <ref target="n31032312" n="12"/> which was as much as our Canoes Could ride.    above <name type="place" key="Tongue Point (Point William)">point William</name> we came too at the Camp of <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name> &amp; the <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph and Reubin">2 Field's</name>.    they had killed 2 Elk which was about 1½ miles distant.    here we Encampd. for the night having made 16 miles.

</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-03-23.03" n="lc.geo.1806-03-23.01">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Sunday 23rd March 1806.<ref target="n31032313" n="13"/>    the one hunter stayed out last night rained hard the greater part of last night.<ref target="n31032314" n="14"/>   this morning proved so rainy and uncertain that our officers were undetermined for Some time whether they had best Set out &amp; risque the [wind?] which appeared to be riseing or not. <name type="person" key="Colter, John">John Colter</name> returned having killed an Elk about 3 miles towards <name type="place" key="Point Adams">point adams</name>.<ref target="n31032315" n="15"/>    the rain Seased and it became fair about meridian at which time we loaded our canoes &amp; at 1 P. M. left <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name> on our homeward bound journey.    at this place we had wintered and remained from the 7th of Decr. 1805 to this day, and have lived as well as we had any right to expect, and we can Say that we were never one day without 3 meals of Some kind a day, either poor Elk meat or roots, notwithstanding the reputed fall of rain which has fallen almost continualy Since we passed the <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">long narrows</name> on the [<hi rend="italic">blank</hi>] of Novr last, indeed we have had only [<hi rend="italic">blank</hi>] days fair weather Since that time. Soon after we had set out from <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">fort Clatsop</name> we were met by a party of the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinooks</name>,<ref target="n31032316" n="16"/> the old baud and hir Six Girls, they had a canoe, a Sea otter Skin dryed fish &amp; hats for Sale.    we purchased a Sea otter and proceeded on thro <name type="place" key="Youngs (Meriwether's) Bay">Meriwethers Bay</name>.    their was a stiff breeze from the S. W. which raised considerable Swells around <name type="place" key="Smith Point">Merewethers Point</name>,<ref target="n31032317" n="17"/> which was as much as our canoes could ride    above <name type="place" key="Tongue Point (Point William)">point william</name> we came too at the Camp of <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">G. Drewyer</name> &amp; the <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph and Reubin">2 Fields</name>    they had killed 2 Elk which was about 1½ mile distant.    here we Encamped<ref target="n31032318" n="18"/> for the night, having made 16 miles.—


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-03-23.04" n="lc.geo.1806-03-23.01">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Sunday 23d.</hi>    There was a cloudy wet morning.— The hunter<ref target="n31032319" n="19"/> who remained out last night, came in early, and had killed an elk. We were employed this forenoon in dividing and packing up our loading; and distributing it among the canoes, which were five in number, three large and two small. At noon, we put it on board; and at 1 o'clock, left <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">fort Clatsop</name>. The afternoon was fair. We proceeded round <name type="place" key="Tongue Point (Point William)">Point William</name>, went about 19 miles, and encamped at the mouth of a creek, where we found the three hunters<ref target="n31032320" n="20"/> that had been sent on a-head, and who had killed two elk about a mile and an half distant.



</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-03-23.05" n="lc.geo.1806-03-23.01">
            <sp who="jw">
               <speaker>Whitehouse</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Sunday March 23d    It rained very hard, during the whole of last night.    One of our hunters did not return to the fort during that time; This morning it still continued raining, &amp; the Weather appeared very uncertain.    Our Officers were undetermined, whether they would set out, on our homeward bound Voyage; or not.    About 9 o'Clock A. M., the hunter that had staid out during last night, returned to the Fort; he had killed one Elk, which he mention'd, he had left about 3 Miles from the Fort, towards <name type="place" key="Point Adams">Point Adams</name>.    About 12 o'Clock A. M. it ceased raining; &amp; the weather became Clear &amp; pleasant, &amp; we loaded our Canoes, &amp; got every thing in readiness to ascend the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>.    We have been at <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name> from the 7th day of December last past; and our party had lived as well, 〈as they〉 as could be expected, &amp; can say that they never were, without 3 Meals each day, of some kind of food, either Elk meat, Roots, fish &amp;ca. notwithstanding the repeated rainey Weather; which fell (with a few days intermission) ever since, we passed the <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">long Narrows of Columbia River</name>; which was the 2nd of November last past.—    <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name> is situated on the South side of <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>, and about 1½ Miles up a small River (which empties itself into the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>) called by the Natives <name type="place" key="Lewis and Clark (Fort, Netul) River">Ne-tul</name>, and lay a small distance back, from the West bank of said River.    The fort was built in the form of an oblong Square, &amp; the front of it facing the River, was picketed in, &amp; had a Gate on the North &amp; one on the South side of it.    The distance from the head waters of the <name type="place"
                        key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">So fork of the Columbia River; (〈or〉 Kiomenum or Lewis's River</name>), to <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">fort Clatsop</name> is 994 Miles, (this being the fork which we descended) &amp; from the Mouth of the <name type="place" key="Dubois River">River de Bois</name> 4134 Miles, the place from whence we took our departure, 〈&amp; in〉 Latitude 46° 19' 11 1/10S North, The <name type="place" key="Columbia River">River Columbia</name> at its mouth also, lay:    in Latitude 46° 19' 11 1/10S North, &amp; Longitude 124° 57' 0 1/10S West from Greenwich; &amp; is 21 Miles wide from <name type="place" key="Cape Disappointment">Cape disappointment</name> on the No side, to <name type="place" key="Point Adams">Point Adams</name> on So. side of the River; which is where the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name> enters into the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Western or pacific Ocean</name>.    the Tide rises &amp; falls, about 8 feet at the small River, 〈on〉 near which was built <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name>.    We have been 60 Miles from <name type="place" key="Cape Disappointment">Cape disappointment</name> (Where the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chin-ook</name> Indian village lays) which is on the No. side of the River &amp; or its entrance into the Ocean to the No. North West.    The two points, <name type="place" key="Cape Disappointment">Cape disappointment</name>, &amp; <name type="place" key="Point Adams">point Adams</name>; lay nearly opposite to each other, &amp; about 10 Miles below <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">fort Clatsop</name>    The distance that we have went to the Mouth of <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>; from the <name type="place" key="Dubois River">River du Bois</name>, from whence we took our departure is 4,144 Miles, <name type="place" key="Point Adams">fort Adams</name> being the extreme So point, &amp; lay near to where our party made Salt.—    We found that Bands of the <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">flatt head</name> Nation of Indians;  are far more numerous that we expected; they extending from the head waters of the <name type="place"
                        key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Ki-o-me-num River</name>, to the Mouth of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>; &amp; to the head of all the Rivers, which runs into the No. fork of <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>; &amp; to the head of the same.    This information we received from numbers of Indians belonging to the different bands of that Nation.—    They are called <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">flatt heads</name> from the custom they have among them, of binding flatt pieces of wood, on the foreheads, &amp; back parts of the heads of their Children, when 
born, which occasions their foreheads &amp; back part of their heads to be flatt.—    End of first Volume.<ref target="n31032321" n="21"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Sunday March 23d<ref target="n31032322" n="22"/>    At 1 o'Clock P. M. we embarked, on board our Canoes from <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name>, on our homeward bound Voyage.    We proceeded on up the South side of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>, when we were met by a party of the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chin-ook</name> tribe of Indians,<ref target="n31032323" n="23"/> who belong to the <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Flatt head</name> nation.    These Indians were in Canoes, &amp; were on their way to <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name> in Order to trade with us; they had with them a Canoe &amp; a Sea Otter Skin, which they Intended trading with us.    We halted a short time, &amp; <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Lewis</name> purchased the Sea Otter skin from them.    We then continued on our Voyage, and went round a point of land called by our officers <name type="place" key="Smith Point">Merryweather point</name> (the Sirname of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Lewis</name>) when the wind rose &amp; blew hard from the South West, &amp; the waves ran very high.    We proceeded on, &amp; passed another point of land called <name type="place" key="Tongue Point (Point William)">point William</name> by our officers the Sirname of <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain Clark</name>.    We halted a short distance above this last point, at a Camp where the two hunters<ref target="n31032324" n="24"/> that were sent on ahead of us were.    These two hunters had killed 2 Elk, which they informed us lay 1½ Miles from this place.    We encamped at that place having come 16 Miles this day.—


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n31032301" n="1">The party departs for home on this date. Since they were traveling over country already traversed on the westward journey, they did not record the detailed courses and distances characteristic of earlier writing. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> indicates on March 26 that they relied at first on their estimated mileages from the previous year in calculating distance on the return up the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>. Some days only one or neither of the men gives mileages for the day, and when both do there are sometimes discrepancies, which are not themselves consistent.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31032302" n="2">Present <name type="place" key="Tongue Point (Point William)">Tongue Point</name>, <name type="place" key="Clatsop County, Oreg.">Clatsop County</name>, <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31032303" n="3">The <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph and Reubin">Field brothers, Joseph and Reubin</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31032304" n="4">His name is Chinookan <hi rend="italic">[i]tla<seg n="u353">š</seg>
                  <seg n="uxu803">x̣</seg>ilwilt,</hi> meaning unknown. See <ref n="1806-03-15" type="related">March 15, 1806</ref>. The Chinook Indians are discussed at <ref n="1805-11-15" type="related">November 15, 1805</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31032305" n="5">They were already supplied because they had stolen a canoe on <ref n="1806-03-18" type="related">March 18, 1806</ref>. See <ref n="1806-03-17" type="related">March 17</ref> and further reference to this canoe on <ref n="1806-03-24" type="related">March 24</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31032306" n="6">Sea otter, <hi rend="italic">Enhydra lutris.</hi>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="n31032307" n="7">Now <name type="place" key="Youngs (Meriwether's) Bay">Youngs Bay</name>, <name type="place" key="Clatsop County, Oreg.">Clatsop County</name>. See <ref n="1805-11-29" type="related">November 29, 1805</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31032308" n="8">
               <name type="place" key="John Day (Kekemarque) River (Clatsop County, Oreg.)">"Ke ke mar que Creek"</name> on <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 82; present <name type="place" key="John Day (Kekemarque) River (Clatsop County, Oreg.)">John Day River</name> in <name type="place" key="Clatsop County, Oreg.">Clatsop County</name>. See note at <ref n="1805-11-27" type="related">November 27, 1805</ref>. They camped just below the mouth of the stream and east of their camp of the previous November before selecting the <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name> site. The night's campsite was close to the <name type="place" key="Ivy Station site">Ivy Station archaeological site</name>, where occupation began around 1,300 years ago and continued into historic times. Minor (ASCR).</note>
            <note xml:id="n31032309" n="9">Elk, or more properly, wapiti, <hi rend="italic">Cervus elaphus.</hi>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="n31032310" n="10">Only one line at the end of this entry is carried over to a page that is otherwise blank.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31032311" n="11">In fact, they passed the <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">Long Narrows</name>, part of <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The Dalles of the Columbia River</name>, on <ref n="1805-10-25" type="related">October 25, 1805</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31032312" n="12">Presumably <name type="place" key="Smith Point">Smith Point</name>, the present location of <name type="place" key="Astoria, Oreg.">Astoria</name>, <name type="place" key="Clatsop County, Oreg.">Clatsop County</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31032313" n="13">From this point to the end of this notebook <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway's</name> writing gets smaller and he adds
more lines to each page.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31032314" n="14">From this point to the end of the entry <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> copies <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> nearly word for word.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31032315" n="15">
               <name type="place" key="Point Adams">Point Adams</name> at the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>, <name type="place" key="Clatsop County, Oreg.">Clatsop County</name>, <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31032316" n="16">
               <name type="person" key="Delashelwilt">Delashelwilt</name>, his wife, and her train.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31032317" n="17">
               <name type="place" key="Astoria, Oreg.">Astoria</name>, <name type="place" key="Clatsop County, Oreg.">Clatsop County</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31032318" n="18">Just below the mouth of <name type="place" key="John Day (Kekemarque) River (Clatsop County, Oreg.)">John Day River</name>, the captains' <name type="place" key="John Day (Kekemarque) River (Clatsop County, Oreg.)">Kekemarque Creek</name>, <name type="place" key="Clatsop County, Oreg.">Clatsop
County</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31032319" n="19">
               <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31032320" n="20">
               <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name> and the <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph and Reubin">Field brothers</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31032321" n="21">In this notebook there are several remaining pages, so the note could refer to the end 
of a volume in the original journal. It could be also that the copyist sees a new beginning with the party's departure from <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name> this day.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31032322" n="22">Here begins another portion of the fair copy of <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse's</name> journal. It is introduced 
by the following words: "Volume 2nd Journal of a Voyage from <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name>, on the <name type="place" key="Lewis and Clark (Fort, Netul) River">River Netul</name>, one of the Rivers that empties itself into the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>, across the Continent of North America, to <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">Saint Louis</name> in the Territory of <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name>; under the direction of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captains Merryweather Lewis</name>, &amp; <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark</name>, &amp; patronized by the Government of the United States by <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Joseph Whitehouse</name>."</note>
            <note xml:id="n31032323" n="23">Including <name type="person" key="Delashelwilt">Delashelwilt</name> and "the old baud and hir Six girls," as <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> puts it.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31032324" n="24">Actually three, <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name> and the <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph and Reubin">Field brothers</name>.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-1806.winter.part3" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-03-24" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
