<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-02-18">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
February 18, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               
               
               
               
               
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 6</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">November 2, 1805–March 22, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1990</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">325-328</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">272</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">193</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jw">Joseph Whitehouse</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 11</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of Joseph Whitehouse, May 14, 1804–April 2, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1997</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">421</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Journal Entries</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-08-26</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1806-02-18">February 18, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-02-18.01" n="">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Tuesday February 18th 1806.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
This morning we dispatched a party to the <name type="place" key="Saltmaking Camp (Oreg.)">Saltworks</name> with <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Sergt. Ordway</name>    and a second with Sergt. <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name> after the Elk killed over the Netul. in the evening <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Sergt. Ordway</name> returned and reported that the waves ran so high in the bay that he could not pass to the entrance of the creek<ref target="n28021801" n="1"/> which we had directed him to assend with the canoe. <name type="person" key="Collins, John">Collins</name> and <name type="person" key="Windsor, Richard">Winsor</name> returned this evening with one deer which they had killed.    the deer are poor and their flesh by no means as good as that of the Elk which is also poor but appears to be geting better than some weeks past.—    in the forenoon we were visited by eight <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clasops</name> and <name type="place" key="Chinook Indians">Chinnooks</name> from whom we purchased a Sea Otter's skin and two hats made of waytape and white ceder bark.    they remained untill late in the evening and departed for their village.    these people are not readily obstructed by waves in their canoes.— <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Sergt. Ordway</name> brought me a specemine of a species of pine<ref target="n28021802" n="2"/> peculiar to the swamps and marshes frequently overflown by the tide as this is a distinct species I shall call it No. 7.    this tree seldom rises to a greater hight than 35 feet and is from 2½ to 4 feet in diameter; the stem is simple branching diffuse and proliferous.    the bark the same with that of No. 1 only reather more rugged.    the leaf is acerose, 2/10th of an inch in width and ¾ in length.    they are firm stif and somewhat accuminated, ending in a short pointed hard tendril, gibbous, thickly scattered on all sides of the bough but rispect the three upper sides only.    those which have there insersion on the underside incline sidewise with their points upwards giving the leaf the figure of a sythe.    the others are perpendicular or pointing upwards.    is sessile growing as in No. 1 from small triangular pedestals of a soft spungy elastic bark.    the under disk of these leaves or that which grows nearest towards the base of the bough is a deep glossey green while the upper or opposite side is of a mealy whiteish pale green; in this rispect differing from almost all leaves.    the boughs retain their leaves as far back as to the sixth years growth.    the peculiarity of the bud scales observed in No 1 is observed in this species. The cone is 3½ inhes in length and 3 in circumpherence, of an ovate figure being thickest in the middle and tapering in two obtuse points. it is composes of small, flexible, thin, obtusely pointed smooth and redish brown imbricated scales.    each scale covering two small winged seeds and being itself covered in the center by a small thin inferior scale accutely pointed.    the cone is somewhat of this figure.<ref target="n28021803" n="3"/>    they proceede from the side as well as the extremities of the bough but in the former case always at or near the commencement of some one years growth which is some instances are as far back as the third year.—
</p>
               <p>
                  <figure rend="aps">
                     <p>Pine Cone (Sitka spruce, <hi rend="italic">Picea sitchensis</hi>),<lb/>
February 18, 1806, Codex J, p. 83
<bibl>
                           <orgName>(American Philosophical Society library, </orgName>
                           <note place="inline"> used with permission.)</note>
                        </bibl>
                     </p>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-02-18.02" n="">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Tuesday February 18th 1806</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
This morning we dispatched a party to the <name type="place" key="Saltmaking Camp (Oreg.)">Salt works</name> with <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Sergt. Ordway</name>.    and a Second party with Sergt. <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name> after the Eight Elk killed over the <name type="place" key="Lewis and Clark (Fort, Netul) River">Netul</name>.    in the evening <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Sergt. Ordway</name> returned and reported that the waves ran So high in the Bay that he could not pass to the enterance of a Creek which we had directed him to assend with the Canoe. <name type="person" key="Collins, John">Collins</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Windsor, Richard">Windsir</name> returned this evening with one Deer which they had Killed.    the deer are pore and their flesh by no means a[s] good as that of the Elk which is also poore but appears to be getting better than Some weeks past.    in the forenoon we were visited by a <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsop</name> &amp; Seven <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinnooks</name> from whome I purchased a Sea otter's Skin and two hats made of way tape and Silk grass and white cedar bark.    they remained untill late in the evening and departed for their village.    those people are not readily obstructed by waves in their Canoes.    Since their departure we have discovered that they have Stole an ax.— <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse</name> brought me a roab which he purchased of the Indians formed of three Skins of the <hi rend="italic">Tiger Cat,</hi>
                  <ref target="n28021804" n="4"/> this Cat differs from any which I have ever Seen.    it is found on the borders of the plains and the woody Country lying along <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">the Pacific Ocian</name>.    this animale is about the Size or reather larger than the wild Cat of our Countrey and is much the Same in form, agility and ferosity.    the colour of the back, neck and Sides, is a redish brown irrigular varigated with Small Spots of dark brown    the tail is about two inches long nearly white except the extremity which is black; it termonates abruptly as if it has been cut off.    the belly is white with Small black spots.    butifully varigated.    the legs are of the Same Colour with the Sides and back marked with transvers stripes of black    the ears are black on the outer Side Covered with fine black hair, Short except at the upper point which is furnished with a pencil of verry fine Streight black hair, ¾ of an inch in length, the fur of this animale is long and fine.    much more So than the wild Cat of the U States but less so than the Louserva of the N West.<ref target="n28021805" n="5"/>    the nativs of this Country make great use of the skins of this Cat, to form the robes which they wear; three whole Skins is the complement usually employed, and Sometimes four in each roab. Those Cats are not marked alike maney of them have but fiew Spots of a darker Colour, particularly on the Back.

</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-02-18.03" n="">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Tuesday 18th Feby. 1806. I and five more of the party Set out with a canoe for the <name type="place" key="Saltmaking Camp (Oreg.)">Salt works</name>.    10 more set out for the Elk meat.<ref target="n28021806" n="6"/>    we found the wind so high at the bay that we had to return to the Fort.    had Several Squawls of wind &amp; rain.


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-02-18.04" n="">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Tuesday 18th.</hi>    The morning of this day was cloudy. A sergeant<ref target="n28021807" n="7"/> and six men set out to go to the <name type="place" key="Saltmaking Camp (Oreg.)">salt works</name>, to bring the salt and kettles to the fort. At the same time I started with ten more to bring in meat; but the weather was so stormy, we could not get round the bay, and we all returned to the fort.


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-02-18.05" n="">
            <sp who="jw">
               <speaker>Whitehouse</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Tuesday Febry. 18th<ref target="n28021808" n="8"/>    This morning clear &amp; pleasant weather, Six of our Men<ref target="n28021809" n="9"/> went from the fort with 2 Canoes to go round on the Sea coast to the 
<name type="place" key="Saltmaking Camp (Oreg.)">Salt works</name>.    Ten Men of our party was sent at some time, in order to bring in the Elk meat, which was left by our hunters Yesterday.    The party that were going to the <name type="place" key="Saltmaking Camp (Oreg.)">Salt Camp</name> on arriving at the bay, found the wind blowing so hard, that they had to return to the fort.—</p>
               <p>
We had several squalls of wind attended with rain in the course of this day.—    About noon several Indians belonging to the <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsop</name> Nation came in Canoes to the Fort.    They brought with them some Roots to trade with us,—,    which we purchased of them.    Towards evening these Indians left 
the Fort &amp; embarked in their Canoes in order to return to their Village.—    Two of our hunters<ref target="n28021810" n="10"/> also returned to the Fort, but had killed no Game of any kind.    The Men remaining at the fort were employed as usual in dressing Skins &amp;ca.—




</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n28021801" n="1">Again, probably the <name type="place" key="Skipanon River">Skipanon River</name>, <name type="place" key="Clatsop County, Oreg.">Clatsop County</name>, <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>. According to <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, his party consisted of five men. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> maps 82, 84.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28021802" n="2">Sitka spruce, already described by <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> on <ref n="1806-02-04" type="related">February 4, 1806</ref>. The small stature, and enhanced, whitish stomatal bands on the upper surface, which led <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> to believe that this was a new species, probably resulted from the brackish tidal inundation in its marsh habitat as described. All morphological features including the drawing of the pointed conescale bract correspond to those of Sitka spruce. There is a vertical line running through the first several lines of this passage, perhaps set down by <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28021803" n="3">A sketch of the Sitka spruce cone (fig. 40; cf. fig. 31) appears here in Lewis's Codex J. p. 83.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28021804" n="4">The first description of the Oregon bobcat.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28021805" n="5">The wild cat is presumably the bobcat, <hi rend="italic">Lynx rufus.</hi> "Louserva" (<hi rend="italic">loup cervier</hi>) is the Canada lynx.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28021806" n="6">Led by <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name>, as he reports.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28021807" n="7">
               <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, who like <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name>, found the waves so high that he could not enter the <name type="place" key="Skipanon River">Skipanon
River</name> on the first leg of his trip, and so returned to the fort.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28021808" n="8">At this point a page has been cut from the notebook, but apparently no text is missing.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28021809" n="9">Led by <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>. <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse</name> says he was with <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> the next day when he tried again, 
but it is not clear that he was along this day, also.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28021810" n="10">
               <name type="person" key="Collins, John">Collins</name> and <name type="person" key="Windsor, Richard">Windsor</name>, report the captains, who say that, in fact, they brought in 
one deer.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-02-17" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-02-19" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
