<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.introduction.v02">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">Introduction to Volume 2</title>
            <title type="sub">August 30, 1803-August 24, 1804</title>
            <author>Gary E. Moulton</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               
               
               
               
               
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 2</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">August 30, 1803–August 24, 1804</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1986</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">59-61</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Journal Editorial</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-03-01</date>
            <date/>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>
            <name/>Initial creation Transcribed</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="main">Introduction to Volume 2<lb/>
Pittsburgh, <name type="place" key="Pennsylvania">Pennsylvania</name> to 
Vermillion River, South Dakota</head>
         <head type="sub">August 30, 1803–August 24, 1804</head>
         <div type="introduction">
            <p>

On August 31, 1803, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name> left <name type="place" key="Pittsburgh, Pa.">Pittsburgh</name> in his newly completed keelboat, heading down the <name type="place" key="Ohio River">Ohio</name> with perhaps eleven men. Impeded by low water, he took nearly a month to reach <name type="place" key="Cincinnati, Ohio">Cincinnati</name>. About October 15 he reached <name type="place" key="Clarksville, Ind.">Clarksville</name>, <name type="place" key="Indiana Territory">Indiana Territory</name>, just below the Falls of the <name type="place" key="Ohio River">Ohio</name>, where <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark</name> awaited him. There they gained several recruits, chiefly young <name type="place" key="Kentucky">Kentucky</name> woodsmen gathered in by <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, and <name type="person" key="York">York</name>, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> black slave. Leaving <name type="place" key="Clarksville, Ind.">Clarksville</name> on October 26, they recruited two or three men at <name type="place" key="Fort Massac (Ill.)">Fort Massac</name> (present <name type="place" key="Illinois">Illinois</name>) on November 11 and 12, including hunter and interpreter <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">George Drouillard</name> and <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Private Joseph Whitehouse</name>, one of the expedition's journalists.</p>
            <p>
At the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Ohio River">Ohio</name>, which they reached on November 14, they spent a week mapping and measuring and taking celestial observations, then started up the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name> on November 20. On their left hand now was present-day <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, part of the Louisiana Purchase, still under the rule of Spanish officials pending the transfer to the United States the following spring. On November 28, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> left <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> in charge of the boat and the men at the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Kaskaskia River">Kaskaskia River</name> and proceeded by land to <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> to confer with the Spanish authorities. He found them by no means pleased by the expedition; they requested that he make his winter camp on the American side of the river, pending the transfer of <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name>. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> proceeded upriver, met and conferred with <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> on December 9, then left his partner at <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> and moved to the American side near the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Dubois River">River Dubois</name> in modern <name type="place" key="Illinois">Illinois</name>. There on December 13 he established the camp where the Corps of Discovery awaited the coming of spring to begin the trip up the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>.</p>
            <p>
During the five months at <name type="place" key="Camp Dubois (Camp Wood, River Dubois) (Ill.)">Camp Dubois</name> the captains gathered further recruits, some of them frontiersmen who enlisted especially for the expedition, others army enlisted men from various western garrisons who were assigned to the expedition by their commanding officers. The long and inevitably tedious winter enabled the captains to evaluate their men, to weed out a few undesirables, and to introduce the more undisciplined to the rigors of army regimen. During the wait they were also able to gather much knowledge about the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri River</name> and its native peoples from the fur traders and river men of the region, in particular <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">James Mackay</name>, and to acquire copies of <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">John Thomas Evans's</name> maps of the river. The transfer of <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name> to the United States was formally accomplished in March 1803, and spring soon brought weather suited for travel.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> was in <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> when <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> left <name type="place" key="Camp Dubois (Camp Wood, River Dubois) (Ill.)">Camp Dubois</name> on May 14, 1804, with the keelboat and two pirogues, manned by perhaps 42 men. The party arrived at <name type="place" key="Saint Charles, Mo.">St. Charles</name> on the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> on May 16, and <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> joined them on the twentieth. At <name type="place" key="Saint Charles, Mo.">St. Charles</name> they added a few more boatmen and set out on the afternoon of May 21.</p>
            <p>
The journey up the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, against the current, was slow and laborious; occasionally they could sail with a favorable wind, but more often they poled upstream or the men pulled the boats with a tow rope, walking on the shore. They soon left the last white settlements behind and began to exercise more caution as they entered Indian country. Several times they met fur traders headed down river with their pelts, having wintered among one tribe or another. One of them, <name type="person" key="Dorion, Pierre, Sr.">Pierre Dorion, Sr.</name>, the captains hired to return upstream with them as an interpreter.</p>
            <p>
Toiling along in the increasing summer heat, plagued by boils, diarrhea, mosquitoes, and sandbars, the Corps of Discovery reached the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Kansas (Decaugh, Kaw) River">Kansas River</name>, the future site of <name type="place" key="Kansas City, Mo.">Kansas City</name>, on June 26. Almost another month was required to reach the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Platte River (Nebr.)">Platte</name>, on July 21. Just above the <name type="place" key="Platte River (Nebr.)">Platte</name> they established <name type="place" key="Camp White Catfish (Iowa)">Camp White Catfish</name>, on the present <name type="place" key="Iowa">Iowa</name> shore, and rested a few days (July 22-26). On July 30 they reached a high bluff near the river in modern <name type="place" key="Nebraska">Nebraska</name>, which they would call <name type="place" key="Council Bluff (Nebr.)">Council Bluff</name>, for there they had their first council with the chiefs of the <name type="native_nation" key="Oto Indians">Otos</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Missouri Indians">Missouris</name>, informing them of the change in sovereignty in <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name>; they remained at the bluffs until August 2.</p>
            <p>
Some disciplinary problems marred their progress; unauthorized tapping of the whiskey supply earned <name type="person" key="Collins, John">Private John Collins</name> one hundred lashes. More serious was the desertion of <name type="person" key="Reed, Moses B.">Private Moses B. Reed</name> and the boatman <name type="person" key="La Liberté">La Liberté</name> in early August; <name type="person" key="Reed, Moses B.">Reed</name> was captured, forced to run the gauntlet, and officially expelled from the party, though he remained with them for the time being because he could not be abandoned in the wilderness. <name type="person" key="La Liberté">La Liberté</name> made good his escape.</p>
            <p>
A loss of a different sort soon followed. Just after a second council with the chiefs of the <name type="native_nation" key="Oto Indians">Otos</name> in northeast <name type="place" key="Nebraska">Nebraska</name>, <name type="person" key="Floyd, Charles">Sergeant Charles Floyd</name> died, probably of a ruptured appendix, at the present site of <name type="place" key="Sioux City, Iowa">Sioux City</name>, <name type="place" key="Iowa">Iowa</name>. His comrades buried him on a bluff on the <name type="place" key="Iowa">Iowa</name> shore, naming a nearby stream <name type="place" key="Floyd River">Floyd's River</name>. He would, in fact, be the only man to die on the expedition, but this must have seemed too much to hope for at the time. Four days later they reached the <name type="place" key="Vermillion (White Stone) River (S. Dak.)">Vermillion River</name>, in present <name type="place" key="South Dakota">South Dakota</name>, 112 days and about 860 miles out from <name type="place" key="Camp Dubois (Camp Wood, River Dubois) (Ill.)">Camp Dubois</name>.

</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
