<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.sup.lavender.01.13">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Way to the Western Sea</title>
            <title type="sub">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> across the Continent</title>
            <title type="sub" level="a">Chapter 13</title>
            <author>David Lavender</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2005</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               
               
               
               
               
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Way to the Western Sea</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">Chapter 13</title>
               <author>David Lavender</author>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>2001</date>
               <idno type="ISBN">0-8032-8003-3</idno>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Supplements</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Texts</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-11-09</date>
            <date>2005-04-20</date>
            <name>Becky Potter</name>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Split into chapters Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="thirteen" type="chapter">
            <head rend="center">THIRTEEN. The Great Divide</head>
            <div type="section">
               <p>
Shortly before breakfast on July 16, as the men were rowing against a gentle current, one of them spotted near the river bank a cluster of about forty empty "booths," or arbors, that had been built of willow boughs as shelters against the sun. Because the bowers were different from other temporary lodgings the captains had seen along the river, they decided, probably after asking <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name> her opinion, that the structures had been put together by some of her people, the <name type="place" key="Shoshone Indians">Snake</name> or <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name> Indians. But where were the builders? The captains had been hoping to meet some of the tribe ever since learning they customarily ranged along the headwaters of both the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> and <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> rivers.<ref target="n1301" n="1"/>
               </p>
               <p>
A meeting had, in fact, been tantalizingly close. Horse sign around the camp suggested the Indians had departed ten or twelve days earlier. At that time, July 4 to 6, the whites had been gathered at the <name type="place" key="White Bear Islands">White Bear Islands</name>, separated from the Indian bowers by approximately forty-five river miles—but only sixteen land miles.<ref target="n1302" n="2"/> White hunters had ranged nearly that far from their base, and Indian food gatherers had probably matched the range. If timing had been right, <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name> foragers, armed only with bows, might well have heard the guns of their counterparts. Although the Corps's journalists do not speculate on the matter, it is even possible that the sound of shooting had frightened the <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name> into breaking camp.</p>
               <p>
So very close! Yet there was no use trying to overtake, on foot or in dugout canoes, mounted Indians who had a ten-day start. On the party went, to a buffalo <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name> had just killed and butchered for their breakfast. There <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, experimenting again, ate for the first time "of the small guts of the buffalo cooked over a blazing
fire in the Indian stile without preperation of washing or other cleansing and found them very good."</p>
               <p>
The meal finished, he, <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name> (who had become <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> almost constant companion), and two crewmen started ahead of the dugouts on foot. Their aim was to obtain an astronomical fix on the point, only a few miles ahead, where the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> breaks out of the spur of the northern <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rockies</name> now known as the <name type="place" key="Big Belt Mountains">Big Belts</name>. It was a pleasant excursion. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> liked to walk, and the slopes leading to the gap made by the river were washed with the lemony-gold sheen of blooming cactus and massed sunflowers. He scrambled up a tall pinnacle at the mouth of the canyon and, looking back, marveled at the view of the great herds of buffalo grazing on the plains. Though he did not suspect it, it would be his last sight of those mobile mountains of meat for many, often hungry months to come.</p>
               <p>
Calculations for latitude made, the four men pushed about five miles into the lower canyon, between walls of hard, black rock some eight hundred feet high. At the foot of a rapid that "roled white over the rocks" (<name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>), <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> killed an elk for supper. The joy ended after that, for he had forgotten his mosquito netting, and he spent the night flailing at the hordes of insects that attacked him.</p>
               <p>
The next morning, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> and the boats overtook the scouts at the foot of the rapid. As a precaution against water damage, the soldiers carried the most vulnerable supplies on their backs to the upper end of the turbulence. The dugouts, double manned, were dragged up with two ropes. The river then became deep, the current slow. Cliffs soared on either side. Tall pines and stunted aspens seemed to rise directly out of the dark, vaulting stone. The 
constricted bottomlands were choked with sunflowers whose seeds, when mature, could be pounded into flour, currants and serviceberries already "ripe and in great perfection," and gooseberries and chokecherries that soon would be edible. All this <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> recorded in scientific detail in camp that night, as he did the next morning's sighting of a large herd of bighorn sheep clambering on walls five hundred feet above them, "where we should suppose it impossible for any animal to stand."</p>
               <p>
About three miles farther on, the fleet came to "a handsome, bold and clear stream, eighty yards wide," which the captains named <name type="place" key="Dearborn River">Dearborn's River</name>, after <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name> secretary of war. During the winter, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> informants had included the <name type="place" key="Dearborn River">Dearborn's</name> valley with that of the <name type="place" key="Sun (Mah-pah-pah,-ah-zhah, Medicine) River">Medicine (Sun) River</name> as furnishing a short way to tributaries of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>. There is no indication in the journals that the captains associated the stream they saw with the one the Indians had told about.<ref target="n1303" n="3"/> Indeed, the whites were growing increasingly baffled by the disparity between what they were seeing and what they had understood the Hidatsas to say during the winter. The river Indians had not mentioned <name type="place" key="Marias River">Maria's River</name>, they had been at least partly wrong about the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">Great Falls</name>, and they had given no forewarning about the profound gorge the Corps was now threading. And so, as <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> put it, "we are anxious now to meet with the <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Sosonees or snake Indians</name> . . . in order to obtain information relative to the geography of the country and also if necessary, some horses."</p>
               <p>
Horses—if necessary. It is a strange qualification. They had been thinking horses ever since <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had drawn his conjectural map of the West. But their successful traverse of the Grand Portage had, perhaps, inspired them to believe they could cross the <name type="place" key="Continental Divide">Continental Divide</name> in the same manner, without horses, if the carrying place were no longer than the half-day labor the <name type="place" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name> had predicted. But how trustworthy was <name type="place" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> information?</p>
               <p>
The <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name> could answer the questions—if the explorers could lay hold of some of that tribe. And so <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> continued in one of his convoluted sentences, "we thought it better for . . . either <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name> or myself to take a small party &amp; proceed on up the river some distance before [i.e., ahead of] the boats, in order to discover them, should they be on the river, before the daily discharge of our guns, which was necessary in procuring subsistence for the party, should allarm and cause them to retreat to the mountains and conceal themselves, supposing us to be their enemies who reach them usually by way of the river."<ref target="n1304" n="4"/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Joseph Field</name>, <name type="person" key="Potts, John">John Potts</name>, and <name type="person" key="York">York</name> took the first turn at land travel. It was miserable. Uneven masses of small, sharp fragments of rock covered the ridge tops while blankets of prickly pear covered the lower levels. The second night out, sitting beside their campfire, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> pulled seventeen thorns out of his cut, bruised feet.
Because the others had suffered equally, he decided to drop down to the river the next day and rest until the boats appeared. While waiting, he could hunt game for the dugout crews. Locked in the gorge, they might be having trouble getting enough to eat. And after they arrived he could admit, reluctantly, to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> that except for a streak of signal smoke he and his scouts had seen (it had been too far off to investigate) the Indian sign he had noticed was too old to mean much. They were still on a blind path.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>
Back on the river, the boats moved slowly, pulled against the strong current by tow ropes. Then the canyon grew still narrower. Water filled its bottom from wall to wall, leaving no banks to walk on. Willy-nilly the men had to return to their oars and fight a stream thrust almost as powerful as they were. By <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> estimate the walls of the gorge rose twelve hundred feet above their heads. Evergreens cloaked the north-facing slope. The cover on the opposite side was thinner and heavily scarred and pitted by erosion. Unable to land in that gloomy place, the rowers labored on until after dark before finding a flat spot big enough to hold their camp. Searching for a suitable name for so singular a place, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> called it, with underlining for emphasis, "<hi rend="italic">the <name type="place" key="Gates of the Rocky Mountains">gates of the rocky mountains</name>
                  </hi>."<ref target="n1305" n="5"/>
               </p>
               <p>
The next day the mountains receded. By afternoon the river had split into several channels and was winding through a broad plain bound by parallel ranges. Here <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> noted the double timberlines characteristic of the high valleys of the northern <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rockies</name>: a broad belt of evergreens bordered on top by the gray rocks of the "snowey regions" and on the bottom by the treeless, slowly rising floor of the valley. The spacious land looked fine for grazing, but 
although the men noticed old buffalo bones and excrement, they detected no living buffalo. As if to help make up for the lack of food, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> dog, <name type="person" key="Seaman">Seaman</name>, caught several young geese, their wings not yet feathered enough for them to fly, and brought them to his master. (A few days earlier the dog had dragged a wounded deer from the water, killed it, and added it to the larder.)</p>
               <p>
On July 22, the swift, shallow water of the narrow channels forced the soldiers to resort again to the tow ropes. At times, when the brush was too thick to crash through, they took up their setting poles. These entailed standing in the wobbly dugouts, jamming one end of the pole onto the smooth, slippery stones of the bottom, and forcing the craft upward with all the strength the boatman could muster. Along this stretch, afternoon temperatures, taken 
always in the shade, rose into the eighties from the pleasant seventies where the mercury had hovered for several weeks.<ref target="n1306" n="6"/> Even worse was discouragement. At the <name type="place" key="Gates of the Rocky Mountains">Gates of the Mountains</name>, to use modern terminology, the river valley had bent not just south but a little east of south, so that their travail was actually taking them away from the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>.</p>
               <p>
Into this misery came sudden rejoicing. As the boats were passing a small creek whose banks showed patches of white earth, <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name> made her first gesture of recognition. At this place her people collected material for white body paint. Almost surely, she indicated, the expedition would find <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name> a little farther on at a place called the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Three Forks of the">Three Forks</name>. Because the Americans had heard of this key spot during their stay among the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>, "This peice of information," <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> wrote, "has cheered the sperits of the party who . . . console themselves with the anticipation of shortly seeing the head of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> yet unknown to the civilized world."</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, too, was buoyed by the news when he heard it from the boatmen at his resting place. Any Indians camped at <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Three Forks of the">Three Forks</name> or thereabouts, he thought, would be the ones who had set the smoke signals he had seen. Obsessed with the idea of being the first to meet them, he declined to trade places with <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>. Since only <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Joseph Field</name> of his original party was fit to continue by land, he enlisted three fresh men—<name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Joseph's</name> brother, <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">Reuben</name>, <name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">Robert Frazer</name>, and <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name>, who begged to go and might be able to interpret a little. Then off he limped on July 23, covering twenty-three miles in spite of his fatigue and aching feet. He also killed four deer and left them beside the river for the water travelers. On the 24th he went thirty miles. On the 25th he was even more demanding. That morning he led his men onto a low swell of hills and saw the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Three Forks of the">Three Forks</name>. Left and right and ahead of them a majestic vastness rose to black bands of timber capped by gray, round-topped peaks dappled with snow. Puffs of clouds floated overhead. Below the clouds three streams coiled like dropped pieces of string through sage and grass, willows and rose bushes, but only occasional narrow-leafed cottonwoods. The westernmost stream and the middle one joined first and then drifted on a short distance to pick up the eastern river, where it finished lapping around a gray snout of limestone. He had reached the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Three Forks of the">Three Forks of the Missouri</name>. Beaver sign was everywhere. Otter. Deer. Some antelope. Occasional elk. But no sign of Indians. Whoever had set the smoke signal had vanished. Where?</p>
               <p>
Clearly the westernmost of the forks reached the high country sooner than the other two did, and so, after impaling a note to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> on a stick and thrusting the stick into the marshy ground, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> took his men twenty-five miles up the gentle valley, traveling west and southwest. When <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name> collapsed, they camped, "all of them much fatigued, their feet blistered and wounded by the prickly pear."<ref target="n1307" n="7"/>
               </p>
               <p>
The next morning the interpreter was unable to travel. Leaving one man with him, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> led the other two on a dry walk through unseasonable heat to the top of a hill twelve miles away. The view was tremendous but revealed no Indians. On the way back the scouts stopped at an icy spring. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> took what he thought were proper precautions before drinking: he wet his face, hands, and feet in the cold water. The preventative failed him. Almost immediately after gulping copiously, he felt as if he had been slugged. Sore-footed, cramped, and dead tired, he hobbled to the camp where he had left <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussiant">Charbonneau</name>. When <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name> said he could walk again, the captain decided to cross the stream they had been following and examine the middle of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Three Forks of the">Missouri's three forks</name>. They chose as a ford a place where the river was divided by an island. After reaching the island they killed two grizzlies and then waded out into the much deeper water of the second channel. The current was swift and <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name>, who could not swim, lost his footing. He might well have drowned if <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had not dragged him out.</p>
               <p>
These last exertions almost finished the captain. After forcing himself along for another three miles he caved in, shivering with chills and aching in every muscle. The next morning he staggered on. Arriving at the <name type="place" key="Madison River (Middle Fork)">middle fork</name>, he turned down it, and at three in the afternoon rejoined the main party at the camp <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> had established near the junction. After he had told <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> he felt bilious (an old complaint of <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>) and hadn't had a passage for several days, his friend gave him a dose of <name type="person" key="Rush, Benjamin">Rush's</name> thunderbolt pills and directed some of the men to build a bower where <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> could sleep out of the sun.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>
Bringing the boats up the river to the forks had been no picnic, either. There were the usual struggles with setting poles and tow ropes. When handling the latter the men often had to leave the brushy banks for the cold, waist-deep water, under a broiling sun. Bearded needle grass added its miseries to the familiar pests of gnats, mosquitoes, and prickly pears. Its barbed seeds, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> complained to his diary, "penetrate our mockersons and leather legins and give us great pain until they are removed. My poor dog suffers from them excessively." As for the exhausted men, "I occassionaly encourage them by assisting in the labour of navigating the canoes, and have learned <hi rend="italic">to push a tolerable good pole</hi> in their fraize [phrase]."</p>
               <p>
In spite of all this and amid his worries about Indians, he found time, good Jeffersonian that he was, to jot down a continuing run of natural history observations. He described lovely fields of wild flax that he thought could, in time, be profitably cultivated by pioneering farmers. He was less taken by some wild onions he boiled up for one meal—"strong, tough, and disagreeable." As usual he had a sharp eye for new birds such as ruffed grouse and 
a colorful woodpecker that later ornithologists would name for him (<hi rend="italic">asyndesmus lewis</hi>). On seeing several snakes that sought refuge in the water as the boats neared, he helped the men catch some so that he could examine their teeth to learn whether the fangs were hollow and thus capable of releasing stored poison. (They weren't.) On reaching <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Three Forks of the">Three Forks</name> he promptly climbed the limestone bluff around which the eastern branch curled and from that vantage point drew a chart of the meandering streams.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> return on the afternoon of July 27 sealed a decision <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> had already made. In spite of the dangers inherent in additional delay, the boatmen, weakened "from this continual state of violent exertion," had to have rest and time for making new buckskin moccasins and garments to replace clothing ruined by long periods of immersion in water. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, too, badly needed a pause. So the word went around: for the next two days they would stay where they were.</p>
               <p>
They were not idle days.<ref target="n1308" n="8"/> While hunters went after deer for venison and skins, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> struggled with a problem of definition. Which of the river's <name type="person" key="Missouri River, Three Forks of the">three forks</name> was most worthy of keeping the name <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>? He ruled out the eastern fork, which was the smallest, but the other two were so nearly equal in size that, in his mind, it would be wrong to give either one the preference. This meant thinking up appropriate new names. Consultations with <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> in his bower resulted in their calling the eastern fork <name type="person" key="Gallatin, Albert">Gallatin</name>, in honor of the secretary of the treasury, <name type="person" key="Gallatin, Albert">Albert Gallatin</name>; the <name type="place" key="Madison River (Middle Fork)">middle fork the Madison</name>, after <name type="person" key="Madison, James">Secretary of State James Madison</name>; and the western the <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, after "the author of our enterprize."</p>
               <p>
A poignant Indian drama, they soon learned, was associated with the <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>. Five years previously, according to <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name>, talking through her husband, her family had been encamped with a mobile village of <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name> at exactly the spot where the American explorers were then resting. On being warned by lookouts of an advancing war party of <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name>, the mountain Indians had retreated up the <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> to a sheltering grove of stunted cottonwoods and brush. The <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name> discovered the ruse and attacked. In a running fight they killed four men, four women, and a number of boys. As the defeated <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name> warriors fled on horseback from the battleground, the rest of the band scampered for safety as best they could. While <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name> was splashing frantically across a shoal place in the river, a mounted <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> had swooped her up and had taken her, probably by way of the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone</name>, to an enforced new home. But, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> wrote, she seemed stirred neither by memories of the abduction nor by anticipation of joining 
her people again. "If she has enough to eat, and a few trinkets to wear I believe she would be content anywhere."</p>
               <p>
It was a stoicism the captains were having to match in their own way. Certain shocking geographic truths were dawning on them. From what the <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name> had said earlier in the year about the 225-mile southwestern course of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> between <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">Great Falls</name> and <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Three Forks of the">Three Forks</name>, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had estimated the longitude of the latter to be about 117°. To this assumption the captains had attached two known facts: the longitude of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia's</name> mouth was almost 124° and the distance from one meridian of longitude to the next was, in <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> lexicon, about 41 miles. Seven meridians multiplied by 41 supposedly meant that only 300 or so direct-line miles would separate them, at the forks, from the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>.</p>
               <p>
Matters had not worked out that way, however. Instead of traveling southwest from <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">Great Falls</name>, they had gone a little east of south for about 250 miles. As a consequence they were somewhere between meridians 111° and 112°—or about 500, not 300, direct-line miles from the ocean.<ref target="n1309" n="9"/> And of course they could not travel in direct lines. Windings like those they had been following from <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">Great Falls</name> would probably swell the distance ahead of them to more than a thousand miles.</p>
               <p>
There were other considerations. They could no longer be sure they could cross the divide in half a day, even with horses, as the <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name> had said. And once the Corps did reach a navigable stream leading to the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>, would they find trees suitable for building dugouts or would the land, like the valley of the upper <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, be devoid of timber? In addition, there was the problem of altitude. Although the mountains cupping the <name type="place" key="Gallatin (South, Southeast Fork) River">Gallatin</name>, <name type="place" key="Madison River (Middle Fork)">Madison</name>, and <name type="place" key="Jefferson River (North, Southwest Fork)">Jefferson</name> rivers did not seem to rise particularly high above the broad valley floor, the appearance was deceptive. Since leaving <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>, the expedition had followed the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> for close to twenty-five hundred miles and in that distance must have gained almost a mile in elevation. Winters, for anyone caught in the mountains, would be severe, as snow patches still lingering near the summits late in July attested. "Game," <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> wrote, "may 
rationally be expected shortly to become scarce and subsistence precarious."</p>
               <p>
In spite of this bleak prospect, there is no indication the captains thought of turning back or even sitting where they were on the chance a band of <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name> would eventually come long with extra horses they would be willing to barter. The explorers had to advance. The <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> lay ahead and, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> wrote, with just a little posturing for whoever might read his journals in the future, "if any Indians can subsist . . . in these mountains with the means they have of acquiring food we can also subsist."</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>
When the Corps resumed its journey on July 30, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> again took up his custom of walking off to the sides of the river—the <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> now—to see as much of the local flora and fauna as he could while staying more or less abreast of the boats. This day a maze of beaver dams entangled him. He clambered over the obstructions from pond to pond, waded in mud and water to his waist, fought the dense willow brush, and in spite of his labors 
missed the boats. No worry. He shot a duck for supper, built a fire, made a bed of willow boughs, "and should have had a comfortable nights lodge but for the musquetoes which infested me."<ref target="n1310" n="10"/>
               </p>
               <p>
When the time came to write up his notes, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> remarked, as he had at other points along the upper <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, on the "vast number of beaver" inhabiting the upper river. He knew fur men would be interested in that and in his recommendation of <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Three Forks of the">Three Forks</name> as a site for a trading post (a post would be built there in 1810, but <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfoot Indians</name> soon put it out of business). What he did not foresee, though the development would not have surprised 
him, was that at least four of the expedition's men, <name type="person" key="Weiser, Peter">Peter Wiser</name>, <name type="person" key="Potts, John">John Potts</name>, <name type="person" key="Colter, John">John Colter</name>, and <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">George Drouillard</name>, would return to the high, bleak region with parties hunting beaver. Casualties would be high. Indians killed <name type="person" key="Potts, John">Potts</name> in 1808 and <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name> in 1810, after horribly mutilating him. <name type="person" key="Weiser, Peter">Wiser</name>, his tracks befogged by now, found new ways to cross the divide into <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>, where new bonanzas of fur awaited, only to be killed under circumstances now unknown. <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name> escaped a similar fate by outrunning the <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name>, who had stripped him stark naked, in a race that became an American legend.<ref target="n1311" n="11"/> As for little <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Jean Baptiste">Jean Baptiste Charbonneau</name>, <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea's</name> son—but that's another story, for later on.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>
After the boats picked up <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> the following day, his sense of the expedition's predicament grew to urgency. All of the men were on the edge of exhaustion in spite of their rest at <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Three Forks of the">Three Forks</name>, and there was neither grog nor, on that day, July 31, fresh meat for reviving their morale and strength. The latter shortage led <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> to one of his rare criticisms of the crew: "when we have a plenty of fresh meat I find it impossible to make the men take any 
care of it, or use it with the least frugality. tho' I expect that necessity will shortly teach them this art."<ref target="n1312" n="12"/>
               </p>
               <p>
A portage like the one at <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">Great Falls</name> would not do after all. The Corps must have horses. The next day (August 1, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> birthday) <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> began a new search for the <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name>. As companions he chose, in addition to <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name>, two men who were not in shape to help with the boats. One was <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name>, whose ankles still bothered him. The other was <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Sergeant Gass</name>, who had wrenched his back in a fall. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> himself was discomfited by a combined attack of diarrhea and the operation of the salts he had taken to cure it. The day was hot, and they wasted miles on a mistaken shortcut. Still, there were compensations. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> saw and described a noticeable new bird, the pinyon jay. He and <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name> killed two elk and left most of the meat beside the stream as a birthday present for <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> and his hungry boatmen. Curiously, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> seems not to have taken his dog, <name type="person" key="Seaman">Seaman</name>, along on these exploratory expeditions, perhaps because of the difficulty of feeding the animal but more probably because of the foot-lacerating needle grass and prickly pear cactus that blanketed the ground away from the stream.</p>
               <p>
During the next two days they struggled with hot days and cold nights, with foot problems on the dry slopes, and, near the stream, with thickets of brush and with marshes caused by overflow from innumerable beaver dams. On August 4, the splitting of the <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> into two nearly equal branches confused them briefly. After carefully examining both banks <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> decided that the one to the left, as he faced upstream, was the proper choice for the boats. He 
wanted to make sure, however, by first exploring the right (westerly) fork while at the same time acquiring a little more geographic knowledge. He wrote a note to <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, advising him to take the flotilla up the <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, as he continued calling the left fork, and said he and his party would rejoin the boats somewhere along its course. <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Sergeant Gass</name> then cut down a willow pole, fastened the note to the green wood, and set up the message beside the stream where he thought the boatmen would be sure to see it. Then off the scouts went, up the right fork toward the mountains, at whose toes they camped.</p>
               <p>
The next day neither <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name> nor <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name> was able to continue. Accordingly <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> sent them back across country to a timbered hill beside the main fork with orders to wait there for him and for the boats. Accompanied by <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name>, the captain pushed up the sparkling, swift-flowing, but very shallow right fork into the mountains. Finding that it bent due west and then north, the explorers forsook it to scramble up a high point in the foothills. This gave them an aerial view of the wide valley. No question: the <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> was the way. It surely held more water than the unnavigable right fork, and it continued southwest—the direction emphasized by the <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name>—to a distant gap in the mountains. True, the <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> geographers had not always been right, but where nothing is known with surety any firm statement is a reed to clutch at.</p>
               <p>
These conclusions reached, <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name> and <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> made their way to the camp <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name> and <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name> had established, arriving two hours after dark. (One has to assume the two invalids had built a large fire as a beacon.) Because they had no food for breakfast the next morning, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> sent <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name> hunting in the triangle between the forks while he went downstream with <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name> and <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name> to meet the boats. A lucky decision. From a high point <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name> caught sight of the dugouts toiling up the wrong branch and hurried over to turn them back.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="related">
               <p>
The days had been brutal for the boatmen.<ref target="n1313" n="13"/> Every two or three hundred yards they encountered rapids so shallow the dugouts grounded and the crew had to go into the water and drag the heavy boats up to the next pool. More immersions came when they were towing the craft and impassable brush on the banks again drove them back into the stream. The constant sliding around on the stony bottom injured their feet and occasionally caused painful falls. The river wound through so many hairpin bends that hours of toil actually advanced them relatively few miles toward their goal. But at least the hunters began getting a little meat, including a bighorn sheep <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> bagged on his birthday out of a herd bounding up a cliff on the far side of the river. Supplemented by trout, a few geese, and an occasional beaver, the sheep meat and small daily rations of venison were spread thinly among the twenty-nine adults of the party and the dog.</p>
               <p>
On reaching the forks of the <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> found only the stub of the green pole on which <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name> had placed <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> note. For some reason a beaver, ignoring the masses of willow nearby, had nipped off the lone pole and had carried the note away. After seeing the scouts' tracks going up the west fork, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> followed. Soon the group was trapped in a braid of channels so narrow that the brush hanging over them united at the top and created hot, green tunnels through which, for one stretch a quarter of a mile long, they had to cut a way with axes and knives. That night they camped on an island so marshy they had to heap up beds of willow boughs to stay out of the mud.</p>
               <p>
The next morning, August 6, <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name> turned them back into more trouble. Two dugouts, hanging up on rocks in swift riffles, filled with water washing over the gunwales. A third upset. Another, swinging against a rock, jarred <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse</name> overboard and then floated heavily across him, injuring one of his legs. After meeting <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> group at the forks, they crossed to a sunny gravel bar opposite this river of bad luck. There they spread out the baggage to dry. On taking inventory they discovered that so great a quantity of trade goods and equipment had been lost they could abandon one of the dugouts—a bonus, for the action freed more men to hunt the increasingly scarce game they needed.</p>
               <p>
At noon on the seventh they repacked and moved up the fork <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> had chosen—the <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>. On the morning of the eighth they encountered still another fork, this one coming in from the southeast. Since this new fork and the one where <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had encountered so much grief were the principal affluents of the <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, the captains decided to name them after what they considered to be two of the president's principal attributes—<name type="place" key="Big Hole (Sensable, Wisdom) River">Wisdom</name> for the lower tributary, <name type="place" key="Ruby (Philanthropy) River">Philanthropy</name> for the upper. Not surprisingly, later pioneers renamed the streams after geographic landmarks. The <name type="place" key="Big Hole (Sensable, Wisdom) River">Wisdom</name> has become the <name type="place" key="Big Hole (Senseble, Wisdom) River">Big Hole</name> after the high, handsome valley in which it originates; the <name type="place" key="Ruby (Philanthropy) River">Philanthropy</name> is now the <name type="place" key="Ruby (Philanthropy) River">Ruby</name>, for the mountain range that is its birthplace. The <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> was renamed, above the forks, for <name type="place" key="Beaverhead Rock">Beaverhead Rock</name>, an imposing bluff visible for miles in almost every direction. The <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name> were its 
original christeners, for they fancied they saw in its contours the shape of a swimming beaver.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name> explained the name as soon as she saw <name type="place" key="Beaverhead Rock">Beaverhead</name>. Unquestionably, she went on, her people would be camped either on the headwaters of the <name type="place" key="Beaverhead (Jefferson) River">Jefferson</name>/<name type="place" key="Beaverhead (Jefferson) River">Beaverhead</name> or on another river just beyond the mountains.</p>
               <p>
The information impelled <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> to go ahead once again with a small scouting party consisting of <name type="person" key="Shields, John">John Shields</name>, <name type="person" key="McNeal, Hugh">Hugh McNeal</name>, and, inevitably, <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">George Drouillard</name>. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> was disappointed. It was his turn to lead the advance party, but he could not because of "the raging fury of a turner on my anckle muscle." Ominously he added, "three hunters Could kill only two antelopes to day."<ref target="n1314" n="14"/> Because of the shortage, the only food the scouts took with them was a little salt pork and flour purchased more than a year ago in <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>, plus a sack of parched corn prepared at the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> villages.</p>
               <p>
Walking briskly, they passed <name type="place" key="Beaverhead Rock">Beaverhead Rock</name> and the <name type="place" key="Rattlesnake Cliffs">Rattlesnake Cliffs</name>, named for the great number of rattlers in the vicinity. On August 10, they stumbled onto a trail that took them through an abrupt little canyon to yet another fork in the river. After deciding that the most recent horse tracks went up the west fork (later named <name type="place" key="Horse Prairie Creek (West Fork Jefferson River)">Horse Prairie Creek</name>), <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> decided to turn that way and put a note on a dry stick advising <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> to wait at the junction until he returned. This was the end of boat travel. But how wonderful to have come so far! "I do not believe," he wrote in his journal, "that the world can furnish an example of a river running to the extent which the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> and <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> do through such a mountainous country and at the same time so navigable as they are. If the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> furnishes another such example, a communication across the continent will be practicable and safe."<ref target="n1315" n="15"/>
               </p>
               <p>
It was self-delusion. Passing the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">Great Falls</name> had hardly been an example of practical travel, and even though the river above that landmark had proved passable, safe limits certainly did not extend beyond <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Three Forks of the">Three Forks</name>. He knew, too, that the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> dropped to the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name> in half the distance the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> coursed on its way to the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name> and would be correspondingly rougher. But he had been directed by his president to find a waterway. Therefore he would disregard whatever ran contrary to his desire.</p>
               <p>
After camping that night in a wide valley that <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> called "the handsomest cove I ever saw" (he later named it <name type="place" key="Shoshone Cove">Shoshoni Cove</name>) the  scouts continued up gentle tan slopes and among scattered copses of spruce and fir toward the divide. Losing the Indian trail in thick sagebrush, the quartet spread out at a considerable distance from each other in the hope that one of them would pick it up again. After they had marched about five miles in this fashion, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> spotted a human figure, tiny in the distance. Up came his spyglass. A mounted Indian! Making gestures of friendship and finally setting aside his gun so that he could hold out tempting gifts, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> advanced toward the now motionless <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name>, all the while bellowing "tab-ba-bone," which he thought meant "white man." (He had asked <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name> the word for "white man." Since the <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name> apparently had no word for such people, she gave him the  closest translation she could, tab-ba-bone, or "stranger." This did nothing to reassure the horseman.)<ref target="n1316" n="16"/> Meanwhile, one of the privates, <name type="person" key="Shields, John">John Shields</name>, blundered along in a fashion that alarmed the <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name>, who suddenly wheeled around, gave his horse the whip, and disappeared into the brush. "With him," the frustrated <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> wrote, "disappeared all my hopes of obtaining horses for the preasant."</p>
               <p>
After chewing out <name type="person" key="Shields, John">Shields</name> in the best army fashion, the captain calmed down, and they set about trying to track the rider to his camp. A heavy rain ended the effort. The next day, however, they picked up a major trail that led past a collection of huts made of willow brush and on through ground recently disturbed by root diggers. Spirits soared: they were close now. Where the trail crossed a little rivulet, <name type="person" key="McNeal, Hugh">Private McNeal</name> "exultingly stood with a foot on each side . . . and thanked his god that he had lived to bestride the mighty and heretofore deemed endless <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>."<ref target="n13unnumbered" n="*"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Two miles farther on they reached the spring from which the rivulet gushed. Now <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> exulted. He had reached the very source of "the Mighty <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> in surch of which we have spent so many toilsome days and wristless nights. Thus far I have accomplished one of those great objects on which my mind has been set for many years, judge then of the pleasure I felt in all[a]ying my thirst with this pure and ice-cold water." Moving on, they topped the dividing ridge, "from which I discovered immence ranges of high mountains still to the West of us with their tops partially
covered with snow. I now decended the mountain . . . to a handsome bold running Creek of cold Clear water. here I first tasted the water of the great <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia river</name>."<ref target="n1317" n="17"/>
               </p>
               <p>
He was a proud and excited young man, knowing he had just helped write a new chapter in American history, and it takes the carpings of hindsight to raise questions. Such as:</p>
               <p>
His statement about his long dream of finding the sources of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>. Such things happen; many young Britons dreamed, before and after <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> time, of finding the sources of the Nile. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name> may well have believed he belonged in that sort of company. Not quite, however. This was <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Thomas Jefferson's</name> project. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> had been called on to execute it not because of any dreams he may have had or plans he may have laid, but simply because he had happened to be available when <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> decided to expand his original strategies concerning <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name>. This, of course, does not detract from <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> manifold accomplishments during the expedition. But it does make him a first-class manager rather than the innovator he quite naturally viewed himself to be, there on top of <name type="place" key="Lemhi Pass">Lemhi Pass</name>, 7,373 feet above the level of the sea.</p>
               <p>
He was also kidding himself about the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>. Like all white geographers of the time, none of whom had seen the area, he accepted as an article of faith, not of knowledge, the statement that the headwaters of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> were separated from those of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> by a single, thin dividing ridge.<ref target="n1318" n="18"/>
                  <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> map, drawn at <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name> and based on that same faith, showed no major chain of mountains beyond the last range of the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rockies</name>. So when <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> surmounted the hills from which the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> sprang and saw "immence ranges still to the West," what did he think they were? Perhaps, for all he knew, those were the true divide. Perhaps some tributary of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>—the <name type="place" key="Dearborn, Henry">Dearborn</name>, say—took its rise on the western side of <name type="place" key="Lemhi Pass">Lemhi Pass</name>, flowed north a distance as the <name type="person" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name> had said, and then broke east through the ridge to join the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>. If so, his exultations were premature, and the expedition had a lot more work to do.</p>
               <p>
He declined to face that issue. He had been conditioned to think <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> and he did think <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>. Yet even if that faith was right (it was), his and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> notion of what lay between the river's headwaters and the ocean—a wide plain like the one the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> crossed in the Midwest—was shockingly wrong and chilling times 
lay ahead. Either way, horses would become more essential than ever.</p>
               <p>
Finally, a matter of boundaries. Upper <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name> ended wherever the watershed of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> ended. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had shown a full awareness of the limitation when considering branches of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> that ran north toward <name type="place" key="Canada">Canada</name>. But no word of political barriers marked the pages of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> journal when he wrote of crossing <name type="place" key="Lemhi Pass">Lemhi Pass</name> westward into regions where <name type="place" key="England">Great Britain's</name> rights were as strong as those of the United States. He intended to exercise the privileges of sovereignty by opening communications with the West Coast, trading and treating with the Indians along the way, and studying the resources of the land as thoroughly as <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> and he had been doing in fully owned <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name> Territory. He was, in short, an advance agent of American imperialism, and it is hard to believe he wasn't as conscious of his role as <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Thomas Jefferson</name> was. But you would never know it from what he wrote in his journal as he left the United States and entered what was then no country's land.</p>
               <p>
They dropped down what may have been <name type="place" key="Agency Creek">Agency Creek</name> toward what they certainly hoped was the south fork of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>. At nightfall they ate the last of their pork, saving a little flour and parched meal until they could find other food. Walking on the next morning, they startled two <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name> women and one man into flight. Unable to overtake them, the explorers backtracked the trio toward whatever place they had come from. Along the way they 
surprised three females, made contact, and calmed their terror with gifts of beads, awls, mirrors, and vermilion. Rejoicing over the miraculous windfall, the women led the strangers toward their band's camp.<ref target="n1319" n="19"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Of a sudden sixty mounted warriors, armed primarily with bows, arrows, and bull-hide shields, galloped pell-mell around a bend in the valley toward them. They had reason to charge. Earlier in the year raiders they called <name type="native_nation" key="Atsina Indians">Pahkees</name> (<name type="native_nation" key="Atsina Indians">Atsinas</name>, allies of the <name type="place" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name>) had killed or captured twenty <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name>, had stolen many horses, and had burned all but one of the band's leather tepees. Recently word had arrived that the <name type="native_nation" key="Atsina Indians">Pahkees</name> were back; the people 
responsible for the smoke the Americans had seen had heard gunfire and had assumed <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name>.<ref target="n1320" n="20"/> Next, the three Indians who had fled from the explorers that very day had run to the village gasping that <name type="native_nation" key="Atsina Indians">Pahkees</name> had actually crossed the divide. So the warriors had dashed out to repel the invasion. They were dazzling horsemen, all of them, even though they rode crude saddles without stirrups and their bridles consisted of no more than a single cord tied around each horse's lower jaw.</p>
               <p>
Dropping his gun and seizing the American flag <name type="person" key="McNeal, Hugh">Private Hugh McNeal</name> had been carrying, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> stepped out to confront the force. The ecstatic women held up the trinkets they had been given, and the warriors reined in. Explanations flowed. Discovering their mistake, the Indians became instantly curious and affable. Dismounting, they took turns embracing the whites and pressing their greased and painted faces against the Americans' cheeks until, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> grumbled later, "I was heartily tired of the national hug."</p>
               <p>
Formal rituals of welcome followed, both at the meeting place and at the nomad's camp in the treeless valley of the yet unnamed <name type="place" key="Lemhi (East Fork Lewis's) River">Lemhi River</name>. (Curiously, the captains, who named nearly every tributary along the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, did not do as much for the <name type="place" key="Lemhi (East Fork Lewis's) River">Lemhi</name>, nor did they report the name the Indians used.) On the surface affairs went smoothly. The principal chief of the band, <name type="person" key="Cameahwait">Cameahwait</name>, was an exceptional individual. After meeting him <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> described him as having "Influence sence &amp; easy &amp; reserved manners, appears to possess a great deal of Cincerity."<ref target="n1321" n="21"/> Among his accomplishments was his ability to converse in the sign language familiar to all the tribes of the <name type="place" key="Great Plains">Great Plains</name>.</p>
               <p>
The <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name> were not a plains people. Their roots lay in the bleak <name type="place" key="Great Basin">Great Basin</name> country of <name type="place" key="Nevada">Nevada</name> and eastern <name type="place" key="California">California</name>. About A.D. 1500, archeologists believe, a search for food led some of them across the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rockies</name> into what is now southern <name type="place" key="Saskatchewan">Saskatchewan</name> and northern <name type="place" key="North Dakota">North Dakota</name>. There they began their long feud with the <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name>, <name type="native_nation" key="Crow Indians">Crows</name>, and <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name>. In those days the battles had been neither bloody nor conclusive, but matters changed in the early 1700s when the <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name> acquired horses through the <name type="native_nation" key="Ute Indians">Utes</name> and perhaps the <name type="native_nation" key="Comanche Indians">Comanches</name> who lived on the borders of Spanish <name type="place" key="New Mexico">New Mexico</name>. Astride these terrifying animals, they had been able not only to cow their enemies but to slay all the bison they needed for food and leather. During that period of supremacy, they adopted many plains customs, including sign language.<ref target="n1322" n="22"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Not long after the advent of horses, the Indians of the northern plains began picking up guns from the French and British traders of <name type="place" key="Canada">Canada</name>, and the <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshonis'</name> advantage disappeared. Driven back into the mountain-sheltered valley of the <name type="place" key="Lemhi (East Fork Lewis's) River">Lemhi</name>, they found the quality of their life deteriorating. From May to September, when salmon came up the river to spawn, they depended mostly on fish for food—but that was uncertain because the migrants arrived in 
sometimes widely spaced waves and, after laying their eggs, died. Roots, berries, and other plant foods, when mature, staved off starvation, but as the hard months of winter neared, the members of the band had to gather up their courage along with their bows, arrows, and lances (the only three guns <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> saw in <name type="person" key="Cameahwait">Cameahwait's</name> village were inoperable) and risk going onto the plains for buffalo, whose dried meat might last until the fish returned.</p>
               <p>
Through <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard's</name> sign language <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> was able to explain something of the Corps's intentions to <name type="person" key="Cameahwait">Cameahwait</name> and his council. After this initial talk they went down to the riverbank to discuss routes. <name type="person" key="Cameahwait">Cameahwait</name> was not encouraging. He said the <name type="place" key="Lemhi (East Fork Lewis's) River">Lemhi</name> ran north several miles (as the <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name> had also said) to join a bigger stream, which then wheeled west through impassable mountains to enter a huge lake where men like the visiting Americans lived. Privately <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> doubted the information. As far as he knew, no whites had established a settlement at the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> (assuming that by "lake" <name type="person" key="Cameahwait">Cameahwait</name> meant the ocean). Nor did the land-based Indian appreciate what could be done with boats by skilled rivermen. <name type="person" key="Cameahwait">Cameahwait</name>, he decided, was probably trying to keep the whites from going on so the village could benefit, during the coming winter, from their wondrous technology.<ref target="n1323" n="23"/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> was not about to bite. But he was worried. The Corps was going to need many horses, not just for bringing baggage across the divide but also for packing it down the <name type="place" key="Lemhi (East Fork Lewis's) River">Lemhi</name> to some point where trees big enough for boat building could be found—and that was a long distance, again according to <name type="person" key="Cameahwait">Cameahwait</name>. Taking a big party across the divide to meet <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> would involve commissary problems. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> party, armed with rifles, had not killed enough game for subsistence during their own crossing. And he knew the Indians had no backup supply. For when he had chanced to remark, earlier in the day, that he and his men had had nothing to eat for twenty-four hours, the <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name> had generously shared the few cakes of dried, pounded chokecherries and serviceberries they had.</p>
               <p>
Salmon? The run had slacked off. One man had given <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> a "morsel."<ref target="n1324" n="24"/> It "perfectly convinced me we were on the waters of the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific Ocean</name>" (so there had been a thread of doubt about that when he'd viewed the tumbled scene from the top of the pass) but it had also emphasized the problem of scarcity. How willing would the Indians be to go hungry while helping strangers?</p>
               <p>
They seemed amiable enough that first evening, entertaining their guests with a dance. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> went to bed at midnight, "leaving the men to amuse themselves with the Indians." Quite a party. The yelling awoke him several times, but "I . . . was too much fortiegued to be deprived of a tolerable sound night's repose."</p>
               <p>
The next morning <name type="person" key="McNeal, Hugh">Hugh McNeal</name> divided in half the last of the explorers' flour—one part for breakfast, the rest for evening. He added water and berries to the breakfast portion, cooked it, and distributed the results among the four scouts and <name type="person" key="Cameahwait">Cameahwait</name>. The chief liked the new food and his new friends, but not all his people shared his trust in them. Evidently the rank and file had talked things over during the night and had begun to doubt that the whites were as harmless as they pretended to be. When <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> harangued them about renting "30 spare horses to transport our baggage," he was met with sullen silence. Did not their implacable enemies, the horse-stealing <name type="native_nation" key="Atsina Indians">Pahkees</name> and the <name type="place" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name>, always come at them from the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> watershed? How did they know these four alien whites were not trying to lead them into an ambush where their horses would be lost?</p>
               <p>
After various fruitless arguments, delivered in <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard's</name> sign talk, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> struck a note that worked. The <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name> were cowards. At that <name type="person" key="Cameahwait">Cameahwait</name> swung aboard his horse and delivered another speech that declared his bravery and that of his warriors. Six or eight males thereupon fell in line. The old women of the village promptly began wailing as if the braves were going to certain destruction. <name type="person" key="Cameahwait">Cameahwait's</name> speech had shifted momentum, however. As the cavalcade moved ahead, more men and a number of women joined in.</p>
               <p>
It was not what <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> had hoped for. No packhorses—easy prey for raiders—were being led along by the mounted Indians. No riding animals had been provided for <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and his men. The suspect whites traveled afoot with their knapsacks on their backs until the captain, by offering compensation, prevailed on four <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name> to let the Americans ride double, each clinging to the warrior in front of him. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> soon found jogging along without 
stirrups to be more uncomfortable than walking, and he dropped to the ground while letting the Indian continue toting his pack. They camped that night in the upper part of the valley called <name type="place" key="Shoshone Cove">Shoshoni Cove</name>. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> himself boiled, in a small amount of water, the whites' last pound of flour and divided it among his men, <name type="person" key="Cameahwait">Cameahwait</name>, and a lesser chief. The next morning no one had anything to eat. Faced with the general discontent, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> sent <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name> and <name type="person" key="Shields, John">Shields</name> out for game, though they had not been able to produce anything during the past few days. The sight of 
these two strangers riding with their rifles toward an unannounced destination sent a flutter of alarm through the gathering. More than half the people retreated toward the pass, leaving only twenty-eight men and three women to follow <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, who was riding double again, and <name type="person" key="Cameahwait">Cameahwait</name> toward the assigned meeting place with <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>.</p>
               <p>
Before this remnant was well started, a <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name> who had been spying on <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name> charged up full speed. A deer, fresh killed! A headlong race for breakfast followed. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> Indian companion lashed the horse they were riding at every jump. Unbearably jostled, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> demanded a halt, whereupon the Indian jumped off and raced ahead on foot to the feast. By the time <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> arrived, <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name> had gutted the kill and had rolled the viscera aside preparatory to cutting up the carcass. Compassion struggling with disgust, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether</name> described a scene that has become infamous 
in pioneer literature. "each one had a peice of some description and all eating most ravenously. Some were eating the kidnies the melt [spleen] and liver and the blood running from the corners of their mouths, others were in a similar situation with the paunch and guts but the exuding substance in this case from their lips was of a different discription. . . . I really did not untill now think that human nature ever presented itself in a shape so nearly allyed to the brute creation." Actually the episode was not exceptional, except perhaps for the speed of the gulping. Centuries of necessity had conditioned the <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name> to devour every bit of a slain animal, down to the soft parts of the hoof. Moreover, as <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> neglected to point out, the half-starved people did not attempt to seize the meat of the deer's body. They stood aside until <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> had reserved a quarter for himself and his men and had turned the balance over to <name type="person" key="Cameahwait">Cameahwait</name> to be divided among his people.<ref target="n1325" n="25"/>
               </p>
               <p>
As the procession neared the lower end of <name type="place" key="Shoshone Cove">Shoshoni Cove</name> the Indians took <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> cocked military hat from him and in its place draped over his head and shoulders <name type="person" key="Cameahwait">Cameahwait's</name> splendid tippet of one hundred and forty ermine skins.<ref target="n1326" n="26"/>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> men were also adorned with native headpieces. Clearly the additions were to make them look so much like important <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name> that if the <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name> attacked, the Americans would likely be among the first to be killed. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> reacted to the insult (or precaution, depending on the viewpoint) by handing <name type="person" key="Cameahwait">Cameahwait</name> his rifle: You don't trust me. Very well, shoot me if an enemy strikes.</p>
               <p>
His position, he realized, was growing precarious. If the boats were not at the junction when the cavalcade arrived, the suspicious, taut-strung Indians might well vanish into mountainous areas where he could not find them again. Earnestly he tried, through <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard's</name> hand talk (and some of his own, for he had picked up many of the gestures through observation), to arouse enough interest in the boats that the Indians would want to wait for them. Again he told <name type="person" key="Cameahwait">Cameahwait</name> a woman of their band was with the whites. He expatiated on the merchandise that would soon be available for barter. <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name> sagaciously added that not all the newcomers would be white; among them was an amazing black man with short, curly hair. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> then tried to clinch the argument by saying that even if the boats weren't there, a magic message from the approaching whites would be. He sent <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name> to the junction to fetch it. It was, of course, the note he had left at the junction, telling <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> to wait there for him. Staring at his own handwriting, he declared to the ring of Indians around him that the boats would arrive at the forks on the morrow. <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name> would return to meet them. To prove he was telling the truth and that no ambush was being prepared, he would give a knife and some beads to any young Indian brave enough to go with the hunter to check on whom he met. Meanwhile <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, <name type="person" key="Shields, John">Shields</name>, and <name type="person" key="McNeal, Hugh">McNeal</name> would stay as hostages with the main body of the <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name>.<ref target="n1327" n="27"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Reluctantly the Indians agreed to the proposal. There was little sleep for anyone that night. Tossing and turning under his mosquito netting, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> tormented himself with fears that <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had found the <name type="place" key="Beaverhead (Jefferson) River">Jefferson</name>/<name type="place" key="Beaverhead (Jefferson) River">Beaverhead</name> unnavigable and had stopped far below the junction, in which case <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> could never again persuade the <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name> he spoke honestly. As for the Indians, most of them secreted themselves in the brush, suspicious still that an attack was coming.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>
The boats were, in fact, traveling very slowly. The reasons were as they had been for several days—dense brush on the stream-banks, gravel bars that grounded the dugouts, treacherous footing, intense daytime heat and cold nights. The stream curved inordinately, so that each day the fleet traveled many miles but went forward very few. Again and again the soldiers begged <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> to let them travel by land, packing their supplies and essential trade goods on their backs as they had done at the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">Great Falls</name>. Lacking word from <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> about what lay ahead, he always refused.</p>
               <p>
As they neared the forks, they heard <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard's</name> voice shouting at them. Soon they saw him, dressed like a native and accompanied not by one but by several Indians curious to see the black marvel and the <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name> woman they had heard about. At the same time <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name> lost the impassivity that <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> had thought was one of her characteristics. Dancing with the most extravagant joy, she pointed to the Indians and sucked on her finger to indicate they were of her native band. Delighted by the sights, the Indians began singing boisterously.<ref target="n1328" n="28"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Then one of the riders drew away from the flotilla and galloped back to the camp in <name type="place" key="Shoshone Cove">Shoshoni Cove</name>, crying that the tab-ha-bones, not the <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name>, were on the way. The waiting Indians whooped, <name type="person" key="Cameahwait">Cameahwait</name> hugged <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> again, and this time <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> hugged back.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="notes" type="notes">
            <head rend="center">Notes</head>
            <div type="section">
               <note xml:id="n1301" n="1">II, 230. <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>, 264. From <name type="place" key="White Bear Islands">White Bear Islands</name> to <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Three Forks of the">Three Forks</name>: II, 232–79; <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>, 263–86; <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> in Quaife, 247–53.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1302" n="2">See chart of distances in II, 233–34.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1303" n="3">DeVoto, <hi rend="italic">Course</hi>, 483–90, diligently points out the shortcuts the Corps might have taken if <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jeffersons'</name> instructions, the rigid set of the captains' minds, and the hope of horses had not held them to the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1304" n="4">II, 244.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1305" n="5">Modern travelers coming upcanyon on waters impounded behind a dam are treated, at a little distance into the gorge, to an optical illusion. Slabs of rock running at right angles into the water from both canyon walls seem to meet and form a solid barrier. As one draws nearer, the slabs appear to separate, like sliding doors pulling apart. Tour guides call the spot the <name type="place" key="Gates of the Rocky Mountains">Gates of the Mountains</name>, and it is an intriguing sight. There is 
no indication, however, that <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> was talking about the illusion. To him the whole splendid gorge was the entrance into (or exit from) the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rockies</name>–a gate on a scale appropriate to the rest of the setting. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> on the name is in II, 248.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1306" n="6">Temperature charts in <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>, III, 858.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1307" n="7">
                  <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>, I, 280.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1308" n="8">The pause at <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Three Forks of the">Three Forks</name>: II, 275–81; <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>, I, 284–11, 290; <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> in Quaife, 253–55.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1309" n="9">Allen, 161, for <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> figure of forty-one miles between meridians. Ibid., 288, for the assumption the captains knew the proper location of <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Three Forks of the">Three Forks</name> when they arrived there. Well, sort of. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> maps of the river from <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name> to <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Three Forks of the">Three Forks</name>, which were quite accurate, showed two sides of a wobbly triangle. By drawing a hypotenuse between the fort, whose longitude was known, and the forks and by keeping the figure forty-one in mind (actually it wasn't all that accurate) he could reach a rough approximation of the forks' longitude. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> says, meanwhile, that he took observations to determine both the latitude and longitude of the site, but he does not record the figures for longitude (II, 284–85). The mathematics connected with lunar observations for longitude arc complex, and <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> generally jotted down the figures for solution by experts in the East. (They found his figures muddled.) At best, then, the captains had only an educated guess about how far west they really were. It was enough, however, to let them know the ocean was a lot farther off than they had been supposing.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1310" n="10">From <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Three Forks of the">Three Forks</name> to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> crossing of the divide: II, 286–336; <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>, II, 290–322; <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> in Quaife, 262–64; <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse</name> in VII, 132–35. <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> and <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse</name> were with <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1311" n="11">Thomas James, 29–35 and 46, gives a contemporary account of <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter's</name> and <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard's</name> (<name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer's</name>) deaths. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> statement that <name type="person" key="Weiser, Peter">Wiser</name> had been killed is in Jackson, <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, II, 639.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1312" n="12">II, 290.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1313" n="13">
                  <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> on the wrong fork: II, 312–17; <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> in Quaife, 258–60.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1314" n="14">II, 324.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1315" n="15">II, 326.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1316" n="16">II, 330. Bakeless, <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>
                  </hi>, 233–36. Ronda, 139–40.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1317" n="17">
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> first crossing of the divide: II, 333–56; <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>, II, 315. When rewriting the journals under <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> direction, <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name> omitted <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> remark about attaining one of his great objectives. Perhaps they, too, wondered about how long <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> had actually been committed to this goal.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1318" n="18">Allen, 292.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1319" n="19">
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> second crossing of the divide: II, 337–51, passim.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1320" n="20">II, 353, 354.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1321" n="21">II, 366.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1322" n="22">
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name> background: Trenholm and Carley, 3–40.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1323" n="23">II, 342.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1324" n="24">II, 366.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1325" n="25">II, 355. <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>, II, 349.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1326" n="26">The tippet: II, 356, 378; <name type="person" key="Peale, Charles Wilson">Charles Peale</name> to <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, January 29, 1808, in Jackson, <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, II, 439. Unlike many objects collected by <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, <name type="person" key="Cameahwait">Cameahwait's</name> tippet survived. A wax statue of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> wearing it stood for many years in <name type="person" key="Peale, Charles, Wilson">Peale's</name>
                  <name type="place" key="Philadelphia, Pa.">Philadelphia</name> museum. Charles de Saint-Mémin 
painted a picture of the explorer in the same tippet. Cutright, <hi rend="italic">Pioneering Naturalists</hi>, facing 240.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1327" n="27">II, 356–58.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1328" n="28">
                  <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> to <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>, Jackson, <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, II, 518–19.</note>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <note xml:id="n13unnumbered" n="*" type="footnote">Since <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> time, geographers have decided the true headwater of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> is <name type="place" key="Red Rock Creek">Red Rock Creek</name>, the fork the Corps did not follow to the divide.</note>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.lavender.01.12" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.lavender.01.00" type="contents"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.lavender.01.14" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
