<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.sup.ronda.01.afterword">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Lewis &amp; Clark among the Indians</title>
            <title type="sub" level="a">Afterword</title>
            <title type="sub"/>
            <author>James P. Ronda</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2005</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               
               
               
               
               
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title level="m" type="main">Lewis &amp; Clark among the Indians</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">Afterword</title>
               <author>James P. Ronda</author>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1984</date>
               <idno type="ISBN">0-8032-8990-1</idno>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Supplements</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Texts</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-11-01</date>
            <date>2005-02-01</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>File splitting Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="afterword" type="chapter" n="afterword">
            <quote>
               <lg type="linegroup">
                  <l>"We have been to the great lake of the west and are now on our return to my</l>
                  <l>country. I have seen all my red children quite to that great lake and talked with</l>
                  <l>them, and taken them by the hand in the name of their great father the Great</l>
                  <l>Chief of all the white people."</l>
               </lg>
               <bibl>—<name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark</name>, 1806</bibl>
            </quote>
            <div type="section">
               <p>
On a cold rainy day in mid-May 1806, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name> sat in camp along the <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Clearwater River</name> and wondered where the Indians were. For the first time in many weeks no <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perces</name>
                  </ref> came to talk, trade, or stare at the bearded strangers.<ref target="n1001" n="1"/> It was almost two years to the day since the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> expedition had begun its western venture. Those years had been filled with a native presence that bound Indians and explorers together in a common struggle to survive. Formal conferences, personal friendships, and chance meetings all bridged the cultural divide. Indians were so much a part of the life of the expedition that their absence was worthy of note. When no Indians were present as actors and audience, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> felt strangely alone.</p>
               <p>
Whether written as simple fact or out of belief to be free from inquisitive neighbors, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> observation reveals something fundamental about western exploration in general and <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Thomas Jefferson's</name> Corps of Discovery in particular. Exploration was a cooperative endeavor requiring substantial information and support from the Indians. The Indians shaped the exploratory effort by their very presence on the land. They were people to be reckoned with, whether as potential sources of aid or as possible enemies. No latter-day Coronado or Champlain could ignore them. The anticipated behavior of the Indians was a decisive factor in the choice of equipment, personnel, routes, camp rules, and even ultimate destination. Whatever the official objectives, explorers carefully considered their presence.</p>
               <p>
But we need to measure more than explorer's reactions to a passive population. Indians were active participants in exploration, as the first comers to the land and, later, as guides for Euro-Americans. To a vast enterprise they lent their intelligence, skill, and nerve. Certainly the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> expedition benefited greatly from the Indians' knowledge and support. Maps, route information, food, horses, openhanded friendship—all gave the Corps of Discovery the edge that spelled the difference between success and failure. The presence of <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name> on the expedition's roster is only the barest hint of what Indian support meant to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> "darling project." That roster should also include names like <name type="person" key="Big White (Sheheke)">Sheheke</name>, <name type="person" key="Cameahwait">Cameahwait</name>, <name type="person" key="Old Toby">Old Toby</name>, <name type="person" key="Tetoharsky">Tetoharsky</name>, <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">Twisted Hair</name>, and <name type="person" key="Apash Wyakaikt">Flint Necklace</name>. There needs to be a place for those unnamed <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Shoshoni.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name>
                  </ref> women who carried expedition baggage over <name type="place" key="Lemhi Pass">Lemhi Pass</name> as well as for countless Indians who traded food and affection. As guides, packers, interpreters, and cartographers, native Americans were essential to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> achievement.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> left <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> filled with apprehension about encounters with hostile Indians. But what emerged over nearly two and a half years of western travel was an atmosphere of friendship and mutual trust between men and women who shared a common frontier life. Indians and explorers stood together in the rituals of hunting, holidays, and horse racing. Sex, sports, and music were simple pleasures that united strangers. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> admitted as much when he wrote, "So long have our men been accustomed to a friendly intercourse with the natives, that we find it difficult to impress on their minds the necessity of always being on guard with rispect to them."<ref target="n1002" n="2"/> The assertion that the Corps of Discovery acted like "a conquering army" of hungry imperialists does not square with either the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> record or the larger history of North American exploration.<ref target="n1003" n="3"/>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> neither enslaved Indians as did DeSoto nor pillaged pueblos as did Coronado. Stealing a canoe from <name type="person" key="Coboway">Coboway</name> and tricking <name type="person" key="Cameahwait">Cameahwait</name> stand out in the journal notes because they were exceptional acts, not typical of the captains and their crew.</p>
               <p>
The typical patterns of friendship and sharing that generally characterized Indian-expedition relations were not the result of any special nobility of character on either side of the cultural divide. Native hospitality was both genuine and useful as tribal people sought trade or attempted to manipulate the expedition for personal ends. For their part, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> recognized the necessity of Indian cooperation. There were undeniable moments of swagger, bluster, and arrogance, but more often than not good sense and patience won the day. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> once bragged that he could have tomahawked terrified <name type="native_nation" key="Umatilla Indians">Umatillas</name>, but he did not do the deed. Despite angry threats, no member of the expedition put the torch to mat lodges at <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The Dalles</name>. And <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> would not allow <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">George Drouillard</name> and the <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph and Reubin">Field brothers</name> to shoot unarmed <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians, Piegan">Piegans</name> in the heat of the <name type="place"
                        key="Two Medicine River (Main or South Branch Marias River)">Two Medicine</name> fray. For most of the journey there was mutual respect born of expediency. That respect and friendship was genuine nonetheless. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> left behind among many Indians a legacy of nonviolent contact. Those who came later enjoyed that legacy and too often betrayed it.</p>
               <p>
If expedition-Indian personal relations were amiable, success did not come so easily when <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> ventured into diplomatic waters. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> claimed that the swivel gun he gave to the <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> chief <name type="person" key="Le Borgne (One Eye)">Le Borgne</name> had spoken in thunder to "all the nations we had seen."<ref target="n1004" n="4"/> But what the gun said and how its report was answered depended on circumstances far beyond the expedition's control. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> believed that official diplomacy was a simple matter of rearranging Indian patterns to suit the needs of the new nation. Proclaiming American sovereignty, establishing trade connections, and constituting delegations to visit <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> all seemed goals within each reach. Who could deny the rationality of intertribal peace or a united front against common enemies? But when the captains sought to implement those policies, they met the often unyielding realities of village and band politics. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> ill-considered attempt to forge a villager alliance against the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name>
                  <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> illustrates the depth of their ignorance. The explorers comprehended neither river economics nor plains politics. In a world where "peace" meant "truce" and where warriors fought one day and traded the next, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> were simply unable and sometimes unwilling to face the facts of native life.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> Indian diplomacy failed in part because the explorers were blind to those western facts of life. But the failure of the villager alliance and the promises of intertribal peace extracted at so many councils came from something more fundamental than naive optimism. What seemed failure for the captains was often success for the chiefs. It was more than inept policy and cultural arrogance that kept federal goals just out of reach. When <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> came into the West and Pacific Northwest, native political sovereignty and autonomy were still potent realities. Men like <name type="person" key="Le Borgne (One Eye)">Le Borgne</name>, <name type="person" key="Cameahwait">Cameahwait</name>, and <name type="person" key="Broken Arm">Broken Arm</name> enjoyed genuine power. They and their counselors could make decisions without bowing to the dictates of faraway white fathers. Despite <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> rhetoric, western Indians were not "our red children." Rather, they were mature adults with a substantial measure of freedom to choose those parts of the American program that best suited their own needs. Diplomacy during the journey was ceremony and talk among equals, even if <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> did not always recognize that fact. If the captains failed to persuade the Indians to become children of a distant father, it was because the Indians still had the power to accept American guns whie rejecting less useful gifts.</p>
               <p>
Bernard DeVoto once wrote that the records of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> expedition amounted to "the first detailed account of whatever length, of the western tribes."<ref target="n1005" n="5"/> The ethnographic legacy has proven to be one of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> most durable contributions, although its value was not plain at the time of the expedition. Guided by <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name> precise instructions and their own curiosity, expedition ethnographers amassed a virtual library of information about the Indians. Journal entries, vocabularies, drawings, maps, artifacts, population estimates—all hold priceless knowledge about Indian ways from the great river to the western sea. When <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Nicholas Biddle</name> first examined that ethnographic data, he felt some reason to apologize for its inadequacies. "Those who first visit the ground," wrote the Philadelphian," can only be expected to furnish sketches, rude and imperfect."<ref target="n1006" n="6"/> But <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle's</name> evaluation missed the mark. The expedition gathered far more than "rude and imperfect" records. In their writing, drawing, and collecting they managed to capture an essential part of American life on the edge of profound change.</p>
               <p>
In 1821 an obscure North West Company mariner named Peter Corney wrote, "By the journey of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captains Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> across the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky mountains</name> to the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific Ocean</name>, the whole of that western region is now laid open."<ref target="n1007" n="7"/> It was more than rivers and mountains that were laid open to view. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> were part of an expansionist movement that steadily brought traders, bureaucrats, ranchers, and farmers into <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>, <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Shoshoni.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name>
                  </ref>, <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref>, and <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookan</name> homelands. "We were happy when he [the white man] first came," explained the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Flathead.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Flathead</name>
                  </ref> chief <name type="person" key="Charlot">Charlot</name>. "We first thought he came from the light; but he comes like the dusk of evening now, not like the dawn of morning. He comes like a day that has passed, and night enters our future with him."<ref target="n1008" n="8"/> But that night had not yet come in 1806. In tales repeated in lodge and tepee, in the faces of children paler than their brothers and sisters, in cherished flags and medals, and in individual memories now lost, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> seemed part of the dawn. They appeared as the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Shoshoni.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshonis</name>
                  </ref> described them—"children of the Great Spirit" who offered dazzling gifts. That the coming day would bring other, duller lights was a scene not yet revealed to <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark</name> and <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name>, much less to men like <name type="person" key="Cameahwait">Cameahwait</name> and <name type="person" key="Yelleppit">Yelleppit</name>. Having shared a moment in history, each slipped away to wonder about the fate of the other.

</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="section">
            <head rend="center">Abbreviations</head>
            <p>
B A E       Bureau of American Ethnology</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">Field Notes.</hi>        Osgood, Ernest, S., ed. <hi rend="italic">The Field Notes of <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain William Clark</name>, 1803–1805.</hi> New Haven: Yale University Press, 1964.</p>
            <p>
Gass, <hi rend="italic">Journal.</hi>        <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass, Patrick</name>. <hi rend="italic">A Journal of the Voyages and Travels of a Corps of Discovery.</hi> Edited by <name type="person" key="McKeehan, David">David McKeehan</name>. 1807. Reprint, with preface by Earle R. Forrest. Minneapolis: Ross and Haines, 1958.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal.</hi>        Quaife, Milo M., ed. <hi rend="italic">The Journals of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Meriwether Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Sergeant John Ordway</name>.</hi> Madison: Historical Society of Wisconsin, 1916.</p>
            <p>
Thw.       Thwaites, Reuben G., ed. <hi rend="italic">The Original Journals of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition.</hi> 8 vols. New York: Dodd, Mead &amp; Co., 1904–1905.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal.</hi>        "The Journal of <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Private Joseph Whitehouse</name>." In Thw. 7:29–190.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="notes" type="notes">
            <head rend="center">Notes</head>
            <note xml:id="n1001" n="1">Thw. 5:44.</note>
            <note xml:id="n1002" n="2">Ibid. 4:89–90.</note>
            <note xml:id="n1003" n="3">William Nichols, "<name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Probe the Heart of Darkness," <hi rend="italic">American Scholar</hi> 49 (1979–80): 97.</note>
            <note xml:id="n1004" n="4">Thw. 5:343.</note>
            <note xml:id="n1005" n="5">Bernard DeVoto, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Journals of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>
               </hi> (Boston: Houghton Mifflin Co., 1953), p. lii.</note>
            <note xml:id="n1006" n="6">
               <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>-Coues, <hi rend="italic">History,</hi> 2:762.</note>
            <note xml:id="n1007" n="7">Peter Corney, <hi rend="italic">Voyages in the Northern Pacific, 1813–1818</hi> (1821; reprint, Fairfield, Washington: Ye Galleon Press, 1965), p. 91.</note>
            <note xml:id="n1008" n="8">Frederick W. Turner III, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Portable North American Indian Reader</hi> (New York: Viking Press, 1974), pp. 253–54.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.ronda.01.09" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.ronda.01.00" type="contents"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.ronda.01.appendix" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
