<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-08-08">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
August 8, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 8</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">June 10–September 26, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1987</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">152-153, 283-286</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">347</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">264</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
         <geoDecl datum="WGS" xml:id="lc.geo.1806-08-08.01">
            <placeName/>
            <geo>48.1333 -103.6333</geo>
            <note>The party camped in Williams County, several miles southwest of Williston, ND. Remained at this camp until 08-10.</note>
         </geoDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc/>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-12-09</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1806-08-08">August 8, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-08-08.01" n="lc.geo.1806-08-08.01">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Friday August 8th 1806.</hi>
                     <ref target="n37080801" n="1"/>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
Beleiving from the recent appearances about the fire which we past last evening that <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt Clark</name> could be at no great distance below I set out early; the wind 〈by〉 heard from the N. E. but by the force of the oars and currant we traveled at a good rate untill 10 A. M. by which time we reached the center of the beaver bends about 8 ms. by water and 3 by land above the entrance of <name type="place" key="Little Muddy (White Earth) River">White earth river</name>.<ref target="n37080802" n="2"/>    not finding <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name> I knew not what calculation to make with rispect to his halting and therefore determined to proceed as tho' he was not before me and leave the rest to the chapter of accedents.    at this place I found a good beach for the purpose of drawing out the perogue and one of the canoes which wanted corking and reparing.    the men with me have not had leasure since we left the West side of the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky mountains</name> to dress any skins or make themselves cloaths and most of them are therefore extreemly bare. I therefore determined to halt at this place untill the perogue and canoe could be repared and the men dress skins and make themselves the necessary cloathing.    we encamped on the N. E. side of the river;<ref target="n37080803" n="3"/> we found the Musquetoes extreemly troublesome but in this rispect there is but little choise of camps from hence down to <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>.    from this place to the <name type="place" key="Little Missouri (E-mâh-tark',-Ah'-zhah) River">little Missouri</name> there is an abundance of game    I shall therefore when I leave this place travel at my leasure and avail myself of every opportunity to collect and dry meat untill I provide a sufficient quantity for our voyage not knowing what provision <name type="person" key=" Clark, William">Capt C.</name> has made in this rispect. I formed a camp unloaded the canoes and perogue, had the latter and one of the canoes drawn out to dry, fleased what meat we had collected and hung it on poles in the sun, after which the men busied themselves in dressing skins and making themselves cloaths. <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name> killed 2 Elk and a deer this evening.    the air is cold yet the Musquetoes continue to be troublesome.—

</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-08-08.02" n="lc.geo.1806-08-08.01">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Sunday 8th August 1806</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
A cool windey morning    I derected <name type="person" key="Shields, John">Shields</name> and <name type="person" key="Gibson, George">Gibson</name> to turn out and hunt this morning.    at 8 A. M. <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Sergt. N. Pryor</name>
                  <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name>, <name type="person" key="Hall, Hugh">hall</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Windsor, Richard">Windsor</name> Came down the river in two Canoes made of Buffalow Skins.<ref target="n37080804" n="4"/>
                  <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Sergt. Pryor</name> informed me that the Second night after he parted with me<ref target="n37080805" n="5"/> on the river <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Rochejhone</name> he arived about 4 P M on the banks of a large Creek which contained no running water.<ref target="n37080806" n="6"/>    he halted to let the horses graze dureing which time a heavy Shower of rain raised the Creek so high that Several horses which had Stragled across the Chanel of this Creek was obliged to Swim back.    here he deturmined to Continue all night it being in good food for the horses. In the morning he could See no horses.    in lookg about their Camp they discovered Several tracks within 100 paces of their Camp, which they pursued found where they had Caught and drove off all the horses.    they prosued on five miles the Indians<ref target="n37080807" n="7"/> there divided into two parties.    they Continued in pursute of the largest party five miles further finding that there was not the Smallest Chance of overtakeing them, they returned to their Camp and packed up their baggage on their backs and Steared a N. E. course to the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">River Rochejhone</name> which they Struck at <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="place" key="Pompeys Pillar (Pompy's Tower)">pompys Tower</name>,</hi> there they killed a Buffalow Bull and made a Canoe in the form and shape of the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">mandans</name> &amp; <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Ricares</name> [<hi rend="italic">NB: <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name> killed Buf. &amp; made Canoe</hi>] (the form of a bason) and made in the following manner. Viz: 2 Sticks of 1¼ inch diameter is tied together So as to form a round hoop of the Size you wish the canoe, or as large as the Skin will allow to cover, two of those hoops are made one for the top or brim and the for the bottom the deabth you wish the Canoe, then Sticks of the Same Size are Crossed at right angles and fastened with a throng to each hoop and also where each Stick Crosses each other.    then the Skin when green is drawn tight over this fraim and fastened with throngs to the brim or outer hoop So as to form a perfect bason.    one of those Canoes will carry 6 or 8 Men and their loads. Those two Canoes are nearly the Same size 7 feet 3 inches diamieter &amp; 16 inchs deep 15 ribs or Cross Sticks in each. <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Sergt. Pryor</name> informs me that the Cause of his building two Canoes was for fear of ones meating with Some accedent in passing down the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">rochejhone</name> a river entirely unknown to either of them by which means they might loose their guns and amunition and be left entirely destitute of the means of precureing food.    he informed me that they passed through the worst parts of the rapids &amp; Shoals in the river without takeing a drop of water, and waves raised from the hardest winds dose not effect them.    on the night of the 26th ulto: the night after the horses had been stolen a Wolf bit <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Sergt. Pryor</name> through his hand when asleep, and this animal was So vicious as to make an attempt to Seize <name type="person" key="Windsor, Richard">Windsor</name>, when <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name> fortunately Shot him.<ref target="n37080808" n="8"/>
                  <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Sergt. Pryers</name> hand was nearly recovered. The Country through which <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">St. Pryor</name> Passed after he parted with me is a broken open Country.    he passed one Small river which I have Called <name type="place" key="Pryor Creek">Pryors river</name> which [<hi rend="italic">NB: rises</hi>] in a Mtn. to the South of <name type="place" key="Pompeys Pillar (Pompy's Tower)">Pompys tower</name>.<ref target="n37080809" n="9"/>    The note I left on a pole at the Mouth of the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">River Rochejhone</name>
                  <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Sergt. Pryor</name> concluding that <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name> had passed took the note and brought it with him. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt Lewis</name> I except will be certain of my passing by the Sign which I have made and the encampment imediately in the point. <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Sergt. Pryor</name> bing anxious to overtake me Set out Some time before day this morning and forgot his Saddlebags which contains his papers &amp;c.<ref target="n37080810" n="10"/> I Sent <name type="person" key="Bratton, William E.">Bratten</name> back with him in Serch of them. I also Sent <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name> over to hunt the bottom on the opposit Side. <name type="person" key="Shields, John">Shields</name> and <name type="person" key="Gibson, George">Gibson</name> returned at 10 A. M. with the Skins and part of the flesh of three deer which they had killed in this bottom. I derected them to take one of the Skin Canoes and proceed down to the next bottom and untill my arival which will be this evening if <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Sergt. Pryor</name> returns in time. My object is to precure as many Skins as possible for the purpose of purchaseing Corn and Beans of the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>.    as we have now no article of Merchindize nor horses to purchase with, our only resort is Skins which those people were very fond the winter we were Stationed near them. after dark <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Sergt. Pryor</name> returned with his Saddlebeggs &amp;c.    they were much further up than he expected.

</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-08-08.03" n="lc.geo.1806-08-08.01">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Friday 8th August 1806.    a fair morng.    we Set out as usal and procd. on verry well untill 10 A. M.    then not overtaking <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name> &amp; party <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name> concluded to halt and dry our baggage dress Some Skins as the party is nearly naked and repair the canoes. So we Camped at a bottom on N. Side    drew out the white perogue after unloading and my canoe as they leaked    the musquetoes troublesome at this Camp. <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name> killed two deer.—


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-08-08.04" n="lc.geo.1806-08-08.01">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Friday 8th:</hi>    We had a fine clear cool morning with some white frost; proceeded on early and in a short time past one of <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain Clarke's</name> camps.<ref target="n37080811" n="11"/> At nine o'clock we halted to repair the periogue,<ref target="n37080812" n="12"/> and to dress some skins to make ourselves clothing. The musquitoes are more troublesome here than at any place since we left the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">falls of the Missouri</name>. A party of men went out to hunt and killed some elk and deer; the rest were employed in dressing deer and cabre skins.


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n37080801" n="1">Here end the daily entries in Codex L: the remainder consists of weather diaries for June, July, and August (through the twelfth), 1806. Immediately following this entry is a notation by <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>: "a Suplt. to Come in here." The reference is to Codex Lb, which contains <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> last few daily entries; see <ref n="v02.appendix.c" type="related">Appendix C.</ref> vol. 2. On the end flyleaf is the following notation in <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> hand (see <ref n="1806-08-12" type="related">August 12, 1806</ref>, for information about these men):
<table rows="2" cols="3">
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                        <name type="person" key="Dickson, Joseph">Joseph Dickson</name>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="data" rows="2" cols="1">}</cell>
                     <cell role="data" rows="2" cols="1">from the <name type="place" key="Illinois">Illinois</name> the former<lb/>
the latter from <name type="place" key="Boone's Settlement">Boon's settlement</name>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                        <name type="person" key="Hancock, Forrest">Forrest Hancock</name>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="n37080802" n="2">In <name type="place" key="Williams County, N. Dak.">Williams</name> and <name type="place" key="McKenzie County, N. Dak.">McKenzie</name> counties, <name type="place" key="North Dakota">North Dakota</name>, above present <name type="place" key="Williston, N. Dak.">Williston</name>, "<name type="place" key="Little Muddy (White Earth) River">White earth river</name>" is present <name type="place" key="Little Muddy (White Earth) River">Little Muddy River</name>, in <name type="place" key="Williams County, N. Dak.">Williams County</name>; see <ref n="1805-04-21" type="related">April 21, 1805</ref>. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 35; MRC map 59.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37080803" n="3">In <name type="place" key="Williams County, N. Dak.">Williams County</name>, several miles southwest of <name type="place" key="Williston, N. Dak.">Williston</name>. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 35; MRC map 59.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37080804" n="4">Probably bullboats, which <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Pryor</name> and his companions would have seen among the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name>; see <ref n="1804-10-06" type="related">October 6, 1804</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37080805" n="5">
               <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Pryor</name> parted with <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> on July 24, 1806, above present <name type="place" key="Billings, Mont.">Billings</name>, <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>; see the first part of his route on <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> maps 108, 116. The incident he now tells of would have occurred on the night of July 25–26.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37080806" n="6">
               <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Pryor's</name> route probably roughly paralleled present <name type="place" key="Interstate Highway 90">Interstate Highway 90</name>, headed easterly; he may have camped on <name type="place" key="Fly Creek (Big Horn County, Mont.)">Fly Creek</name> in <name type="place" key="Big Horn County, Mont.">Big Horn County</name>, <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>, several miles west of present <name type="place" key="Hardin, Mont.">Hardin</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37080807" n="7">
               <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Pryor</name> and his men were in the country of the <name type="native_nation" key="Crow Indians">Crows</name>, or <name type="native_nation" key="Crow Indians">Absaroke</name> (see <ref n="1804-11-12" type="related">November 12, 1804</ref>), who were renowned as horse thieves.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37080808" n="8">The wolf's behavior suggests rabies, but neither <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Pryor</name> nor <name type="person" key="Windsor, Richard">Windsor</name> contracted the disease, as far as is known.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37080809" n="9">Present <name type="place" key="Pryor Creek">Pryor Creek</name> (see <ref n="1806-07-25" type="related">July 25, 1806</ref>), which rises in the <name type="place" key="Pryor Mountains">Pryor Mountains</name> in <name type="place" key="Big Horn County, Mont.">Big Horn</name> and <name type="place" key="Carbon County, Mont.">Carbon</name> counties, <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> maps 109, 116.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37080810" n="10">There is no indication of what the "papers &amp;c." consisted of, but this is the only hint that <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Pryor</name> may have been keeping a journal, as the sergeants supposedly were required to do. However, the papers may simply have been the letters he was supposed to deliver. Since the entry makes it clear that the papers were recovered, this is not the explanation of <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Pryor's</name> journal not being available.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37080811" n="11">Determination of <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> campsites below the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone</name> is difficult. This was presumably the camp of <ref n="1806-08-04" type="related">August 4, 1806</ref>, in <name type="place" key="McKenzie County, N. Dak.">McKenzie</name> or <name type="place" key="Williams County, N. Dak.">Williams County</name>, <name type="place" key="North Dakota">North Dakota</name>;  see <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> entry of <ref n="1806-08-04" type="related">August 4</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37080812" n="12">In <name type="place" key="Williams County, N. Dak.">Williams County</name>, several miles southwest of <name type="place" key="Williston, N. Dak.">Williston</name>, where they remained until August 10.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-08-07" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-08-09" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
