<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-10-30">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
October 30, 1805</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 5</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">July 28–November 1, 1805</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1989</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">354-358</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">247</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">164</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jw">Joseph Whitehouse</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 11</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of Joseph Whitehouse, May 14, 1804–April 2, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1997</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">377-379</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
         <geoDecl datum="WGS" xml:id="lc.geo.1805-10-30.01">
            <placeName/>
            <geo>45.6693 -121.8912</geo>
            <note>Camped just above the Cascades of the Columbia (Ordway's "Shoote"), on an island in Skamania County, nearly opposite Cascade Locks, Hoodriver County, OR. Remained here until 11-01.</note>
         </geoDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc/>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-07-09</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1805-10-30">October 30, 1805</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-10-30.01" n="lc.geo.1805-10-30.01">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">October 30th Wednesday 1805</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
A Cloudy morning. Some little rain all night, after eating a Slight brackfast of venison we Set out.</p>
               <p>
The rocks project into the river in maney places and have the appearance of haveing fallen from the highe hills    those projected rocks is common &amp; Small Bays below &amp; nitches in the rocks    passed 4 Cascades or Small Streams falling from the mountains on Lard.<ref target="n24103001" n="1"/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <table rows="1" cols="3">
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 70° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">3</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">miles to a point of rocks on the Stard. Side, passed a number<lb/>
of Stumps at Some distance in the Water,</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>	
This part of the river resembles a pond partly dreaned leaving many Stumps bare both in &amp; out of the water, current about 1 mil pr. Hour</p>
               <p>
                  <table rows="2" cols="3">
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 74° W</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">2</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">miles to a point of a timbered bottom on Stard. Side    halted<lb/>
to Dine, killed a Deer &amp; 3 ducks &amp; a Squirel of the Mountains<ref target="n24103002" n="2"/>
                           <lb/>
we can plainly hear the roreing of the grand Shutes below, saw<lb/>
the large Buzard white head and part of the wings white</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">West</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">4</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">miles to the mouth of a river on th Stard. Side of about 60<lb/>
yards wide    passed Std. point &amp; many large rocks promis-<lb/>
cuissly in the river both above and below this river a large<lb/>
Sand bar on the Lard Side</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>	
The bottom above the river is about ¾ of a mile wide and rich, Some deer &amp; bear Sign—    rained moderately all day we are wet and cold. Saw Several Specis of wood which I never Saw before, Some resembling Beech &amp; others Poplar.—    Day dark and disagreeable.</p>
               <p>
                  <table rows="3" cols="3">
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 45° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  2</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">miles to a large rock in the river, passed Several rocks and a<lb/>
large Sand bar on the Lard. Sid    verry large rock near the<lb/>
Stard. Side    High Mounts. on each Side, ruged and covd.<lb/>
with a variety of timber Such as Pine Spruce Seder Cotton<lb/>
wood Oake</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 30 W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                           <hi rend="underline">  4</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">miles to a Island, at the Commencement of the grand Shute<lb/>
and the Stard. Side where we Campd.    passed maney large<lb/>
rocks in the river [neither?] in th, a large Creek on the Std.<lb/>
Side at 2 miles, with an Island in the mouth.    passed 3 Islands<lb/>
on the Stard. one on the Lard above 2 Small Islands opsd. to<lb/>
us on which there growes 6 large Pine, 4 rock Islands which<lb/>
almost Chokes up the river—    a deep bay to th Stard. on<lb/>
which the Indians live in 8 large worm Houses    2 ponds back<lb/>
of this on the Stard 1 above the Islands, one on the Lard. side.<lb/>
Several Small rocks—in dift. pts.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">15</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>
I with 2 men proceeded down the river 2 miles on an old Indian parth to view the rapids, which I found impassable for our canoes without a portage, the roade bad    at 1 mile I saw a Town of Houses laterly abandoned<ref target="n24103003" n="3"/> on an elevated Situation opsd. a 2d Shute, returned at dark. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name> and 5 men went to the Town found them kind<ref target="n24103004" n="4"/>    they gave Beries &amp; nuts, but he cd. get nothin from them in the way of Information, the greater part of those people out collecting roots below, rained all the evining    Those people have one gun &amp; maney articles which they have purchased of the white people their food is principally fish
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-10-30.02" n="lc.geo.1805-10-30.01">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">October 30th Wednesday 1805</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
A cool morning, a moderate rain all the last night, after eating a partial brackfast of venison we Set out    passed Several places where the rocks projected into the river &amp; have the appearance of haveing Seperated from the mountains and fallen promiscuisly into the river, Small nitches are formed in the banks below those projecting rocks which is comon in this part of the river, Saw 4 Cascades caused by Small Streams falling from the mountains on the Lard. Side, a remarkable circumstance in this part of the river is, the Stumps of pine trees are in maney places are at Some distance in the river, and gives every appearance of the rivers being damed up below from Some cause which I am not at this time acquainted with, the Current of the river is also verry jentle not exceeding 1½ mile pr. hour and about ¾ of a mile in width. Some rain, we landed above the mouth of a Small river on the Stard. Side<ref target="n24103005" n="5"/> and Dined    <name type="person" key="Shields, John">J. Shields</name> Killed a Buck &amp; <name type="person" key="Labiche, François">Labiech</name> 3 Ducks, here the river widens to about one mile large Sand bar in the middle, a Great [rock] both in and out of the water, large 〈round〉 Stones, or rocks are also permiscuisly Scattered about in the river, this day we Saw Some fiew of the large Buzzard<ref target="n24103006" n="6"/>    <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name> Shot at one, those Buzzards are much larger than any other of ther Spece or the largest Eagle white under part of their wings &amp;c. The bottoms above the mouth of this little river 〈which we Call〉 is rich covered with grass &amp; firn &amp; is about ¾ of a mile wide rich and rises gradually, below the river (which is 60 yards wide above its mouth) the Countery rises with Steep assent.    we call this little river 〈fr Ash〉 <name type="place" key="Wind (Cruzatte's) River (Wash.)">New Timbered river</name> from a Speces of Ash<ref target="n24103007" n="7"/> 〈that wood〉 which grows on its banks of a verry large and different from any we had before Seen, and a timber resembling the beech<ref target="n24103008" n="8"/> in bark 〈&amp; groth〉 but different in its leaf which is Smaller and the tree smaller.    passed maney large rocks in the river and a large creek on the Stard. Side in the mouth of which is an Island,<ref target="n24103009" n="9"/> passed on the right of 3 Islands 〈on〉 near the Stard. Side, and landed on an Island close under the Stard. Side at the head of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Cascades (Great Rapids, Great Shute)">great Shute</name>,<ref target="n24103010" n="10"/> and a little below a village of 8 large houses on a Deep bend on the Stard. Side, and opposit 2 Small Islands imediately in the head of the Shute, which Islands are covered with Pine, maney large rocks also, in the head of the Shute. Ponds back of the houses, and Countrey low for a Short distance. The day proved Cloudy dark and disagreeable with Some rain all day which kept us wet. The Countary a high mountain on each Side thickly Covered with timber, Such as Spruc, Pine, Cedar, Oake Cotton &amp;c. &amp;c.<ref target="n24103011" n="11"/> I took two men and walked down three miles to examine the Shute and river below proceeded along an old Indian path, passd. an old village at 1 mile on an ellevated Situation of    this village contained verry large houses built in a different form from any I had Seen, and laterly abandoned, and the most of the boads put into a pond of water near the village, as I conceived to drown the flees, which was emencely noumerous about the houses—. I found by examonation that we must make a portage of the greater perpotion of our Stores 2½ miles, and the Canoes we Could haul over the rocks, I returned at Dark    <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt Lewis</name> and 5 men had just returned from the village, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Cap L.</name> informed me that he found the nativs kind, they gave him berries, nuts &amp; fish to eate; but he could get nothing from them in the way of information. The greater part of the inhabitants of this village being absent down the river Some distance Colecting roots    Capt. L. Saw one gun and Several articles which must have been precured from the white people.    a wet disagreeable evening, the only wood we could get to burn on this little Island on which we have encamped is the newly discovered <hi rend="italic">Ash,</hi> which makes a tolerable fire.    we made fifteen miles to daye.
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-10-30.03" n="lc.geo.1805-10-30.01">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Wednesday 30th Oct. 1805.    a cloudy morning.    we bought 3 dogs of the Indians and Set out and proceeded on    the River wide and Strait    the current gentle.    the timber thick on each Side. Saw a number of beautiful Springs which came in on each Side.    the narrow bottoms along the Shores are covred with cotten timber and under brush.    the after part of the day rainy and foggy.    one of the hunters killed a Deer    we Saw a great number of Swan<ref target="n24103012" n="12"/> and geese along the Shores. Some turkey bazzards<ref target="n24103013" n="13"/> which had white under their wings. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name> killed a black loon.<ref target="n24103014" n="14"/>    towards evening we heared a great roaring a Short distance a head which we expect is another falls.    we passed the mouth of a River<ref target="n24103015" n="15"/> which came in on the Stard. Side about 40 yards wide    we passed a large Indian village on the Stard. Side a Short distance above the <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Cascades (Great Rapids, Great Shute)">big Shoote</name>.    we Camped<ref target="n24103016" n="16"/> close above the Shoote.    a number of the Savages came to our Camp and Signed to us that they were Surprized to See us    they thought we had rained down out of the clouds. Several of the party went to the village and was treated verry friendly.    we had come about 15 miles this day.—


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-10-30.04" n="lc.geo.1805-10-30.01">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Wednesday 30th.</hi>    The morning was cloudy; the river and country we found much the same as yesterday. At noon we stopped to dine and one of the men<ref target="n24103017" n="17"/> went out and killed a large buck. A number of fine springs come down the hills on the South side; and we passed a small river on the north.<ref target="n24103018" n="18"/> In the evening we came to the head of falls, where there is a large Indian village.<ref target="n24103019" n="19"/> On our way down we saw a great many swans, geese and ducks; and a number of sea otter. There are some small bottoms along the river, with cotton wood<ref target="n24103020" n="20"/> on them, and on the Banks of the river some white oak, ash and hazlenut.<ref target="n24103021" n="21"/> At a distance there are ponds which abound with geese and ducks. It rained hard all day, and we came only 15 miles.


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-10-30.05" n="lc.geo.1805-10-30.01">
            <sp who="jw">
               <speaker>Whitehouse</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Wednesday 30th Oct. 1805</hi>.    cloudy.    we bought 3 dogs of the Indians, and Set out about 7 oClock and proceeded on.    the river verry Strait and wide.    the Timber thick on each Side.    Saw a nomber of beautiful Springs running out of the clifts on the Lard. Side    high hills covred with pine and Spruce.    Some bottoms along the Shores covred with cotton timber, and under brush &amp;c.    the after part of the day rainy and foggey.    one of the hunters killed a Deer.    we Saw a great nomber of Swan and geese, turkey buzzards which had white on their wings &amp;c.    <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name> killed a black loon.    in the evening we arived at another <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Cascades (Great Rapids, Great Shute)">verry bad rapid or falls</name>, above which the River is gentle and wide a nomber of Islands and high rocks &amp;c    one half mile above the falls is a village<ref target="n24103022" n="22"/> of about 10 well looking cabbins covred with bark, Sunk in the ground like those at the narrows above, only these are much larger and verry comfortable, and warm.    these Savages were Surprized to See us    they Signed to us that they thought that we had rained down out of the clouds.    a nomber of the party went in the village, and was treated in a friendly manner    gave fish and the best they had to eat &amp;c.    we went 15 miles and Camped between the village and falls.    continued raining.    high mountains on each Side of the falls &amp;c.    we passed the mouth of a River    came in on the S. Side 50 yds wide.<ref target="n24103023" n="23"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Wednesday October 30th    We had a cool Cloudy morning.    The Natives came early to our Camp and our officers purchased from them 3 more fat dogs.    We set out on our Voyage again, down the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>.    We found the River at a short distance from where we started this morning to be very strait &amp; wide and Trees of different kinds very thick on the Shores, on both sides of the River, and beautiful Springs running from under Clifts of 
Rocks, along the Shores.    We also saw on the South side of the River, a small distance back from it, pine &amp; Spruce Timber; which grew on high hills, and in the bottoms on both shores were Covered with Cotton Wood trees &amp; under brush.—    The latter part of this day we had some Rain &amp; it became foggy.    One of our hunters that had went out this morning, met us with a deer, which he had killed.    We saw a great quantity of Geese &amp; Ducks in the River, &amp; Turkey buzzards which differed in Colour to those we had before seen, having white feathers on their wings.    <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain Clark</name> killed along the Shore a black Raccoon.    In the Evening we arrived at a very bad Rapid or falls, above which, the River run very gentle &amp; was wide, having a number of Islands &amp; high Rocks in it.—    We saw about half a Mile above those falls, an 
Indian Village.—</p>
               <p>
This Village contained about 10 well looking Cabbins, (which were covered with bark) sunk in the ground, as those we had seen at the falls, which I have already described &amp; were much more comfortable &amp; larger sized.    The Indians belonging to this Village made signs to us as we passed along by their village, that they thought &amp; supposed that we had rained down from the Clouds, and seemed very much surprized at seeing us, they not beleiving that we could possibly descended the River at that season of the Year.    A number of our party went to this Indian Village, &amp; the Indians treated them in a very friendly manner, &amp; gave them the best they had to eat.    On each side of these falls, lays very high mountains, and about 2 Miles above them, we passed the mouth of a River which lay on the South side of this River, 
which was about 30 Yards wide &amp; by us called the <name type="place" key="Hood (Labiche's) River">River La Bache</name>.<ref target="n24103024" n="24"/>    We came about 15 Miles this day, &amp; encamped between the Indian Village &amp; the falls.    The Rain continued the greater part of this night.—


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n24103001" n="1">Shown nameless on <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 78. There are a number of creeks near <name type="place" key="Viento, Oreg.">Viento</name>, <name type="place" key="Hood River County, Oreg.">Hood River County</name>, <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon </name>in the right location, including <name type="place" key="Viento Creek">Viento</name>, <name type="place" key="Starvation Creek">Starvation</name>, <name type="place" key="Cabin Creek (Oreg.)">Cabin</name>, <name type="place" key="Warren Creek">Warren</name>, <name type="place" key="Lindsey Creek">Lindsey</name>, and <name type="place" key="Summit Creek">Summit</name> creeks.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24103002" n="2">Probably the western gray squirrel. By mountains <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> does not mean the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky Mountains</name>, but rather the hills along the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>. See <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> entry of <ref n="1806-02-25" type="related">February 25, 1806</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24103003" n="3">This is the area below <name type="place" key="Cascade Range">the Cascades</name> in <name type="place" key="Skamania County, Wash.">Skamania County</name>, <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> texts and maps of the terrain and of Indian settlements in this region cannot be matched with precision to twentieth-century archaeological work. This site appears on figures as "old village" and "a village of large wood houses" and is shown on <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> maps 78 and 79 as "an old village of very large houses." It is the "old village . . . on an ellevated Situation" in the codex entry. Investigators have called it <hi rend="italic">wała'la</hi> and Wahlala ("their lake"). Spier &amp; Sapir, 167; Beckham, 17–19, 27. It appears to have sat very near the Bridge of the Gods.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24103004" n="4">Identified on <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 79 as the <name type="native_nation" key="Yehuh Indians">Yehuh</name>, a Chinookan-language group of whom little is known. The town is variously noted as having eight houses. Investigators have reported it as the <name type="place" key="Y-eh-huh village">Y-eh-huh village</name>. Minor, Toepel, &amp; Beckham, 41–51; Beckham, 17–19, 24–26. It was located downstream from Stevenson and near the Bridge of the Gods.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24103005" n="5">"<name type="place" key="Wind (Cruzatte's) River (Wash.)">New Timbered River</name>" in this entry, but "<name type="place" key="Wind (Cruzatte's) River (Wash.)">Crusats River</name>" after <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Pierre Cruzatte</name> of the party on <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 78 and in the combined course table at <ref n="1805-11-01" type="related">November 1</ref>. An earlier name has been scratched out on the map. It is the present <name type="place" key="Wind (Cruzatte's) River (Wash.)">Wind River</name>, in <name type="place" key="Skamania County, Wash.">Skamania County</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24103006" n="6">The California condor, <hi rend="italic">Gymnogyps californianus</hi> [AOU, 324], now nearly extinct. The last wild condor was captured for care in southern <name type="place" key="California">California</name> in April 1987. Correctly described by <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> as the largest North American bird, it was already known to science, but they were the first to note its presence on the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>. See below, <ref n="1806-02-16" type="related">February 16, 1806</ref>, for a lengthy description, and <ref n="1805-10-31-1" type="related">weather remarks</ref> for October 28 and 29, 1805. Burroughs, 201–3; Cutright (LCPN), 241.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24103007" n="7">Oregon ash, <hi rend="italic">Fraxinus latifolia</hi> Benth. This large tree is the only native species of ash in <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">the Pacific</name> Northwest. It is interesting that the Oregon ash and the red, or Oregon, alder, <hi rend="italic">Alnus rubra</hi> Bong., are mentioned together, since the flora of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> gorge here is an extension of the flora of the western <name type="place" key="Cascade Range">Cascade</name> lowlands, which the explorers were encountering for the first time. The red alder and Oregon ash reach their easternmost distributional limits in southern <name type="place" key="Skamania County, Wash.">Skamania</name> and western <name type="place" key="Klickitat County, Wash.">Klickitat</name> counties. Other species such as Sitka spruce, Oregon white oak, hazelnut, and western redcedar are all part of this lowland flora which extends eastward up the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> gorge. Hitchcock et al., 4:57; Little (CIH), 127-W.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24103008" n="8">The red alder, then new to science. The comparison of this tree with the American beech, <hi rend="italic">Fagus grandifolia</hi> Ehrh., which is commonly found in the eastern United States is appropriate. The bark of the red alder is thin, gray, and smooth, just like the beech and the growth form is somewhat similar. The leaves of the red alder are similar in terms of the toothed margin and shape, but smaller than the beech, which confirms the red alder identification. Little (CIH), 104-W, 125-E; Hitchcock et al., 2:74; Cutright (LCPN), 261 n. 19, 274.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24103009" n="9">Nameless on <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 79; present <name type="place" key="Rock Creek (Klickitat County, Wash.)">Rock Creek</name>, below <name type="place" key="Stevenson, Wash.">Stevenson</name> in <name type="place" key="Skamania County, Wash.">Skamania County</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24103010" n="10">Nearly opposite present <name type="place" key="Cascade Locks, Oreg.">Cascade Locks</name>, <name type="place" key="Hood River County, Oreg.">Hood River County</name>, where they camped until <ref n="1805-11-01" type="related">November 1, 1805</ref>, on an island in <name type="place" key="Skamania County, Wash.">Skamania County</name>. They were just above the <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Cascades (Great Rapids, Great Shute)">Cadcades of the Columbia</name> (the "<name type="place" key="Columbia River, Cascades (Great Rapids, Great Shute)">Great Shute</name>"), now inundated by <name type="place" key="Bonneville Dam">Bonneville Dam</name>. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> maps 78, 79.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24103011" n="11">The spruce is Sitka spruce, <hi rend="italic">Picea sitchensis</hi> (Bong.) Carr., at its eastern distributional limit along the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>. Little (CIH), 42-W. The cottonwood is black cottonwood, the pine is ponderosa pine, and the oak is Oregon white oak.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24103012" n="12">Probably <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> whistling swan, now the tundra swan, <hi rend="italic">Cygnus columbianus</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24103013" n="13">California condor, <hi rend="italic">Gymnogyps californianus</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24103014" n="14">Mentioned this day by <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse</name> but not mentioned by <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, it may be either the red-throated loon, <hi rend="italic">Gavia stellata,</hi> or <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">the Pacific</name> loon, <hi rend="italic">G. arctica pacifica,</hi> of the coastal area. It might also have been the widely dispersed common loon, <hi rend="italic">G. immer</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24103015" n="15">"<name type="place" key="Wind (Cruzatte's) River (Wash.)">Crusat River</name>" to the party, named for member <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Pierre Cruzatte</name>, now <name type="place" key="Wind (Cruzatte's) River (Wash.)">Wind River</name>, <name type="place" key="Skamania County, Wash.">Skamania County</name>, <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24103016" n="16">Until November 1 they camped here, just above <name type="place" key="Cascade Range">the Cascades</name> of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> (<name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway's</name> "Shoote"), on an island in <name type="place" key="Skamania County, Wash.">Skamania County</name>, nearly opposite <name type="place" key="Cascade Locks, Oreg.">Cascade Locks</name>, <name type="place" key="Hood River County, Oreg.">Hood
River County</name>, <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>. The Indians are <name type="native_nation" key="Yehuh Indians">Yehuhs</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24103017" n="17">
               <name type="person" key="Shields, John">Shields</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24103018" n="18">The captains named it <name type="place" key="Wind (Cruzatte's) River (Wash.)">Cruzatte's River</name>, after <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Pierre Cruzatte</name> of the party; it is now <name type="place" key="Wind (Cruzatte's) River (Wash.)">Wind River</name>, <name type="place" key="Skamania County, Wash.">Skamania County</name>, <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24103019" n="19">They camped here, just above <name type="place" key="Cascade Range">the Cascades</name> of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>, on an island in <name type="place" key="Skamania County, Wash.">Skamania County</name>, nearly opposite <name type="place" key="Cascade Locks, Oreg.">Cascade Locks</name>, <name type="place" key="Hood River County, Oreg.">Hood River County</name>, <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>. The nearby Indians were <name type="native_nation" key="Yehuh Indians">Yehuhs</name>, a Chinookan-language people of whom little is known.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24103020" n="20">Probably black cottonwood, <hi rend="italic">Populus trichocarpa</hi> T. &amp; G.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24103021" n="21">Oregon ash, <hi rend="italic">Fraxinus latifolia</hi> Benth., and hazelnut, <hi rend="italic">Corylus cornuta</hi> Marsh. var. <hi rend="italic">californica</hi> (DC.) Sharp.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24103022" n="22">
               <name type="native_nation" key="Yehuh Indians">Yehuhs</name>, a Chinookan-language people of whom little is known.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24103023" n="23">Beginning with "high mountains," these last several sentences are crowded in between 
entries.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24103024" n="24">They had passed <name type="place" key="Hood (Labiche's) River">Hood (Labiche) River</name> the previous day.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-10-29" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-10-31" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
