<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-11-14">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
November 14, 1805</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 6</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">November 2, 1805–March 22, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1990</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">46-48</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">253</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">170-171</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jw">Joseph Whitehouse</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 11</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of Joseph Whitehouse, May 14, 1804–April 2, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1997</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">393</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc/>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-07-21</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1805-11-14">November 14, 1805</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-11-14.01" n="">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Novr. 14th Thursday 1805</hi>
                     <ref target="n25111401" n="1"/>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
Rained last night without intermission and this morning the wind blew hard from the [<hi rend="italic">blank</hi>]    We Could not move, one Canoe was broken last night against the rocks, by the waves dashing her against them in high <hi rend="italic">tide</hi>    about 10 oClock 5 Indians Come up in a Canoe thro emence waves &amp; Swells, they landed and informed us they Saw the 3 men we Sent down yesterday, at Some distance below    Soon after those people Came <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name> one of the 3 men returned and informed us that he had proceeded with his Canoe as far as they Could, for the waves and Could find no white people, or Bay, he Saw a good Canoe harber &amp; 2 Camps of Indians at no great distance below and that those with us had taken his gig &amp; knife &amp;c. which he forcably took from them &amp; they left us, after our treating them well.    The rain Continue all day    all wet as usial, killed only 2 fish to day for the whole Party, at 3 oClock <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name>
                  <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name>
                  <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Jo.</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">R. Fields</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">Frasure</name> Set out down on the Shore to examine if any white men were below within our reach,<ref target="n25111402" n="2"/> they took a empty Canoe &amp; 5 men to Set them around the Point on a Gravelley Beech which <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name> informed was at no great distance below. The Canoe returned at dusk half full of water, from the waves which dashed over in passing the point <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt Lewis</name> is object is also to find a Small Bay as laid down by <name type="person" key="Vancouver, George">Vancouver</name> just out of the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>.<ref target="n25111403" n="3"/>    rained as usial 〈untill〉 all the evening, all wet and disagreeable Situated
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-11-14.02" n="">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">November 14th Thursday 1805</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
rained all the last night without intermition, and this morning.    wind blows verry hard but our Situation is Such that we Cannot tell from what point it comes—    one of our Canoes is much broken by the waves dashing it against the rocks—    5 Indians Came up in a Canoe, thro' the waves, which is verry high and role with great fury—    They made Signs to us that they Saw the 3 men we Sent down yesterday.    only 3 of those Indians landed, the other 2 which was women played off in the waves, which induced me to Suspect that they had taken Something from our men below, at this time one of the men <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name> returnd by land and informed us that those Indians had taken his Gigg &amp; basket, I called to the Squars to land and give back the gigg, which they would not doe untill a man run with a gun, as if he intended to Shute them when they landed, and <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name> got his gig &amp; basket    I then ordered those fellows off, and they verry readily Cleared out    they are of the <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Wahkiakum Indians">War-ci-a-cum</name>
                  </hi> N. <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name> informed us that "it was but a Short distance from where we lay around the point to a butifull Sand beech, which continud for a long ways, that he had found a good harber in the mouth of a creek near 2 Indian Lodges—that he had proceeded in the Canoe as far as he could for the waves, the other two men <name type="person" key="Willard, Alexander">Willard</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name> had proceeded on down["]</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt Lewis</name> concluded to proceed on by land &amp; find if possible the white people the Indians Say is below and examine if a Bay is Situated near the mouth of this river as laid down by <name type="person" key="Vancouver, George">Vancouver</name> in which we expect, if there is white traders to find them &amp;c.    at 3 oClock he Set out with 4 men <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name>
                  <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Jos.</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">Reu. Fields</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">R. Frasure</name>, in one of our large canoes and 5 men to Set them around the point on the Sand beech.    this canoe returned nearly filled with water at Dark which it receved by the waves dashing into it on its return, haveing landed <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name> &amp; his party Safe on the Sand beech. The rain Continues all day all wet. The rain &amp;c. which has continued without a longer intermition than 2 hours at a time for ten days past had distroyd. the robes and rotted 〈a great maney〉 nearly one half of the fiew Clothes the party has, perticularley the leather Clothes,—    fortunately for us we have no very Cold weather as yet and if we have Cold weather before we Can kill &amp; Dress Skins for Clothing 〈we〉 the bulk of the party will Suffer verry much.
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-11-14.03" n="">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Thursday 14th Nov. 1805.    the Storm continues, and obledges us to Stay in this disagreeable harbour with nothing but pounded Sammon to Eat.    one of the men<ref target="n25111404" n="4"/> returned who had been down the River and informed us that they went down to an Indian Village in the bay about 10 miles down but Saw no white people. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name> and four men<ref target="n25111405" n="5"/> Set out by land to go down the River to the mouth.
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-11-14.04" n="">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Thursday 14th.</hi>    We expected last night to have been able to proceed on this morning, but the rain continued, and the river still remained rough; and we are therefore obliged to lie by. About noon one of the 3 men who had 
gone in the canoe, returned having broke the lock of his gun: but the other two went on by land, as the swells ran so high that they could not possibly get the canoe along. About the same time some Indians in a canoe came up the river, and had stolen a gig from the men; but the one who returned got it from them again when he came up. In the evening <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Lewis</name> with 4 men started by land to see if any white people were to be found. The rest 
remained in camp; and the weather continued wet, and the most disagreeable I had ever seen.


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-11-14.05" n="">
            <sp who="jw">
               <speaker>Whitehouse</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Thursday Novemr. 13th<ref target="n25111406" n="6"/>    The storm continued hard during the whole of last night, and this morning we have rainey disagreeable weather.    The waves continued to run very high and we continued at our encampment waiting for moderate weather.    We have nothing to subsist on but fresh fish, &amp; pounded Salmon; which is by no means nourishing.    One of the Men that had went down the River Yesterday [<hi rend="italic">crossed out, illegible</hi>] returned by land.    He informed us that he had been at an Indian Village near the mouth of the River, but had not seen any white people.    <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Lewis</name> &amp; 4 of our party set out in order to go down to that Indian Village by land.    The waves continued high &amp; the Storm continued during the whole of this day.—




</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n25111401" n="1">Two asterisks precede the dateline, but their purpose is unknown.</note>
            <note xml:id="n25111402" n="2">Apparently it is <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> route that is shown as a dotted line on <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 89, ending at <name type="place" key="Cape Disappointment">Cape Disappointment</name> at the words, "<name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt Lewis</name> left the Sea Coast here." <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> moved inland for his return somewhere south of <name type="place" key="Seaview, Wash.">Seaview</name>, <name type="place" key="Pacific County, Wash.">Pacific County</name>, <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>, and arrived at the main party on November 17.</note>
            <note xml:id="n25111403" n="3">
               <name type="place" key="Baker (Haley's) Bay">Baker (Haleys) Bay</name>, just east of <name type="place" key="Cape Disappointment">Cape Disappointment</name> in <name type="place" key="Pacific County, Wash.">Pacific County</name>. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> maps 82, 89. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> had with him on the expedition copies of <name type="person" key="Vancouver, George">Vancouver's</name> maps. <hi rend="italic">Atlas,</hi> 16 n. 21. <name type="person" key="Broughton, William Robert">Broughton</name> of the <name type="person" key="Vancouver, George">Vancouver</name> party named the bay after <name type="person" key="Baker, James">Captain James Baker</name> who had a ship anchored in the bay when <name type="person" key="Broughton, William Robert">Broughton</name> arrived in 1792. Barry (BOC), 398. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> gave it as <name type="place" key="Baker (Haley's) Bay">Haleys</name> after the locals' favorite trader. See <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> second entry of <ref n="1805-11-15" type="related">November 15, 1805</ref>; for <name type="person" key="Hill, Samuel or William Shaler">Haley</name>, see note at <ref n="1805-11-06" type="related">November 6, 1805</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n25111404" n="4">
               <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name>, according to <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n25111405" n="5">
               <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name>, <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Joseph</name> and <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">Reubin Field</name>, and <name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">Frazer</name>, says <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n25111406" n="6">Misdated and clearly the activities of November 14.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-11-13" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-11-15" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
