<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-06-21">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
June 21, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 8</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">June 10–September 26, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1987</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">43-45</biblScope>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">325-326</biblScope>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">242-243</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc/>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-11-03</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date>June 21, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Saturday June 21st 1806.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
We collected our horses early set out on our return to the flatts.    we all felt some mortification in being thus compelled to retrace our steps through this tedious and difficult part of our rout, obstructed with brush and innumerable logs of fallen timber which renders the traveling distressing and even dangerous to our horses.    one of <name type="person" key="Thompson, John B.">Thompson's</name> horses is either choked this morning or has the distemper very badly I fear he is to be of no further servive to us.    an excellent horse of <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Cruzatte's</name> snagged himself so badly in the groin in jumping over a parsel of fallen timber that he will evidently be of no further service to us.    at the pass of <name type="place" key="Lolo (Collins's) Creek (Idaho)">Collin's Creek</name> we met two indians who were on their way over the mountain; they had brought with them the three horses and the mule that had left us and returned to the <name type="place" key="Weippe Prairie (Camas Flats, Quawmash Flats)">quawmash grounds</name>.    these indians returned with us about ½ a mile down the creek where we halted to dine and graize or horses at the same place I had halted and remained all night with the party on the [<hi rend="italic">blank</hi>] of Septembr last.<ref target="n36062101" n="1"/>    as well as we could understand the indians they informed us that they had seen <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name> and <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name> and that they would not return untill the expiration of two days; the cause why <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name> and <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name> had not returned with these men we are at a loss to account for.    we pressed these indians to remain with us and to conduct us over the mountain on the return of <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name> and <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name>.    they consented to remain two nights for us and accordingly deposited their store of roots and bread in the bushes at no great distance and after dinner returned with us, as far as the little prarie<ref target="n36062102" n="2"/> about 2 miles distant from the creek, here they halted with their horses and informed us they would remain untill we overtook them or at least two nights. they had four supenumery horses with them.    we sent on four hunters a head to the <name type="place" key="Weippe Prairie (Camas Flats, Quawmash Flats)">quawmash flatts</name> to take an evenings hunt; they so far succeeded as to kill one deer.    we left <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">Reubin</name> and <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">J. Feilds</name> at the Creek where we dined together with <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Sergt Gass</name> in order to hunt about that place untill our return.    at seven in the evening we found ourselves once more at our old encampment<ref target="n36062103" n="3"/> where we shall anxious await the return of <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name> and <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name>.—
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Saturday June 21st 1806</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
We collected our horses early and Set out on our return to the flatts. we all felt Some mortification in being thus compelled to retrace our Steps through this tedious and difficuelt part of our rout, obstructed with brush and innumerable logs and fallen timber which renders the traveling distressing and even dangerous to our horses.    one of <name type="person" key="Thompson, John B.">Thompsons</name> horses is either choked this morning or has the distemper badly. I fear he is to be of no further Survice to us.    an excellent horse of <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Cruzatt's</name> snagged himself So badly in the groin in jumping over a parcel of fallen timber that he will eventually be of no further Survice to us.    at the pass of <name type="place" key="Lolo (Collins's) Creek (Idaho)">Collin's Creek</name> we met two indians who were on their way over the mountains, they had brought with them the three horses and the Mule which had left us and returned to the <name type="place" key="Weippe Prairie (Camas Flats, Quawmash Flats)">quawmash ground</name>.    those indians returned with us about ½ mile down the Creek where we 〈expected〉 halted to dine and graze our horses.    as well as we Could understand the indians they informed us they had Seen <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Geo Drewyer</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name>, and that they would not return untill the expiration of two days.    the cause why <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name> did not return with these men we are at a loss to account for.    we pressed those indians to remain with us and conduct us over the Mountains on the return of <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name>.    they consented to remain two nights for us and accordingly deposited their Stores of roots &amp; Bread in the bushes at no great distance and after Dinner returned with us, as far as the little prarie about 2 Miles distance from the Creek, here they halted with their horses and informed us they would remain untill we overtook them or at least 2 nights.    they had four Supernoumery horses with them. We Sent on four hunters a head to the <name type="place" key="Weippe Prairie (Camas Flats, Quawmash Flats)">quawmash flats</name> to make an evening hunt; they So far Suckceeded as to kill one deer. We left <name type="place" key="Field, Reubin">R.</name> and <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Jo. Fields</name> at the Creek where we dined, and <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Sergt. Gass</name> in order to hunt about that place untill our return.    at 7 in the evening we found ourselves once more at our old encampment where we Shall anxiously await the return of <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name>.

</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Saturday 21st June 1806.    a fair morning.    we got up our horses all except 4 which we expect has gone back to the Commass ground.    we Set out on our return to the <name type="place" key="Weippe Prairie (Camas Flats, Quawmash Flats)">Commass flat</name> where we expect we can kill Some more meat to Start again with &amp; to take us back in mount.    when we got down on <name type="place" key="Lolo (Collins's) Creek (Idaho)">Collinses Creek</name> we met 2 Indians who were on their way to cross the mountn.    they had our 4 horses takeing them back to us    had 5 horses of their own and provision to last them across the mountains.    we halted and dined below the forks of <name type="place" key="Lolo (Collins's) Creek (Idaho)">Collinses Creek</name>.<ref target="n36062104" n="4"/>    these 2 Indians told us that we could have went on if in case we could have found the road, for as the Snow bears up the horses all can cross the high parts which is covred So thick with Snow in about 3 days and our horses cannot git any thing to eat dureing that time.    we ascended the hill to the Samll prarie    the 2 Indians halted here to stay 2 or 3 days &amp; wait for us to kill some meat &amp; then pilot us across the <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Snow) Mountains">Snow mountains</name>. Sergt. <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name> &amp; the <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph and Reubin">2 Fields</name> Stayed here to hunt.    we descended the mountain down to the <name type="place" key="Weippe Prairie (Camas Flats, Quawmash Flats)">Commass flat</name> towards evening and Camped at the old Camping ground. Several went out a Short distance to hunt &amp; came in at dark. <name type="person" key="Shields, John">Shields</name> had killed &amp; brought in one deer—


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Saturday 21st.</hi>    We had again a fine morning; and we collected our horses in order to return to the <name type="place" key="Weippe Prairie (Camas Flats, Quawmash Flats)">Com-mas flat</name>. We proceeded on to a creek, where we met two young Indians, who said they were come to go over the mountains with us. We halted here for dinner; after which, all our party proceeded on to <name type="place" key="Weippe Prairie (Camas Flats, Quawmash Flats)">Com-mas flat</name>, except myself and two men<ref target="n36062105" n="5"/> who remained here to hunt.<ref target="n36062106" n="6"/> We wish to kill as much meat as will serve the party, until we get back where our loading was left, as we have plenty of roots there to serve us over the mountains. One of our best horses got snagged to-day, and was left here. The two Indians remained with us, and in the evening one of the men killed a deer.



</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n36062101" n="1"> The camp of <ref n="1805-09-21" type="related">September 21, 1805</ref>, on <name type="place" key="Lolo (Collins's) Creek (Idaho)">Lolo Creek</name> in <name type="place" key="Clearwater County, Idaho">Clearwater County</name>, <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 71.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36062102" n="2">
               <name type="place" key="Crane Meadows">Crane Meadows</name>; see <ref n="1806-06-15" type="related">June 15, 1806</ref>. Peebles (RLC), 23.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36062103" n="3">The camp of June 10–15, 1806, on <name type="place" key="Weippe Prairie (Camas Flats, Quawmash Flats)">Weippe Prarie ("quawmash flatts")</name>. Peebles (LT), map; <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 71.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36062104" n="4">On <name type="place" key="Lolo (Collins's) Creek (Idaho)">Lolo Creek</name>, <name type="place" key="Clearwater County, Idaho">Clearwater County</name>, <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>, where <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> party had camped on <ref n="1805-09-21" type="related">September 21, 1805</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36062105" n="5">The <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph and Reubin">Field brothers</name>, say <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, and <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36062106" n="6">
               <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass's</name> hunting party remained at <name type="place" key="Crane Meadows">Crane Meadows</name>, <name type="place" key="Clearwater County, Idaho">Clearwater County</name>, <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>. The rest 
of the party returned to <name type="place" key="Weippe Prairie (Camas Flats, Quawmash Flats)">Weippe Prairie</name>.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-06-20" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-06-22" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
