<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-04-16">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
April 16, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 7</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">March 23–June 9, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1991</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">125-130</biblScope>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">293</biblScope>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">211-212</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc/>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-10-04</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date>April 16, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Wednesday April 16th 1806.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
About 8 A. M. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name> passed the river with the two interpreters, the indian woman and nine men<ref target="n31041601" n="1"/> in order to trade with the natives for their horses, for which purpose he took with him a good part of our stock of merchandize. I remained in camp; sent out the hunters very early in the morning, and set Sergts. <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name> and <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Pryor</name> with some others at work to make a parsel of packsaddles.    twelve horses will be sufficient to transport our baggage and some pounded fish which we intend taking with us as a reserved store for the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">rocky mountains</name>. I was visited today by several of the natives, and amused myself in making a collection of the esculent plants in the neighbourhood such as the Indians use, a specemine of which I preserved. I also met with sundry other plants which were strangers to me which I also preserved, among others there is a currant<ref target="n31041602" n="2"/> which is now in blume and has yellow blossom something like the yellow currant of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> but is a different speceis. <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">Reubin Feilds</name> returned in the evening and brought with him a large grey squrrel and two others of a kind I had never before seen.<ref target="n31041603" n="3"/>    they are a size less than the grey squirrel common to the middle atlantic states and of a pided grey and yellowish brown colour, in form it resembles our grey squrrel precisely. I had them skined leaving the head feet and tail to them and placed in the sun to dry. <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Joseph Feilds</name> brought me a black pheasant which he had killed; this I found on examination to be the large black or dark brown pheasant I had met with on the upper part of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>.<ref target="n31041604" n="4"/>    it is as large as a well grown fowl the iris of the eye is of a dark yellowish brown, the puple black, the legs are booted to the toes, the tail is composed of 18 black feathers tiped with bluish white, of which the two in the center are reather shorter than the others which are all of the same length.    over the eye there is a stripe of a ¼ of an inch in width uncovered with feathers of a fine orrange yellow.    the wide spaces void of feathers on the side of the neck are also of the same colour. I had some parts of this bird preserved.    our present station is the last point at which there is a single stick of timber on the river for a great distance and is the commencement of the open plains which extend nearly to the base of the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">rocky Mts.</name>
                  <name type="person" key="Labiche, François">Labuish</name> returned this evening having killed two deer I sent and had them brought in.    this evening <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. C.</name> informed me by some of the men whom he sent over that that he had obtained no horses as yet of the natives.    that they promised to trade with him provided he would remove to their village.    to this he had consented and should proceeded to the <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skillute</name> village<ref target="n31041605" n="5"/> above the <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">long narrows</name> as soon as the men returned whom he had sent to me for some other articles. I dispatched the men on their return to <name type="person" key="Clark, William">capt. C.</name> immediately with these articles and he set out with his party accompanyed by the natives to their village where he remained all night.—    the natives who had spent the day with me seemed very well disposed, they left me at 6 in the evening and returned to their rispective villages.    the hunters informed me that they saw some Antelopes, &amp; the tracks of several black bear, but no appearance of any Elk.    we were informed by the Indians that the river which falls in on the S. side of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> just above the <name type="native_nation" key="Tenino Indians">Eneshur</name> village heads in <name type="place" key="Mount Hood (Timm, Falls Mountain)">Mount hood</name> and dose not water the extensive country which we have heretofore calculated on.<ref target="n31041606" n="6"/>    a great portion of that extensive tract of country to the S. and S. W. of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> and it's <name type="place"
                        key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">S. E. branch</name>,<ref target="n31041607" n="7"/> and between the same and the <name type="place" key="Gulf of California">waters of Callifornia</name> must be watered by the <name type="place" key="Willamette (Multnomah) River">Multnomah river</name>.—<ref target="n31041608" n="8"/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Observed Equal Altitudes of the sun with Sextant</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <table rows="4" cols="11">
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">h</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">m</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">s</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">h</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">m</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">s</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">A.M.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">6</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">52</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">43</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">P.M.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">2</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">20</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">45</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="3" cols="1">}</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="3" cols="1">Chronometer too slow<lb/>M.T.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">"</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">54</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">20</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">"</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">22</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">26</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">"</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">55</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">26</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">"</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">24</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">—</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>April 16th 1806<ref target="n31041609" n="9"/>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>	 						 
Crossed the river and Sent <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Goodrich, Silas">Goodrich</name> to the <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skil lute</name> village to envite the Indians to trade horses with us, also sent <name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">Frazer</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Shabono</name> to the <name type="native_nation" key="Wishram-Wasco Indians">Che-luck-kit-ti-quar</name> village for the same purpose    a number of Indians came of both nations and delayed the greater part of the day without tradeing a Single horse    the Great Chief of the <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skillutes</name> also came with <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name>.    he was lame and Could not walk    he told me if I would go to his Town his people would trade with me. I Set out late and arrived at Sunset and informed. the natives that in the morning I would trade with them.    he gave me onions to eate which had been Sweated. <name type="place" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Peter</name> played the violin and the men danced. Saw abt. 100 Stacks of fish.    maney nations visit this place for trade.    the discription of the houses, their dress habits &amp;c. Smoked &amp;c.    I saw great numbers of horses
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Wednesday April 16th 1806</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>	
about 8 oClock this morning I passed the river with the two interpreters, and nine men in order to trade with the nativs for their horses, for which purpose I took with me a good part of our Stock of merchindize. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt L.</name> Sent out the hunters and Set Several men at work makeing pack Saddles.    twelve horses will be Sufficient to trans port our baggage and Some pounded fish with our dried Elk.    which we intend takeing with us as a reserved Store for the Plains &amp; <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">rocky mountains</name>. I formed a Camp on the N. Side<ref target="n31041610" n="10"/> and Sent <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Goodrich, Silas">Goodrich</name> to the <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skillute</name> Village, and <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Shabono</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">Frazer</name> down to the <name type="native_nation" key="Wishram-Wasco Indians">Wishram</name> Villages with derections to inform the nativs that I had Crossed the river for the purpose of purchaseing horses, and if they had horses to Sell us to bring them to my Camp. Great numbers of Indians came from both Villages and delayed the greater part of the day without tradeing a Single horse. <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name> returned with the principal Chief of the <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skillutes</name> who was lame and Could not walk.    after his arival Some horses were offered for Sale, but they asked nearly half the merchindize I had with me for one horse.    this price I could not think of giveing.    the Chief informed me if I would go to his town with him, his people would Sell me horses. I therefore Concluded to accompany him to his Village 7 miles distant.<ref target="n31041611" n="11"/>    we Set out and arrived at the Village at Sunset.    after Some Serimony I entered the house of the Chief. I then informed them that I would trade with them for their horses in the morning for which I would give for each horse the articles which I had offered yestered. The Chief Set before me a large platter of Onions which had been Sweeted. I gave a part of those onions to all my party and we all eate of them, in this State the root is very Sweet and the tops tender.    the nativs requested the party to dance which they were readily consented and <name type="place" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Peter Cruzat</name> played on the Violin and the men danced Several dances &amp; retired to rest in the houses of the 1st and Second Cheif.</p>
               <p>
this village is moved about 300 yards below the Spot it Stood last fall at the time we passed down.    they were all above grown and built in the Same form of those below already discribed. We observed maney stacks of fish remaining untouched on either Side of the river. The Inhabitents of this Village ware the robe of deer Elk Goat &amp;c. and 〈maney〉 most of the men ware Legins and mockersons and Shirts highly ornimented with Porcupine quills &amp; beeds.    the women were the Truss most Commonly.    tho Some of them have long Shirts    all of those articles they precure from other nations who visit them for the purpose of exchangeing those articles for their pounded fish of which they prepare great quantities. This is the Great Mart of all this Country.<ref target="n31041612" n="12"/>    ten different tribes who reside on <name type="place" key="Yakima (Tapteete) River">Taptate</name>
                  <ref target="n31041613" n="13"/> and <name type="place" key="Klickitat (Cataract) River">Catteract River</name> visit those people for the purpose of purchaseing their fish, and the Indians on the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> and <name type="place" key="Lewis (Cahwahnakiooks) River">Lewis's river</name> quite to the <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Chopunnish</name> Nation Visit them for the purpose of tradeing horses buffalow robes for beeds, and Such articles as they have not. The <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skillutes</name> precure the most of their Cloth knivs axes &amp; beeds from the Indians from the North of them who trade with white people who come into the inlets to the North at no great distance from the <name type="place" key="Yakima (Tapteete) River">Tapteet</name>.<ref target="n31041614" n="14"/>    their horses of which I saw great numbers, they precure from the Indians who reside on the banks of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> above, and what fiew they take from the <name type="native_nation" key="Paiute Indians">To war ne hi ooks</name> or <name type="native_nation" key="Paiute Indians">Snake Indians</name>. I smoked with all the principal men of this nation in the house of their great Cheif and lay my Self down on a Mat to Sleep but was prevented by the mice<ref target="n31041615" n="15"/> and vermin with which this house abounded and which was very troublesom to me.
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Wednesday 16th of April 1806.    a clear pleasant morning. Several Indians Stayed at our Camp last night.    6 of the party went out eairly a hunting. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name> and 8 more of the party<ref target="n31041616" n="16"/> went across the River and took Some marchandize &amp; other articles in order to purchase horses &amp;C. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name> intends going up to the falls &amp; See if any is to be had their.    a number of
Indians Came to our Camp    Some of them on horse back. Sergt. <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name> and 2 men Set at makeing pack Saddles. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt Clark</name> Sent back a part of the articles as the Indians asked more for their horses than our goods would admit
of, but he was going up to the falls in hopes to git Some their by giving a little more than has been offered as yet.    our hunters killed this day only two Deer 2 Squerrells<ref target="n31041617" n="17"/> of a new kind of any we ever Saw before. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name> had the Skins Stuffed &amp; taken care of.    one large new kind of a grey Squerrell<ref target="n31041618" n="18"/> also.    1 or 2 ducks    the game is verry Scarce about this place.


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Wednesday 16th.</hi>    This was a plesant day. As we did not expect to be able to navigate the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia river</name> much farther, Captain <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clarke</name>, with some of the men and some goods went over the river to endeavour to procure some horses. I was out hunting this morning, and killed a rattlesnake among the rocks. Some hunters that went out in the morning returned in the evening and had killed two deer, some ducks and four squirrels, three of a beautiful speckled kind, and as large as a common grey squirrel, but the tail not so bushy.



</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n31041601" n="1">The two interpreters would be <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name> and <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name>. Among the nine men were apparently <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Cruzatte</name>, <name type="person" key="Goodrich, Silas">Goodrich</name>, <name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">Frazer</name>, <name type="person" key="Willard, Alexander">Willard</name>, <name type="person" key="McNeal, Hugh">McNeal</name>, <name type="person" key="Weiser, Peter">Weiser</name>, and perhaps <name type="person" key="Werner, William">Werner</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31041602" n="2">The golden currant, <hi rend="italic">Ribes aureum</hi> Pursh, was collected by <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> on this day, and later described by Frederick Pursh, making this place the type locality of the species. The "yellow currant of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>," collected on <ref n="1805-06-29" type="related">July 29, 1805</ref>, at the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Three Forks of the">Three Forks of the Missouri</name>, was also a specimen of golden currant, although <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> thinks the two were different. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> may refer to another species of currant with yellow flowers that he saw lower on the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, and earlier in 1805. These species would be the buffalo currant, <hi rend="italic">R. odoratum</hi> Wendl., or the wild black currant, <hi rend="italic">R. americanum</hi> Mill. See discussion at <ref n="1805-04-30" type="related">April 30, 1805</ref>. Cutright (LCPN), 417; Pursh, 164. Some vertical lines cross through these passages to where <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> writes "our present station," all perhaps drawn by <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31041603" n="3">The large gray squirrel is the western gray squirrel, <hi rend="italic">Sciurus griseus,</hi> described by <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> on <ref n="1806-02-25" type="related">February 25, 1806</ref>. The other squirrels may be the California ground squirrel, <hi rend="italic">Spermophilus beecheyi,</hi> assuming that <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Field</name> had stayed with the main party on the <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name> side; the California ground squirrel did not cross to the <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name> side until the twentieth century.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31041604" n="4">Blue grouse, <hi rend="italic">Dendragapus obscurus</hi> [AOU, 297]. To some authorities this would be the sooty grouse, <hi rend="italic">D. fuliginosus</hi> [AOU, 297.1], otherwise regarded as a subspecies of the above. Burroughs, 216–17; Holmgren, 32. See <ref n="1805-08-01" type="related">August 1, 1805</ref>, for a full description of the bird.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31041605" n="5">On <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 78 and in entries for October 1805 the captains called these Indians at the <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">Long Narrows</name> the <name type="native_nation" key="Wishram-Wasco Indians">Echelutes</name> (see <ref n="1805-10-24" type="related">October 24, 1805</ref>). They are now applying the name <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skillute</name> for these people, a term they previously used for Indians at the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Cowlitz (Coweliskee) River">Cowlitz River</name> (<hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 81). See <ref n="1806-03-27" type="related">March 27, 1806</ref>. It is unclear why the captains have used this seemingly inappropriate designation.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31041606" n="6">The <name type="place" key="Deschutes (Clark's, Towanahiook's) River">Deschutes River</name>; a tributary, the <name type="place" key="White River">White River</name>, heads in the vicinity of <name type="place" key="Mount Hood (Timm, Falls Mountain)">Mt. Hood</name>. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 78. The captains' term may represent <name type="native_nation" key="Wishram-Wasco Indians">Wishram-Wasco Chinookan</name>
               <hi rend="italic">i-mi-<seg n="u353">š</seg>úx</hi>
               <hi rend="superscript">w</hi>, "he (is) your relative." The "Eneshur" were probably <name type="native_nation" key="Tenino Indians">Tenino Indians</name>. At <ref n="1805-10-22" type="related">October 22, 1805</ref>, they were identified as <name type="native_nation" key="Tenino Indians">Tapanashs</name>, an outdated term replaced by <name type="native_nation" key="Tenino Indians">Tenino</name>. Spier (TDW), 19; Ray (LCEN).</note>
            <note xml:id="n31041607" n="7">The <name type="place"
                     key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Snake River</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31041608" n="8">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> is still attributing to the <name type="place" key="Willamette (Multnomah) River">Willamette (Multnomah)</name> a much greater extent than is actually the fact. Much of that "extensive tract of country" lies in the <name type="place" key="Great Basin">Great Basin</name>, which has no outlet to the sea. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> had no way of knowing this, for the basin had only been visited previously by a few Spanish explorers who entered its southeastern periphery without realizing its character. Allen (PG), 394.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31041609" n="9">Here begins a fragment from the Voorhis Collection covering April 16-21, 1806, and designated First Draft. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> wrote these entries on letter paper, probably because he was separated from <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and the main party on these dates. See <ref n="introduction.general" type="related">Introduction</ref> and <ref n="v02.appendix.c" type="related">Appendix C</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31041610" n="10">In <name type="place" key="Klickitat County, Wash.">Klickitat County</name>, <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>, probably a little above <name type="place" key="Dallesport, Wash.">Dallesport</name> and opposite <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The Dalles</name>. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 78.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31041611" n="11">The "<name type="native_nation" key="Wishram-Wasco Indians">E-che-lute</name>" village above the <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">Long Narrows of the Columbia</name> in <name type="place" key="Klickitat County, Wash.">Klickitat County</name>. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 78. See n. 5 above.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31041612" n="12">The importance of <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The Dalles</name>-<name type="place" key="Columbia River, Great Falls of the">Celilo Falls</name> area in the native interregional exchange systems is discussed by Anastasio and by Wood (CF). The long history of archaeological investigations in this area has most recently been reviewed by Minor (PH).</note>
            <note xml:id="n31041613" n="13">The <name type="place" key="Yakima (Tapteete) River">Yakima River</name>, meeting the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> in <name type="place" key="Benton County, Wash.">Benton County</name>, <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 75. The name <hi rend="italic">taptat</hi> refers to a <name type="native_nation" key="Yakima Indians">Yakima</name> village near <name type="place" key="Posser, Wash.">Posser</name>, <name type="place" key="Benton County, Wash.">Benton County</name>. See October 17, 1805.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31041614" n="14">These traders were presumably coming into <name type="place" key="Grays Harbor">Grays Harbor</name> and the <name type="place" key="Strait of Juan de Fuca">Strait of Juan de Fuca</name> and <name type="place" key="Puget Sound">Puget Sound</name>, farther from the "<name type="place" key="Yakima (Tapteete) River">Tapteet</name>," today's <name type="place" key="Yakima (Tapteete) River">Yakima River</name>, than <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> may have imagined.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31041615" n="15">Perhaps the deer mouse, <hi rend="italic">Peromyscus maniculatus.</hi>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="n31041616" n="16">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> counts twelve persons with <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, among whom were <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name>, <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name>,
<name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name>, <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Cruzatte</name>, <name type="person" key="Goodrich, Silas">Goodrich</name>, <name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">Frazer</name>, <name type="person" key="Willard, Alexander">Willard</name>, <name type="person" key="McNeal, Hugh">McNeal</name>, <name type="person" key="Weiser, Peter">Weiser</name>, and perhaps <name type="person" key="Werner, William">Werner</name>. They went across the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> to <name type="place" key="Klickitat County, Wash.">Klickitat County</name>, <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>, and camped in the vicinity of <name type="place" key="Dallesport, Wash.">Dallesport</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31041617" n="17">Perhaps the California ground squirrel, <hi rend="italic">Spermophilus beecheyi;</hi> see <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> entry for this date. <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Joseph Field</name> brought the animals in.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31041618" n="18">Western gray squirrel.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-04-15" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-04-17" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
