<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-04-18">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
April 18, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 7</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">March 23–June 9, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1991</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">136-142</biblScope>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">294</biblScope>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">212</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc/>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-10-05</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date>April 18, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Friday April 18th 1806.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
Late last evening we were visited by the principal cheif of <name type="native_nation" key="Wishram-Wasco Indians">Chilluckkittaquaws</name> and 12 of his nation they remained with us untill 9 OC. when they all departed except the Cheif and two others who slept at my feet.    we loaded our vessels and set out after an early breakfast this morning.    we gave the indians a passage to the N. shore on which they reside and pursued our rout to the foot of the first rapid<ref target="n32041801" n="1"/> at the distance of 4 ms.    here we found it necessary to unload the perogues and canoes and make a portage of 70 paces over a rock; we then drew our vessels up by a cord and the assistance of setingpoles.    from hence we proceeded to the bason below the <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">long narrows</name> 5 ms. further and landed on the Lard. side at ½ after 3.<ref target="n32041802" n="2"/>    the Cheif when he left me this morning promised to bring some horses to barter with me at the bason.—    the <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">long narrows</name>
                  <ref target="n32041803" n="3"/> are much more formidable than they were when we decended them last fall    there would be no possibility of passind either up or down them in any vessel.—    after unloading the canoes and arranging the camp I walked up to the <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skillute</name> Village and jouined Capt.    he had procured four horses only for which a high price had been given, at least more than double that which we had formerly given for those which we purchased from the <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshonees</name> and the first band of <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Flatheads</name>.    they have a great abundance of horses but will not dispose of them.    we determined to make the portage to the head of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">long narrows</name> with our baggage and five small canoes.    the 2 perogues we could take no further and therefore cut them up for fuel.    in the evening <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. C.</name> and myself returned to the camp at the bason and left <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name> and three others with the merchandize at the village, three parsels of which had been laid by at the request of individuals who promised to give us horses for them in the morning.—    I shot my airgun in the presents of the natives at the village which excited great astonishment.—
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">April 18th 1806</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
early this morning I was awoke by a Indian from the nieghbourhood of our horses, he had he arived here yesterday &amp; this morning found a Small bag of powder and ball which had been left when we exposed our goods yesterday and brought it to me. I had a fire made out and exposed the articles &amp;c. 〈Several Indians Came〉 having increased the articles for each horse, and Sent out 2 men to hunt the horses bought yesterday. after Colecting them Sent <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Shabono</name> and <name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">Frazer</name> with the 4 I had purchased down to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt Lewis</name>.    and was tanterlised with the expectation of purchaseing more imediately. Great numbers of the Indians from the falls and both above and below.    none of them appeared anxious to part with their horses but told me that Several were Comeing from the plains about 1 or 2 P M. and laid by 2 parcels of merchindize and told me that they had Sent for their horses.    among other Tribes was those of the <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Klickitat Indians">Skad-datts</name>
                  </hi>
                  <ref target="n32041804" n="4"/> who bantered the <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skillutes</name> to play with them at a Singular Kind of game<ref target="n32041805" n="5"/> which was Soon Made up and 9 of a side Sat down    they were Some time making up their bets of Beeds, brass thimbles or tubes robes &amp;c. &amp;c.    when the bets were all made up the nine on each Side took opposides faceing each other at the distance of about 12 feet.    in front of each party was placed a long pole on which they Struck with a Stick and Sung.    they made use of 2 Small pices of bone in this form<ref target="n32041806" n="6"/> and Size    a bone 〈of〉 was given to 2 men of the Same party who changed it from 〈side〉 hand to hand with great dexterity one hand above the other looking down, and when he was ready for the opposit party to guess he Seperated his hands Swinging them around the breast looking at the opposit party who waved their hand to the Side the bone was in.    if the opposit party guessed the hand of each man the bone was given to them.    if 〈not〉 neither it was nothing.    if they guessed one which they might single out if they pleased they recived his bone, and 〈won or〉 lost on the other as they hapened to fail in guessing    the also lose one if they fail guessing both The game is plaid at different numbers &amp; each party has 5 sticks. Several of those games were played to day in which the <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skillute</name> won, indeed the won all the beeds and Som robes of the <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Klickitat Indians">Skad datts</name>
                  </hi> which they [<hi rend="italic">word unclear</hi>]    one other game<ref target="n32041807" n="7"/> which they also played [<hi rend="italic">word illegible</hi>] 2 by men with 4 Sticks.    2 black &amp; 2 White under a kind of hat made of bark.    as this is a very intrecut game I cannot describe it:    the one who holds the Sticks places them in different positions, and the opposit party, guess the position of the black Sticks by a motion of either one or both of the hands.    each man has 4 Sticks.    this as also the other is accompanied with a kind of Song. This hat is about 12 inches diamuter and the Sticks about 5 inches long—.    at 3 P M Sergt <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> arived with 3 men from <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt Lewis</name> with elk skins and Some fiew articles Such as a Coat &amp; robes. I had 3 dogs purchased, Soon after <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name> Came up with <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">J. Fields</name>    he had assended the river with much dificuelty to the bason 2 Miles below. I left <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name>, <name type="person" key="Werner, William">Warner</name>, <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Goodrich, Silas">Goodrich</name> with the articles and went down with <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt Lewis</name> to the bason, Cut up 2 of our canoes for fire wood  no horses more    maney nations resort here for trade</p>
               <p>
                  <figure rend="mhs">
                     <p>Game Bone, April 18, 1806, First Draft Voorhis Fragment
<bibl>
                           <orgName>Missouri Historical Society</orgName>
                        </bibl>
                     </p>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Friday 18th April 1806</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
Early this Morning I was awoke by an indian man of the <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Chopunnish</name> Nation who informed me that he lived in the neighbourhood of our horses.    this man delivered me a bag of powder and ball which he had picked up this morning at the place the goods were exposed yesterday—. I had a fire made of Some poles purchased of the nativs at a Short distance from the houses and the articles exposed as yesterday. Collected the 4 horses purchased yesterday and Sent <name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">Frazier</name> and <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Shabono</name> with them to the bason where I expected they would meet <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Cap L—s</name> and Commence the portage of the baggage on those horses.    about 10 A. M. the Indians Came down from the <name type="native_nation" key="Tenino Indians">Eneesher</name> Villages and I expected would take the articles which they had laid by yesterday. but to my estonishment not one would make the exchange to day—.    two other parcels of good were laid by and the horses promised at 2 P. M. I payed but little attention to this bargain however Suffered the bundles to lye. I dressed the Sores of the principal Chief gave Some Small things to his children and promised the Chief Some Medicine for to Cure his Sores.    his wife who I found to be a Sulky Bitch and was Somewhat efflicted with pains in her back.    this I thought a good oppertunity to get her on my Side giveing here Something for her back. I rubed a little Camphere<ref target="n32041808" n="8"/> on her temples and back, and applyed worm flannel to her back which She thought had nearly restored her to her former feelings.    this I thought a favourable time to trade with the Chief who had more horses than all the nation besides. I accordingly made him an offer which he excepted and Sold me two horses. Great numbers of Indians from defferent derections visited me at this place to day, none of them appeared willing to part with their horses, but told me that Several were Comeing from the plains this evening. among other Nations who visit this place for the purpose of trade is the <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Klickitat Indians">Skad-datt's</name>.</hi>    those people bantered the <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skillutes</name> to play at a Singular kind of game.    in the Course of the day the <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skillutes</name> won all their beeds Skins arrows &amp;c. This game was Composed of 9 men on a Side.    they Set down opposit to each other at the distance of about 10 feet.    in front of each party a long pole was placed on which they Struck with a Small Stick to the time of their Songs.    after the bets were made up which was nearly half an hour after they Set down, two round bones was producd about the Size of a mans little finger or Something Smaller and 2¼ inches in length.    which they held in their hand Changeing it from one hand to the other with great dexterity.    2 men on 〈each〉 the Same Side performed this part, and when they had the bone in the hand they wished, they looked at their advosarys Swinging arms around their Sholders for their advosary Guess which they pirformed by the motion the hand either to the right or left.    if the opposit party guessed the hand of both of the men who had the bone, the bones were given to them.    if neither the bones was retained and nothing Counted.    if they guessed one and not the other, one bone was dilivered up and the party possessing the other bone Counted one.    and one for every time the advosary miss guessed untill they guessed the hand in which the bone was in—in this game each party has 5 Sticks.    and one Side wins all the Sticks, once twice or thrice as the game may be Set. I observed another game which those people also play and is played by 2 persons with 4 Sticks about the Size of a mans finger and about 7 inches in length.    two of those Sticks are black and the other 2 White and Something larger than the black ones.    those Sticks they place in defferent positions which they perform under a kind of trencher made of bark round and about 14 inches diamieter.    this is a very intricate game and I cannot Sufficiently understand to discribe it.    the man who is in possession of the Sticks &amp;c places them in defferent positions, and the opposit party tels the position of the black Sticks by a motion of either or both of his hands &amp;c.    this game is Counted in the Same way as the one before mentioned.    all their games are accompanied with Songs and time.    at 3 P. M <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Sergt. Ordway</name> &amp; three men arived from <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Cap Lewis</name>    they brought with them Several Elk Skins, two of my Coats and 4 robes of the party to add to the Stores I had with me for the purchase of horses. <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Sgt. O.</name> informed me that <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Cap L.</name> had arived with all the Canoes into the bason 2 miles below and wished Some dogs to eate. I had 3 dogs purchased and Sent down.    at 5 P. M. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name> Came up.    he informed me that he had the river to the bason with much difecuelty and danger, haveing made one portage.    as I had not Slept but very little for the two nights past on account of mice &amp; virmen with which those indian houses abounded, and haveing no blanket with me, and the means of keeping a fire Sufficent to keep me worm out was too Expensive I deturmined to poceed with <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt L.</name> down to Camp at the bason. I left the Articles of Merchendize &amp;c. with <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name>, <name type="person" key="Werner, William">Werner</name>, <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Goodrich, Silas">Goodrich</name> untill the morning—.    at the bason we Cut up two of our Canoes for fire wood verry much to the Sagreen [chagrin] of the nativs    not with standing they would give us nothing for them. In my absence Several Inds. visited <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name> at his camp among others was the great Cheif of the <name type="native_nation" key="Wishram-Wasco Indians">Chilluckitquaw</name> who Continued with him untill he left <name type="place" key="Fort Rock Camp (Oreg.)">Rock fort Camp</name>. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt L.</name> had 12 pack Saddles Completed and Strings prepared of the Elk skins for Lashing the loads    he also kept out all the hunters who killed just deer enough for the party with him to Subsist on. The Cheif who had Visited <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt Lewis</name> promised him that he would bring Some horses to the bason and trade with him.    but he was not as good as his word. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt Lewis</name> gave a large Kittle for a horse which was offered to him at the bason this evening.
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Friday 18th of April 1806.    a clear cool morning    we took breakfast and Set out    crossed the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name> to the N. Side proceeded on    Soon came to a rapid<ref target="n32041809" n="9"/> where we made a Short portage and towed up the canoes &amp; proceeded on up a rapid current to the bason &amp; landed<ref target="n32041810" n="10"/> on the N. Side about 3 P. M.    unloaded the canoes    cut the large ones for firewood    <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name> had purchased 4 horses.    we packed several articles to the village to purchase horses.    bought 2 dogs Several cakes of chappalell &amp;C.


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Friday 18th.</hi>    We had fine weather, and all set out from this place, and 
proceeded on with great difficulty and danger to the foot of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">long narrows</name>;<ref target="n32041811" n="11"/> and expect to be able to take the canoes no further.— Here we met one of the men<ref target="n32041812" n="12"/> from Captain <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clarke</name>, with 4 horses. In coming up, one of our small canoes got split so that we were obliged to carry the load two miles by land to this place.<ref target="n32041813" n="13"/> Wood here is very scarce, as the <name type="place" key="Great Columbian Plain">Columbia plains</name> have commenced. Several of the men<ref target="n32041814" n="14"/> went up to the village with their buffaloe robes, to dispose of them for horses. Could we get about 12 horses we would be able to go by land.

</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n32041801" n="1">Not shown on any expedition map. Perhaps <name type="place" key="Threemile Rapids">Threemile Rapids</name> below today's <name type="place" key="The Dalles Dam">The Dalles Dam</name>. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 78.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32041802" n="2">In <name type="place" key="Klickitat County, Wash.">Klickitat County</name>, <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>, perhaps at today's <name type="place" key="Spearfish Lake">Spearfish Lake</name>. If so, it is the "Bason of dead water" in <ref n="1805-10-24" type="related">fig. 25</ref>, vol. 5 of this edition. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 78.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32041803" n="3">The <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">Long Narrows</name>, with the <name type="place" key="Short (Little) Narrows">Short Narrows</name>, constitute <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The Dalles</name> of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 78. See <ref n="1805-10-24" type="related">October 24, 1805</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32041804" n="4">They lived on <name type="native_nation" key="Klickitat (Cataract) River">Klickitat River</name>, and were possibly a division of the <name type="native_nation" key="Klickitat Indians">Klickitat Indians</name>. In the <ref n="1805-1806.winter.part2" type="related">Estimate of Western Indians</ref>, they were incorrectly identified as being <name type="native_nation" key="Pisquow Indians">Pisquows</name> or <name type="native_nation" key="Kittita Indians">Kittitas</name>; see <ref n="1806-04-20" type="related">April 20, 1806</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32041805" n="5">A variation on the widespread hand game, a version of which <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> notes on <ref n="1805-12-09" type="related">December 9, 1805</ref>. Culin, 282.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32041806" n="6">Here in the First Draft Voorhis fragment appears a sketch of the bone used in the game (fig. 10).</note>
            <note xml:id="n32041807" n="7">Evidently a variation of the four-stick game described in Culin, 327–35.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32041808" n="8">Camphor. Cutright (LCPN), 282.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32041809" n="9">Perhaps <name type="place" key="Threemile Rapids">Threemile Rapids</name> below <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles Dam">The Dalles Dam</name>, <name type="place" key="Wasco County, Oreg.">Wasco County</name>, <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32041810" n="10">Perhaps at <name type="place" key="Spearfish Lake">Spearfish Lake</name>, <name type="place" key="Klickitat County, Wash.">Klickitat County</name>, <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32041811" n="11">Part of <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The Dalles of the Columbia River</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32041812" n="12">
               <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> says he sent <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name> and <name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">Frazer</name> with these horses.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32041813" n="13">In <name type="native_nation" key="Klickitat County, Wash.">Klickitat County</name>, <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>, perhaps at today's <name type="place" key="Spearfish Lake">Spearfish Lake</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32041814" n="14">
               <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> and three men, according to <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-04-17" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-04-19" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
