<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-03-20">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
March 20, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 6</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">November 2, 1805–March 22, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1990</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">440-442</biblScope>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">278</biblScope>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">199</biblScope>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 11</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of Joseph Whitehouse, May 14, 1804–April 2, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1997</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">430</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc/>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-09-03</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date>March 20, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Thursday March 20th 1806.</hi>
                     <ref target="n29032001" n="1"/>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
It continued to rain and blow so violently today that nothing could be done towards forwarding our departure.    we intended to have Dispatched <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name> and the <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph and Reubin">two Fieldses</name> to hunt near the bay on this side of the <name type="native_nation" key="Cathlamet Indians">Cathlahmahs</name> untill we jounded them from hence, but the rain rendered our departure so uncertain that we declined this measure for the present.    nothing remarkable happened during the day.    we have yet several days provision on hand, which we hope will be sufficient to subsist us during the time we are compelled by the weather to remain at this place.—</p>
               <p>
Altho' we have not fared sumptuously this winter and spring at <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name>, we have lived quite as comfortably as we had any reason to expect we should; and have accomplished every object which induced our remaining at this place except that of meeting with the traders who visit the entrance of this river.    our salt will be very sufficient to last us to the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> where we have a stock in store.—    it would have been very fortunate for us had some of those traders arrived previous to our departure from hence, as we should then have had it our power to obtain an addition to our stock of merchandize which would have made our homeward bound journey much more comfortable.    many of our men are still complaining of being unwell; <name type="person" key="Willard, Alexander">Willard</name> and <name type="person" key="Bratton, William E.">Bratton</name> remain weak, principally I beleive for the want of proper food. I expect when we get under way we shall be much more healthy.    it has always had that effect on us heretofore. The guns of <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name> and <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Sergt. Pryor</name> were both out of order.    the first was repared with a new lock, the old one having become unfit for uce; the second had the cock screw broken which was replaced by a duplicate which had been prepared for the lock at <name type="place" key="Harpers Ferry, W. Va.">Harpers ferry</name> where she was manufactured.    but for the precaution taken in bringing on those extra locks, and parts of locks, in addition to the ingenuity of <name type="person" key="Shields, John">John Shields</name>, most of our guns would at this moment been untirely unfit for use; but fortunately for us I have it in my power here to record that they are all in good order.
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Thursday March 20th 1806</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
It continued to rain and blow so violently to day that nothing could be done towards forwarding our departure.    we intended to have dispatched <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name> &amp; the <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph and Reubin">2 Field'es</name> to hunt above <name type="place" key="Tongue Point (Point William)">Point William</name> untill we joined them from hense but the rain renders our departure So uncertain that we decline this measure for the present.    nothing remarkable happened dureing the day.    we have yet Several days provisions on hand, which we hope will be Sufficient to Serve us dureing the time we are compell'd by the weather to remain at this place.—.</p>
               <p>
Altho' we have not fared Sumptuously this winter &amp; Spring at <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name>, we have lived quit as comfortably as we had any reason to expect we Should; and have accomplished every object which induced our remaining at this place except that of meeting with the traders who visit the enterance of this river.    our Salt will be very sufficient to last us to the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> where we have a Stock in Store.—    it would have been very fortunate for us has Some of those traders arrived previous to our departure from hence; as we Should then have had it in our power to obtain an addition to our Stock of merchandize, which would have made our homeward bound journey much more comfortable.</p>
               <p>
Maney of our men are Still Complaining of being unwell; <name type="person" key="Bratton, William E.">Bratten</name> and <name type="person" key="Willard, Alexander">Willard</name> remain weak principally I believe for the want of proper food. I expect when we get under way that we Shall be much more healthy.    it has always had that effect on us heretofore.</p>
               <p>
The Guns of <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Sergt. Pryor</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name> were both out of order.    the first had a Cock screw broken which was replaced by a duplicate which had been prepared for the Locks at <name type="place" key="Harpers Ferry, W. Va.">Harpers Ferry</name>; the Second repared with a new Lock, the old one becoming unfit for use.    but for the precaution taken in bringing on those extra locks, and parts of locks, in addition to the ingenuity of <name type="person" key="Shields, John">John Shields</name>, most of our guns would at this moment been entirely unfit for use; but fortunate for us I have it in my power here to record that they are in good order, and Complete in every respect—

</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Thursday 20th March 1806.    rained hard the grater part of last night and continues this morning. So we are only waiting for good weather to Start.    their has been 150 odd Elk killed by this party in the course of the last winter and 20 deer.    the party has now got in all 338 pair of good Mockasons    the most of them good Elk Skins Mockasons.

</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Thursday 20th.</hi>    The whole of this day was wet and disagreeable. We intended to have set out today on our return, but the weather was too bad. I made a calculation of the number of elk and deer killed by the party from the 1st of Dec. 1805 to the 20th March 1806, which gave 131 elk, and 20 deer. There were a few smaller quadrupeds killed, such as otter and beaver, and one raccoon. The meat of some of the elk was not brought to the fort.

</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry">
            <sp who="jw">
               <speaker>Whitehouse</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Thursday March 20th    A Rainey wet day.    We are now waiting for fair weather in Order to make a Start to the United States.    the party has killed 155 Elk<ref target="n29032002" n="2"/> &amp; 20 Deer since we came to this place.    The party has now among them 338 pair of good moccosins.    The most of them are strong &amp; made out of Elk skins



</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n29032001" n="1">This ends the daily entries in <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> Codex J; the rest of the codex consists of weather diaries for the months January–March 1806, reading backwards (pp. 145–52). On the flyleaf at the end of the notebook are the following figures:<lb/>
               <table rows="3" cols="1">
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">      35</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                        <hi rend="underline">        8</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">2[8?]0</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <lb/>
See also <ref n="v02.appendix.c" type="related">Appendix C</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n29032002" n="2">
               <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> counts "150 odd" and <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name>, 131.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-03-19" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-03-21" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
