<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1803-09-10">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">September 10, 1803</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2003</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 2</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">August 30, 1803–August 24, 1804</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1986</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">76-79</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc/>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2003-12-10</date>
            <date/>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>
            <name/>Initial creation Transcribed</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date>September 10, 1803</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>10th</date>
               </ab>
               <p>
The rain ceased about day, the clouds had not dispersed, and looked very much like giving us a repetition of the last evening's frallic, there was but little fogg and I should have been able to have set out at sunrise, but the Corporal had not yet returned with the bread—    I began to fear that he was 〈miffed〉 piqued with the sharp reprimand I gave him the evening before for his negligence &amp; inattention with respect to the bread and had deserted; in this however I was agreeably disappointed, about 8 in the morning he came up bring with him the two men and the bread, they instantly embarked and we set out    we passed several very bad riffles this morning at at 11 Oclock six miles below our encampment of last evening I landed on the east side of R. and went on shore to view a remarkable artificial mound of earth called by the people in this neighbourhood the Indian grave.—<ref target="n02091001" n="1"/>
               </p>
               <p>
	This remarkable mound of earth stands on the east bank of the <name type="place" key="Ohio River">Ohio</name> 12 miles below <name type="place" key="Wheeling, W. Va.">Wheeling</name> and about 700 paces from the river, as the land is not cleard the mound is not visible from the river—this mound gives name to two small creeks called <name type="place" key="Grave Creek">little and big grave creek</name>
                  <ref target="n02091002" n="2"/> which passing about a half a mile on each side of it &amp; fall into <name type="place" key="Ohio">ohio</name> about a mile distant from each other    the small creek is above, the mound stands on the most elivated ground of a large bottom containing about 4000 acres of land    the bottom is bounded from N. E. to S. W. by a high range of hills which seem to discribe a simecircle around it of which the river is the dimater, the hills being more distant from the mound than the river, near the mound to the N. stands a small town lately laid out called <name type="place" key="Elizabethtown, Ohio">Elizabeth-town</name>
                  <ref target="n02091003" n="3"/>  there are but about six or seven dwelling houses in it as yet, in this town there are several mounds of the same kind of the large one but not near as large, in various parts of this bottom the traces of old intrenchments are to be seen tho' they are so imperfect that they cannot be traced in such manner as to make any complete figure; for this enquire I had not leasure. I shall therefore content myself by giving a discription of the large mound and offering some conjectures with regard to the probable purposes for which they were intended by their founders; who ever they may have been.—</p>
               <p>
	the mound is nearly a regular cone 310 yards in circumpherence at it's base &amp; 65 feet high terminating in a blont point whose diameter is 30 feet, this point is concave being depressed about five feet in the center, arround the base runs a ditch 60 feet in width which is broken or intesected by a ledge of earth raised as high as the outer bank of the ditch on the N. W. side, this bank is about 30 feet wide and appers to have formed the enterence to fortifyed mound—    near the summet of this mound grows a white oak tree whose girth is 13 ½ feet, from the aged appeance of this tree I think it's age might resonably calculated at 300 years, the whole mound is covered with large timber, sugar tree, hickory, poplar, red and white oak &amp;c—<ref target="n02091004" n="4"/>  I was informed that in removing the earth of a part of one of those lesser mounds that stands in the town the skeletons of two men were found and some brass beads were found among the earth near these bones, my informant told me the beads were sent to <name type="person" key="Peale, Charles Willson">Mr. Peals</name> museum<ref target="n02091005" n="5"/> in <name type="place" key="Philadelphia, Pa.">Philadelphia</name> where he believed they now were.—<ref target="n02091006" n="6"/>
               </p>
               <p>
	we got on twenty four miles this day.    we passed some bad riffles but got over them without the assistance of cattle    came too on the E. side in deep water and a bold shore    staid all night a little above <name type="place" key="Sunfish Creek">sunfish creek</name>
                  <ref target="n02091007" n="7"/>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n02091001" n="1">Now <name type="place" key="Grave Creek Mound">Grave Creek Mound</name>, at <name type="place" key="Moundsville, W. Va.">Moundsville</name>, <name type="place" key="Marshall County, W. Va.">Marshall County</name>, <name type="place" key="West Virginia">West Virginia</name>, the largest conical tumulus in the <name type="place" key="Ohio River">Ohio</name> valley, similar to those of the Adena culture of the area. Descriptions vary, but it is over seventy feet in height, some nine hundred feet in circumference at the base, and approximately fifty feet across at the top. One excavation found it to contain two large timbered burial vaults. <hi rend="italic">West Virginia Guide</hi>, 513; Hodge, 1:506–7. The mound is pre-Hopewellian and is estimated to date from 100 B.C. James B. Griffin, professor emeritus of anthropology, University of Michigan, personal communication.</note>
            <note xml:id="n02091002" n="2">Now <name type="place" key="Little Grave Creek">Little Grave Creek</name> and <name type="place" key="Grave Creek">Grave Creek</name>, flowing into the <name type="place" key="Ohio River">Ohio</name> north and south of <name type="place" key="Moundsville, W. Va.">Moundsville</name>, respectively.</note>
            <note xml:id="n02091003" n="3">
               <name type="person" key="Tomlinson, Joseph, Jr.">Joseph Tomlinson, Jr.</name>, laid out the town in 1798 and named it for his wife. It was consolidated with nearby <name type="place" key="Mound City, W. Va.">Mound City</name> in 1865 as <name type="place" key="Moundsville, W. Va.">Moundsville</name>, county seat of <name type="place" key="Marshall County, W. Va.">Marshall County</name>
               <hi rend="italic">West Virginia Guide</hi>, 513; Thwaites (EWT), 3:360 n. 40.</note>
            <note xml:id="n02091004" n="4">The "sugar tree" is probably <hi rend="italic">Acer saccharum</hi> Marsh., sugar, rock, or hard maple, but possibly <hi rend="italic">A. saccharinum</hi> L., silver, white, or soft maple; the hickory can be one of five species of <hi rend="italic">Carya;</hi> the poplar is <hi rend="italic">Liriodendron tulipifera</hi> L., tulip tree, tulip-poplar, poplar, whitewood; the red oak is <hi rend="italic">Quercus borealis</hi> Michx. var. <hi rend="italic">maxima</hi> (Marsh.) Ashe, northern red oak; the white oak is <hi rend="italic">Q. alba</hi> L. Fernald, 986–88, 676, 543; Gleason &amp; Cronquist, 453–54, 252; Little, 112-E, 113-E, 115-E, 117-E, 118-E. These species are more or less typical of the upland dedicuous mixed mesophytic forests of the <name type="place" key="Cumberland Plateau">Cumberland Plateau</name> region as described by Braun, 52.</note>
            <note xml:id="n02091005" n="5">
               <name type="person" key="Peale, Charles Willson">Charles Willson Peale</name>, noted portrait painter and father of a family of artists, was also the proprietor of <name type="person" key="Peale, Charles Willson">Peale's</name> Museum in <name type="place" key="Philadelphia, Pa.">Philadelphia</name>, at the time the only natural history museum in the country. He began it in 1786 with fossils from <name type="place" key="Big Bone Lick">Big Bone Lick</name> in <name type="place" key="Kentucky">Kentucky</name>; by 1802 he had 1,800 different birds, 250 "quadrupeds," and innumerable other species. At the time of the expedition the museum was housed in present <name type="place" key="Independence Hall (Pa.)">Independence Hall</name>. <name type="person" key="Peale, Charles Willson">Peale</name> was a friend of <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> and probably acquainted with <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, who would send back specimens eventually housed in his institution. Sellers; Kastner, 143–58.</note>
            <note xml:id="n02091006" n="6">The remaining one-half page and the next five pages are blank. Perhaps <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> had in mind writing further descriptions.</note>
            <note xml:id="n02091007" n="7">In <name type="place" key="Marshall County, W. Va.">Marshall County</name>, nearly opposite <name type="place" key="Clarington, Ohio">Clarington</name>, <name type="place" key="Ohio">Ohio</name>. There may be some confusion about <name type="place" key="Sunfish Creek">Sunfish Creek</name> which is identified by Cramer (5th), as another stream higher up the <name type="place" key="Ohio River">Ohio</name>. Quaife (MLJO), 42 n. 2.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1803-09-09" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1803-09-11" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
