<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-09-04">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
September 4, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 8</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">June 10–September 26, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1987</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">348-350</biblScope>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">358-359</biblScope>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">275-276</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc/>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-12-21</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date>September 4, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Thursday 4th September 1806</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
The Musquitors became troublesom early this morning    I rose at the usial hour found all the party as wet as rain could make them.    as we were in want of Some tobacco I purposed to <name type="person" key="Aird, James">Mr. Airs</name> to furnish us with 4 Carrots for which we would Pay the amount to any Merchant of <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> he very readily agreed to furnish us with tobacco and gave to each man as much as it is necessary for them to use between this and <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>, an instance of Generossity for which every man of the party appears to acknowledge. <name type="person" key="Aird, James">Mr. Airs</name> also insisted on our accepting a barrel of flour—we gave to this gentleman what Corn we Could Spear amounting to about 6 bushels, this Corn was well Calculated for his purpose as he was about to make his establishment and would have it in his power to hull the Corn &amp; The flower was very acceptable to us.    we have yet a little flour part of what we carried up from the <name type="place" key="Illinois">Illinois</name> as high as <name type="place" key="Marias River">Maria's river</name> and buried it there untill our return &amp;c.    at 8 A. M    we took our leave and Set out, and proceeded on very well, at 11 A. M. passed the Enterance of the <name type="place" key="Big Sioux River (Rivière des Sioux)">big Sieoux River</name>
                  <ref target="n40090401" n="1"/> which is low, and at meridian we came too at <name type="place" key="Floyd's Bluff">Floyds Bluff</name> below the Enterance of <name type="place" key="Floyd River">Floyds river</name>
                  <ref target="n40090402" n="2"/> and assended the hill, with <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt Lewis</name> and Several men, found the grave had been opened by the nativs and left half Covered.<ref target="n40090403" n="3"/>    we had this grave Completely filled up, and returned to the Canoes and proceeded on to the Sand bar on which we encamped from the 12th to the 20th of August 1804<ref target="n40090404" n="4"/> near the <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Mahar</name> Village,<ref target="n40090405" n="5"/> here we came to and derected every wet article put out to dry, all the bedding of the party and Skins being wet.    as it was late in the evening we deturmined to continue all night.    had issued to each man of the party a cup of flour.    we See no Species of Game on the river as usial except wild geese and pelicans. I observed near <name type="person" key="Floyd, Charles">Sergt Floyds</name> Grave a number of flurishing black walnut trees,<ref target="n40090406" n="6"/> these are the first which I have seen decending the river.    a little before night Several Guns were heard below and in a direction towards the <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Mahar</name> village which induced us to suspect that <name type="person" key="McClellan, Robert">Mr. McClellin</name> who we was informed was on his way up to trade with the <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Mahars</name> had arived at the Creek below and that those reports of Guns was Some of his party out hunting.    every thing being dry we derected the Perogue &amp; Canoes to be loaded and in readiness to Set out in the morning early. at dark the Musquetors became troublesom and continued So all night the party obtained but little Sleep—    we made <hi rend="italic">36</hi> miles only to daye.
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Thursday 4th Sept. 1806.    a fair morning, but the hard rain and Thunder continued the greater part of last night.    the Musquetoes troublesome. <name type="person" key="Aird, James">Mr. Herd</name> Gave us a berril of flour although he had a boat Sunk and nearly all his provisions lost but they have a good hunter hired for that purpose a malattoe &amp;C.    we gave them a quantity of corn which the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name> gave us. <name type="person" key="Aird, James">Mr. Heard</name> gave us Some tobacco &amp;C &amp;C    we Set out Soon after Sunrise and procd. on verry well    towards evening we arived at the <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Mahars</name> village<ref target="n40090407" n="7"/>    found that this nation were out a hunting but had fields of corn growing at the back part of the bottom where they formerly had a large village but were cut off in a great measure by the Small pox Some years ago. So we Camped<ref target="n40090408" n="8"/> here and dryed our baggage which got wet last night, &amp;C    the Musquetoes verry troublesome indeed.—


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Thursday 4th.</hi>    There was a cloudy morning. We exchanged some corn with <name type="person" key="Aird, James">Mr. Aird</name> for tobacco, which our party stood much in need of; and his party, having lost a boat load of provisions in their way up, wanted the corn. We then proceeded on till we came to our old camp near the <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Maha</name> village, where we halted to dry our baggage, which got very wet last night, and remained all night. The natives are all out in the plains.



</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n40090401" n="1">The <name type="place" key="Big Sioux River (Rivière des Sioux)">Big Sioux River</name> reaches the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> between <name type="place" key="Union County, S. Dak.">Union County</name>, <name type="place" key="South Dakota">South Dakota</name>, and <name type="place" key="Woodbury County, Iowa">Woodbury County</name>, <name type="place" key="Iowa">Iowa</name>, at <name type="place" key="Sioux City, Iowa">Sioux City</name>; the party first passed it on <ref n="1804-08-21" type="related">August 21, 1804</ref>. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> maps 16, 17; MRC map 28.</note>
            <note xml:id="n40090402" n="2">
               <name type="place" key="Floyd River">Floyd River</name> in <name type="place" key="Woodbury County, Iowa">Woodbury County</name>, passed the day <name type="person" key="Floyd, Charles">Sergeant Charles Floyd</name> died and was buried at <name type="place" key="Sioux City, Iowa">Sioux City</name>, <ref n="1804-08-20" type="related">August 20, 1804</ref>. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 16; MRC map 27.</note>
            <note xml:id="n40090403" n="3">In 1810 <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> told <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name> that a <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name> chief encamped near the gravesite had lost a son and had opened the grave and placed the son's body with <name type="person" key="Floyd, Charles">Floyd's</name>, "for the purpose of accompanying him to the other world believing the white man's future state was happier than that of the Savages." It is not clear whether the opening of the grave <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> refers to here was this second burial, or whether that was done some time after the party's return. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> could easily have learned of a later disturbance of the site through his fur trade contacts. It raises the question of whether all the bones buried under the present <name type="person" key="Floyd, Charles">Sergeant Floyd</name> Monument at <name type="Iowa" key="Sioux City, Iowa">Sioux City</name> actually belonged to the sergeant. <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name> Notes [ca. April 1810], Jackson (LLC), 2:541–42; Appleman (LC), 285–87.</note>
            <note xml:id="n40090404" n="4">They camped here again, in either <name type="place" key="Woodbury County, Iowa">Woodbury County</name>, or in <name type="place" key="Dakota County, Nebr.">Dakota County</name>, <name type="place" key="Nebraska">Nebraska</name>, but <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> is mistaken about the date they first came there, which was <ref n="1804-08-13" type="related">August 13, 1804</ref>. They called it the "<name type="place" key="Fish Camp">Fishing Camp</name>"</note>
            <note xml:id="n40090405" n="5">The <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Omaha</name> village noted on <ref n="1804-08-13" type="related">August 13, 1804</ref>, situated just north of <name type="place" key="Homer, Nebr.">Homer</name> in <name type="place" key="Dakota County, Nebr.">Dakota County</name>, <name type="place" key="Nebraska">Nebraska</name>. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 16.</note>
            <note xml:id="n40090406" n="6">Black walnut, <hi rend="italic">Juglans nigra</hi> L., actually extends farther up the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri River</name> than <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> allows. However, the walnut probably existed in sheltered ravines and would be noticed only well back from the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> floodplain and beyond <name type="person"
                     key="Clark Fork (Clark's, East Fork Clark's, Flathead) River">Clark's view</name>. Barkley, 38; Little (CIH), 134-E.</note>
            <note xml:id="n40090407" n="7">The <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Omaha</name> village they had visited on <ref n="1804-08-13" type="related">August 13, 1804</ref>, just north of <name type="place" key="Homer, Nebr.">Homer</name>, <name type="place" key="Dakota County, Nebr.">Dakota County</name>, <name type="place" key="Nebraska">Nebraska</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n40090408" n="8">In either <name type="place" key="Woodbury County, Iowa">Woodbury County</name>, <name type="place" key="Iowa">Iowa</name>, or <name type="place" key="Dakota County, Nebr.">Dakota County</name>, <name type="place" key="Nebraska">Nebraska</name>. <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> and <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name> fail to mention that some of the party visited <name type="person" key="Floyd, Charles">Floyd's</name> grave this day and covered it again after it had been opened by some Indians.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-09-03" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-09-05" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
