<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.introduction.v04">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">Introduction to Volume 4</title>
            <title type="sub">April 7-July 27, 1805</title>
            <author>Gary E. Moulton</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 4</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">April7–July 27, 1805</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1987</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">1-4</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-03-30</date>
            <date/>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>
            <name/>Initial creation Transcribed</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="main">Introduction to Volume 4<lb/>
            <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name>, <name type="place" key="North Dakota">North Dakota</name>, to <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Three Forks of the">Three Forks of Missouri River</name>, <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>
         </head>
         <head type="sub">April 7–July 27, 1805</head>
         <div type="introduction">
            <p>On April 7, 1805, the permanent party of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> expedition set out
up the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri River</name> from <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name> in present day <name type="place" key="North Dakota">North Dakota</name>. They had
spent the winter among the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> Indians, waiting for the river's 
ice to break up and make travel possible. On the same day that they headed 
upriver, their keelboat which had brought them as far as the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> villages set 
off downriver for <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> with most of their French boatmen and a squad of 
soldiers under <name type="person" key="Warfington, Richard">Corporal Richard Warfington</name>. The boat carried dispatches and 
ethnological and natural history specimens which the captains were sending back 
to <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">President Thomas Jefferson</name>—the first fruits of the expedition.
</p>
            <p>
The Corps of Discovery was now entering an area where there had been no 
previous white exploration, although they were informed about the country 
as far as the <name type="place" key="Continental Divide">Continental Divide</name> from the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name>. They also had 
with them the <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshone</name> woman <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name>, through whom they hoped to make 
friendly contact with her people living along the <name type="place" key="Continental Divide">divide</name>. Beyond that point they 
could only hope that with Indian assistance and guidance they could make a portage of the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky Mountains</name> to some navigable stream flowing into the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>, and thus reach the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>.
</p>
            <p>
They would spend the rest of the spring and summer toiling their way up the 
<name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> to its headwaters in their two pirogues and six canoes. On April 25 
<name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> with four men reached the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone River</name>, near the present <name type="place" key="North Dakota">North
Dakota</name>-<name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name> boundary. Two days later, after taking astronomical readings
to fix the position of the site, they passed on into <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>. The journey across 
<name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>, unlike the earlier stages of the trip, brought no encounters with Indians. The party observed signs of <name type="native_nation" key="Assiniboine Indians">Assiniboine</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name> encampments, but 
the people themselves were absent. It may be, however, that Indians did observe 
the group's passage without making themselves known. In place of meetings with 
Indians, however, the party began a series of combats with grizzly bears. At first 
they had thought that their superior weaponry would give them an advantage 
over these animals—one not possessed by the Indians. Instead, the subsequent 
encounters led them to feel some of the same awe and respect for the bear that 
the Indians did.
</p>
            <p>
Other natural phenomena posed even greater dangers. The severe spring 
winds sometimes made it impossible to navigate safely on the river, thus impeding their progress. On May 14 a pirogue turned on its side in a squall of wind, 
nearly causing the loss of its contents and passengers, including <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name> and 
her baby. Aside from the potential human tragedy, the loss of the supplies in the 
pirogue might have made it impossible for the expedition to continue; fortunately the quick action of boatman <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Pierre Cruzatte</name> righted the craft and saved 
the situation.
</p>
            <p>
As they moved west the country grew increasingly arid and rugged. Small 
mountain ranges in the distance came into view which the captains assumed to be 
part of the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rockies</name>. To the north and south they were viewing the present <name type="place" key="Bears Paw (North) Mountains">Bears
Paw</name>, <name type="place" key="Little Rocky (North) Mountains">Little Rocky</name>, and <name type="place" key="Judith (South) Mountains">Judith mountains</name>. In late May the travelers entered the 
<name type="place" key="Missouri River, Breaks of the">Breaks of the Missouri</name>, an area of colorful and impressive geological formations, 
including the fantastically sculpted <name type="place" key="Missouri River, White Cliffs of the">White Cliffs</name>, which prompted <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> to pen a 
romantic description of these "seens of visionary enchantment." <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> named one 
major stream in the area for a young woman, <name type="person" key="Hancock, Julia">Julia Hancock</name>, who would later 
become his wife and today it retains that name, the <name type="place" key="Judith River">Judith</name>. The captains were 
also beginning to notice new species not seen on the lower <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>. Ponderosa 
pine began to appear as did quaking aspen, sagebrush, and new varieties of 
willows and cottonwood trees. They were also taken with the abundance of currants and gooseberries. While the expedition's fisherman <name type="person" key="Goodrich, Silas">Silas Goodrich</name> caught 
goldeye and cutthroat trout, others saw new animals such as the prairie rattlesnake, the <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name> horned owl, and the thirteen-lined ground squirrel.
</p>
            <p>
After nearly two months of travel, on June 2, the Corps arrived at the mouth 
of a major fork of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> which they named the <name type="place" key="Marias River">Marias River</name>, after a cousin 
of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>. This stream posed a dilemma, for none of the information given them 
by the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name> had referred to this stream. The problem was to determine which fork was the true <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, which would lead them to the <name type="place" key="Continental Divide">Contiental Divide</name>. To make the wrong decision and take the wrong river might cause 
such delay as to leave them stranded in the mountains in winter with the likelihood that the expedition would fail altogether. Matters were not helped by the 
fact that, while the captains believed that the river coming from the southwest 
was the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, virtually all their men were sure that the other fork was the one 
to be followed. The captains led reconnaissances a short distance up each stream, 
without reaching any satisfactory conclusion. Finally they decided to set off up 
the southwest fork, with <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> going ahead with a few men in the hope of finding an identifiable landmark soon enough to determine if they were in error.
</p>
            <p>
On June 13 <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> found the evidence that proved they were on the right 
river; the <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name> had told them of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">Great Falls of the Missouri</name>, the point at 
which the river emerged from the mountains. As his little group walked upstream, Lewis heard a roaring and saw clouds of spray that could only come from 
the falls. His relief was great, reflected in his ecstatic description of the beauty of 
the "sublime" spectacle, but the presence of the five cascades and intervening 
rapids presented a new problem, for the canoes and supplies must now be portaged around this obstacle. This task would consume an entire month of their 
precious time.
</p>
            <p>
A survey of the area showed that a portage of about eighteen miles would be 
necessary to skirt the falls. To transport the heavy canoes and goods to their upper 
portage camp they constructed crude carriages out of cottonwood, the wheels 
being rounded slabs of the trunks. The men had to pull heavy loads across ground 
roughened by the dried tracks of buffalo and infested with prickly pear cactus, 
all of which tormented their moccasined feet. The exertion was so great that at 
every rest stop they fell down and went immediately to sleep. Some of the men 
were exempted from this labor to hunt for the party's food, but they had to contend with the numerous grizzly bears. Heavy rain showers drenched everyone, 
and large hailstones injured several. During one downpour <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, surveying the 
falls with <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name>, <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name>, her <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Jean Baptiste">baby</name>, and <name type="person" key="York">York</name>, was nearly swept into 
the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> by a flash flood coming down the gully in which the little group had 
taken refuge.
</p>
            <p>
At the upper portage camp <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> labored on a collapsible boat of his own 
design, whose dismantled frame the party had transported across the continent 
for use when heavier boats had to be left behind. The frame could be bolted 
together and covered with animal skins. Unfortunately, tar was required to make 
the invention waterproof, and there were no pine trees near the area to provide 
it. Attempts to contrive a substitute were unsuccessful; the boat leaked too badly 
to be useful. The captains decided that <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> should go ahead several miles 
upriver where there were some sizable cottonwood trees and build two more 
dugout canoes.
</p>
            <p>
On July 15 the party set out from the canoe-building camp, after more than 
three months of travel from <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name>. First <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and then <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> forged
ahead of the main party looking for the <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshones</name>, for it was now vital to find 
these Indians to obtain horses and guides for the mountain crossing which increasingly appeared likely. The party moved through the deep canyon which 
they called "<name type="place" key="Gates of the Rocky Mountains">Gates of the Rocky Mountains</name>," a name which remains today. 
They were now within the mountains, and shallow waters and rapids would make 
navigation increasingly difficult. On July 25 <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> with four men reached the 
<name type="place" key="Missouri River, Three Forks of the">Three Forks of the Missouri</name>, of which the <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name> had told them. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> with the 
main party reached the forks two days later, and the captains decided to name 
the three streams the <name type="place" key="Jefferson River (North, Southwest Fork)">Jefferson</name>, the <name type="place" key="Madison River (Middle Fork)">Madison</name>, and the <name type="place" key="Gallatin (South, Southeast Fork) River">Gallatin</name>, after the president and his secretaries of state and treasury. There was still no contact with the 
<name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshones</name>, although various signs of their presence were evident. <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name> 
was now recognizing familiar landmarks. A meeting with her people was now 
their most urgent concern.

</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
