<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.preface.v06">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">Volume 6 Preface</title>
            <title type="sub"/>
            <author>Gary E. Moulton</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition, Volume 6</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">November 2, 1805–March 22, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1990</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">ix-x</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-07-16</date>
            <date/>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>
            <name/>Initial creation Transcribed</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="main">Volume 6 Preface</head>
         <head type="sub"/>
         <div type="preface">
            <p>
Numerous persons have helped us in bringing this volume to completion. Their subject knowledge or love of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> expedition and their selfless sharing of time and talents have increased the worth of the annotations to the text tremendously. The great captains and their party may have been able to accomplish their explorations without the help of native guides, but the going would have been far more difficult, time consuming, and hazardous. We too, may have completed our work without the assistance of specialists and dedicated laypersons, but the quality of the work would have suffered and our journeys into unknown areas would have been more burdensome without them. Our guides were friendly, wise, and generous.</p>
            <p>
Three special friends of this project have died since the publication of the last volume: Donald Jackson, Paul Russell Cutright, and Robert B. Betts. These men aided this endeavor with their writings, their advice, and their good will; they will be sorely missed. Their good names and good works will live on.</p>
            <p>
A number of people have continued helping the project. Robert E. Lange of Portland, Oregon, assisted in tracking down <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name> nomenclature and provided numerous other services. James P. Ronda and W. Raymond Wood were always at hand with comments, encouragement, and friendly advice. Robert B. Betts (New York City), Gladys Watkins Allen (Alton, Illinois), William P. Sherman (Portland, Oregon), and Lyle S. Woodcock (St. Louis, Missouri) contributed financially to the project. Likewise, the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Trail Heritage Foundation provided financial aid, and its many members have been steadfast friends and supporters.</p>
            <p>
At the principal repositories of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> materials we again had the professional and capable assistance of Beth Carroll-Horrocks, Martin L. Levitt, Roy E. Goodman, Edward C. Carter II, and Randolph S. Klein, all of the American Philosophical Society, Philadelphia, and Duane R. Sneddeker and Bryan Stephen Thomas of the Missouri Historical Society, St. Louis. Staff, office, and administrative help came from the Center for Great Plains Studies and the project itself at the University of Nebraska–Lincoln. We can thank Frederick C. Luebke, Rosalind K. Carr, and Lori L. Gourama of the Center, and Cindy L. Donnelly of the project for their important work.</p>
            <p>
We again turned to scholars in areas where we had little experience. As usual, we found these persons to be knowledgeable, patient, and generous.</p>
            <p>
ARCHAEOLOGY: Rick Minor, Heritage Research Associates, Eugene, Oregon; Kenneth M. Ames, Portland State University. BOTANY: A. T. Harrison, Westminster College, Salt Lake City; Margaret R. Bolick, University of Nebraska–Lincoln. GEOLOGY: Robert N. Bergantino, Montana Bureau of Mines and Geology, Butte; John Eliot Allen, Portland State University (emeritus). LINGUISTICS: American Indian linguistic data in the notes were collected by Raymond J. DeMallie, Indiana University, and were provided by the following individuals: <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Algonquian Indians">Algonquian</name>.</hi> Ives Goddard, Smithsonian Institution. <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookan</name>.</hi> Michael Silverstein and Robert E. Moore, both of the University of Chicago. <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Makah Indians">Makah</name>.</hi> Ann M. Bates, Indiana University. <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Salishan</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Alsea Indians">Alsea</name>.</hi> M. Dale Kinkade, University of British Columbia. <hi rend="italic">Latin.</hi> John D. Turner, University of Nebraska–Lincoln. ZOOLOGY: Patricia Freeman, University of Nebraska–Lincoln (mammals, taxonomy); Gary L. Hergenrader, University of Nebraska–Lincoln (fish); Thomas O. Holtzer, University of Nebraska–Lincoln (insects); John Janovy, University of Nebraska–Lincoln (coastal marine life); Jon D. Lynch, University of Nebraska–Lincoln (fish); Jim R. Rosowski, University of Nebraska–Lincoln (coastal marine life); Thomas B. Thorson, University of Nebraska–Lincoln (emeritus) (coastal marine life).</p>
            <p>
It is not expected that these persons' generosity extends to accepting blame for errors that may appear herein; we reserve that right.




</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
