<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-02-14">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
February 14, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 6</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">November 2, 1805–March 22, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1990</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">307-312</biblScope>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">271</biblScope>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 11</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of Joseph Whitehouse, May 14, 1804–April 2, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1997</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">420</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc/>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-08-26</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date>February 14, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Friday February 14th 1806.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
We are very uneasy with rispect to our sick men<ref target="n28021401" n="1"/> at the <name type="place" key="Saltmaking Camp (Oreg.)">salt works</name>. <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Sergt. Pryor</name> and party have not yet returned nor can we conceive what causes their delay. <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name> visited his traps today and caught a very fine fat beaver on which we feasted this evening.    on the 11th inst. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt Clark</name> completed a map of the country through which we have been passing from <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name> to this place.<ref target="n28021402" n="2"/>    in this map the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>
                  <name type="place" key="Beaverhead (Jefferson) River">Jefferson's river</name> the <name type="place" key="Gallatin (South, Southeast Fork) River">S. E. branch of the Columbia</name>, <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Kooskooske</name>
                  <ref target="n28021403" n="3"/> and <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> from the entrance of the S. E. fork to the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">pacific Ocean</name> as well as a part of 〈<name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">Flathead</name>〉 [<hi rend="italic">WC?: <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">Clarks</name>
                  </hi>] river<ref target="n28021404" n="4"/> and our tract across the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky Mountains</name> are laid down by celestial observation and survey.    the rivers are also connected at their sources with other rivers agreeably to the information of the natives and the most probable conjecture arrising from their capacities and the relative positions of their rispective entrances which last have with but few exceptions been established by celestial observation. we now discover that we have found the most practicable and navigable passage across the Continent of North America; it is that which we traveled with the exception of that part of our rout from the neighbourhood of the entrance of <name type="place" key="Dearborn River">Dearborn's River</name> untill we arrived on 〈the <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">Flat head</name>〉 [<hi rend="italic">WC?: <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">Clarks</name>
                  </hi>] <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">Clarks river</name> at the entrance of <name type="place" key="Lolo (Travelers' Rest) Creek (Mont.)">Traveler's rest creek</name>;<ref target="n28021405" n="5"/> the distance between those two points would be traveled more advantageously by land as the navigation of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> above the <name type="place" key="Dearborn River">river Dearborn</name> is laborious and 420 miles distant by which no advantage is gained as the rout which we are compelled to travel by land from the source of <name type="place" key="Beaverhead (Jefferson) River">Jefferson's river</name> to the entrance of <name type="place" key="Lolo (Travelers' Rest) Creek (Mont.)">Travelers rest Creek</name> is 220 miles being further by 500 miles than that from the entrance of <name type="place" key="Dearborn River">Dearborn's river</name> to the last mentioned point and a much <hi rend="italic">worse</hi> rout if Indian information is to be relyed on; from the same information the <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">Flathead river</name> like that of the <name type="place" key="Gallatin (South, Southeast Fork) River">S. E. fork of the Columbia</name> which heads with <name type="place" key="Beaverhead (Jefferson) River">Jefferson's</name> and <name type="place" key="Madison River (Middle Fork)">Maddison's</name> Rivers can not be navigated through the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky Mountains</name> in consequence of falls &amp; rappids and as a confermation of this fact, we discovered that there were no salmon in the <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">Flathead river</name>, which is the case in the <name type="place" key="Gallatin (South, Southeast Fork) River">S. E. branch of the Columbia</name> although it is not navigable.    added to this, the Indians further inform us, that the <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">Flathead river</name> runs in the direction of the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky Mountains</name> for a great distance to the North before it discharges itself into the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia river</name>, which last from the same information from the entrance of the S. E. fork to that of 〈<name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">Flathead</name>〉 [<hi rend="italic">WC?: <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">Clarks</name>
                  </hi>] river is obstructed with a great number of difficult and dangerous rappids.    considering therefore the danger and difficulties attending the navigation of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> in this part, as well as the circuitous and distant rout formed by itself and the 〈<name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">Flathead</name>〉 [<hi rend="italic">WC?: <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">Clarks</name>
                  </hi>] river we conceive that even admitting the 〈<name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">Flathead</name>〉 [<hi rend="italic">WC?: <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">Clarks</name>
                  </hi>] river contrary to information to be as navigable as the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia river</name> below it's entrance, that the tract by land over the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky Mountains</name> usually traveled by the natives from the Entrance of <name type="place" key="Lolo (Travelers' Rest) Creek (Mont.)">Traveller's-rest Creek</name> to the forks of the <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Kooskooske</name> is preferable; the same being a distance of 184 Miles. The inferrence therefore deduced from those premices are that the best and most Practicable rout across the Continent is by way of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> [<hi rend="italic">NB: <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">falls of Missouri</name>
                  </hi>] to the entrance of <name type="place" key="Dearborn River">Dearborn's river</name> or near that place; from thence to 〈<name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">flathead</name>〉 [<hi rend="italic">NB: <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">Clarks</name>
                  </hi>] river [<hi rend="italic">NB: by land to</hi>] at the entrance of <name type="place" key="Lolo (Travelers' Rest) Creek (Mont.)">Traveller's rest Creek</name>, from thence up <name type="place" key="Lolo (Travelers' Rest) Creek (Mont.)">Traveller's rest creek</name> to the forks, from whence you pursue a range of mounttains which divides the waters of the two forks of the <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Kooskooske river</name> to their junction; from thence to decend this river by water to the S. E. branch of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>, thence down that river to the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> and with the latter to the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific Ocean</name>.—
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Friday February 14th 1806</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
We are very uneasy with respect to our Sick men at the <name type="place" key="Saltmaking Camp (Oreg.)">Salt works</name>. <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Serjt. Pryor</name> and party haveing not yet returneded, nor can we conceive what can be the Cause of their delay. <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name> visited his traps &amp; to day and Cought a fine fat beaver on which we feasted this evening and thought it a great delecessey.—.</p>
               <p>
I compleated a <hi rend="italic">map</hi> of the Countrey through which we have been passing from the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name> at the Mouth of <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> to this place. In the Map the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>
                  <name type="place" key="Beaverhead (Jefferson) River">Jefferson's river</name> the S. E. branch of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> or <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Lewis's river</name>, <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Koos-koos-ke</name> and <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> from the enterance of the S. E fork to the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">pacific Ocian</name>, as well as a part of <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">Clark's<ref target="n28021406" n="6"/> river</name> and our track across the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky Mountains</name> are laid down by celestial observations and Survey.    the rivers are also conected at their Sources with other rivers agreeably to the information of the nativs and the most probable conjecture arrising from their capacities and the relative positions of their respective enterances which last have with but fiew exceptions been established by celestial observations. We now discover that we have found the most practicable and navigable passage across the Continent of North America; it is that which we have traveled with the exception of that part of our rout from the foot of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">
                     <hi rend="italic">Falls</hi> of the Missouri</name>, or in neighbourhood of the enterance of the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky Mountains</name> untill we arive on <name type="person" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">Clarks river</name> at the enterence of <name type="place" key="Lolo (Travelers' Rest) Creek (Mont.)">Travelers-rest Creek</name>; the distance between those two points would be traveled more advantagiously by land as the navigation of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> above the <hi rend="italic">Falls</hi> is crooked laborious and 521 miles distant by which no advantage is gained as the rout which we are compelled to travel by land from the Source of <name type="person" key="Beaverhead (Jefferson) River">Jeffersons River</name> to the enterance of <name type="place" key="Lolo (Travelers' Rest) Creek (Mont.)">
                     <hi rend="italic">Travellers rest</hi> Creek</name> is 220 miles being further by abt. 600 miles than that from the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">Falls of the Missourie</name> to the last mentioned point (<name type="place" key="Lolo (Travelers' Rest) Creek (Mont.)">Travellers rest Creek</name>) and a much worse rout if indian information is to be relied on which is from the <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">So so nee</name> or <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Snake</name> Indians, and the <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Flatheads</name> of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> west of the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">rocky mountains</name>.    from the Same information <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">Clarks river</name> like that of the S. E. branch of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> which heads with <name type="place" key="Beaverhead (Jefferson) River">Jefferson's</name> and <name type="place" key="Madison River (Middle Fork)">Maddisons</name> river's can not be navagated thro' the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">rocky mountain</name>s in consequence of falls and rapids, and as a confirmation of the fact we discovered that there were no Salmon in <name type="person" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">Clark's river</name>, which is not the Case in the S. E. branch of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> altho it is not navagable.    added to this, the Indians of different quartes further inform us, that <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">Clark's river</name> runs in the direction of the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky Mountains</name> for a great distance to the north before it discharges itself into the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia river</name>—.    from the Same information the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> from the enterance of the S. E. branch to the enterance of <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">Clark's river</name> is obstructed with a great number of dificuelt and dangerous rapids (and the place <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">Clark's river</name> comes out of the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky mountains</name> is a tremendious falls &amp;c which there is no possibillity of passing the mountains either by land or water.) Considering therefore the dangers and deficuelties attending the navigation of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> in this part, as well as the circuitous and distant rout formed by itself and that of <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">Clark's River</name> we Conceive that even admitting that <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">Clarks river</name> contrary to information to be as navagable as the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> below it's enterance, that the tract by land over the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky Mountains</name> usially traveled by the nativs from the enterance of <name type="place" key="Lolo (Travelers' Rest) Creek (Mont.)">Travellers rest Creek</name> to the Forks of the <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Kooskooske</name> is preferable; the Same being a distance of 184 miles. The inferrence therefore deduced from these premises are, that the best and most practicable rout across the Continent is by way of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> to the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">Great <hi rend="italic">Falls;</hi>
                  </name> thence to <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">
                     <hi rend="italic">Clarks </hi> river</name> at the enterance of <name type="place" key="Lolo (Travelers' Rest) Creek (Mont.)">Travellers rest Creek</name>, from thence up <name type="place" key="Lolo (Travelers' Rest) Creek (Mont.)">travillers rest Creek</name> to the forks, from whence you prosue a range of mountains which divides the waters of the two forks of this Creek, and which still Continues it's westwardly Course on the mountains which divides the waters of the two forks of the <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Kooskooske river</name> to their junction; from thence to decend this river to the S. E. branch of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>, thence down that river to the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>, and down the Latter to the <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific Ocian</name>—.</hi> There is a large river which falls into the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> on its South Side at what point we could not lern;<ref target="n28021407" n="7"/> which passes thro those extencive <name type="place" key="Great Columbian Plain">Columbian Plains</name> from the South East, and as the Indians inform us head in the mountains South of the head of <name type="person" key="Beaverhead (Jefferson) River">Jeffersons River</name> and at no great distance [<hi rend="italic">WC:</hi> ☞ <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="place" key="Willamette (Multnomah) River">Multnomah</name>
                  </hi>] from the Spanish Settlements, and that that fork which heads with the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">River Rajhone</name> and waters of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> passes through those extensive plains in which there is no wood, and the river Crowded with rapids &amp; falls many of which are impassable.    the other or westerly fork passes near a range of mountains and is the fork which great numbers of Indian Bands of the <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="place" key="Shoshone Indians">So sone</name>
                  </hi> or <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Snake</name> Indians, this fork most probably heads with North River or the waters of <name type="place" key="California">Callifornia</name>. This River may afford a practicable land Communication with <name type="place" key="New Mexico">New Mexico</name> by means of its western fork. This river cannot be navagable as an unpracticable rapid is within one mile of its enterance into the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>, and we are fully purswaded that a rout by this river if practicable at all, would lengthen the distance greatly and incounter the Same dificuelties in passing the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky Mountains</name> with the rout by way of <name type="place" key="Lolo (Travelers' Rest) Creek (Mont.)">Travellers rest Creek</name> &amp; <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">Clarks river</name>.

</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Friday 14th Feby. 1806.    the morning warm and Showers of rain through the course of this day.—

</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry">
            <sp who="jw">
               <speaker>Whitehouse</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Friday Febry 14th    This morning was warm, &amp; we had showers of rain during the whole of this day.—    The Men at the fort were employed in repairing the Carpenters Tools, making Moccasins &amp; dressing Elk &amp; Deer Skins.—

</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n28021401" n="1">
               <name type="place" key="Gibson, George">Gibson</name> and <name type="person" key="Bratton, William E.">Bratton</name>; see above, <ref n="1806-02-11" type="related">February 11, 1806</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28021402" n="2">Note the discrepancy between Lewis's description of this map and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> description, below. No single map that exactly matches the description has been found, but it was very likely a source for <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 123, or that map itself.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28021403" n="3">The "S. E. branch" is the <name type="place"
                     key="Salmon (Lewis's, Main Fork Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">Salmon</name> and the <name type="place"
                     key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Snake</name> below the confluence with the <name type="place"
                     key="Salmon (Lewis's, Main Fork Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">Salmon</name>; the captains' "<name type="place"
                     key="Salmon (Lewis's, Main Fork Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">Lewis's River</name>." The <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Kooskooske</name> is the <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Clearwater</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28021404" n="4">The combination of the <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">Bitterroot</name> and <name type="person"
                     key="Clark Fork (Clark's, East Fork Clark's, Flathead) River">Clark Fork rivers</name>. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 125.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28021405" n="5">
               <name type="place" key="Lolo (Travelers' Rest) Creek (Mont.)">Lolo Creek</name>, <name type="place" key="Missoula County, Mont.">Missoula County</name>, <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 69.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28021406" n="6">Each "<name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>" in this entry appears to have been written in later over some erasing, after the name was decided upon. Again the <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">Bitterroot</name>-<name type="place"
                     key="Clark Fork (Clark's, East Fork Clark's, Flathead) River">Clark Fork</name> combination. See the Introduction to the <hi rend="italic">Atlas.</hi>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="n28021407" n="7">Here <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> apparently combined Indian information about the <name type="place" key="Willamette (Multnomah) River">Willamette</name> and the <name type="place"
                     key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Snake</name> with deductions of their own. When they discovered the <name type="place" key="Willamette (Multnomah) River">Willamette</name> on their return journey, they assumed that the "<name type="place" key="Willamette (Multnomah) River">Multnomah</name>," as they called it, was the great river coming from the southeast. They believed that this river began near the headwaters of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> and the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone</name>, which is in fact the case with the <name type="place"
                     key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Snake</name>. Their notion that the Rio Grande (North River, or Rio del Norte) and the "waters of <name type="place" key="California">California</name>" (the <name type="place" key="Colorado River">Colorado River</name>?) also rose in this same general area (which is true of the <name type="place" key="Green River">Green River</name>, the principal tributary of the <name type="place" key="Colorado River">Colorado</name>) meant that they still clung to the conception of a height of land which gave rise to all the great rivers of the West. They still did not fully appreciate the extent of territory involved, nor could they know of the existence of the <name type="place" key="Great Basin">Great Basin</name>. Allen (PG), 327–28; <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 125.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-02-13" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-02-15" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
