<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1804-09-30">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
September 30, 1804</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 3</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">August 25, 1804–April 6, 1805</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1987</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">128-130</biblScope>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">73-74</biblScope>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">49</biblScope>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 11</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of Joseph Whitehouse, May 14, 1804–April 2, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1997</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">92-93</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc/>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-03-16</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date>September 30, 1804</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">30th of September</hi> Sunday 1804    had not proceeded far before we discovered an Indian running after us, he requstd to go with us to the <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Ricaras</name>
                  </hi>, we refused to take him, I discovered at a great Distanc a great number of men women &amp; Children decending a hill towards the river above which the Chief with us told us was the other Band, Some rain &amp; hard wind    at about 10 oClock we anchored opposit the Camps of this band and told them we took them by the hand, and Sent to each Chief a Carrot of Tobacco &amp; Some to the principal men and farth[er] Said that after Staying with the band below 2 days to See them we had been badly treated and Should not land again, as we had not time to Delay—    refured then to <name type="person" key="Dorion, Pierre, Sr.">Mr. Durion</name> for a full account of us, and an explination of what had been Said, they appeard ansioes for us to eat with them and observed they were friendly    we apoligised &amp; proceeded on under a Double reafed Sale—<ref target="n07093001" n="1"/>    the Chief on board threw out to those that ran up Small pieces of Tobacco &amp; told them to go back and open thier ears, We Saw great number of white guls—    refresh the party with whiskey, in the evening we Saw 2 Indians at a Distance, The boat turned by accident &amp; was nearly filling and rocked verry much, allarmed the Indian Chief on board who ran and hid himself, we landed &amp; the Indian express a wish to return, we gave him a Blanket Knife &amp; Some tobacco and advised him to keep his men away, we camped on a Sand bar.<ref target="n07093002" n="2"/> verry Cold &amp; windy—</p>
               <p>
                  <table rows="8" cols="3">
                     <head>Course &amp; Distance</head>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 30° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">3</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">m. to the upper point of Some woods S. S.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 80° W</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">1 ½</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">m on the S. S—</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 64° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">3</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">m. to a Bush on the L. S.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 46° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">1 ½</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">m. on the L. S.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 10° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">3</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">m. to a pt. on the S. S.    passed the 2nd Band of <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Tetons</name>,</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">North</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">2</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">m. to a tree on the S. S.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 24° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">4</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">m. to a point on the L. S.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 50° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">2 ½</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">m to the Lower point of <name type="place" key="Cheyenne (Pawnee) Island">Pania Island</name>.</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">30th Septr.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <table rows="9" cols="3">
                     <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Course Distance &amp; reffurenc</hi>
                     </head>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 30° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  3</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">miles to a tree at the upper pt. of Some woods on the S. S.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 80° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  1 ½</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">miles on the S. S.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 64° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  3</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">ms. to a Bush on L. S.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 46° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  1 ½</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">mes. on the L. S.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 10 W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  3</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">mes. to a pt. on the S. S.    passed Several Sand bars &amp; the<lb/>
Camp of a Band of <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Tetons</name> (1)</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">North</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  2</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">miles to a tree on the S. S.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 24° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  4</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">mes. to a pt. on the L. S.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N 50° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                           <hi rend="underline">  2 ½</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">mes. to the Lower pt. of <name type="place" key="Cheyenne (Pawnee) Island">Pania Island</name> Situated in the Mide.<lb/>
of the river (2)</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                           <hi rend="double underline">20 ½</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="right">30th of Septr. Sunday 1804.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
Set out this morning early    had not proceeded on far before we discovered an Indn. running after us, he came up with us at 7 oClock &amp; requested to come on bord and go up to the <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">recorees</name>
                  </hi>    we refused to take any of that band on board    if he chose to proceed on Shore it was verry well   Soon after I discovered on the hills at a great distance great numbers of Indians which appeared to be makeing to the river above us, we proceeded on under a Double reafed Sail, &amp; Some rain    at 9 oClock observed a large band of Indians the Same which I had before Seen on the hills incamping on the bank 〈of〉 the L. S.    we Came too on a Sand bar Brackfast &amp; proceeded on &amp; cast the ancher opposit their Lodgs. at about 100 yards distand, and informed the Indians which we found to be a part of the Band we had before Seen, that [<hi rend="italic">NB?: we</hi>] took them by the hand and Sent to each Chief a Carrot of tobacco, as we had been treated badly by Some of the band below, after Staying 2 days for them, we Could not delay any time, &amp; refured them to <name type="person" key="Dorion, Pierre, Sr.">Mr. Duron</name> for a full account of us and to here our talk Sent by him to the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Tetons</name>, those were verry Selecitious for us to land and eate with them, that they were friendly &amp;c. &amp;.    we appoligised &amp; proceeded on, Sent the peroge to Shore above with the Tobacco &amp; Delivd. it to a Soldr. of the Chief with us    Several of them    ran up the river, the Chf. on board threw then out a Small twist of Tobacco &amp; told them to go back &amp; open ther ears.    they recved the Tobacco &amp; returned to their lodges—    we Saw great numbers of white guls    this day is cloudy &amp; rainey—    refresh the men with a glass of whisky after Brackfast.</p>
               <p>
we Saw about 6 miles above 2 Indians who came to the bank and looked at us a about ½ an hour &amp; went over the hills to the S W.    we proceeded on under a verry Stiff Breeze from the S. 〈W〉 E, the Stern of the boat got fast on a log and the boat turned &amp; was verry near filling before we got her righted, the waves being verry high, The Chief on board was So fritined at the motion of the boat which in its rocking caused Several loose articles to fall on the Deck from the lockers, he ran off and hid himself, we landed    he got his gun and informed us he wished to return, that all things were Cleare for us to go on we would not See <hi rend="italic">any</hi> more <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Tetons</name> &amp;c.    we repeated to him what had been Said before and advised him to keep his men away, gave him a blanket a Knife &amp; Some Tobacco, Smokd a pipe &amp; he 〈Dep〉 Set out.    we also Set Sale and Came to at a Sand bar, &amp; Camped, a verrey Cold evening, all on ou[r] guard

</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Sunday 30th Sept. 1804</hi>.    we Set off eairly under a fine Breeze of wind from the E.    passed a willow Island N. S.    passd. a large Bottom covered with Timber on N. S. Barron hills on S. S. See an Indian on S. S. Spoke to him.    found it was one of those we Saw at village below.    he told us that the other band was comming on, and wished us to Stop.    we told him we could not Stop neither did we wish to See them.    passed handsom Bottom prarie on N. S.    a bottom covered with Timber on S. S.    proceeded on 10 miles    at 10 oClock we discovered a large nomber of Indians on a hill S. Side comming down towards the river a head of.    we halted on a Sand bar, took breakfast.    the Indians assembled on S. Shore hoisted a white flag.    we then took down our red flag.    directly after they hoisted another. We then took them to be our friends.    the weather being cool, cloudy a mist of rain 〈the〉 our officers Gave Each man of the party a draghm.    we then hoisted our Sails &amp; Sailed up to where the Indians was assembled about 200 of them on the Bank of the River S. S.    had put up one or 2 lodges which was white.    we ankered out opposite to them about 100 yards. Spoke to them to know what they wanted.    they Sayed they wanted us to come on Shore and eat with them &amp; Smoak, for they were our friends &amp;.C.    our Capts. told them our reason was that we had been ill treated by the band below, and that we would not Stop but we were friends to them &amp; would Send them Some tobacco for a token that he had taken them by the hand. And then we Should go on to the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Rick Rees</name> where we Should halt again.    we then Sent them Some tobacco &amp;.C.    hoisted Sail    proceeded on    passed a Creek on S. S.<ref target="n07093003" n="3"/>    passd. a bottom covered with Timber on N. S.    passd an Island &amp; large Sand bars on S. Side.    the old <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name> chief remained with us in order to go to the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">R. Rees</name> nation.—    We passed a large quantity of Grapes in the Bottom of Small Timber on N. Side.—    proceeded on till about 4 oClock    put to Shore in order to take Some fire wood on board.    when we put off the Stern of our Barge got fast. She Swang round in the Stream    the wind being So hard from E. that caused the waves to run high the Boat got in the trough &amp; She rocked verry much before we could git hir Strait    we hoisted Sail and came Strait. Sailed verry fast.    the Indian chief we had on board was verry fraid.    he Said he thought our Boat was a medicine &amp; he would go no further with us.    we then put him to Shore    our Captains Gave him a Blanket, Some tobacco a knife and Some other Small articles.    he then Set of to return to his Band. We Sailed on verry fast.    came 24 miles this day. Camped on a Sand bar on N. S.


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Sunday 30th.</hi> We set out early in a cloudy morning; passed black buffs on the south side, and handsome bottom prairie on the north; saw an Indian on the shore, and the chief we had on board spoke to him. He said he wished to come on board and go with us to the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Rees</name>; but we did not take him. The wind was fair and we made 9 miles by 10 o'clock. We saw a great number of Indians coming down to the river on the south side. We stopt for breakfast about 200 yards from the shore; then proceeded about a mile; near to the place where the Indians were encamped on the south side; we halted and spoke to them<ref target="n07093004" n="4"/> and then went on under a fine breeze of wind.</p>
               <p>
A short time before night, the waves ran very high and the boat rocked a great deal, which so alarmed our old chief, that he would not go any further. We encamped on the north side.


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry">
            <sp who="jw">
               <speaker>Whitehouse</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Sunday 30th Sept. 1804.    Set off eairly.    a cloudy morning.    we proceeded on    Saw a Great nomber of Indians on the S. S. comming down the river.    we halted a fiew minutes and Gave them Some tobacco &amp; Spoke a fiew words to them, and went on under a fine breeze of wind    towards night the waves ran &amp; our boat rocked So that it Skared our old Indian which was on board    He was afraid to go any further with us, and went out on Shore in order to return to his nation.    we Camped on the N. S. of the river.—</p>
               <p>
Sunday Septemr 30    We set off early this morning, having cloudy weather, We proceeded on, &amp; saw a great number of Indians, on the South side of the River; Running down to the River, The Officers stopped the boat a few minutes, and gave them some Tobacco, The Interpreter<ref target="n07093005" n="5"/> spoke a few Words to them; they belonging to the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Souix</name> nation; which is by farr the most numerous Tribe of Indians, that Inhabit along the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Mesouri</name>, We proceeded on with a favourable breeze of Wind, towards evening, the Waves ran very high, and our boat Rocked exceedingly—</p>
               <p>
The Indian who was on board the boat, was so much frightened at the boat rocking,—    that he requested to be put on shore; being afraid to venture any further with us.—</p>
               <p>
We landed this Indian on the shore, after the Officers had made him some presents, and he took a friendly leave of us and returned towards his nation—    We proceeded on 'till Evening, and encamped on a Bank lying on the North side of the River.—


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n07093001" n="1">The sail was reefed, that is, folded or rolled, in two places to reduce the effect of the wind.</note>
            <note xml:id="n07093002" n="2">
               <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> clearly states that they camped on a sand bar, but the last course ends at "<name type="place" key="Cheyenne (Pawnee) Island">Pania Island</name>," which from <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 23 is apparently the later <name type="place" key="Cheyenne (Pawnee) Island">Cheyenne Island</name>, just below the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Cheyenne River">Cheyenne River</name>. It is unclear whether the camp was on the island or on a sand bar on the <name type="place" key="Sully County, S. Dak.">Sully County</name>, <name type="place" key="South Dakota">South Dakota</name>, shore, but <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> says they camped on the north, that is, starboard, side. The area is now inundated by the <name type="place" key="Oahe Reservoir">Oahe Reservoir</name>. Mattison (OR), 56–57; MRC map 42.</note>
            <note xml:id="n07093003" n="3">Not mentioned by <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> or other journalists, nor shown on expedition maps. It may be
<name type="place" key="Agency Creek">Agency Creek</name>, <name type="place" key="Stanley County, S. Dak.">Stanley County</name>, <name type="place" key="South Dakota">South Dakota</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n07093004" n="4">See <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> account of this conversation.</note>
            <note xml:id="n07093005" n="5">Perhaps <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Cruzatte</name>, who spoke the <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Omaha</name> language and perhaps a little <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name>
               <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name> or 
Lakota.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1804-09-29" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1804-09-30-1" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
