<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-12-03">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
December 3, 1805</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 6</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">November 2, 1805–March 22, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1990</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">106-107</biblScope>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">258</biblScope>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">179</biblScope>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 11</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of Joseph Whitehouse, May 14, 1804–April 2, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1997</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">401</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc/>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-07-29</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date>December 3, 1805</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">December 3rd Tuesday 1805</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
a fair windey morning wind from the East, the men Sent after an Elk yesterday returnd. with an Elk which revived the Sperits of my men verry much, I am unwell and cannot Eate, the flesh    O! how disagreeable my Situation, a plenty of meat and incaple of eateing any—    an Indian Canoe Came down with 8 Indians in it from the upper village, I gave a fish hook for a fiew <hi rend="italic">Wap-e-to</hi> roots, which I eate in a little Elk Supe, The Indians proceeded on down.    wind Contines to blow, and <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Serjt. Pryor</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Gibson, George">Gibson</name> who went to hunt yesterday has not returnd. as yet    I marked my name &amp; the day of the month and year on a large Pine tree on this Peninsella &amp; by land "<name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt William Clark</name> 〈November〉 December 3rd 1805.    By Land. U States in 1804 &amp; 1805"—<ref target="n26120301" n="1"/> The Squar Broke the two Shank bones of the Elk after the marrow was taken out, boiled them &amp; extracted a Pint of Greese or tallow from them—    <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Serjt. Pryor</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Gibson, George">Gibson</name> returned after night and informed me they had been lost the greater part of the time they were out, and had killed 6 Elk which they left lying haveing taken out their internals. Some rain this afternoon
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Tuesday 3d December 1805</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
a fair windey morning wind from the East    the men returned with the Elk which revived the Spirits of my party verry much    I am Still unwell and Can't eate even the flesh of the Elk.    an Indian Canoe of 8 Indians Came too, those Inds. are on their way down to the <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clât Sops</name>
                  </hi> with <hi rend="italic">Wap pa to</hi> to barter with that nation, I purchasd. a fiew of those roots for which I gave Small fish hooks, those roots I eate with a little Elks Soupe which I found gave me great relief    I found the roots both nurishing and as a check to my disorder.    The Indians proceeded on down through emence high waves maney times their Canoe was entirely out of Sight before they were ½ a mile distance. <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Serjt. Pryor</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Gibson, George">Gibson</name> who went hunting yesterday has not returned untill after night, they informed me that they had killed 6 Elk at a great distance which they left lying, haveing taken out their interals that they had been lost and in their ramble saw a great deel of Elk Sign.    after eateing the marrow out of two Shank bones of an Elk, the Squar choped the bones fine boiled them and extracted a pint of Grease, which is Superior to the tallow of the animal.  Some rain this evening</p>
               <p>
I marked my name on a large pine tree imediately on the isthmus <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark</name> December 3rd 1805. By Land from the U. States in 1804 &amp; 1805.—

</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Tuesday 3rd Decr. 1805. Cloudy    about 10 oClock A. M. the men returned with the meat.    2 hunters<ref target="n26120302" n="2"/> Stayed out a hunting    a number of Indians came in a Canoe to our Camp.    in the evening the two hunters returned    had killed Six Elk about 5 miles distance from this place.—


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Tuesday 3rd.</hi>    The morning was foggy. About 9 o'clock the men came in with the meat of the elk.— They had a disagreeable trip, it being dark before they arrived at the place where the elk had been killed; and the darkness, fallen timber and under-brush prevented their return; so that they had to encamp out all night. Six of the natives came to our camp, the first who have appeared since our arrival, and after staying an hour proceeded down the river. The greater part of the day was fair, but in the evening it clouded over and rained again. At dark our other two hunters came in, and had killed 6 elk some distance from the river.

</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry">
            <sp who="jw">
               <speaker>Whitehouse</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Tuesday Decemr 3rd    This morning cloudy.    At 10 o'Clock A. M. the Men returned with the Canoe, &amp; Elk meat, which was a very welcome sight to us all.    A Canoe loaded with Indians came to our Camp, but soon left us 
&amp; went down the River.    In the Evening the 2 hunters<ref target="n26120303" n="3"/> that had staid out 2 days returned to our Camp    they had killed 6 Elk about 5 Miles from this place &amp; had seen a number more of them.—




</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n26120301" n="1">
               <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> probably modeled his inscription after that of <name type="person" key="Mackenzie, Alexander">Alexander Mackenzie</name>, written on a rock at the end of his journey to <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">the Pacific</name>: "<name type="person" key="Mackenzie, Alexander">Alexander Mackenzie</name>, from <name type="place" key="Canada">Canada</name>, by land, the twenty second of July, one thousand seven hundred and ninety-three." DeVoto, 355.</note>
            <note xml:id="n26120302" n="2">
               <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Pryor</name> and <name type="person" key="Gibson, George">Gibson</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n26120303" n="3">
               <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Pryor</name> and <name type="person" key="Gibson, George">Gibson</name>.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-12-02" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-12-04" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
