<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.sup.jackson.02">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">J &amp; MC Quarterly 80.4 (2003): 866–883</title>
            <title type="sub">Jefferson, Meriwether Lewis, and the Reduction of the United States Army</title>
            <author>Donald Jackson</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-11-23</date>
            <name>Jamie Tallman</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="main">
            <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name>, and the Reduction of the United States Army</head>
         <div type="article">
            <p>by Donald Jackson, Retired Editor, <hi rend="italic">The Papers of George Washington</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Read April 20, 1979</hi>)</p>
            <p>(This article first appeared in <hi rend="italic">
                  <ref target="http://www.aps-pub.com/proceedings.htm">Proceedings of the American Philosophical Society</ref>
               </hi> 124.2 [1980]: 91–96.)</p>
         </div>
         <div type="_">
            <p>The American people have always disliked the idea of a large regular army in peacetime. In the early days of the Republic, however, America began to discover that some kind of standing army was essential; militia was not always enough.</p>
            <p>Immediately after the Revolution, the Congress began to divest itself of the army that had defeated Cornwallis at Yorktown. Despite some dissenting voices, soldiers who had enlisted to serve for the duration of the war were discharged. By January, 1784, <name type="person" key="Knox, Henry">Major General Henry Knox</name>, the new commander, could report that only about 620 men were still in service—and the bottom figure was still to come. In June of that year, Congress discharged all but twenty-five men who were to be posted to Fort Pitt and West Point to protect materiel. No officer about the rank of captain was retained in service.<ref target="n01" n="1"/>
            </p>
            <p>Almost at once, the thinking of Congress had to change. Indian hostilities in the old Northwest, and the refusal of <name type="place" key="Great Britain">Great Britain</name> to vacate certain garrisons, necessitated new enlistments and the building of new forts on the frontier. When these threats were lessened somewhat by the signing of Jay's Treaty with <name type="place" key="Great Britain">England</name> in 1794, and the Treaty of Greenville with the Indians in 1795, tensions were eased—and then another new threat appeared. Misunderstandings between the United States and <name type="place" key="France">France</name>, eventually to result in the stand-off now called the Quasi-War, prompted Congress to authorize a provisional army of ten thousand men for a period not to exceed three years.<ref target="n02" n="2"/> When the excitement cooled without any land confrontation with <name type="place" key="France">France</name>, that temporary quantum jump in the number of armed forces was reversed. In the final months of the <name type="person" key="Adams, John">John Adams</name> administration, in 1800, the United States forces consisted mainly of four regiments of infantry, two of artillerists and engineers, and two of light dragons.<ref target="n03" n="3"/> This was the army that <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> took over as commander-in-chief, upon his assumption of office in 1801.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> had run for the presidency on a platform calling for even greater reductions; the discharge of the provisional army was not enough to satisfy the Republican demand for a minimum standing army. When he took office, <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> commanded an authorized force of 5,400 officers and men. By the end of his first year, he and the Congress were to eliminate the cavalry, cut back the number of artillerists and engineers, and thus pare the army enrollment to about one-half.<ref target="n04" n="4"/>
            </p>
            <p>The new president did not know the military as well as he might have. He knew the army, but that was a different thing. The army was that great force in the government about which he could talk knowledgeably with generals and cabinet officers, discussing balance of power, regimental strength, deployment, and logistics. The military were the officers and men of that army, and <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> had never been one of them; he had never worn a uniform.</p>
            <p>Reducing the number of enlisted men would be no problem, for actually the maintaining of regiments up to authorized strength had always been difficult. But reducing the officer corps requited a different approach. These career professionals must be dealt with as individuals, some to stay and some to go.</p>
            <p>By midsummer following his election, <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> had received from the War Department a roster or roll of all his commissioned officers, listed with their rank and the units they commanded or to which they were assigned.<ref target="n05" n="5"/>  Most certainly there were men on the roster who were longtime friends and associates of <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>: <name type="person" key="Wilkinson, James">Brigadier General James Wilkinson</name>, the commanding general; <name type="person" key="Cushing, Thomas F.">Major Thomas F. Cushing</name>, the adjutant and inspector; and such familiar names as <name type="person" key="Hamtramck, John F.">John F. Hamtramck</name>, commanding the First Infantry, and old <name type="person" key="Pike, Zebulon">Major Zebulon Pike</name>, of the Third Infantry, the father of the famous explorer.</p>
            <p>But most of the officers on the roster were strangers to <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, and he would need to rely upon someone else to tell him who the potential leaders were, as well as the incompetents, and to identify those officers as Republican or Federalist. That the Federalists would be in the majority he could have no doubt, for the party patronage had become an aspect of the military policy under the administration of <name type="person" key="Adams, John">John Adams</name>.</p>
            <p>The measure that <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> took to obtain a profile of the army is shown upon the roster, dated July 24, 1801. After each officer's name, one or more symbols appear. They are mysterious marks—circles, crosses, and combinations of dots—intended to be understood only by someone who possessed a key to the symbols. That key, written on a single sheet of paper, is present with the roster in the <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> papers at the Library of Congress. On it the symbols are given such meanings as these: officers who are superior; those who are respectable but not superior; those unfit to serve; officers who are Republicans, or Federalists, and—the ultimate downgrading—those "most violently opposed to the Administration and still active in its vilification."</p>
            <p>These symbols, and the sheet explaining their meaning, have until recently been described as being "in an unknown hand."<ref target="n06" n="6"/>  They are, in fact, in the hand of a young man whose name is a familiar one today wherever American history is read. It is the hand of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name>, of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition.</p>
            <p>While we cannot assume with certainty that <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> made the evaluations, merely because the symbols are in his handwriting, a re-examination of his relationship with <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> renders this assumption quite tenable.</p>
            <p>Nothing in the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> story is more firmly believed than the tradition that <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> hired <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name> in 1801, not as a secretary or aide, but as a trainee for a transcontinental expedition. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> was a hometown boy whom <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> had known since childhood. He had received some conventional grammar-school education with classical overtones, and had absorbed a greater than average interest in natural history. Much of his knowledge was self-acquired. He seemed born to rise, in the agricultural-mercantile circles of <name type="place" key="Virginia">Virginia</name>, and he chose one of the most routinely traveled routes: a career in the United States Army.</p>
            <p>Joining the militia during the Whiskey Rebellion in 1794, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> moved north and languished in various cantonments in western <name type="place" key="Maryland">Maryland</name> and <name type="place" key="Pennsylvania">Pennsylvania</name>, deciding the following year to try life in the regular army. He was appointed ensign in the second sub-legion in 1795, transferring the next year to the First Infantry Regiment. This was to be his outfit for the duration of his military career. His active duty was spent partly in the recruiting service and partly as a paymaster. As a special messenger for <name type="person" key="Wayne, Anthony">General Anthony Wayne</name>, and as paymaster to his regiment, he traveled much. During a furlough he went to <name type="place" key="Kentucky">Kentucky</name> on family business, and his duties took him from post to post in the <name type="place" key="Ohio">Ohio</name> Valley: <name type="place" key="Fort Wayne, Ind.">Fort Wayne</name>, <name type="place" key="Detroit, Mich.">Detroit</name>, <name type="place" key="Pittsburgh, Penn.">Pittsburgh</name>, and <name type="place" key="Cincinnati, Ohio">Cincinnati</name>.</p>
            <p>Soon after <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> learned the results of the election that made him president he wrote young <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and offered him a position as his secretary. Sending the request through channels, he told <name type="person" key="Wilkinson, James">General Wilkinson</name> that he thought it would be advantageous "to take one who possessing a knolege of Western country, of the army &amp; it's situation, might sometimes aid us with information of interest, which we may not otherwise possess." He used similar language in his letter to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> himself, saying "Your knolege of the Western country, of the army and of all it's interests &amp; relations has rendered it desirable for public as well as private purpose that you should be engaged in that office."<ref target="n07" n="7"/>
            </p>
            <p>At this point, historians go astray by stacking one conjecture upon another. They reason that <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> had long wished for an expedition to the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>; that he was at last in a position to carry out such an operation; and that he placed <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> on his staff so that he could personally guide the study and preparation necessary for such an expedition. Dozens of books and articles on the expedition contain these assumptions.</p>
            <p>To accept this easy train of events is to sidestep several matters about which we can never be entirely informed. It is true that <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> had since 1783 shown specific signs that he valued the idea of a transcontinental exploration. He had asked <name type="person" key="Clark, George Rogers">George Rogers Clark</name> in that year how he would like to lead such an enterprise, and <name type="person" key="Clark, George Rogers">Clark</name> had declined. He had helped the American Philosophical Society to raise the money and draw the plans for botanist <name type="person" key="Michaux, André">André Michaux</name>, who proposed to visit the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name> Coast but whose plans were canceled. In both these instances, <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> apparently was acting as a private citizen. But during the seven years he served in the federal government, in the 1790s, he did nothing whatsoever to press for a government–sponsored expedition. His correspondence during the last half of the 1790s contains almost nothing about the American West.</p>
            <p>Perhaps what brought <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>'s thoughts back to hemispheric geography was the publication of a book in <name type="place" key="London">London</name>. Late in 1801, <name type="person" key="Mackenzie, Alexander">Alexander Mackenzie</name>'s <hi rend="italic">Voyages…Through the Continent of North American, to the Frozen and <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific Ocean</name>
               </hi> was published; copies were available in <name type="place" key="Philadelphia, Penn.">Philadelphia</name> and <name type="place" key="New York, New York">New York</name> within a short time. <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> already knew something of <name type="person" key="Mackenzie, Alexander">Mackenzie</name>'s travels, but his first knowledge of the book probably came in a letter from <name type="person" key="Wistar, Caspar">Dr. Caspar Wistar</name>, of <name type="place" key="Philadelphia, Penn.">Philadelphia</name>, who frequently sent the president bits of new information. In January, 1802, he wrote: "Have you seen <name type="person" key="Mackenzie, Alexander">McKenzie</name>'s account of his journeys across the Continent &amp; to the Northern Ocean?"<ref target="n08" n="8"/>  He was referring, of course, to <name type="person" key="Mackenzie, Alexander">Mackenzie</name>'s expedition across <name type="place" key="Canada">Canada</name>—during which he reached the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>. At the end of the <name type="person" key="Mackenzie, Alexander">Mackenzie</name>'s narrative, he had urged the British government to lose no time in establishing a trading post in the Pacific Northwest, to gain control of the very profitable trade with the Orient in sea-otter skins. <name type="person" key="Mackenzie, Alexander">Mackenzie</name>'s suggestion with filled with implications for the control not only of the fur trade but of an enormously important part of the continent.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> ordered a copy of <name type="person" key="Mackenzie, Alexander">Mackenzie</name>'s book, probably receiving it in the summer of 1802.<ref target="n09" n="9"/> During August he had as a house guest his old <name type="place" key="Philadelphia, Penn.">Philadelphia</name> friend, and member of the American Philosophical Society, <name type="person" key="Barton, Benjamin Smith">Benjamin Smith Barton</name>. <name type="person" key="Barton, Benjamin Smith">Barton</name>'s travel diary for the period is missing or was not kept, so we have no record of his stay at <name type="place" key="Monticello">Monticello</name>. The two men might well have discussed the Far West, as <name type="person" key="Barton, Benjamin Smith">Barton</name> had been a participant in the earlier plan to send <name type="person" key="Michaux, Andre">Michaux</name> to the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>. It is not likely, however, that <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> mentioned a specific new western enterprise; we may suspect this because, when he finally informed <name type="person" key="Barton, Benjamin Smith">Barton</name> that he was sending <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> to the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>, some months later, he wrote in terms that suggest he was then advising his friend for the first time.<ref target="n10" n="10"/>
            </p>
            <p>Sometime within the weeks immediately following <name type="person" key="Barton, Benjamin Smith">Barton</name>'s visit, <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> must have decided to act. By early December, 1802, he had approached the Spanish minister to United States, <name type="person" key="Marinez de Irujo, Carlos">Carlos Martinez de Irujo</name>, setting forth his plan to explore the course of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri River</name>, cross the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky Mountains</name>, and descend the western watercourses to the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>.<ref target="n11" n="11"/>  It appears, then, that <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>'s decision to set on foot what was to become the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition was made about a year and a half after he had hired <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> as a member of his staff.</p>
            <p>In reviewing the wording of the <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>'s first letter, offering <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> the post of secretary, perhaps we have been paying attention to the wrong phrase. The two key phrases in the message are: <hi rend="italic">Your knolege of the Western country</hi> and <hi rend="italic">the army and of all it's interests &amp; relations</hi>. By "western country" <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> meant the <name type="place" key="Ohio Valley">Ohio</name> Valley. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> had traveled there and knew what the westerners were thinking—a matter of deep concern to <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, who must be alert to the separatist elements on the outer edge of his constituency. An intelligent young officer who had recently traveled as far as <name type="place" key="Kentucky">Kentucky</name> could be useful especially if he were someone long known and trusted by <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>.</p>
            <p>The phase mentioning "the army and all it's interests &amp; relations" may be the more important one. Here was a young military man who could be expected to escalate for <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, in complete candor, the officers of high and low rank whom he had come to know so well as he traveled his paymaster's route. If one can read into <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>'s knowledge of the "western country" the potential for a transcontinental expedition, it is equally logical to see in <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>'s reference to "the army and all it's interests" an assignment to help him with the task of reshaping the military forces.</p>
            <p>Below is the list of qualifications which <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> set forth on his sheet of symbols, then transferred to the roster (see also fig. 1). For simplicity the symbols have been converted to letters of the alphabet, and the wording slightly altered. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> called the listing: "Explanation of the notes set opposite (in the column of remarks) to the names of the several officers composing the Army of the United States."</p>
            <p>[a] Denotes such officers as are of the 1st Class, so esteemed from a superiority of genius &amp; Military proficiency. 
[b] Officers of the second class, respectable as officers, but not altogether entitled to the 1st grade.
[c] The same. Republican.
[d] Officers whose political opinions are not positively ascertained.
[e] Political apathy.
[g] Opposed to the Administration more decisively.
[h] Most violently opposed to the administration and still active in the vilification.
[i] Professionally the soldier without any political creed. 
[j] Unworthy of the commissions they bear.
[k] Unknown to us. </p>
            <table rows="19" cols="4">
               <row role="data">
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Table 1</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">D<hi rend="smallcaps">ISTRIBUTION</hi> O<hi rend="smallcaps">F</hi> O<hi rend="smallcaps">FFICERS</hi> B<hi rend="smallcaps">Y</hi> P<hi rend="smallcaps">LACE</hi> O<hi rend="smallcaps">F</hi> O<hi rend="smallcaps">RIGIN</hi>*</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                     <name type="place" key="Connecticut">Connecticut</name>
                  </cell>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">14</cell>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                     <name type="place" key="Pennsylvania">Pennsylvania</name>
                  </cell>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">46</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                     <name type="place" key="Delaware">Delaware</name>
                  </cell>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">2</cell>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                     <name type="place" key="Rhode Island">Rhode Island</name>
                  </cell>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">3</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                     <name type="place" key="Georgia">Georgia</name>
                  </cell>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">4</cell>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                     <name type="place" key="South Carolina">South Carolina</name>
                  </cell>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">8</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                     <name type="place" key="Kentucky">Kentucky</name>
                  </cell>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">5</cell>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                     <name type="place" key="Tennessee">Tennessee</name>
                  </cell>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">3</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                     <name type="place" key="Maryland">Maryland</name>
                  </cell>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">32</cell>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                     <name type="place" key="Vermont">Vermont</name>
                  </cell>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">6</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                     <name type="place" key="Massachusetts">Massachusetts</name>
                  </cell>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">34</cell>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                     <name type="place" key="Virginia">Virginia</name>
                  </cell>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">36</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                     <name type="place" key="Mississippi">Mississippi</name>
                  </cell>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">1</cell>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                     <name type="place" key="Canada">Canada</name>
                  </cell>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">1</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                     <name type="place" key="New Hampshire">New Hampshire</name>
                  </cell>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">4</cell>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                     <name type="place" key="France">France</name>
                  </cell>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">5</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                     <name type="place" key="New Jersey">New Jersey</name>
                  </cell>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">12</cell>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                     <name type="place" key="Great Britain">England</name>
                  </cell>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">3</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                     <name type="place" key="New York">New York</name>
                  </cell>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">26</cell>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                     <name type="place" key="Ireland">Ireland</name>
                  </cell>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">7</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                     <name type="place" key="North Carolina">North Carolina</name>
                  </cell>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">9</cell>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                     <name type="place" key="Scotland">Scotland</name>
                  </cell>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">1</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                     <name type="place" key="Northwest Territory">Northwest Terr.</name>
                  </cell>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">1</cell>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                     <name type="place" key="Switzerland">Switzerland</name>
                  </cell>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">1</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                     <name type="place" key="Germany">Germany</name>
                  </cell>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">4</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell cols="3" role="data" rows="1">*Names on the roster total 269, but one officer, Richard Skinner, is not listed by place of origin. States<lb/>
or countries on the roster do not always correspond with those in Francis B. Heitman, <hi rend="italic">Historical Register and<lb/> Dictionary of the United States Army</hi>(Washington, 1903).</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <table rows="21" cols="3">
               <row role="data">
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Table 2</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Evaluation of Officers in Service*</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">In service</cell>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Retained</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">July 24, 1801</cell>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">June 1, 1802</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Superior [a]</cell>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Republican [c]</cell>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">9</cell>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">4</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Federalist [f,g,h]</cell>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">23</cell>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">18</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Nonpolitical [e,i]</cell>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">11</cell>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">9</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Undetermined [k]</cell>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">24</cell>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">18</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Acceptable [b]</cell>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Republican [c]</cell>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">4</cell>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">4</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Federalist [f,g,h]</cell>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">18</cell>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">7</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Nonpolitical [e,i]</cell>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">20</cell>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">12</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Undetermined [k]</cell>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">25</cell>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">14</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Unfit [j]</cell>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">44</cell>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">6</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Qualifications unknown [i]</cell>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">91</cell>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">39</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">—</cell>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">—</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">269</cell>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">131</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell cols="3" role="data" rows="1">*Letters in brackets correspond to Lewis's key. The total of 6 unfit officers retained does not include one<lb/>
who died after the evaluation was made.</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>Tables 1 and 2 present some data compiled from the roster of officers and the evaluations added by <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>. Table 1, showing distribution to officers by state, would have come as no surprise to <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>; a large proportion of his officers came from the more heavily populated Federalist states in the Northeast. In Table 2, the data have been adapted and simplified; for example, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>'s three categories of Federalist, ranging from mild to unregenerate, have been combined under a single heading.</p>
            <p>It is clear that in the winnowing process, military qualifications were given greater consideration that party preference. There are however, two ways to state this conclusion. We can say that <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> and his advisers followed the practice of ignoring party preference, selecting the officers to be retained on the basis of military proficiency. It may be more realistic to phrase the conclusion in a different way: no matter how much <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> might have wished for an army heavily weighted with Republicans, there was no way that he could have it in the early years of his administration.</p>
            <p>In converting to a non-Federalist army, <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> had to pay attention first to his small general staff, all but one of whom had multiple crosses after their names to denote their category as "most violently opposed to the administration." Of the seven officers on the general staff, three were discharged within a year after their evaluation. Two old officers who had served honorably in the Revolution were retained, despite their Federalist leanings: <name type="person" key="Cushing, Thomas H.">Thomas H. Cushing</name>, the adjutant and inspector, and <name type="person" key="Swan, Caleb">Caleb Swan</name>, the paymaster general. <name type="person" key="Turner, Edward D.">Edward D. Turner</name>, brigade inspector, was retained as a captain but resigned three years later. In assigning political ranking to the men of the general staff, young <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Lewis</name> had a problem about the commanding general himself, <name type="person" key="Wilkinson, James">James Wilkinson</name>. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> placed no symbols at all after <name type="person" key="Wilkinson, James">Wilkinson</name>'s name, perhaps because he felt it presumptuous to evaluate him, or because he felt that <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> knew <name type="person" key="Wilkinson, James">Wilkinson</name>'s strengths and weaknesses all too well. <name type="person" key="Wilkinson, James">Wilkinson</name> son was retained as commanding general, and in later years, when he was implicated in the <name type="person" key="Burr, Aaron">Aaron Burr</name> conspiracy and other intrigues, <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> defended him—though not without some equivocation.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> wanted Republicans in his top civilian posts, military and naval, as well as in the commissioned ranks. His appointment of <name type="person" key="Dearborn, Henry">Henry Dearborn</name>, of <name type="place" key="Maine">Maine</name>, to be secretary of war was a gesture to the strongly Federalist Northeast, as was his appointment of <name type="person" key="Lincoln, Levi">Attorney General Levi Lincoln</name>, of <name type="place" key="Massachusetts">Massachusetts</name>. He offered the post of secretary of the navy to four Republicans before filling it with <name type="person" key="Stoddert, Benjamin">Benjamin Stoddert</name>, who soon resigned to be replaced by <name type="person" key="Smith, Robert">Robert Smith</name>.<ref target="n12" n="12"/>
            </p>
            <p>The conversion of the army was no secret. In June, 1802, the attorney general warned <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> that much unrest was evident in the Northeast although he believed that federalism was losing ground. He wrote, "<name type="person" key="Dearborn, Henry">General Dearborn</name> &amp; myself endeavored to prepare a list of names this morning, for commissions for <name type="place" key="Massachusetts">Massachusetts</name>, to submit to your consideration. As soon as we have done the best we can do, we will wait on you with it."<ref target="n13" n="13"/> When the secretary of the navy recommended that <name type="person" key="Gamble, Robert">Robert Gamble</name>, of <name type="place" key="Pennsylvania">Pennsylvania</name>, be appointed a midshipman, he was careful to remind the president that the young man was highly recommended by <name type="person" key="Muhlenberg, John P. G.">John P. G. Muhlenberg</name>, and active Republican. And when <name type="person" key="Dallas, Alexander">Alexander Dallas</name> came up for his midshipman's commission, his only character reference was his father, <name type="person" key="Dallas, Alexander J.">Alexander J. Dallas</name>, another influential Republican who was secretary of the commonwealth of <name type="place" key="Pennsylvania">Pennsylvania</name>.<ref target="n14" n="14"/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>'s patronage policy was personally a moderate one, but he was subject to conflicting pressures. <name type="person" key="Gallatin, Albert">Secretary of Treasury Albert Gallatin</name> favored a completely nonpartisan appointment policy in some areas of government. On the other hand, <name type="person" key="Dearborn, Henry">Henry Dearborn</name> was unrelenting in his insistence on removing Federalists. He told <name type="person" key="Varnum, Joseph B.">House speaker Joseph B. Varnum</name>: "We have been much more liberal towards them, that they would be towards us, and in future I think we ought to give them measure for measure."<ref target="n15" n="15"/>
            </p>
            <p>In remaking the regular army, <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> was more successful in controlling its size than its political complexion. After Congress passed the act fixing the military peace establishment in 1802, there was no increase in the regular army for six years—until a conflict with England began to seem likely.<ref target="n16" n="16"/>
            </p>
            <p>To summarize, it seems probably that <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> hired <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Meriwether Lewis</name> for quite another purpose that to train him for a transcontinental expedition, and that he decided on that expedition much later than has been previously believed. And so when <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> set out from <name type="place" key="Washington D.C.">Washington</name> and <name type="place" key="Philadelphia, Penn.">Philadelphia</name>, in the spring of 1803, to begin the nation's most enduring tale of exploration and adventure, he had the satisfaction of knowing that he already had served his president and his party in a rather unusual way.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="_">
            <note xml:id="n01" n="1">
               <hi rend="italic">Journals of the Continental Congress</hi> (34 vols., Washington, 1904–1907), 25: p. 703, 27: pp. 513–524. Two sound works on the post-Revolutionary army are Francis Paul Prucha, <hi rend="italic">The Sword of the Republic: The United States Army on the Frontier, 1783–1846</hi> (Bloomington, Ind., 1969), and Richard H. Kohn, <hi rend="italic">Eagle and Sword: The Beginnings of the Military Establishment in America</hi> (New York, 1975).</note>
            <note xml:id="n02" n="2"> Prucha, <hi rend="italic">Sword of the Republic</hi>, pp. 39–40. The Federalists, determined to base their appointments on political considerations delayed the completion of the new army by at least three months (Kohn, <hi rend="italic">Eagle and Sword</hi>, p. 244).</note>
            <note xml:id="n03" n="3"> Under an act reducing the Additional Army, the discharges were effective June 5, 1800 (<hi rend="italic">2 U. S. Statutes</hi>, pp. 85–86).</note>
            <note xml:id="n04" n="4"> "An act fixing the military peace establishment of the United States," March 16, 1802, <hi rend="italic">2 U. S. Statutes</hi>, pp. 85–86).</note>
            <note xml:id="n05" n="5"> This roster of officers, dated July 24, 1801, is among the papers of <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Thomas Jefferson</name>, Library of Congress. For the microfilm copy, see reel 24, folios 1969–1975.</note>
            <note xml:id="n06" n="6"> For example, in Noble E. Cunningham, Jr., <hi rend="italic">The Jeffersonian Republicans in Power</hi> (Chapel Hill, N. C., 1963), p. 66. He has later recognized <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>'s hand in <hi rend="italic">The Process of Government Under <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>
               </hi> (Princeton, N. J., 1978), p. 127.</note>
            <note xml:id="n07" n="7"> See <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> to <name type="person" key="Wilkinson, James">Wilkinson</name>, Feb. 23, 1801, and to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, Feb. 23, 1801, both in the <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> Papers, Library of Congress.</note>
            <note xml:id="n08" n="8">
               <name type="person" key="Wistar, Casper">Wistar</name> to <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, Jan. 8, 1802, Library of Congress.</note>
            <note xml:id="n09" n="9"> Bookseller James Cheetham's bill for the book, Feb. 22, 1803, shows June 21, 1802, as the date of the order (Library of Congress). Cheetham was also a journalist, publishing the bi-weekly <name type="place" key="New York, New York">New York</name> newspaper, <hi rend="italic">The Republican Watch-Tower</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n10" n="10"> "You know we have been many years wishing to have the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> explored &amp; whatever river, heading with that, runs into the Western ocean. Congress, in some secret proceedings, have yielded to a proposition I made them for permitting me to have it done; it is to be undertaken immediately, with a party of about ten, &amp; I have appointed <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name>, my secretary, to conduct it." <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> to <name type="person" key="Barton, Benjamin Smith">Barton</name>, Feb. 27, 1803, Library of Congress. See also W. E. McAtee, ed., "Journal of <name type="person" key="Barton, Benjamin Smith">Benjamin Smith Barton</name> on a Visit to <name type="place" key="Virginia">Virginia</name>, 1802," <hi rend="italic">Castanea: Journal of the Southern Appalachian Botany Club</hi> 3 (1938): pp. 85–117. Manuscript fragment from <name type="person" key="Barton, Benjamin Smith">Barton</name>'s trip to <name type="place" key="Virginia">Virginia</name> are in the American Philosophical Society Library.</note>
            <note xml:id="n11" n="11">
               <name type="person" key="Martinez de Irujo, Carlos">Carlos Martinez de Irujo</name> to <name type="person" key="Cevallos, Pedro">Pedro Cevallos</name>, Dec. 2, 1802, Archivo Históico Nacional (Madrid), Papeles de Estado, legajo 5630, apartado 2.</note>
            <note xml:id="n12" n="12"> Jacob E. Cooke, <hi rend="italic">Tench Coxe and the Early Republic</hi> (Chapel Hill, N. C., 1978), pp. 394, 395n. After <name type="person" key="Stoddert, Benjamin">Stoddert</name> resigned April 1, 1801, <name type="person" key="Dearborn, Henry">Dearborn</name> occupied the post along with his own until July 15, when <name type="person" key="Smith, Robert">Smith</name> accepted the appointment.</note>
            <note xml:id="n13" n="13">
               <name type="person" key="Lincoln, Levi">Levi Lincoln</name> to <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, June 28, 1802, Library of Congress. These proposed commissions probably included civilian posts as well as military appointments.</note>
            <note xml:id="n14" n="14">
               <name type="person" key="Smith, Robert">Robert Smith</name> to <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, May 9, 1803, Library of Congress.</note>
            <note xml:id="n15" n="15"> Cunningham, <hi rend="italic">Jeffersonian Republicans</hi>, pp. 68–69. Cunningham deals briefly with <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>'s coded roster and its implications.</note>
            <note xml:id="n16" n="16"> Cooke, <hi rend="italic">Tench Coxe</hi>, p. 427. On April 12, 1808, Congress approved an addition of eight regiments to the regular army.</note>
            <p>This article has been reproduced with the permission of the <ref target="http://www.amphilsoc.org/">American Philosophical Society</ref>.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
