<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.preface.v05">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">Volume 5 Preface</title>
            <title type="sub"/>
            <author>Gary E. Moulton</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition, Volume 5</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">April 7–November 1, 1805</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1989</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">vii-ix</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Journal Editorial</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic"/>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-05-26</date>
            <date/>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>
            <name/>Initial creation Transcribed</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="main">Volume 5 Preface</head>
         <head type="sub"/>
         <div type="preface">
            <p>
Annotation in this volume again makes use of United States Geological Survey (USGS) maps and other maps not specifically cited in the sources. We continued to use Robert N. Bergantino's set of USGS maps (1° x 2°, 1:250,000) on which he has plotted <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> route, camps, and points of astronomical observation through <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name> and part of <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name> (from <name type="place" key="Lemhi Pass">Lemhi Pass</name> to <name type="place" key="Lost Trail Pass">Lost Trail Pass</name>). Bergantino was also kind enough to read the portion of this volume dealing with <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>. We used his maps in checking <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> locale and for obtaining modern place names but did not cite them in notes. For more detail we also used other USGS maps (30° x 60°, 1:100,000); these are cited in notes where used and are also listed in "Sources Cited."</p>
            <p>
Other special maps were also used but not cited in the sources. For the <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Snow) Mountains">Bitterroot Mountains</name> portion of the expedition we turned to the Salmon National Forest map (<name type="place" key="Lemhi Pass">Lemhi Pass</name> to <name type="place" key="Lost Trail Pass">Lost Trail Pass</name>), the Bitterroot National Forest map (<name type="place" key="North Fork, Idaho">North Fork</name>, <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>, to <name type="place" key="Missoula, Mont.">Missoula</name>, <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>), and the Clearwater National Forest map (<name type="place" key="Lolo Trail">Lolo Trail</name>). Beyond the <name type="place" key="Lolo Trail">Lolo Trail</name>, as the party entered modern <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name> and <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>, we returned to the USGS maps. As the notes indicate, we used extensively the works of Ralph Space and John J. Peebles about the <name type="place" key="Lolo Trail">Lolo Trail</name>. Space was also generous enough to read the portion of the volume dealing with the trail and to provide us with useful comments. We have cited the articles Peebles published in <hi rend="italic">Idaho Yesterdays</hi> in the 1960s. Not specifically cited but carefully consulted was his map of the <name type="place" key="Lolo Trail">Lolo Trail</name>, which was published with his article about the crossing. The Idaho Historical Society later published Pebble's three articles (the third being about the expedition's return trip on the <name type="place" key="Lolo Trail">Lolo Trail</name>) together as <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> in <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>
               </hi>, Idaho Historical Series Number 16 (December 1966). With these essays and map, Space's magnificent book, and the Clearwater National Forest map, one is fully prepared to follow the Corps of Discovery along the <name type="place" key="Lolo Trail">Lolo Trail</name>.</p>
            <p>
Persons who have shown us kindnesses and courtesies in numerous ways deserve our gratitude for their help in carrying this project forward and they have our heartfelt thanks as friends and colleagues. John L. Allen, Donald Jackson, James P. Ronda, and W. Raymond Wood not only wrote books and essays which serve this endeavor well but also added personal encouragement and professional assistance in many ways. Robert E. Lange of Portland, Oregon, has done leg work for the project at the Oregon Historical Society and answered questions about the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name> portion of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> trip, while Bob Saindon of Helena, Montana, has happily responded to some difficult questions about <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name> nomenclature. Michael E. Dotson of Crest Hill, Illinois, reminded us not to overlook clothing as a <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> topic. Advice for tracing the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> trail in their locales or places of interest came from Duane Annis (Orofino, Idaho), Stephen D. Beckham (Portland, Oregon), Fred Crandall (Nevada City, California), Ralph H. Rudeen (Olympia, Washington), and James R. Wolf (Bethesda, Maryland).</p>
            <p>
At the two principal repositories of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> expedition materials we have had the gracious assistance of able curators, librarians, and administrators: Beth Carroll-Horrocks, Edward C. Carter II, Roy E. Goodman, Randolph S. Klein, and Murphy D. Smith (all of the American Philosophical Society, Philadelphia); and Duane R. Sneddeker (Missouri Historical Society, St. Louis). At the project's office we have benefited from the work of a dedicated staff and research assistants: Jennifer Frost, Virginia J. Maca, Vernon Volpe, and Thomas Wakeley. Persons from the Center for Great Plains Studies, University of Nebraska–Lincoln, provided much-appreciated administrative help: Rosalind Carr, Georgia Lowenberg, Frederick C. Luebke, and Mary Lee Yetter. The <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Trail Heritage Foundation has continued to support the project financially as have individual contributors, Robert B. Betts (New York City), Gladys Levis (Alton, Illinois), William P. Sherman (Portland, Oregon), and Lyle S. Woodcock (St. Louis, Missouri). Their gifts lifted our spirits as much as they filled our coffers.</p>
            <p>
Scholars have been generous in their help in explaining <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> references to their areas of expertise. The depth of the scientific annotation in this and other volumes owes its existence to such unselfish labors.</p>
            <p>
ARCHAEOLOGY: Kenneth M. Ames, Portland State University: Warren Caldwell, Orofino, Idaho; R. Lee Lyman, University of Missouri–Columbia. BOTANY: A. T. Harrison, Sandy, Utah. GEOLOGY: Robert N. Bergantino, Montana Bureau of Mines and Geology, Butte. LINGUISTICS: American Indian linguistic data in the notes were collected by Raymond J. DeMallie, Indiana University, and were provided by the following individuals: <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshone</name>.</hi> Sven Liljeblad, University of Nevada, Reno. All forms are given in the Numic orthography used by Catherine S. Fowler and Sven Liljeblad, "Northern Paiute," in <hi rend="italic">Handbook of North American Indians,</hi> vol. 11, <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="place" key="Great Basin">Great Basin</name>,</hi> edited by Warren L. D'Azevado (Washington, D.C.: Smithsonian Institution, 1986). Additional and corroborative <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshone</name> data were provided by Wick R. Miller, University of Utah, and David Shaul, Indiana University–Purdue University, Fort Wayne. <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Flathead</name>.</hi> Sarah G. Thomason, University of Pittsburgh. <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>/Shahaptian</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Sahaptin</hi>). Haruo Aoki, University of California, Berkeley, and Bruce Rigsby, University of Queensland, Australia. For <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name> orthography, see Haruo Aoki, <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name> Grammar</hi> (Berkeley: University of California Press, 1970). <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinook/Chinookan</name>.</hi> Michael Silverstein, with additional data from Robert Moore, both of the University of Chicago. For <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookan</name> orthography, see Michael Silverstein, "<name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookans</name> of the Lower <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>," in <hi rend="italic">Handbook of North American Indians,</hi> vol. 7, <hi rend="italic">Northwest Coast,</hi> edited by Wayne Suttles (Washington, D.C.: Smithsonian Institution, 1990). METEOROLOGY: Jay S. Hobgood, University of Nebraska–Lincoln; ZOOLOGY: Royce E. Ballenger, University of Nebraska–Lincoln (frogs); Thomas O. Holtzer, University of Nebraska–Lincoln (insects); Paul A. Johnsgard, University of Nebraska–Lincoln (birds); John D. Lynch, University of Nebraska–Lincoln (fish).</p>
            <p>
Custom prescribes and honesty dictates that we state that none of these persons is responsible for any errors that might appear in this edition.


</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
