<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1804-11-03">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
November 3, 1804</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 3</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">August 25, 1804–April 6, 1805</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1987</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">226-227</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">93-94</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">62</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jw">Joseph Whitehouse</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 11</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of Joseph Whitehouse, May 14, 1804–April 2, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1997</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">108-110</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Journal Entries</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic"/>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-03-24</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1804-11-03">November 3, 1804</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1804-11-03.01" n="">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">3rd of November Satturday 1804</hi>    wind hard from the west    Commence building our Cabins,<ref target="n08110301" n="1"/> Dispatched 6 hunters in a perogue Down the River to hunt, Discharged the french hands,<ref target="n08110302" n="2"/>
                  <name type="person" key="Jusseaume, René">Mr. Jessomme</name> his Squar &amp; child moved to camp, the <name type="person" key="Little Crow (Ka-goh-ha-me)">little Crow</name> loaded his Squar with meat for us also a Roabe, we gave the Squar an ax &amp;. &amp;.    Cought 2 bever near Camp</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1804-11-03.02" n="">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">3rd of November Satterday 1804</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
a fine morning    wind hard from the <hi rend="italic">West</hi>    we commence building our Cabins, Send Down in Perogue 6 men to hunt    Engaged one man,<ref target="n08110303" n="3"/> [<hi rend="italic">NB: Canadian Frenchman who had been with the <name type="native_nation" key="Cheyenne Indians">Chayenne</name> Inds on the <name type="place" key="Black Hills">Cote noir</name> &amp; last summer descended thence the <name type="place" key="Little Missouri (E-mâh-tark',-Ah'-zhah) River">little Missouri</name>—he was of our permanent.</hi>]    Set the french who intend to return to build a perogue, many Indians pass to hunt, <name type="person" key="Jusseaume, René">Mr. Jessomme</name> [<hi rend="italic">NB: <name type="person" key="Jusseaume, René">Jesseaume</name>
                  </hi>] with his Squar &amp; Children.    come Down to live, as Interpter, we recive [<hi rend="italic">NB: hired</hi>] a hors for our Sirvice, in the evening the <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="person" key="Little Crow (Ka-goh-ha-me)">Ka goh ha mi</name>
                  </hi> or <name type="person" key="Little Crow (Ka-goh-ha-me)">little ravin</name> Came &amp; brought us on his Squar [<hi rend="italic">NB: who carried it on her back</hi>] about 60 Wt. of Dried Buffalow meat a roabe, &amp; Pot of Meal &amp;.    they Delayed all night—    we gave his Squar an ax &amp; a fiew Small articles &amp; himself a piece of Tobacco, the Men were indulged with a Dram, this evening</p>
               <p>
two Beaver Cought This morning—    and one Trap Lost [<hi rend="italic">NB: The Frenchmen 9 engaged thus far now returning.    but 2 or 3 volunteered to remain with us the winter which they did &amp; in the Spring left us</hi>.]<ref target="n08110304" n="4"/>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1804-11-03.03" n="">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Saturday 3rd Nov</hi>. 1804.    a clear and pleasant morning. Six hunters Set out to Go 20 or 30 miles down the River in a pearogue to good hunting Ground in order to kill meat for the party.    we continued building.    layed the foundation of the other line of huts 4 by 14 feet also.    the timber large and heavy. Mr [<hi rend="italic">blank</hi>]<ref target="n08110305" n="5"/> our Intreperter moved down from village with his famialy to Stay with us.    a frenchman<ref target="n08110306" n="6"/> came from the village also who has engaged to join us for the expedition &amp;.C—    Some of the Squaws came from the vil.    brot. Capt. meat &amp;C.


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1804-11-03.04" n="">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Saturday 3rd.</hi>
                  <ref target="n08110307" n="7"/>    A clear day; we continued building, and six men went down the river in a periogue to hunt. They will perhaps have to go 30 or 40 miles before they come to good hunting ground.— The following is the manner in which our huts and fort were built;<ref target="n08110308" n="8"/> the huts were in two rows, containing four rooms each, and joined at one end forming an angle. When rasied about 7 feet high a floor of puncheons or split plank were laid, and covered with grass and clay; which made a warm loft. The upper part projected a foot over and the roofs were made shed-fashion, rising from the inner side, and making the outer wall about 18 feet high. The part not inclosed by the huts we intended to picket. In the angle formed by the two rows of huts we built two rooms, for holding our provisions and stores.


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1804-11-03.05" n="">
            <sp who="jw">
               <speaker>Whitehouse</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Saturday 3rd<ref target="n08110309" n="9"/>    a party of hunters was Sent down the river with a Peirogue to Bring the meat whome, in the[y] Remaind 15 days, and On the 18th Inst the[y] had good Success    the[y] Killd. 34 deers 10 Elks and 5 Buffelows, in all they had Upwards of 20 hundred Wt.    Nothing Else happnd. Extraordinary—</p>
               <p>
Untill the 30th Inst. a messenger from the mandans Came to the fort to Inform Our Officers that a hunting party of theirs was Robed by the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sues</name> &amp; <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Rees</name>,<ref target="n08110310" n="10"/> Indians, on the 27th last, of Eight horses and their meat that they had Killd, &amp; Killd One of their men and wounded two Others</p>
               <p>
the[y] Applyd. for Some Assistance from the fort which <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captn. Lewis</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Readly granted them.    Twenty Men turnd Out Volentary Under the Command of <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captn. Clark</name> out of the fort to goe to fight the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sues</name>    the Guard Set us Across the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missourie</name> at Eleven Oclock at the fort    the Captn. formd. his men On the S. W Side of the river <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missourie</name> and told them off in Sections, from the right, and Sent out a Noncommissiond. Officer and a file of men on Each flank to Reconitere the woods at the distance of neerly One hundred Yds. from the head of Company.    After a march of 6 miles we Arivd. at the first Village of mandans, with our two Interprators One of the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">mandans</name> &amp; one of the <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Grosvauinties</name>,<ref target="n08110311" n="11"/> thinking to be Reignd. forsd. [reinforced] by a party of Each Nation With a Detachment from the 〈Watoonse〉 <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians, Awaxawi">Watesoons</name> Nation like-ways, as they and <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Groce Vaunties</name>, are Nigh Neighbours to the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name> Nation    but after we Arivd. At the Village the Cheifs of Both Nations Concluded not to goe to fight as the weather was Cold and the Snow Upwards of 18 Inches Deep on the Ground, before Spring Nixt.</p>
               <p>
The Captn. &amp; the party halted two hours at the Village    he told the Cheifs and Warieres of the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name> that he and his Men was on the Ground Ready to Assist them And the[y] Should See that Him and his Men Could fight.    After Some little Conversation with the Savages, we took Our leave of them and Started for the fort    we Crossd. the river between the first &amp; Second Village On the Ise And Came whome to the fort    Arivd. at dark    the Evening was Cold.    Each Drank Some Good Spirits After which Revivd. Us 〈much〉 Very Much And Retird. to Our Rooms Each—</p>
               <p>
Saturday Novemr. 3d    A party of hunters was this day sent down the River.    they carried with them a Pettyauger to bring what Meat they killid on their hunt; they remained down the River a hunting 15 days, and on the 18th November they returned, having had good success in hunting, they brought with them 34 deer, 10 Elk, and 5 buffaloes all weighing 2,000 lbs as near as we could guess.—</p>
               <p>
Nothing happened extraordinary till the 30th day of November (instant) when an Express arrived from the 2nd <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> Village, at our Fort; who informed our Officers that a hunting party of theirs was robbed, by the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sues</name> &amp; <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Rees</name> Indians on the 27th of last Month of Eight horses, and all their meat, &amp; that they had killed one of their Men, and wounded two others, and applied to 〈the〉 Our Officers for some assistance from the fort which the Officers readily granted to them.    Twenty of our Men immediately turned out Volunteers, under the Command of <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain Clark</name> to go against those Indians, (the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sues</name>) and the Guard at the Fort set us across the River.—    <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain Clark</name> formed his Men on the South West side of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">River Mesouri</name> on their landing; and told them off in Sections from the right, and sent a file of Men and a Non commission'd Officer on each flank, to reconitre the Woods, at the distance of nearly 100 Yards from the head of the Company.—    After we had marched about 6 Miles, we arriv'd at the first Village of the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> Indians, with our Two Interpreters, One for the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name> &amp; the other for the <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Grovanters</name>
                  <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain Clark</name> thinking that he would be reinforced by a party, from each nation, and a detatchment from the <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians, Awaxawi">Watesoons</name> a part of the Nation, who are neighbours to the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> Nation, and their friends.—    On our arrival at the Village, the chiefs of both nations, concluded, not to go to fight those Indians with us, they saying the Weather was cold, and the Snow was deep, (being upwards of 18 Inches on the Ground,) and that they should put it off, 'till the next spring—    The Captain halted 
the party two hours at this Village.    he told the Chief and Warriors of the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> Nation; that he and his Men was on the ground and was ready to assist them, and that they should see that he and his Men could fight.—    After the Captain had some more conversation with those Indians, we all took our leave of them, and started for the Fort, we recrossed the River on the ice.—    between the first and Second Villages of the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan Indians</name>, and came to the Fort, where we arrived at dark.    this Evening, being very cold, the Officers had some Whiskey served out to the Men that was on the March which revived them much, &amp; they all Retired to their Huts.—



</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n08110301" n="1">Sergeant <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name>, who being a carpenter probably had a major part in building the structure, describes <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name> as a roughly triangular stockade, with two converging rows of huts and some sort of bastion in the angle opposite the gate. This accords with the description given by <name type="person" key="Larocque, François-Antoine">Fran<seg n="u231">ç</seg>ois-Antoine Larocque</name>. According to <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name>, the outer walls were 18 feet high; no other measurements are known. A small sketch on <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 29 confirms the triangular shape. Masson, 1:307–8.</note>
            <note xml:id="n08110302" n="2">Some of the discharged <hi rend="italic">engagés</hi> wintered with the permanent party at <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name>; others seem to have spent the winter at the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>, <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name>, or <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> villages. Those who wished to stay among the Indians, perhaps trading and trapping on their own, apparently received their pay in cash at this time; there is no record of their being paid, which complicates the effort to determine their identities. Five men received their pay from <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> agent in <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> in 1805: <name type="person" key="Deschamps, Jean Baptiste">Baptiste Deschamps</name>, <name type="person" key="La Jeunesse, Jean Baptiste">Jean Baptiste La Jeunesse</name>, <name type="person" key="Malboeuf (Mabbauf), Etienne">Etienne Malboeuf</name>, <name type="person" key="Pinaut, Peter">Charles Pineau</name> (otherwise <name type="person" key="Pinaut, Peter">Peter Pinaut</name>), and <name type="person" key="Rivet, François">Fran<seg n="u231">ç</seg>ois Rivet</name>. These five probably returned with the keelboat sent down the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> in April 1805. It is likely but not certain that among them were the ones who wintered at <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name>. See also n. 4, below, and <ref n="1804-11-30-1" type="related">weather remarks</ref> for November 6, 1804. Jackson (LLC), 1:237 n. 7.</note>
            <note xml:id="n08110303" n="3">
               <name type="person" key="Lepage, Jean Baptiste">Jean Baptiste Lepage</name> took the place of the discharged <name type="person" key="Newman, John">John Newman</name> and went with the permanent party to <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">the Pacific</name> and back. Most of what is known of him is in this entry and elsewhere in the journals. The information in <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle's</name> interlineation indicates that he had been to the <name type="place" key="Black Hills">Black Hills</name> and on the <name type="place" key="Little Missouri (E-mâh-tark',-Ah'-zhah) River">Little Missouri River</name>, in country that few, if any, other whites had seen. He probably contributed some information to the Western map <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> prepared during this winter (<hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> maps 32<hi rend="italic">a</hi>, 32<hi rend="italic">b</hi>, 32<hi rend="italic">c</hi>). <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> record dates his enlistment from November 2 and describes him as of "no particular merit." <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> to <name type="person" key="Dearborn, Henry">Henry Dearborn</name>, January 15, 1807, Jackson (LLC), 1:368; Clarke (MLCE), 147.</note>
            <note xml:id="n08110304" n="4">
               <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name> apparently added this bracketed material, perhaps to aid him in sorting out the number of <hi rend="italic">engagés</hi> who stayed for the winter. <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle's</name> account says that some of the discharged men built a pirogue—probably a dugout canoe—to return to <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>. See also <ref n="1804-11-30-1" type="related">weather remarks</ref>, November 6, 1804. Coues (HLC), 1:189.</note>
            <note xml:id="n08110305" n="5">
               <name type="person" key="Jusseaume, René">Jusseaume</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n08110306" n="6">
               <name type="person" key="Lepage, Jean Baptiste">Jean Baptiste Lepage</name> took the place of the discharged <name type="person" key="Newman, John">Newman</name> and went to <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">the Pacific</name>
and back with the permanent party (see <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> entry for this day).</note>
            <note xml:id="n08110307" n="7">After this date <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name> begins to skip several days' entries at a time through the <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name> winter. Discrepancies of dating from <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, or <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse</name>, the other journalists for the period, will be noted.</note>
            <note xml:id="n08110308" n="8">
               <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name> gives the most detailed information available about the construction of <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name>. The fort was roughly triangular in outline. <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> indicates that each row of huts consisted of four rooms each fourteen feet square, making each row approximately 56 feet in 
length.</note>
            <note xml:id="n08110309" n="9">Here the writer summarizes the events for the remainder of the month as it is also given 
in the fair copy.</note>
            <note xml:id="n08110310" n="10">
               <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n08110311" n="11">
               <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Gros Ventres</name>,</hi> that is, the <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name>.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1804-11-02" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1804-11-04" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
