<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-11-03">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
November 3, 1805</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 6</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">November 2, 1805–March 22, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1990</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">10-14</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">249</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">165-166</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jw">Joseph Whitehouse</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 11</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of Joseph Whitehouse, May 14, 1804–April 2, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1997</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">382-384</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
         <geoDecl datum="WGS" xml:id="lc.geo.1805-11-03.01">
            <placeName/>
            <geo>45.5833 -122.3833</geo>
            <note>Camped on Diamond Island, about 3 miles west of present Camas, Clark County, WA.</note>
         </geoDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Journal Entries</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic"/>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-07-19</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1805-11-03">November 3, 1805</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-11-03.01" n="lc.geo.1805-11-03.01">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">November 3rd Sunday 1805</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
The fog So thick this morning we did not think it prudent to Set out untill 〈it Cleared away at〉 10 oClock we Set out and proceeded on verry well,<ref target="n25110301" n="1"/> accompanied by our Indian friends—    This morning <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="person" key="Labiche, François">Labich</name>
                  </hi> killed 3 Geese flying <name type="person" key="Collins, John">Collins</name> killed a Buck—    The water rose 〈2〉 Inches last night the effects of <hi rend="italic">tide.</hi> The Countrey has a handsom appearance in advance no mountains extensive bottoms—    the water Shallow for a great distance from Shore—.    The fog continued thick untill 12 oClock, we Coasted, and halted at the mouth of a large river on the Lard Side,<ref target="n25110302" n="2"/> This river throws out emence quanty of 〈quick〉 Sand and is verry Shallow, th narrowest part 200 yards wide bold Current, much resembling the river Plat, Several Islands about 1 mile up and has a Sandbar of 3 miles in extend imedately in its mouth, discharging it waters by 2 mouths, and Crowding its Corse Sands So as to throw the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> waters on its Nothern banks,<ref target="n25110303" n="3"/> &amp; confdg it to ½ ms. in width Passed a Small Prarie on the Stard. Side above, a large Creek<ref target="n25110304" n="4"/> opposit <hi rend="italic">qk Sand</hi> River on the Stard. Side, extensive bottoms and low hilley Countrey on each Side (<hi rend="italic">good wintering Place</hi>) a high peaked mountain Suppose to be <name type="place" key="Mount Hood (Timm, Falls Mountain)">Mt. Hood</name> is on the Lard Side S. 85° E. 40 miles distant from the mouth of <name type="place" key="Sandy (Quicksand) River">quick Sand river</name>.—</p>
               <p>
                  <table rows="4" cols="3">
                     <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Course</hi> Nov. 3d</head>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">West</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  3</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">miles to the upper mouth of <name type="place" key="Sandy (Quicksand) River">quick Sand 〈mountain〉 river</name>,<lb/>
Country low on each Side rising to a hilley Countrey passed a<lb/>
large Creek opposit Std. Side &amp; 2 Sand bars</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 70° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  7</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">miles to the upper point of a large Island Covered with<lb/>
[<hi rend="italic">blank</hi>]    passed the Lower mouth of <name type="place" key="Sandy (Quicksand) River">Sandy river</name> at 3 miles<lb/>
opposit the head of a large Island Std. Side faced with rocks<lb/>
and the 〈edge〉 Side is pine &amp; Cotton    a large Creek falls<lb/>
in oppost to the head of this Island Isld of Fowls<ref target="n25110305" n="5"/> as I Saw<lb/>
Som 1000 pass over to the head of this Island on the Stard<lb/>
Sd.    passed Some ruged rocks in the middle of the river op-<lb/>
posit the Island—    river wide The Countrey below quick<lb/>
Sand river on the Lard Side is low Piney Countrey. Passed the<lb/>
lower point of the Island at 3½ miles long &amp; 1½ wide—<lb/>
emence quantity of Geese, Brants, Ducks &amp; Sea otter, Some of<lb/>
the large &amp; Small kind of Swan, &amp; Sand hill Cranes—also luns<lb/>
&amp; White gulls</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 87° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                           <hi rend="underline">  3</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">miles on the North Side of the Island and Encamped    we met<lb/>
2 Canoes, of Indians 15 in number who informed us they had<lb/>
Seen 3 Vestles 2 days below us, we Camped on the Island, and<lb/>
Sent out hunters on it and <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name> walked out, after Dark<lb/>
                           <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name> with 3 men went into a large Pond on this Island<lb/>
&amp; killed a Swan &amp; Several ducks.    〈we〉 The Party killed this<lb/>
day 3 Swan 8 Brant, &amp; 5. The Canoe was borrowed of the<lb/>
Inds. here &amp; taken over by 4 men into the pond. I gave the<lb/>
Indians a Brant to eate.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                           <hi rend="double underline">13</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-11-03.02" n="lc.geo.1805-11-03.01">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">November 3rd Sunday 1805</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>	
The Fog So thick this morning that we could not See a man 50 Steps off, this fog detained us untill 10 oClock at which time we Set out, accompanied by our Indian friends who are from a village near the <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Great Falls of the">great falls</name>, previous to our Setting out <name type="person" key="Collins, John">Collins</name> killed a large Buck, and <name type="person" key="Labiche, François">Labiech</name> killed 3 Geese flying. I walked on the Sand beech Lard. Side, opposit the canoes as they passed allong. The under groth rushes, vines &amp;c. in the bottoms too thick to pass through, at 3 miles I arrived at the enterance of a river which appeared to Scatter over a Sand bar, the bottom of which I could See quite across and did not appear to be 4 Inches deep in any part; I attempted to wade this Stream and to my astonishment found the bottom a quick Sand, and impassable—    I called to the Canoes to put to Shore, I got into the Canoe and landed below the mouth, &amp; <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt Lewis</name> and my Self walked up this river about 1½ miles to examine this river which we found to be a verry Considerable Stream Dischargeing its waters through 2 Chanels which forms an Island of about 3 miles in length on the river and 1½ miles wide, composed of Corse Sand which is thrown out of this <name type="place" key="Sandy (Quicksand) River">quick Sand river</name> Compressing the waters of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> and throwing the whole Current of its waters against its Northern banks, within a Chanel of ½ a mile wide, Several Small Islands 1 mile up this river, This Stream has much the appearance of the <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="place" key="Platte River (Nebr.)">River Platt</name>:</hi> roleing its quick Sands into the bottoms with great velocity after which it is divided into 2 Chanels by a large Sand bar before mentioned, the narrowest part of this River is 120 yards—on the Opposit Side of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> a 〈large Creek〉 [<hi rend="italic">NB: Small river called <name type="place" key="Washougal (Seal) River">Seal river</name>
                  </hi>] falls in above this Creek    on the Same Side is a Small prarie.    extensive low country on each Side thickly timbered.</p>
               <p>
The <name type="place" key="Sandy (Quicksand) River">Quick Sand river</name> appears to pass through the low countrey at the foot of those high range of mountains in a Southerly direction,—    The large Creeks which fall into the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> on the Stard. Side rise in the Same range of mountains to the N. N. E. and pass through Some ridgey land—    A Mountain which we Suppose to be <name type="place" key="Mount Hood (Timm, Falls Mountain)">Mt. Hood</name> is S. 85° E about 47 miles distant from the mouth of <name type="place" key="Sandy (Quicksand) River">quick sand river</name> This mtn. is Covered with Snow and in the range of mountains which we have passed through and is of a Conical form but rugid—    after takeing dinner at the mouth of this river we proceeded on    passed the head of a Island near the lard Side back of which on the Same Side and near the head a large Creek falls in, and nearly opposit &amp; 3 miles below the upper mouth of <name type="place" key="Sandy (Quicksand) River">quick Sand river</name> is the lower mouth, [for?] This Island is 3½ miles long, has rocks at the upper point, Some timber on the borders of this Island in the middle open and ponney [<hi rend="italic">NB: pondy</hi>]. Some rugid rocks in the middle of the Stream opposit this Island.    〈proceeded in〉 [<hi rend="italic">NB: proceeded on</hi>] to Center of a large Island in the middle of the river which we call <name type="place" key="Government (Diamond, White Goose, Swan) Island">Dimond Isld.</name> from its appearance, here we met 15 Indn men in 2 canoes from below, they informed us they Saw 3 vestles below &amp;c. &amp;c.    we landed on the North Side of this <name type="place" key="Government (Diamond, White Goose, Swan) Island">Dimond Island</name> and Encamped,<ref target="n25110306" n="6"/>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. L</name> walked out with his gun on the Island, Sent out hunters &amp; fowlers—    below <name type="place" key="Sandy (Quicksand) River">quick Sand River</name> the Countrey is low rich and thickly timbered on each Side of the river, the Islands open &amp; Some ponds    river wide and emence numbers of fowls flying in every direction Such as Swan, geese, Brants, Cranes, Stalks [<hi rend="italic">NB: Storks</hi>], white guls, comerants &amp; plevers &amp;c.<ref target="n25110307" n="7"/>    also great numbers of Sea Otter in the river—<ref target="n25110308" n="8"/>    a Canoe arrived from the village below the last rapid with a man his wife and 3 children, and a woman whome had been taken prisoner from the <name type="native_nation" key="Paiute Indians">Snake Inds.</name> [<hi rend="italic">NB: on a river from the South which we found to be <name type="place" key="Willamette (Multnomah) River">Mulknoma</name>
                  </hi>] on <name type="place" key="Deschutes (Clark's, Towanahiook's) River">Clarks River</name>
                  <ref target="n25110309" n="9"/> I Sent the <name type="place" key="Sacagawea">Interpreters wife</name> who is a <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">So So ne</name>
                  </hi> or <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Snake Indian</name> of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, to Speake to this Squar, they Could not understand each other Sufficiently to Converse. This familey and the Inds. we met from below continued with us <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt Lewis</name> borrowed a Small Canoe of those Indians &amp; 4 men took her across to a Small lake in the Isld. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Cap L.</name> and 3 men Set out after night in this Canoe in Serch of the Swans, Brants Ducks &amp;c. &amp;c. which appeared in great numbers in the Lake, he Killed a Swan and Several Ducks which made our number of fowls this evening 3 Swan, 8 brant and 5 Ducks, on which we made a Sumptious Supper. We gave the Indian—who lent the Canoe a brant, and Some meat to the others.    one of those Indians, the man from the village near the lower Rapids has a gun with a brass barrel &amp; Cock of which he prises highly—    note the mountain we Saw from near the forks proves to be <name type="place" key="Mount Hood (Timm, Falls Mountain)">Mount <hi rend="italic">Hood</hi>
                  </name>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-11-03.03" n="lc.geo.1805-11-03.01">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Sunday 3rd Nov. 1805.    a foggy morning.    the geese verry pleanty on a marshey green below the Camp    one of our hunters Shot Several flying. Several Savages Stayed with us last night    they have 2 canoes with them.    we perceive the tide rise and fall a little at this place.    one of the hunters<ref target="n25110310" n="10"/> went out a Short distance to hunt and killed a large Deer.    about 9 oClock 
we set out and proceeded on    the fog So thick that we could not See across the River.    passd. Several Sand Islands    about noon we halted to dine at the mouth of a River which is filled with quick Sand and is wide and Shallow    our officers name this River <name type="place" key="Sandy (Quicksand) River">Quick Sand River</name>
                  <ref target="n25110311" n="11"/> on the Lard. Side.    here we perceive the tide water.    we Saw the round mountain some distance a head which we expect is the Same which was discovred by <name type="person" key="Hood, Samuel">Lieut. Hood</name> and is called <name type="place" key="Mount Hood (Timm, Falls Mountain)">Hoods Mountain</name>.<ref target="n25110312" n="12"/>    the after part of the day pleasant    the River is better than a mile wide in general.    towards evening we met several Indians in canoes    they Signed to us that their was Some white people and vessells &amp;C.    passed Several bottoms covred with cotten and oak pine &amp;C.    the Country not so Mountaineous as above.    we came 13 miles this day and Camped<ref target="n25110313" n="13"/> on a verry large Island which is mostly prarie and large ponds, which is full of Swan Geese brants and ducks &amp;C. Several Indians Camped with us.    at Sunset we got a small canoe and carried in the pond    Several Swan geese and brants killed by the party to day and this evening.—


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-11-03.04" n="lc.geo.1805-11-03.01">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Sunday 3rd.</hi>    The morning was foggy: one of the men went out and killed a fine buck. At 9 we proceeded on, but could not see the country we were passing, on account of the fog, which was very thick till noon when it disappeared, and we had a beautiful day. We at that time came to the mouth of a river on the south side, a quarter of a mile broad, but not more than 6 or 8 inches deep, running over a bar of quicksand. At this place we dined on venison and goose; and from which we can see the high point of a mountain covered with snow, in about a southeast direction from us. Our Commanding Officers are of opinion that it is <name type="place" key="Mount Hood (Timm, Falls Mountain)">Mount Hood</name>, discovered by a Lieutenant of <name type="person" key="Vancouver, George">Vancoover</name>, who was up this river 75 miles. The river that falls in here has two mouths, through which it drives out a considerable quantity of sand into the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>. Opposite the lower mouth there is a handsome island. At 2 o'clock we proceeded on, and passed another island. The country on both sides appears level and closely timbered: on the river the timber is cotton wood, maple<ref target="n25110314" n="14"/> and some ash; and back from it mostly spruce pine. We made 13 miles and encamped on a large island, in which is a large pond full of swans, geese and ducks. On our way and here we killed some of each kind. At night, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Lewis</name> had a small canoe carried over to the pond in order to hunt by moon light; but the party did not happen to have good luck, having killed only a swan and three ducks.


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-11-03.05" n="lc.geo.1805-11-03.01">
            <sp who="jw">
               <speaker>Whitehouse</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Sunday 3rd Nov. 1805</hi>.    a foggy morning.    we delayd. untill abt. 9 oClock.    Several men went out a Short distance to hunt.    we Shot Several geese flying over our Camp this morning.    one canoe belonging to the Savages and Several Indians camped with us last night.    a handsom Spring run came in near our Camp.    the fog So thick this morning that we cannot See more than one hundred yards distance.    agreeable to all calculations it cannot be more than two hundred miles from this to the ocean.    one of the men killd. a large buck Deer    we then Set out abt. 9 oC. and proceeded on    the fog continued So thick that we could Scarsely See the Shores or Islands    passed Several Isld.    abt. noon we halted to dine at the mo. of a River which came in on the Lard. Side, the mouth of which was filled with quick Sand So that we could run a pole 6 or 8 feet in it, and it emptyd. in at Several places thro a verry large Sand bar which lay at the mo    we then proceeded on    passd. the mo. of a Small River<ref target="n25110315" n="15"/> on Stard.    the after part of the day clear and pleas[ant]    we Saw a high round mountain on the Lard Side which we expect is the Same we Saw abo. the <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Great Falls of the">great falls</name> and the Same that <name type="person" key="Hood, Samuel">Lieut. Hood</name> gave an account off.    (it is nearly covd. with Snow)    we proceeded on the River verry wide better than a mile in general.    a nomber of large Islands &amp;c.    towards evening we met Several Indians in a canoe who were going up the River.    they Signed to us that in two Sleeps we Should See [the Ocean vessels and?] white people &amp;c. &amp;c.    the Country lower and not So mountanous    the River more handsome the current verry gentle.    Some bottoms covered with cotton and pine &amp;c.    passd. a nomber of large Islands.    went about 13 miles and Camped on a verry large &amp; long Island which was mostly prarie and handsome.    a large lake on it.    we have Seen a great many Sea otter in the River ever Since we came to the <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Great Falls of the">Big falls</name>.    the geese and Swan ducks and brants &amp;c.    we killed Several Swan geese and brants &amp;c. this day.    a nomber of the Savages Camped with us.    at Sunset we got a Small canoe from them and carried it out to the pond or lake and killed a nomber of large Swan and geese.</p>
               <p>
Sunday Novemr. 3d    A foggy morning &amp; we delayed setting out till about 9 oClock A. M.    Several of our men went out a short distance for to hunt.—    The party that remained at Camp, shot this morning several Geese as they were flying over our Camp.    One of the Canoes that we saw at the large rapid stopped at the place we encamped, &amp; the Indians that were in her, &amp; several others of the same Nation that came by land staid with us all night.    The fog got so thick that we could not see 100 Yards distance from the Camp.    We find agreeable to the best calculation we can make that we are not more than 200 Miles from the Ocean.    One of the party that went out hunting this morning returned to the Camp and brought with him a large buck Deer which he had killed.    The remainder of the hunters also returned, &amp; had killed a number of Geese &amp; Ducks.    We then set out on our Voyage, the fog continuing so thick, that we could scarcely see the Shores or Islands as we passed along    We saw about 12 o'Clock A. M. several Islands &amp; halted to dine at the Mouth of a River, which came into the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name> on the South side.    The mouths or entrance of this River is filled with a quick sand, which we run a pole 8 feet down, &amp; had no solid bottom and it emptied itself by several Mouths</p>
               <p>
At 2 o'Clock P. M. we passed also the Mouth of a small river, lying on the North side of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>.    The weather now got clear &amp; pleasant.    We continued on, and saw a high round Mountain, lying on the South side 
of the River, which we supposed to be the same Mountain, that we saw above the <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Great Falls of the">great falls</name> of this River, and believe it to be the same Mountain; that <name type="person" key="Hood, Samuel">Lieutenant Hood</name> gave an account of when on a Voyage round the World with <name type="person" key="Cook, James">Captain Cook</name>, This Mountain appeared nearly covered with Snow.    We proceeded on, the River being nearly One Mile &amp; a quarter wide in general, &amp; a number of large Islands in it, laying on both sides of it.—</p>
               <p>
Towards evening we met with several Indians, who were in a Canoe, &amp; who were going up the River.    The Indians made signs to us, that in 2 Sleeps, (meaning 2 days,) that we should come to a place, where we should see two Vessells, white people &amp;ca.    The country during this day, appears to lay lower than it had been for some time past, &amp; but few mountains to be seen.    The River had a handsomer appearance &amp; the Current of it very gentle.    We passed by some bottom land, lying along the River, which were cover'd with Cotton wood &amp; Pine Trees, and a number of Islands.    We encamped on a very large long Island by us called <name type="place" key="Government (Diamond, White Goose, Swan) Island">Swan Island</name>, which was chiefly a Priari, and had a large lake in it, having gone about 13 Miles this day.    We saw in the River ever since we came through the <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Great Falls of the">great falls</name>, a great many Sea Otters, Geese, Swans, brants, ducks &amp; other water fowl.—    Our party killed several Geese Swans &amp; Ducks 〈of them〉 this day.    A number of Indians came to the Island that we were encamped on, in Canoes, &amp; encamped with us.    Some of our party borrowed a small Canoe from those Indians, &amp; carried it out to the lake, where they killed a further quantity of Swans &amp; Geese.—



</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n25110301" n="1">Between the camp of November 2 and the mouth of <name type="place" key="Sandy (Quicksand) River">Sandy (Quicksand) River</name> they passed the highest point on the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> reached by <name type="person" key="Broughton, William Robert">Lieutenant William Broughton</name> of <name type="person" key="Vancouver, George">George Vancouver's</name> expedition in 1792. This was on a large sand island, today's <name type="place" key="Reed Island">Reed Island</name>, much of which had disappeared by 1805. Thus they returned, for the first time since April 1805, to country previously explored by whites. They also passed the point <name type="person" key="Broughton, William Robert">Broughton</name> named <name type="place" key="Point Vancouver">Point Vancouver</name>, having sighted it from the island; the point is about four miles east of <name type="place" key="Washougal, Wash.">Washougal</name>, <name type="place" key="Clark County, Wash.">Clark County</name>, <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>, and across the river from <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon's</name>
               <name type="place" key="Rooster Rock State Park (Oreg.)">Rooster Rock State Park</name>. Barry (BOC); Anderson (SSGV), 116–17; Meany, 264–65; <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> maps 79, 88.</note>
            <note xml:id="n25110302" n="2">
               <name type="place" key="Sandy (Quicksand) River">Sandy River</name>, "<name type="place" key="Sandy (Quicksand) River">Quick Sand River</name>" on <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 79, in <name type="place" key="Multnomah County, Oreg.">Multnomah County</name>, <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n25110303" n="3">The sand deposited by <name type="place" key="Sandy (Quicksand) River">Sandy River</name> is derived by erosion of mudflows from <name type="place" key="Mount Hood (Timm, Falls Mountain)">Mt. Hood</name> containing abundant volcanic ash and volcaniclastic fragments. The mudflow is the last of many and may have occurred less than two hundred years ago—probably just a few years before <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> passed through here. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> was correct about the impact of the <name type="place" key="Sandy (Quicksand) River">Sandy</name> on the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>, as its delta has diverted the main stream's channel two miles to the north. Allen (MG), 82.</note>
            <note xml:id="n25110304" n="4">
               <name type="place" key="Washougal (Seal) River">Washougal River</name>, meeting the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> near present <name type="place" key="Washougal, Wash.">Washougal</name>; "<name type="place" key="Washougal (Seal) River">Seal R</name>" on <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 79.</note>
            <note xml:id="n25110305" n="5">"<name type="place" key="Lady (White Brant) Island">White Brant Isld</name>" on <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 79, and "Fowl I" on <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 88; apparently later <name type="place" key="Lady (White Brant) Island">Lady Island</name>. Archaeological work here, although largely unpublished, is noteworthy for the discovery of prehistoric ceramic artifacts associated with occupation of a site on the island approximately 2,000–2,500 years ago. Woodward (ECT).</note>
            <note xml:id="n25110306" n="6">
               <name type="place" key="Government (Diamond, White Goose, Swan) Island">Diamond Island</name> is later <name type="place" key="Government (Diamond, White Goose, Swan) Island">Government</name> and <name type="place" key="McGuire (Diamond, Swan, White Goose) Island">McGuire islands</name>, opposite <name type="place" key="Portland, Oreg.">Portland</name>, <name type="place" key="Multnomah County, Oreg.">Multnomah County</name>. The samp was on the island, about three miles west of present <name type="place" key="Camas, Wash.">Camas</name>, <name type="place" key="Clark County, Wash.">Clark County</name>, <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 79.</note>
            <note xml:id="n25110307" n="7">Some of these birds may be identified as the sandhill crane, <hi rend="italic">Grus canadensi</hi> [AOU, 206], and the double-crested cormorant, <hi rend="italic">Phalacrocorax auritus</hi> [AOU, 120]. Although the wood stork, <hi rend="italic">Mycteria americana</hi> [AOU, 188], was once considered to be one of the bird's identified, this information may not be valid since its range is well south of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> path. The swans (noted as the "large &amp; Small kind" in the first entry) would be the trumpeter swan, <hi rend="italic">Cygnus buccinator</hi> [AOU, 181], and the tundra, or whistling, swan, <hi rend="italic">C. columbianus</hi> [AOU, 180]. See below, <ref n="1806-03-09" type="related">March 9, 1806</ref>. The other references are too obscure for precise identification. Holmgren, 33; Burroughs, 199–200.</note>
            <note xml:id="n25110308" n="8">The harbor seal.</note>
            <note xml:id="n25110309" n="9">The "<name type="native_nation" key="Paiute Indians">Snake</name>" woman was probably a <name type="native_nation" key="Paiute Indians">Paiute</name>, but perhaps a <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshone</name>an whose language was unfamiliar to <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name>. <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name> added the red-inked note about the "Mulknoma" knowing the party's discovery of this river on their return journey in April 1806; it is the present <name type="place" key="Willamette (Multnomah) River">Willamette River</name>, meeting the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> at <name type="place" key="Portland, Oreg.">Portland</name>. Actually their original supposition that these Indians were living on the <name type="place" key="Deschutes (Clark's, Towanahiook's) River">"Clark's" River</name> (present <name type="place" key="Deschutes (Clark's, Towanahiook's) River">Deschutes</name>) was probably correct. Ray &amp; Lurie, 365; <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> maps 77, 79.</note>
            <note xml:id="n25110310" n="10">
               <name type="person" key="Collins, John">Collins</name>, according to <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n25110311" n="11">
               <name type="place" key="Sandy (Quicksand) River">Sandy River</name>, <name type="place" key="Multnomah County, Oreg.">Multnomah County</name>, <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n25110312" n="12">
               <name type="place" key="Mount Hood (Timm, Falls Mountain)">Mt. Hood</name>, <name type="place" key="Hood River County, Oreg.">Hood River County</name>, <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>, was named for British <name type="person" key="Hood, Samuel">Admiral Sir Samuel Hood</name> by <name type="person" key="Broughton, William Robert">Lieutenant William Robert Broughton</name> of <name type="person" key="Vancouver, George">George Vancouver's</name> seaborne exploring 
expedition in 1792. They passed his farthest point on the river this day.</note>
            <note xml:id="n25110313" n="13">On either <name type="place" key="Government (Diamond, White Goose, Swan) Island">Government</name> or <name type="place" key="McGuire (Diamond, Swan, White Goose) Island">McGuire islands</name>, opposite and upstream from <name type="place" key="Portland, Oreg.">Portland</name>, 
<name type="place" key="Multnomah County, Oreg.">Multnomah County</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n25110314" n="14">Probably bigleaf maple, <hi rend="italic">Acer macrophyllum</hi> Pursh.</note>
            <note xml:id="n25110315" n="15">
               <name type="place" key="Washougal (Seal) River">Washougal River</name>, joining the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name> near <name type="place" key="Washougal, Wash.">Washougal</name>, <name type="place" key="Clark County, Wash.">Clark County</name>, 
<name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-11-02" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-11-04" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
