<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-08-16">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
August 16, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 8</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">June 10–September 26, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1987</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">303-305</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">350-351</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">268</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Journal Entries</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic"/>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-12-13</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1806-08-16">August 16, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-08-16.01" n="">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Friday 16th August 1806</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
a cool morning. Sent up <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Sergt. Pryor</name> to the <name type="person" key="Mandan Indians">mandan</name> village, for Some Corn which they offered to give us.    he informed that they had more Corn collected for us than our Canoes Could Carry Six loads of which he brought down. I thanked the Chief for his kindness and informed him that our Canoes would not Carry any more Corn than we had already brought down.    at 10 A. M the Chiefs of the different villages came to See us and Smoke a pipe &amp;c.    as our Swivel<ref target="n39081601" n="1"/> Could no longer be Serveceabe to us as it could not be fireed on board the largest Perogue, we Concluded to make a present of it to the Great Chief of the <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Menetaras</name> (the <name type="person" key="Le Borgne (One Eye)">One Eye</name>) with a view to ingratiate him more Strongly in our favour I had the Swivel Charged and Collected the Chiefs in a circle around it and adressed them with great ceremoney.    told them I had listened with much attention to what the <name type="person" key="Le Borgne (One Eye)">One Eye</name> had Said yesterday and beleived that he was Sincere &amp; Spoke from his heart. I reproached them very Severely for not attending to what had been Said to them by us in Council in the fall of 1804 and at different times in the winter of 1804 &amp; 5, and told them our backs were Scerely turned befor a party followed and killed the pore defenceless <name type="native_nation" key="Cheyenne Indians">snake indians</name> whom we had taken by the hand &amp; told them not to be afraid that you would never Strike them again &amp;c. also mentioned the ricers &amp;c. <name type="person" key="Cherry Grows on a Bush (Caltarcota)">The little Cherry</name>
                  <ref target="n39081602" n="2"/> old Chief of the <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Menetarras</name> Spoke as follows Viz: "Father we wish to go down with you to See our Great Father, but we know the nations below and are afraid of the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Scioux</name> who will be on the river and will kill us on our return home. The <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Scioux</name> has Stolen our horses and killed 8 of our men Since you left us, and the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Ricaras</name> have also Struck us.    we Staid at home and listened to what you had told us.    we at length went to war against the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Scioux</name> and met with <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Ricaras</name> and killed two of them, they were on their way to Strike us. We will attend to your word and not hurt any people all Shall be Welcom and we Shall do as you direct—.["] The <name type="person" key="Le Borgne (One Eye)">One Eye</name> Said his ears would always be open to the word of his great father and Shut against bad Council &amp;c. I then a good deel of Ceremony made a preasent of the Swivel to the <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="person" key="Le Borgne (One Eye)">One Eye</name>
                  </hi> Chief and told him when he fired this gun to remember the words of his great father which we had given him.    this gun had anounced the words of his great father to all the nations which we had Seen &amp;c. &amp;c.    after the council was over the gun was fired &amp; delivered, they Chief appeared to be much pelased and conveyed it immediately to his village &amp;c.    we Settled with and discharged <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name>.    in the evening I walked to the village to See the <name type="person" key="Little Crow (Ka-goh-ha-me)">little Crow</name> and know when he would be ready, took with me a flag intending to give him to leave at his lodge but to my astonishment he informed me he had declined going down the reason of which I found was through a jellousy between himself and the principal Chief    he refused a flag &amp; we Sent for <name type="person" key="Jusseaume, René">Mr. Jessomme</name> and told him to use his influn to provail on one of the Chiefs to accompany us and<ref target="n39081603" n="3"/> we would employ him.    he informed us soon after that the <name type="person" key="Big White (Sheheke)">big white Chief</name>
                  <ref target="n39081604" n="4"/> would go if we would take his wife &amp; Son &amp; <name type="person" key="Jusseaume, René">Jessoms</name> wife &amp; 2 children    we wer obliged to agree to do
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-08-16.02" n="">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Saturday 16th August 1806.    a clear cool morning.    great numbers of the natives visited us and traded us good robes and mockasons.    towards evening the <name type="person" key="Big White (Sheheke)">Big White</name> a head chief of the 1st village of <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name> concluded to go down with us and <name type="person" key="Jusseaume, René">Mr. Jessom</name>
                  <ref target="n39081605" n="5"/> and their wives and three children    <name type="person" key="Jusseaume, René">Mr. Jessom</name> two and the <name type="person" key="Big White (Sheheke)">Big White</name> one and verry handsome children    one of <name type="person" key="Jusseaume, René">Mr. jessoms</name> has had a little Scooling at the N. W. Company.—


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-08-16.03" n="">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Saturday 16th.</hi>    There was a fine cool day; and we yet remained here, waiting an answer from the natives. Some of these Indians are very kind and obliging; furnishing us with corn, beans and squashes; but there are others very troublesome, and steal whenever they have an opportunity. Yesterday and to-day, they stole several knives and spoons; and three powder-horns, and two pouches, filled with ammunition.</p>
               <p>
In the afternoon the chief, called the <name type="person" key="Big White (Sheheke)">Big-White</name>, concluded to go down with us, and we agreed to stay until 12 o'clock to-morrow, that he might have an opportunity to get ready for his voyage and mission. The Commanding Officers gave discharges to the man who agreed to return with the hunters up the river, and the interpreter;<ref target="n39081606" n="6"/> who intends settling among these Indians, and to whom they gave the blacksmith's tools; supposing they might be useful to the nation. They also gave a small piece of ordnance<ref target="n39081607" n="7"/> to the <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Grossventers</name>, which they appeared very fond of.



</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n39081601" n="1">The party's small cannon, recently recovered from the cache at the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">Great Falls of the Missouri</name>; see <ref n="1804-05-29" type="related">May 29, 1804</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n39081602" n="2">
               <name type="person" key="Cherry Grows on a Bush (Caltarcota)">Cherry Grows on a Bush</name> of <name type="place" key="Menetarra village">Menetarra village</name>; see <ref n="1804-10-29" type="related">October 29, 1804</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n39081603" n="3">From about here the remainder of the entry appears to be an afterthought, crowded into the bottom of one page and the top of the next in Codex N.</note>
            <note xml:id="n39081604" n="4">
               <name type="person" key="Big White (Sheheke)">Big White</name>, or <name type="person" key="Big White (Sheheke)">Sheheke</name>, of <name type="place" key="Mitutanka (Matootonha) village">Mitutanka village</name>; see <ref n="1804-10-29" type="related">October 29, 1804</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n39081605" n="5">
               <name type="person" key="Jusseaume, René">Rene Jusseaume</name>; see <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> entry of <ref n="1804-10-27" type="related">October 27, 1804</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n39081606" n="6">
               <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name>, who remained here with <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name> and little <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Jean Baptiste">Jean Baptiste</name>. Only <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name> 
mentions that they gave him the blacksmith's tools, an instance of the Jeffersonian policy of gradually "civilizing" the Indians.</note>
            <note xml:id="n39081607" n="7">The small swivel cannon, which they gave to <name type="person" key="Le Borgne (One Eye)">Le Borgne, or One Eye</name>, the <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> chief.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-08-15" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-08-17" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
