<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-06-20">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
June 20, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 8</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">June 10–September 26, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1987</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">39-43</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">325</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">242</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Journal Entries</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic"/>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-11-02</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1806-06-20">June 20, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-06-20.01" n="">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Friday June 20th 1806.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
Our hunters set out early this morning; most of them returned before noon. <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">R. Feilds</name> killed a brown bear the tallons of which were remarkably short broad at their base and sharply pointed this was of the speceis which the <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Chopunnish</name> call <hi rend="italic">Yah-kar.</hi>
                  <ref target="n36062001" n="1"/>    it was in very low order and the flesh of the bear in this situation is much inferior to lean venison or the flesh of poor Elk. <name type="person" key="Labiche, François">Labush</name> and <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Cruzatte</name> returned late in the evening with one deer which the former had killed.    we also caught seven salmon trout in the course of the day.    the hunters assured us that their greatest exertions would not enable them to support us here more than one or two days longer from the great scarcity of game and the difficult access of the country, the under brush being very thick and great quantities of fallen timber.    as we shall necessarily be compelled to remain more than two days for the return of <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name> and <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name> we determined to return in the morning as far as the <name type="place" key="Weippe Prairie (Camas Flats, Quawmash Flats)">quawmash flatts</name> and indeavour to lay in another stock of meat for the mountains, our former stock being now nearly exhausted as well as what we have killed on our return.    by returning to the <name type="place" key="Weippe Prairie (Camas Flats, Quawmash Flats)">quawmash flatts</name> we shall sooner be informed whether or not we can procure a guide to conduct us through the mountains; should we fail in procuring one, we have determined to wrisk a passage on the following plan immediately, because should we wait much longer or untill the snow desolves in such manner as to enable us to follow the road we cannot hope to reach the United States this winter; this is that <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. C.</name> or myself shall take four of our most expert woodsmen with three or four of our best horses and proceed two days in advance taking a plentiful supply of provision.    for this party to follow the road by the marks which the baggage of the indians has made in many places on the sides of the trees by rubing against them, and to blaize the trees with a tomahawk as they proceeded.    that after proceeding two days in advance of <name type="place" key="Hungery Creek">hungary creek</name> two of those men would be sent back to the main party who by the time of their return to <name type="place" key="Hungery Creek">Hungary Creek</name> would have reached that place.    the men so returning would be enabled to inform the main party of the probable success of the preceeding party in finding the road and of their probable progress, in order that should it be necessary, the main party by the delay of a day or two at <name type="place" key="Hungery Creek">hungary creek</name>, should give the advance time to mark the road through before the main party could overtake them, and thus prevent delay on the part of the rout where no food is to be obtained for our horses.    should it so happen that the advance could not find the road by the marks on the trees after attempting it for two days, the whole of then would return to the main party.    in which case we wold bring back our baggage and attempt a passage over these mountains through the country of the <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshones</name> further to the South by way of the main <name type="place" key="Jefferson River (North, Southwest Fork)">S. Westerly fork of Lewis's river</name> and <name type="place" key="Madison River (Middle Fork)">Madison</name> or <name type="place" key="Gallatin (South, Southeast Fork) River">Gallatin's</name> rivers, where from the information of the <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Chopunnish</name> there is a passage which at this season of the year is not obstructed by snow, though the round is very distant and would require at least a month in it's performance.<ref target="n36062002" n="2"/> The <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshones</name> informed us when we first met with them that there was a passage across the mountains in that quarter but represented the difficulties arrising from steep high and rugged mountains and also an extensive and barren plain which was to be passed without game, as infinitely more difficult than the rout by which we came.    from the circumstance of the <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Chopunnish</name> being at war with that part of the <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshones</name> who inhabit the country on this side of the Mountains through which the road passes I think it is highly probable that they cannot be well informed with rispect to the road, and further, had there been a better road in that quarter the <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshones</name>
                  <ref target="n36062003" n="3"/> on the <name type="place"
                        key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">East fork of Lewis's river</name> who knew them both would not have recommended that by which we came to this country.    the travelling in the mountains on the snow at present is very good, the snow bears the horses perfictly; it is a firm coase snow without a crust, and the horses have good foot hold without sliping much; the only dificulty is finding the road, and I think the plan we have devised will succeed even should we not be enabled to obtain a guide. Although the snow may be stated on an average at 10 feet deep yet arround the bodies of the trees it has desolved 〈generally〉 much more than in other parts not being generally more than one or two feet deep immediately at the roots of the trees, and; of course the marks left by the rubing of the indian baggage against them is not concealed.    the reason why the snow is comparitively so shallow about the roots of the tree I presume proceeds as well from the snow in falling being thrown off from their bodies by their thick and spreading branches as from the reflection of the sun against the trees and the warmth which they in some measure acquire from the earth which is never frozen underneath these masses of snow. <name type="person" key="Bratton, William E.">Bratton's</name> horse was also discovered to be absent this evening. I presume he has also returned to the flatts.
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-06-20.02" n="">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Friday June 20th, 1806</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
The hunters turned out early in different directions, our guiggers also turned out with 2 guigs a Bayonet fixed on a pole, a Scooping nett and a Snar made of horse.<ref target="n36062004" n="4"/>    near the ford of the Creek in a deep hole we killed Six Salmon trout &amp; 2 others were killed in the Creek above in the evening. <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">Reubin Field</name> killed a redish brown bear which was very meagure.    the tallons of this bear was remarkably Short broad at their base and Sharply pointed, this was of the Species the <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Chopunnish</name> call <hi rend="italic">Yahkar.</hi>    as it was in very low order the flesh was indifferent. <name type="person" key="Labiche, François">Labiesh</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Crusat</name> returned late in the evening with one deer which the former had killed.    the hunters assured us that, their greatest exertions would not enable them to support us here more than one or two days longer, from the great scercity of game and the dificuelt access of the Country, the under brush being very thick and great quantities of fallen timber.    as we shall necessarily be compelled to remain more than two days for the return of <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name> we determine to return in the morning as far as the <name type="place" key="Weippe Prairie (Camas Flats, Quawmash Flats)">quawmash flatts</name>, and endeaver to lay in another Stock of meat for the mountains, our former Stock now being nearly exhosted as well as what we have killed on our rout.    by returning to the <name type="place" key="Weippe Prairie (Camas Flats, Quawmash Flats)">quawmash flatts</name> were Shall Sooner be informed wheather or not we can precure a guide to conduct us through the Mountains; Should we fail in precureing one, we are deturmined to wrisk a passage on the following plan immediately, because Should we wait much longer, or untill the Snow disolves in Such manner as to enable us to follow the road we cannot expect to reach the U States this Winter; this is that <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. L.</name> or myself shall take four of our most expert woods men with 3 or four of our best horses and proceed two days in advance takeing a plentiful Supply of provisions.    for this party to follow the road by the mark the indins have made in many places with their baggage on the Sides of the trees by rubbing against them, and to blaize the trees with a tomahawk as they proceed.    that after proceeding two days in advance of <name type="place" key="Hungery Creek">Hungary Creek</name>, two of those men would be sent back to the party who by the time of their return to <name type="place" key="Hungery Creek">hungary Creek</name> would have reached that place.    the men So returning would be enabled to inform the main party of the probable Suckcess of the proceeding party in finding the road and of their probable progress, in order that Should it be necessary, the main party by a delay of a day or two a <name type="place" key="Hungery Creek">hungary Creek</name>, should give the advance time to make the road through before the main party could overtake them, and thus prevent delay on that part of the rout where no food is to be obtained for our horses. Should it So happen that the advance Should not find the road by the marks of the trees after attempting it for two days, the whole of them would return to the main party.    in which Case we would bring back our baggage and attempt a passage over the Mountains through the Country of the <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshones</name> further to the South, by way of the main <name type="place" key="Jefferson River (North, Southwest Fork)">S Westerly fork of Lewis's river</name> and <name type="place" key="Madison River (Middle Fork)">Madisons</name> or <name type="place" key="Gallatin (South, Southeast Fork) River">Gallitins</name> river's, where from the information of the <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Chopunnish</name>, there is a passage where at this season of the year is not obstructed by snow, though the round is very distant and would require at least a month in it's preformance. The <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshones</name> informed us when we first met with them that there was a passage across the Mountains in that quarter but represented the difficuelties arriseing from Steep ruggid high mountains, and also an extensive and barren plain which was to be passed without game, as infinitely more difficuelt than the rout by which we Came.    from the Circumstance of the <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Chopunnish</name> being at war with that part of the <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshones</name> who inhabit the Country on this side of the Mountains through which the road passes, I think it is highly probable they cannot be well informed with respect to the road, and further, had there been a better road in that quarter the <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshones</name> on the <name type="place"
                        key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">East fork of Lewis's river</name> who knew them boath would not have recommend'd that by which we came to this country. The travelling in the Mountains on the Snow, at present is very good, the Snow bears the horses perfectly; it is a firm coase Snow without a crust, and the horses have good foot hold without slipping much; the only dificuelty is finding the road, and I think the plan we have 〈deci〉 devised will Suckceed even Should we not be enabled to obtain a guide.    altho the Snow may be Stated on an average at 10 feet deep, yet arround the body of the trees it has disolved much more than in other parts, not being generally more than one or two feet deep imediately at the roots of the trees, and of course the marks made by the rubbing of the Indian baggage against them is not Concealed. The reason why the Snow is 〈not〉 comparitively So Shallow about the roots of the trees, I prosume proceeds as well from the 〈roots〉 Snow in falling being thrown off from their bodies by the thick and Spreading branches, as from the reflection of the Sun against the trees and the warmth which they in Some measure acquire from the earth which is never frozen underneath those masses of Snow.    4 of our horses are absent.
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-06-20.03" n="">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Friday 20th June 1806.    a fair morning. Several hunters went out eairly a hunting.    about 11 A. M. <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">R. Fields</name> came in    had killed a Brown bear about a mile down this glade. Several men went at fishing    fixed gigs of Bayonets &amp; Indn. gigs and fixed a dip net &amp;C. and killd and caught 7 Salmon trout    towards evening <name type="person" key="Labiche, François">Labuche</name> and <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Cruzatte</name> came in    had killed one deer &amp; caught one Salmon trout.—

</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-06-20.04" n="">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Friday 20th.</hi>    There was a fine morning; we caught six of the salmon-trout;  and some hunters went out. About 9 o'clock one<ref target="n36062005" n="5"/> of them returned, and had killed a brown bear. The musquitoes and gnats are very troublesome. In the evening the other hunters<ref target="n36062006" n="6"/> came in and had killed only one deer.


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n36062001" n="1">The cinnamon phase of the black bear; see <ref n="1806-06-11" type="related">June 11, 1806</ref>. <hi rend="italic">Yá·ka,</hi> "brown bear," is the <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name> term for the black bear; see <ref n="1806-05-31" type="related">May 31, 1806</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36062002" n="2">This route would be up the <name type="place"
                     key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Snake River</name> in its long curve through southern <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>, including the arid <name type="place" key="Snake River Plain">Snake River Plain</name>. They would then cross the <name type="place" key="Continental Divide">Continental Divide</name> through one of several passes west of present <name type="place" key="Yellowstone National Park">Yellowstone Park</name> into southwestern <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name> near the headwaters of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Three Forks of the">Missouri forks</name>. The <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perces</name> may also have been thinking of the route from the upper <name type="place"
                     key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Snake River</name> through the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone National Park">Yellowstone plateau (the present park)</name>, to the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone River</name>; this was used by various mountain tribes, and was later called the <name type="place" key="Bannock Trail">Bannock Trail</name>. Either way would have been a long and circuitous route. Allen (PG), 347, 379 and n. 61; Ehrenberg, 77; Sprague (GG), 213, 436.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36062003" n="3">The <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians, Lemhi">Lemhi Shoshones</name> (<name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea's</name> people), whom they met on the <name type="place" key="Lemhi (East Fork Lewis's) River">Lemhi River</name> in eastern <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name> in August 1805.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36062004" n="4">Horsehair, presumably.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36062005" n="5">
               <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">Reubin Field</name>, noted by the captains and <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36062006" n="6">
               <name type="person" key="Labiche, François">Labiche</name> and <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Cruzatte</name>.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-06-19" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-06-21" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
