<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-05-30">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
May 30, 1805</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 4</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">April7–July 27, 1805</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1987</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">221-224</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">158-159</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">96</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jw">Joseph Whitehouse</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 11</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of Joseph Whitehouse, May 14, 1804–April 2, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1997</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">179</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
         <geoDecl datum="WGS" xml:id="lc.geo.1805-05-30.01">
            <placeName/>
            <geo>47.7613 -109.9248</geo>
            <note>In Chouteau County, MT, above Pablo Island. Nearly opposite Sheep Shed Coulee</note>
         </geoDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Journal Entries</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic"/>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-01-23</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1805-05-30">May 30, 1805</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-05-30.01" n="lc.geo.1805-05-30.01">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Thursday May 30th 1805.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
The rain which commenced last evening continued with little intermission untill 11 this morning when we set out; the high wind which accompanied the rain rendered it impracticable to procede earlyer.    more rain has now fallen than we have experienced since the 15th of September last.    many circumstances indicate our near approach to a country whos climate differs considerably from that in which we have been for many months.    the air of the open country is asstonishingly dry as well as pure. I found by several experiments that a table spoon full of water exposed to the air in a saucer would avaporate in 36 hours when the murcury did not stand higher than the temperate point at the greatest heat of the day; my inkstand so frequently becoming dry put me on this experiment. <ref target="n14053001" n="1">I also observed the well seasoned case of my sextant shrunk considerably and the joints opened.</ref> The water of the river still continues to become clearer and notwithstanding the rain which has fallen it is still much clearer than it was a few days past.    this day we proceded with more labour and difficulty than we have yet experienced; in addition to the imbarrasments of the rappid courant, riffles, &amp; rockey point which were as bad if not worse than yesterday, the banks and sides of the bluff were more steep than usual and were now rendered so slippery by the late rain that the men could scarcely walk.    the chord is our only dependance for the courant is too rappid to be resisted with the oar and the river too deep in most places for the pole.    the earth and stone also falling from these immence high bluffs render it dangerous to pass under them.    the wind was also hard and against us.    our chords broke several times today but happily without injury to the vessels.    we had slight showers of rain through the course of the day, the air was could and rendered more disagreeable by the rain.    one of the party ascended the river hills and reported on his return that there was snow intermixed with the rain which fell on the hights; he also informed us that the country was level 〈and untimbered〉 a little back from the river on both sides.    there is now no timber on the hills, an only a few scattering cottonwood, ash, box Alder and willows to be seen along the river.    in the course of the day we passed several old encampment of Indians, from the apparent dates of which we conceived that they were the several encampments of a band of about 100 lodges who were progressing slowly up the river; the most recent appeared to have been evacuated about 5 weeks since.    these we supposed to be the <name type="native_nation" key="Atsina Indians">Minetares</name> or black foot Indians who inhabit the country watered by the <name type="place" key="Saskatchewan River">Suskashawan</name> and who resort to the establishment of <name type="place" key="Fort des Prairies (Canada)">Fort de Prarie</name>, no part of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> from the <name type="native_nation" key="Atsina Indians">Minetaries</name> to this place furnishes a perminent residence for any nation yet there is no part of it but what exhibits appearances of being occasionally visited by some nation on hunting excurtions. The <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Minnetares</name> of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missoury</name> we know extend their excurtions on the S. [<hi rend="italic">NB: south</hi>] side as high as the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">yellowstone river</name>; the <name type="native_nation" key="Assiniboine Indians">Assinniboins</name> still higher on the N. side most probably as high as about <name type="place" key="Poplar (Porcupine) River">Porcupine river</name> and from thence upwards most probably as far as the mountains by the <name type="native_nation" key="Atsina Indians">Minetares</name> of <name type="place" key="Fort des Prairies (Canada)">Fort de Prarie</name> and the <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Black Foot</name> Indians who inhabit the S. fork of the <name type="place" key="Saskatchewan River">Suskashawan</name>. I say the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> to the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky mountains</name> for I am convinced that it penetrates those mountains for a considerable distance—    Two buffaloe killed this evening <ref target="n14053002" n="2">a little above our encampment.</ref>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <table rows="7" cols="3">
                     <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Courses and Distances May 30th 1805.</hi>
                        <ref target="n14053003" n="3"/>
                     </head>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 70° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">   ¼</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Along the timbered bottom on the Stard. side opposite to a<lb/>
high clift.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 50° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">2</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">to a few trees on a Lard. point</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 60° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">   ¾</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">to a broken trunk of a tree on a Stard point opposite to a<lb/>
high black bluff.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 70° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">   ¼</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">On the Stard. side to a few willows.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 30° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">1 ¼</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">On the Stard. side to the entrance of a <ref target="n14053004" n="4">run in a bend.</ref>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 55° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rend="underline" rows="1" cols="1">2 ½</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">to a grove of trees in a bend, on Lard. side at the entrance<lb/>
of a <ref target="n14053005" n="5">run,</ref> passing a small Island on the Stard. side at 2 ms.,<lb/>
above which we encamped on the Stard. side—</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                           <hi rend="right">Miles</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">8</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-05-30.02" n="lc.geo.1805-05-30.01">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">May 30th Thursday 1805</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
The rain conmmenced yesterday evining, and continued moderately through the course of the night, more rain has now fallin than we have experienced Since the 15th of September last, the rain continued this morning, and the wind too high for us to proceed, untill about 11 oClock at which time we Set out, and proceeded on with great labour, we were obliged to make use of the Tow rope &amp; the banks were So muddey &amp; Slipery that the men could Scercely walk not with Standing we proceeded on as well as we could    wind hard from the N W.    in attempting to assend a rapid our toe Cord broke &amp; we turned 〈on〉 without injurey, those rapids or Shoaley points are noumerous and dificuelt, one being at the mouth of every drean    Some little rain at times all day    one man assended the high Countrey and it was raining &amp; Snowing on those hills, the day has
proved to be raw and Cold. Back from the river is tollerably leavel, no timber of any kind on the hills, and only a fiew Scattering cotton willow &amp; ash near the river, much hard rock; &amp; rich earth, the Small portion of rain which has fallen causes the ric h earth as deep as is wet to Slip into the river or bottoms &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
we discover in Several places old encampments of large bands of Indians, a fiew weeks past and appear to be makeing up the river—    Those Indians we believe to be the <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfoot</name> Inds. or <name type="native_nation" key="Atsina Indians">Menetares</name> who inhabit the heads of the <name type="place" key="Saskatchewan River">Saskashowin</name> &amp; north of this place and trade a little in the <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="place" key="Fort des Prairies (Canada)">Fort de Prarie</name>
                  </hi> establishments.    we Camped in a grove of Cotton trees on the Stard Side, river rise 1½ In.</p>
               <p>
                  <table rows="8" cols="3">
                     <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Course &amp; Distance May 30th 1805</hi>
                     </head>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">mile</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 70° W</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">   ¼</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">along the timbered bottom on the Stard point opsd. a high<lb/>
Clift</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 50° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">2</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">to a few trees on a Lard point</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 60° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">   ¾</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">to a Stump on the Stard. point opposit a high black bluff</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 70° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">1 ¼</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">on the Stard Side to a fiew willows</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 30° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">1 ¼</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">on the Stard Side to the mouth of a run in a bend.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 55° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rend="underline" rows="1" cols="1">2 ½</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">to a grove of trees in a bend to the Lard Side at the mouth<lb/>
of a run    passed a Small Island on the Stard. Side at 2 miles<lb/>
above which we encamped on the Stard Side</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                           <hi rend="right">miles</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                           <hi rend="double underline">8</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-05-30.03" n="lc.geo.1805-05-30.01">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">May 30th Thursday 1805</hi>.    the rain commenced yesterday evening &amp; continued moderately through the course of the night.    more rain has now fallen than we have experenced Since the 15th of September last, the rain continued this morning, and the wind too high for us to proceed, untill abt. 11 oClock at which time we Set out &amp; proceeded on with great labour we were oblidged to make use of the tow rope &amp; the banks were So muddy &amp; Slippery that the men could Scarsely walk notwithstanding we proceeded as well as we Could, wind hard from the N. W.    in attempting to assend a rapid our toe cord broke of the white perogue, they turned without injury. those rapids are Shallow points &amp; are numerous &amp; difficult one being at the mouth of every dreen. Some little rain at times all day. one man ascended the high country &amp; it was raining &amp; Snowing on those high hills, the day has proved to be raw and cold    back from the river is tollarably level. no timber of any kind on the hills, &amp; only a fiew Scatering trees of cotton willows &amp;.C.    we discover in many places old encampments of large bands of Indians, a fiew weeks past &amp; appear to be makeing up the River. those Indians we believe to be the <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfoot</name> Indians or <name type="native_nation" key="Atsina Indians">Manetare</name> who Inhabit the Country on the heads of the <name type="place" key="Saskatchewan River">Saskashoarr</name> North of this place &amp; trade a litto [little] in the <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="place" key="Fort des Prairies (Canada)">Fort Deprare</name>
                  </hi> establishments.<ref target="n14053006" n="6"/> we Camped in a handsome grove of cotton trees on the Stard. Side. River rise 1½. Came 8 miles to day



</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-05-30.04" n="lc.geo.1805-05-30.01">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Thursday 30th.</hi>    The forenoon was cloudy, with some rain. We did not set out till late in the day. The hills came in close on the river again, but are not so high. Some of them are as black as coal and some white as chalk.<ref target="n14053007" n="7"/> We see a great many fresh Indian tracks or signs as we pass along. It rained a little all day; we went on slow and encamped early on the North side, in a small bottom with some cotton wood, having proceeded on eight miles. There are no pines to be seen on the hills.

</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-05-30.05" n="lc.geo.1805-05-30.01">
            <sp who="jw">
               <speaker>Whitehouse</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Thursday 30th May 1805</hi>.    Cloudy &amp; rain, the wind high from the N. W.    we delayed untill about 10 oC. then Set off, though disagreeable working.    passed white Straight range of Clifts on the S. S.    proceeded on with the towing lines about 5 miles &amp; halted to dine on the N. S.    Some of the hunters Shot an Elk.    cold chilly wind &amp; rain.    passed a Camp wher 29 lodges of the blackfoot Indians had lately been &amp; left piles of mussel Shells at each fire.    Came 8 miles.    Camped at a handsom narrow bottom covered with thin c. wood timber, where 50 or 60 lodges of Indians had lately been Camped.    they were gone as we expect up the river.    they left Several lodge poles &amp; considerable of fire wood gathered.    2 of the hunters went across the river on the hill &amp; killed 2 buffaloe.—</p>
               <p>
Thursday May 30th    This morning we had the weather Cloudy and Rainey; &amp; the wind blowing hard from the North west, We delayed setting off till 10 oClock A. M. the weather still being very disagreeable, &amp; bad to Tow the Crafts; we then proceeded on our Voyage, and passed a white strait range of Clifts, lying on the South side of the River, we proceed still on, towing our Crafts about 5 Miles, when we halted to dine on the North side of the River; One of our hunters Shot an Elk, which was brought to us.—    the weather still continued Cold &amp; Chilly with some rain,—    We set off about 2 o'Clock P. M. from the place that we dined at; and passed an Old Camp of 20 lodges, which the black foot Indians we supposed had lately left.    they had left, piles of Muscle shells, at each fire, We came 8 Miles, and encamped at a handsome Narrow bottom, thinly covered with Cotton wood; where we found 60 lodges, that some Indians had lately left, and we expected had gone up the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">River Mesouri</name>, Those Indians left several lodge poles, and a considerable quantity of fire Wood, which they had gather'd; 2 of our hunters went across the River to a hill, where they killed 2 Buffalo, which they brought to our Campe.—


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n14053001" n="1">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> is testing the relative humidity of the dry air of the High Plains of <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>
(cf. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> remark in the <ref n="1804-09-30-1" type="related">weather data</ref> of September 23, 1804). Large.</note>
            <note xml:id="n14053002" n="2">In <name type="place" key="Chouteau County, Mont.">Chouteau County</name>, <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>, a little above <name type="place" key="Pablo Island">Pablo Island</name> and nearly opposite the
mouth of <name type="place" key="Sheep Shed Coulee (Crevis Creek)">Sheep Shed Coulee</name>. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> maps 41, 52, 53, 60; MRC map 73.</note>
            <note xml:id="n14053003" n="3">Also given on <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 41, in <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> hand.</note>
            <note xml:id="n14053004" n="4">Unnamed on <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> maps 41, 52, 60, and apparently without a modern name.</note>
            <note xml:id="n14053005" n="5">Perhaps <name type="place" key="Sheep Shed Coulee (Crevis Creek)">Sheep Shed Coulee</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n14053006" n="6">
               <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, still copying <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, mentions the <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Atsina Indians">Atsina</name> Indians, the <name type="place" key="Saskatchewan River">Saskatchewan River</name>, and the North West Company post of <name type="place" key="Fort des Prairies (Canada)">Fort des Prairies</name> where the two tribes traded.</note>
            <note xml:id="n14053007" n="7">The party is entering the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, White Cliffs of the">White Cliffs</name> area of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Breaks of the">Missouri River Breaks</name>, <name type="place" key="Chouteau County, Mont.">Chouteau County</name>, <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-05-29" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-05-31" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
