<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-03-27">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
March 27, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 7</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">March 23–June 9, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1991</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">18-22</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">281-282</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">202</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jw">Joseph Whitehouse</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 11</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of Joseph Whitehouse, May 14, 1804–April 2, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1997</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">434-435</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
         <geoDecl datum="WGS" xml:id="lc.geo.1806-03-27.01">
            <placeName/>
            <geo>46 -122.8667</geo>
            <note>Camped in Columbia County, OR, near Goble, roughly opposite to present Kalama, Cowlitz County, WA. Now called Deer Island.</note>
         </geoDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Journal Entries</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic"/>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-09-24</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1806-03-27">March 27, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-03-27.01" n="lc.geo.1806-03-27.01">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Thursday March 27th 1806.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
We set out early this morning and were shortly after joined by some of the <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skillutes</name> who came along side in a small canoe for the purpose of trading roots and fish.    at 10 A. M. we arrived at two houses of this nation on the Stard. side where we halted for breakfast.<ref target="n31032701" n="1"/>    here we overtook our hunters, they had killed nothing.    the natives appeared extreemly hospitable, gave us dryed Anchovies, Sturgeon, wappetoe, quamash, and a speceis of small white tuberous roots about 2 inches in length and as thick as a man's finger;<ref target="n31032702" n="2"/> these are eaten raw, are crisp, milkey, and agreeably flavored.    most of the party were served by the natives with as much as they could eat; they insisted on our remaining all day with them and hunting the Elk and deer which they informed us were very abundant in their neighbourhood.    but as the weather would not permit us to dry our canoes in order to pitch them we declined their friendly invitation, and resumed our voyage at 12 OCk.    the principal village of these <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skillutes</name> reside on the lower side of the <name type="place" key="Cowlitz (Coweliskee) River">Cow-e-lis'-kee river</name>
                  <ref target="n31032703" n="3"/> a few miles from it's entrance into the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">columbia</name>.    these people are said to be numerous.    in their dress, habits, manners and language they differ but little from the <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsops</name>
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinnooks</name> &amp;c.    they have latterly been at war with <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinnooks</name> but peace is said now to be restored between them, but their intercourse is not yet resumed.    no <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinnooks</name> come above the <name type="place" key="Marsh (Seal) Island">marshey islands</name> nor do the <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skillutes</name> visit the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>.    the <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsops</name>, <name type="native_nation" key="Cathlamet Indians">Cathlahmahs</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Wahkiakum Indians">Wackkiacums</name> are the carriers between these nations being in alliance with both.—    The <name type="place" key="Cowlitz (Coweliskee) River">Coweliskee</name> is 150 yards wide, is deep and from indian Information navigable a very considerable distance for canoes.    it discharges itself into the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> about three miles above a remarkable high rocky nole<ref target="n31032704" n="4"/> which is situated on the N. side of the river by which it is washed on the South side and is seperated from the Nothern hills of the river by a wide bottom of several miles to which it is united. I suspect that this river waters the country lying West of the range of mountains<ref target="n31032705" n="5"/> which pass the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">columbia</name> between the <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Cascades (Great Rapids, Great Shute)">great falls and rapids</name>, and north of the same nearly to the low country which commences on the N. W. coast about Latitude [<hi rend="italic">blank</hi>] North.    above the <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skillutes</name> on this river another nation by the name of the <name type="native_nation" key="Cowlitz Indians">Hul-loo-et-tell</name>
                  <ref target="n31032706" n="6"/> reside, who are said also to be numerous.    at the distance of 2 m. above the village at which we breakfasted we passed the entrance of this river; we saw several fishing camps of the <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skillutes</name> on both sides of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>, and were attended all the evening by parties of the natives in their canoes who visited us for the purpose of trading their fish and roots; we purchased as many as we wished on very moderate terms; they seemed perfectly satisfyed with the exchange and behaved themselves in a very orderly manner.    late in the evening we passed our camp of the 5th of November and encamped about 4½ above at the commencement of the bottom land on stard. below <name type="place" key="Deer (E-lal-lar) Island">Deer Island</name>.<ref target="n31032707" n="7"/>    we had scarcely landed before we were visited by a large canoe with eight men; from them we obtained a dryed fruit which resembled the raspburry<ref target="n31032708" n="8"/> and which I beeive to be the fruit of the large leafed thorn frequently mentioned.    it is reather ascid tho' pleasently flavored. I preserved a specemine of this fruit I fear that it has been baked in the process of drying and if so the seed will not vegitate.    saw the Cottonwood, sweet willow,<ref target="n31032709" n="9"/> oak, ash and the broad leafed ash, the growth which resembles the beach<ref target="n31032710" n="10"/> &amp;c.    these form the growth of the bottom lands while the hills are covered almost exclusively with the various species of fir heretofore discribed.    the black Alder<ref target="n31032711" n="11"/> appears as well on some parts of the hills as the bottoms.    before we set out from the <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skillute</name> village we sent on <name type="person" key="Gibson, George">Gibson's</name> canoe and <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyers</name> with orders to proceed as fast as they could to <name type="place" key="Deer (E-lal-lar) Island">Deer island</name> and there to hunt and wait our arrival.    we wish to halt at that place to repair our canoes if possible.    the indians who visited us this evening remained but a short time, they passed the river to the oposite side and encamped.    the night as well as the day proved cold wet and excessively disagreeable.    we came 20 miles today.—
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-03-27.02" n="lc.geo.1806-03-27.01">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Thursday March 27th 1806.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
a rainey disagreeable night    rained the greater part of the night    we Set out this morning verry early and proceeded on to two houses of the <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skil-lute</name> Indians on the South Side here we found our hunters who had Seperated from us last evening.    the wind rose and the rain became very hard Soon after we landed    here we were very friendly receved by the natives who gave all our party as much fish as they Could eate, they also gave us Wappato and pashaquaw roots to eate prepared in their own way.    also a Species of Small white tuberous roots about 2 inches in length and as thick as a mans finger, these are eaten raw, or crips, milkey and agreeably flavoured; the nativs insists on our remaining all day with them and hunt the Elk and deer which they informed us was very abundant in this neighbourhood.    but as the weather would not permit our drying our Canoes in order to pitch them, we declined their friendly invertation, and resumed our voyage at 12 oClock. The principal village of the <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skil-lutes</name>
                  </hi> is Situated on the lower Side of the <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="place" key="Cowlitz (Coweliskee) River">Cow-e-lis kee</name>
                  </hi> river a fiew miles from it's enterance into the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>.    those people are Said to be noumerous, in their dress, habits, manners and Language they differ but little from the <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsops</name>, <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinnooks</name> &amp;c.    they have latterly been at war with the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinnooks</name>, but peace is Said to be now restored between them, but their inter Course is not yet restored.    〈but〉 no <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinnook</name> Come above the <name type="native_nation" key="Wahkiakum Indians">Warkiacums</name>, nor do the <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skillutes</name> visit the Mouth of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>. The <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsops</name>, <name type="native_nation" key="Cathlamet Indians">Cath lahmahs</name> &amp; <name type="native_nation" key="Wahkiakum Indians">War kia coms</name> are the Carriers between those nations being in alliance with both—. The <name type="place" key="Cowlitz (Coweliskee) River">Cow e lis kee</name> river is 150 yards wide, is deep and from Indian information navigable a very conslderable distance for canoes.    it discharges itself into the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> about 3 miles above a remarkable knob which is high and rocky and Situated on the North Side of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>, and Seperated from the Northern hills of the river by a Wide bottom of Several Miles, to which it united. I Suspect that this river Waters the Country lying west of a range of Mountains which passes the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> between the <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Great Falls of the">Great falls</name> and <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Cascades (Great Rapids, Great Shute)">rapids</name>, and North of the Same nearly to the low country which Commences on the N W. Coast about Latitude 4° [<hi rend="italic">blank</hi>]<ref target="n31032712" n="12"/> North.    above the <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skil lutes</name> on this river another nation by the name of the <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Cowlitz Indians">Hul-loo-et-tell</name>
                  </hi> reside who are Said also the be numerous.    at the distance of 2 miles above the village at which we brackfast we passed the enterance of this river; we Saw Several fishing camps of the <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skillutes</name> on both Sides of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>, and also on both Sides of this river.    we were attended all the evening by parties of the nativs in their Canoes who visited us for the purpose of tradeing their fish and roots; we purchased as maney as we wished on very moderate terms; they Seamed perfectly Satisfied with the exchange and behaved themselves in a very orderly manner.    late in the evening we passed the place we Camped the 5th of Novr. and Encamped about 4 miles above at the Commencement of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbian</name> Vally on the Stard. Side below <name type="place" key="Deer (E-lal-lar) Island">Deer Island</name>.    we had Scercily landed before we were visited by a large Canoe with 8 men; from them we obtained a dried fruit which resembled the raspberry and which I beleave is the fruit of the large leafed thorn frequently mentioned.    it is reather ascide tho' pleasently flavored. Saw Cotton wood, Sweet Willow, w[hite] oake, ash and the broad leafed ash the Growth which resembles the bark &amp;c.    these form the groth of the bottom lands, whilst the Hills are almost exclusively Covered with the various Species of fir heretofore discribed.    the black alder appears on Maney parts of the hills Sides as on the bottoms.    before we Set out from the 2 houses where we brackfast we Sent on two Canoes with the best hunters, with orders to pro ceed as fast as they Could to <name type="place" key="Deer (E-lal-lar) Island">Deer island</name> and there to hunt and wait our arrival.    we wish to halt at that place and repare 2 of our Canoes if possible.    the Indians that visited us this evining remained but a Short time, they passed over to an Island and encamped.    the night as well as the day proved Cold wet and excessively disagreeable.    we Came 20 miles in the Course of this day.

</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-03-27.03" n="lc.geo.1806-03-27.01">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Thursday 27th March 1806.    rain commenced this morning and continued thro the day.    we halted at a village of the <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Chilutes nation</name>
                  <ref target="n31032713" n="13"/>    they treated us in a friendly manner    Gave us Some wapa toes &amp; anchoves to eat. Several Indians followed after us with Small canoes.    our officers purchased a large Sturgeon from them    we proceed on to the mo of a River named <name type="place" key="Kalama (Cath-la-haw's) River">Calams River</name> and Camped<ref target="n31032714" n="14"/> on the South Side little above Said River—    Six of our hunters Sent on this afternoon to <name type="place" key="Deer (E-lal-lar) Island">deer Island</name>
                  <ref target="n31032715" n="15"/> with the Small canoes in order to hunt.


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-03-27.04" n="lc.geo.1806-03-27.01">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Thursday 27th.</hi>    There was a cloudy wet morning. We embarked early and went about 6 miles, when we came to a small Indian village,<ref target="n31032716" n="16"/> where the natives received us very kindly. They belong to the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chil-ook</name> nation,<ref target="n31032717" n="17"/> and differ something in their language from the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chin-ooks</name>. We got some Wapto roots and fish from them and then proceeded on, though it rained very hard. Two small canoes went on ahead to <name type="place" key="Deer Island">Deer island</name>, in order to kill some game by the time we should come up. We passed several Indian lodges where the natives<ref target="n31032718" n="18"/> were fishing for sturgeon, and got a large one out of a small canoe; a number of which followed us with 2 Indians in each of them. At night we encamped where we had plenty of good wood, oak and ash.<ref target="n31032719" n="19"/>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-03-27.05" n="lc.geo.1806-03-27.01">
            <sp who="jw">
               <speaker>Whitehouse</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Thursday March 27th    This morning early it commenced raining, which continued during the whole of this day.    At 7 o'clock A. M. we proceeded on, &amp; crossed over to an Island, which lay on the North side of the River, where we halted.    We found on this Island, an Indian Village of the <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Chilutes Tribe</name>
                  <ref target="n31032720" n="20"/> it contained 7 Houses.—    These Indians treated us in a friendly manner.    At 10 o'Clock A. M. we left this Island and continued on &amp; passed several Indian fishing Camps.    A number of Indians followed us with small Canoes.    Our Officers purchased from these Indians a large Sturgeon.    We continued on &amp; passed the Mouth of a River called by the Natives <name type="place" key="Kalama (Cath-la-haw's) River">Calamus</name>,<ref target="n31032721" n="21"/> &amp; encamped on the South side of the River a small distance above the said River.    Our officers sent 6 of our hunters in Canoes to go on a head, to an Island called <name type="place" key="Deer (E-lal-lar) Island">Deer Island</name>, in order to hunt, untill we came up with them—    These hunters left us this afternoon.    We have still hard rain this evening.    We encamped on the South side of the River, where we found plenty of Oak &amp; Ash wood to make our fires with.—

</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n31032701" n="1">In <name type="place" key="Columbia County, Oreg.">Columbia County</name>, <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>, in the vicinity of present <name type="place" key="Rainier, Wash.">Rainier</name>, and opposite present <name type="place" key="Longview, Wash.">Longview</name> and <name type="place" key="Kelso, Wash.">Kelso</name>, <name type="place" key="Cowlitz County, Wash.">Cowlitz County</name>, <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>, on the <name type="place" key="Cowlitz (Coweliskee) River">Cowlitz River</name>. Symbols for the "houses" are shown near the west edge of <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 80.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31032702" n="2">"Quamash" is camas, <hi rend="italic">Camassia quamash</hi> (Pursh) Greene. Hitchcock et al., 1:780–82. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> calls it "pashaquaw" in his entry for this day. The first term comes from <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
               <hi rend="italic">qé'mes,</hi> while the second is <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshone</name>
               <hi rend="italic">pasigoo,</hi> both signifying the camas. See <ref n="1805-09-20" type="related">September 20, 1805</ref>. The identity of the small edible root is unknown.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31032703" n="3">On the upriver trip the captains applied the name <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skillute</name> (variously spelled) to two separate groups. One group was here at the entrance of the <name type="place" key="Cowlitz (Coweliskee) River">Cowlitz ("Cow-e-lis'-kee") River</name>, in <name type="place" key="Cowlitz County, Wash.">Cowlitz County</name>. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> maps 80, 81. The other group they noted on April 16, 1806; see note there. For the <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skillutes</name>, a <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookan</name> people, see <ref n="1805-11-04" type="related">November 4, 1805</ref>, and <ref n="1806-03-25" type="related">March 25, 1806</ref>. "Cow-e-lis'-kee," <hi rend="italic">qawilick-i[x],</hi> "where the <name type="native_nation" key="Cowlitz Indians">Cowlitz</name> (people) are," was evidently borrowed into the Lower Chinook language from <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Salish</name>
               <hi rend="italic">káwlicq,</hi> "language, people of the <name type="place" key="Cowlitz (Coweliskee) River">Cowlitz River</name>." Hajda (SCS), 516. The final "ee" of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> probably represents the Chinookan locative suffix "<hi rend="italic">-i[x]</hi>".</note>
            <note xml:id="n31032704" n="4">
               <name type="place" key="Mount Coffin">Mount Coffin</name>, in <name type="place" key="Cowlitz County, Wash.">Cowlitz County</name>; see <ref n="1805-11-06" type="related">November 6, 1805</ref>. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 80.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31032705" n="5">The <name type="place" key="Cascade Range">Cascade Range</name>. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 79.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31032706" n="6">These people were a group of Salish-speaking <name type="native_nation" key="Cowlitz Indians">Cowlitz</name>. Ray (HCI); Hajda (SOLC), 107. The term is a Chinookan ethnonym, <hi rend="italic">
                  <seg n="uxu803">x̣</seg>luit íl,</hi> "strange country." Silverstein, 545. According to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> they lived on the <name type="place" key="Cowlitz (Coweliskee) River">Cowlitz River</name>, but on <ref n="1806-03-29" type="related">March 29</ref> both an interlineation and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> entry have them living on <name type="place" key="Lewis (Cahwahnakiooks) River">Lewis River</name>. They were identified incorrectly as <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Watlala Chinookans</name> in the <ref n="1805-1806.winter.part2" type="related">Estimate of Western Indians</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31032707" n="7">In <name type="place" key="Columbia County, Oreg.">Columbia County</name>, <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>, in the vicinity of <name type="place" key="Goble, Oreg.">Goble</name>, and roughly opposite present <name type="place" key="Kalama, Wash.">Kalama</name>, <name type="place" key="Cowlitz County, Wash.">Cowlitz County</name>, <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>. <name type="place" key="Deer (E-lal-lar) Island">Deer Island</name>, in <name type="place" key="Columbia County, Oreg.">Columbia County</name>, retains that name today.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31032708" n="8">Probably the party purchased either dried salmonberries or Pacific blackberries. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> believed the berries had come from the shrub he called "large leafed thorn." See <ref n="1806-04-08" type="related">April 8, 1806</ref>, for a discussion of the confusion concerning these species.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31032709" n="9">Probably the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name> willow, although a number of other willow species are possible. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> mentions the sweet willow as an important species in entries of <ref n="1806-04-02" type="related">April 2</ref> and <ref n="1806-04-30" type="related">30</ref>, 1806. The Pacific willow continues to be an important riparian species along the lower <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31032710" n="10">Probably the red, or Oregon, alder, <hi rend="italic">Alnus rubra</hi> Bong. See <ref n="1805-10-30" type="related">October 30, 1805</ref>. Hitchcock et al., 2:74.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31032711" n="11">This alder species is not identifiable with certainty. Apparently, it is a plant separate from "the growth which resembles the beach." It is possible that <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> black alder refers to the red alder, and that the "beach" may refer to the white alder, <hi rend="italic">Alnus rhombifolia</hi> Nutt., which is a riparian species found in the <name type="place" key="Willamette (Multnomah) River">Willamette</name> Valley and along the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name> on the east side of the <name type="place" key="Cascade Range">Cascades</name>. Ibid.; Little (MWH), 13; Franklin &amp; Dyrness, 126.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31032712" n="12">A space perhaps for some latitude between 40° and 50° North.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31032713" n="13">The name is given as <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skillute</name> or a variant in <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>. See <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>
entries for <ref n="1805-11-04" type="related">November 4, 1805</ref>, <ref n="1806-03-25" type="related">March 25</ref> and <ref n="1806-03-27" type="related">27</ref>, and <ref n="1806-04-16" type="related">April 16, 1806</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31032714" n="14">In the vicinity of <name type="place" key="Goble, Oreg.">Goble</name>, <name type="place" key="Columbia County, Oreg.">Columbia County</name>, <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>, with the <name type="place" key="Kalama (Cath-la-haw's) River">Kalama River</name> on the opposite side in <name type="place" key="Cowlitz County, Wash.">Cowlitz County</name>, <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31032715" n="15">Still <name type="place" key="Deer (E-lal-lar) Island">Deer Island</name>, <name type="place" key="Columbia County, Oreg.">Columbia County</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31032716" n="16">A "<name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skillute</name>" village near <name type="place" key="Rainier, Oreg.">Rainier</name>, <name type="place" key="Columbia County, Oreg.">Columbia County</name>, <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>. See the captains' entries 
for <ref n="1806-03-25" type="related">March 25</ref> and 27, 1806.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31032717" n="17">That is, they spoke a Lower Chinookan dialect.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31032718" n="18">More "<name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skillutes</name>"; see above.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31032719" n="19">The oak is probably Oregon white oak and the ash may be Oregon ash.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31032720" n="20">A <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skillute</name> village, say the captains' entries for <ref n="1806-03-25" type="related">March 25</ref> and 27, 1806. The captains say it contained only two houses; the copyist may have misread the numeral in the original. They also place it on the starboard side, near present <name type="place" key="Rainier, Oreg.">Rainier</name>, <name type="place" key="Columbia County, Oreg.">Columbia County</name>, <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>, which is hard to reconcile with <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse's</name> island on the "North side."</note>
            <note xml:id="n31032721" n="21">The <name type="place" key="Kalama (Cath-la-haw's) River">Kalama River</name> in <name type="place" key="Cowlitz County, Wash.">Cowlitz County</name>, <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-03-26" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-03-28" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
