<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-09-01">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
September 1, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 8</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">June 10–September 26, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1987</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">337-344</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">357</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">274-275</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
         <geoDecl datum="WGS" xml:id="lc.geo.1806-09-01.01">
            <placeName/>
            <geo>42.8619 -97.4875</geo>
            <note>Camped in Yankton County, SD, opposite the present Gavins Point Dam.</note>
         </geoDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Journal Entries</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic"/>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-12-21</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1806-09-01">September 1, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-09-01.01" n="lc.geo.1806-09-01.01">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Monday 1st of September 1806</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
Musquitors very troublesom last night, we set out at the usial hour and had not proceeded on far before the fog became So thick that we were oblige to come too and delay half an hour for the fog to pass off which it did in Some measure and we again proceded on    <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">R.</name>
                  <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Jo. Fields</name> and <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name> landed on an <name type="place" key="Pawnee (Ponceras) Island">Ponceras Island</name>
                  <ref target="n40090101" n="1"/> to try to kill Some deer which was Seen on the beech and the 〈remainder of the〉 Canoes all passed them at 9 A. M we passed the enterance of <name type="place" key="Niobrara (Quicurre, Rapid) River">River <hi rend="italic">Quiequur</hi>
                  </name>
                  <ref target="n40090102" n="2"/> which had the Same appearance it had when we passed up water rapid and of a milky white Colour    about two miles below the <name type="place" key="Niobrara (Quicurre, Rapid) River">Quicurre</name>, 9 Indians ran down the bank and beckened to us to land, they appeared to be a war party, and I took them to be <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Tetons</name> and paid no kind of attention to them further than an enquirey to what tribe they belonged, they did not give me any answer, I prosume they did not understand the man who Spoke to them as he Spoke but little of their language.    as one Canoe was yet behind we landed in an open Commanding Situation<ref target="n40090103" n="3"/> out of Sight of the indians deturmined to delay untill they Came up.    about 15 minits after we had landed Several guns were fired by the indians, which we expected was at the three men behind. I calld out 15 men and ran up with a fill deturmination to Cover them if possible let the number of the indians be what they might. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt Lewis</name> hobled up on the bank and formed the remainder of the party in a Situation well calculated to defend themselves and the Canoes &amp;c.    when I had proceeded to the point about 250 yards I discovered the Canoe about 1 mile above &amp; the indians where we had left them. I then walked on the Sand beech and the indians came down to meet me    I gave them my hand and enquired of them what they were Shooting at, they informed me that they were Shooting off their guns at an old Keg which we had thrown out of one of the Canoes and was floating down.    those Indians informed me they were <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Yankton">Yanktons</name>,<ref target="n40090104" n="4"/> one of the men with me knew one of the Indians to be the brother of <name type="person" key="Dorion, Pierre, Jr.">young Durion's</name>
                  <name type="person" key="Holy Rainbow">wife</name>.<ref target="n40090105" n="5"/>    finding those indians to be <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Yankton">Yanktons</name> I invited them down to the boats to Smoke.    when we arived at the canoes they all eagerly Saluted the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> Chief, and we all Set and Smoked Several pipes. I told them that we took them to be a party of <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Tetons</name> and the fireing I expected was at the three men in the rear Canoe and I had went up with a full intention to kill them all if they had been <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">tetons</name> &amp; fired on the Canoe as we first expected, but finding them <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Yankton">Yanktons</name> and good men we were glad to See them and take them by the hand as faithfull Children who had opened their ears to our Councils.    one of them Spoke and Said that their nation had opened their years, &amp; done as we had directed them ever Since we gave the Meadel to their great Chief, and Should Continue to do as we had told them we enquired if any of their Chiefs had gone down with <name type="person" key="Dorion, Pierre, Sr.">Mr. Durion</name>,<ref target="n40090106" n="6"/> the answered that their great Chief and many of their brave men had gone down, that the white people had built a house near the <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Mahar</name> village where they traded.<ref target="n40090107" n="7"/>    we tied a piec of ribon to each mans hair and gave them Some Corn of which they appeared much pleased. The <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> Cheif gave a par of elegant Legins to the principal man of the indian party, which is an indian fashion. [<hi rend="italic">NB: to make presents</hi>]<ref target="n40090108" n="8"/>    the Canoe &amp; 3 men haveing joined us we took our leave of this party telling them to return to their band and listen to our councils which we had before given to them. Their band of 80 Lodges were on <name type="place" key="Emanuel (Plum) Creek">plum Creek</name>
                  <ref target="n40090109" n="9"/> a fiew miles to north.    those nine men had five fusees and 4 bows &amp; quivers of arrows.    at 2 P. M we came too on the upper point of <name type="place" key="Bon Homme (Good Man's) Island">bon homme</name>
                  <ref target="n40090110" n="10"/> opposit the antient fortification and Sent out men to hunt on each Side and on the island.    and the canoes on each Side of the island to receive any meat might be killed    I walked on the N. E. main Shore found the bottom rich and thickly covered with Peavine rich weed<ref target="n40090111" n="11"/> grass interwoven in Such a manner with grape vines that I could not get through and was obliged to assend a high plains the passing through which I also found tiresom.    the grass was nearly as high as my head and the musquitors excessively bad.    at the lower point of the Island all the Canoes &amp; hunters Came together. <name type="person" key="Labiche, François">Labeech</name> killed an Elk only the flesh of which was brought on in the perogue.    at this island we brought 2 years together or on the 1st of Septr. 1804<ref target="n40090112" n="12"/> we Encamped at the lower point of this Island.    after we all Came together we again proceeded on down to a large Sand bar imediately opposit to the place were we met the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Yankton">Yanktons</name> in Council at the <name type="place" key="Calumet Bluff (Nebr.)">Calumet Bluffs</name> and which place we left on the 1t of Septr. 1804. I observed our old flag Staff or pole Standing as we left it.    the musquitors excessively troublesom untill about 10 P. M. when the S W wind became Strong and blew the most of them off.    we came <hi rend="italic">52</hi> miles to day only with a head wind.    the Country on either Side are butifull and the plains much richer below the <name type="place" key="Niobrara (Quicurre, Rapid) River">Queiquer river</name> than above the river.—
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-09-01.02" n="lc.geo.1806-09-01.01">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>[<hi rend="italic">undated, ca. September 1, 1806</hi>]<ref target="n40090113" n="13"/>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
No. 1.—    a wall of the Antient brook Commincing on the bank of the River and running on a direct line S. 76° W. 96 yard, about 75 feet baece and 8 feet high</p>
               <p>
2.—    Wall Continued and Course S. 84° W. 53 yards from an angle formed by a Slopeing decent No. 13.    has the appearance of a hornwork of nearly the Same hight of the former Angle No. 1—</p>
               <p>
3.—    the Wall Continued on a Course N. 69° W. for 300 yards in which there is a low part of the wall which is Covered by two Circular and lower walls one back of the other.    8 8    which Covers the gate way Completely, between those outer walls 8 8.    there appears to 〈be〉 have been a Covered way out of the Main work into the Vacaney between those two walls No. 9.—    This wall No. 2 is 8 feet high and about 75 feet Bace</p>
               <p>
4.—    a wide port of the wall wich is about 12 feet high and 105 feet base on 〈a〉 the Course Continued N. 69° W. 〈for 56 yards〉 from the gateway</p>
               <p>
5.—    The Wall about 15 feet high and about 90 feet bace on a course N. 32° W. for 56 yds.</p>
               <p>
6.—    the Wall Continus on a Course N. 20° W for 73 yards and ends abruptly near a whole near Several mounds prismiscutly in the Gorge of the work between this and the river</p>
               <p>
10. N. 32° W. 96 yards across a low place much lower than the Common leavel of the plain to the Commencement of a Wall of 8 feet high— this is an open Space from whence there is Some appearance of a Covered way to the Water</p>
               <p>
10    is a large hollow place much lower then the plain</p>
               <p>
12 12.—    Several little mounds in the gouge</p>
               <p>
7.    the gateway to the Strong work</p>
               <p>
14.—    a redoubt Situated on an Island    Which makeing on the Side next to the main work, the wall forming this reboubt is 6 feet high</p>
               <p>
15 15.—    The river banks at the waters edge</p>
               <p>
16.—    a thick wall of about 6 feet high passing from the Rivers edge at the gouge of the work perfectly Strieght 〈and ? self〉 to the bend of the River above and there ends abruptly where the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> is under mineing its banks— on this wall maney large Cotton Trees of two &amp; 3 feet 〈thi〉 diamieter    this Bank passed thro a wood in it's whole Couse</p>
               <p>
No. 17 19.—    a Streaght wall of 1830 yard extending from the Gorge of the Strong work on a Course N. 80° W. This wall is 8 feet high to a round pon (No. 18)    from then it becoms lower and Strikes the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> at a place where that river has the aptr. of haveing incroached on its banks for a great distance.    this wall passes in it's whole Course thro a leavel plain.</p>
               <p>
18.—    a Deep pond of 73 yards diamieter in the Wall, perfectly round</p>
               <p>
20—    This from the extremity of one wall to the other 1100 yards.</p>
               <p>
21—    a Small redoubt on the bank of the river</p>
               <p>
The Strong part of this work which must be about ⅔ of it's original Size Contains Twenty acres.—</p>
               <p>
The part Contained between the two walls is about 500 acres and it Certain that those walls have been longer and must have contained a much greater space—

</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-09-01.03" n="lc.geo.1806-09-01.01">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Monday the 1st day of September 1806.    a fair morning.    we Set out eairly and procd. on    two hunters<ref target="n40090114" n="14"/> went on with a Small canoe to hunt    
about 9 A. M. we passd. the mo. of <name type="place" key="Niobrara (Quicurre, Rapid) River">rapid water river</name>
                  <ref target="n40090115" n="15"/>    a Short distance below we Saw nine Indians on the N. Shore which run out of a thicket    five of them had guns the others bows &amp; arrows.    they Signd. to us to put to shore but we floated a short distance below a point at an open place as we expected they were the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Tetons</name>    as Soon as we halted we heard Several guns fire    we expecting that the Indians were fireing at our hunters who were behind <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name> Instantly run up with 10 men but soon returned with the Indians and found that they had been fireing at a kegg we had thrown out above and our hunters came up Safe.    we found these to be <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Yankton">Yanktons</name> Nation &amp; good Indians and friends to us    our officers Smoaked with them and gave them a bushel of corn &amp; Some ribben and then we procd. on    towards evening we killed a fat Elk on an Island.    in the evening we Camped on a Sand beach N. Side    opposite to this Camp we Counceled with the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Yankton">yanktons</name> or <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">babruleys</name>
                  <ref target="n40090116" n="16"/> on the last of August 1804. Some Musquetoes this evening.


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-09-01.04" n="lc.geo.1806-09-01.01">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Monday 1st Sept.</hi> 1806.    This was a fine pleasant day and we set out early, and about 10 o'clock met nine of the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Yankton">Yonktin</name> band of the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name> nation of Indians<ref target="n40090117" n="17"/> on the south side of the river. We halted and gave them some corn, and then proceeded on with an unfavourable wind. At night we arrived at our encampment of the 31st of August 1804, where we held a treaty with a band of the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name> nation, and encamped for the night.



</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n40090101" n="1">Between <name type="place" key="Bon Homme County, S. Dak.">Bon Homme County</name>, <name type="place" key="South Dakota">South Dakota</name>, and <name type="place" key="Knox County, Nebr.">Knox County</name>, <name type="place" key="Nebraska">Nebraska</name>, at the mouth of <name type="place" key="Ponca (Pania, Poncar) Creek">Ponca Creek</name> in <name type="place" key="Nebraska">Nebraska</name>; "<name type="place" key="Pawnee (Ponceras) Island">Poncar I.</name>" on <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 19, evidently the later <name type="place" key="Pawnee (Ponceras) Island">Pawnee Island</name>. They first passed it on <ref n="1804-09-05" type="related">September 5, 1804</ref>. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 19; MRC map 32.</note>
            <note xml:id="n40090102" n="2">The <name type="place" key="Niobrara (Quicurre, Rapid) River">Niobrara River</name>, which joins the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> in <name type="place" key="Knox County, Nebr.">Knox County</name>, first passed on <ref n="1804-09-04" type="related">September 4, 1804</ref>. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 19; MRC map 32.</note>
            <note xml:id="n40090103" n="3">Apparently this was on the <name type="place" key="Bon Homme County, S. Dak.">Bon Homme County</name> side, since the village of the Indians (see below) was on <name type="place" key="Emanuel (Plum) Creek">Emanual Creek</name>. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 19; MRC maps 31, 32.</note>
            <note xml:id="n40090104" n="4">For the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Yankton">Yanktons</name>, see <ref n="1804-08-28" type="related">August 28</ref>–<ref n="1804-08-31" type="related">31</ref>, 1804.</note>
            <note xml:id="n40090105" n="5">"<name type="person" key="Dorion, Pierre, Jr.">Young Durion</name>" was probably <name type="person" key="Dorion, Pierre, Jr.">Pierre Dorion, Jr.</name>; see <ref n="1804-08-29" type="related">August 29, 1804</ref>. His wife among the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Yankton">Yanktons</name> was named <name type="person" key="Holy Rainbow">Holy Rainbow</name>; she was apparently not the same woman who was the only survivor of an 1812 massacre of Astorians on the <name type="place" key="Boise River">Boise River</name> in <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>, in which <name type="person" key="Dorion, Pierre, Jr.">Pierre</name> died. Speck, 165, 183–85; Irving (Astor), 446–48; Munnick (PD).</note>
            <note xml:id="n40090106" n="6">
               <name type="person" key="Dorion, Pierre, Sr.">Pierre Dorion, Sr.</name>; see <ref n="1804-06-12" type="related">June 12, 1804</ref>. For his assignment to conduct the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Yankton">Yankton</name> delegation to <name type="place" key="Washington D.C.">Washington</name>, see <ref n="1804-08-31" type="related">August 31, 1804</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n40090107" n="7">Presumably the <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Omaha</name> village near <name type="place" key="Homer, Nebr.">Homer</name>, in <name type="place" key="Dakota County, Nebr.">Dakota County</name>, <name type="place" key="Nebraska">Nebraska</name>; see <ref n="1804-08-13" type="related">August 13, 1804</ref>. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 16.</note>
            <note xml:id="n40090108" n="8">
               <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name> added underlining in red ink to "par of elegant Legins . . . of the indian."</note>
            <note xml:id="n40090109" n="9">
               <name type="place" key="Emanuel (Plum) Creek">Emanuel Creek</name> in <name type="place" key="Bon Homme County, S. Dak.">Bon Homme County</name>, near present <name type="place" key="Springfield, S. Dak.">Springfield</name>, first passed on <ref n="1804-09-03" type="related">September 3, 1804</ref>. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> maps 7, 19; MRC map 31.</note>
            <note xml:id="n40090110" n="10">
               <name type="place" key="Bon Homme (Good Man's) Island">Bon Homme Island</name>, now inundated by <name type="place" key="Lewis and Clark Lake">Lewis and Clark Lake</name>, was between <name type="place" key="Bon Homme County, S. Dak.">Bon Homme County</name> and <name type="place" key="Knox County, Nebr.">Knox County</name>. The party first reached it on <ref n="1804-09-01" type="related">September 1, 1804</ref>. The "antient fortification" consisted of natural sand ridges which <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> sketched and described on <ref n="1804-09-02" type="related">September 2, 1804</ref>. On this date, September 1, 1806, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> again made sketches (figs. 7, 8) and descriptive notes on pp. 81–85 of Codex N. The notes are included as the second entry for this date. Another drawing of the areas appears in the Estimate of Western Indians (fig. 9) and may have been inserted there at about this time.</note>
            <note xml:id="n40090111" n="11">Peavine is probably hog peanut, <hi rend="italic">Amphicarpa bracteata</hi> (L.) Fern., and richweed is <hi rend="italic">Pilea pumila</hi> (L.) Gray.</note>
            <note xml:id="n40090112" n="12">On <ref n="1804-08-28" type="related">August 28</ref>–<ref n="1804-09-01" type="related">September 1, 1804</ref>, they had camped at the <name type="place" key="Calumet Bluff (Nebr.)">Calumet Bluff</name> in <name type="place" key="Cedar County, Nebr.">Cedar County</name>, <name type="place" key="Nebraska">Nebraska</name>, just below the present <name type="place" key="Gavins Point Dam">Gavins Point Dam</name>, and had counciled with the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Yankton">Yanktons</name>. Now they camped opposite in <name type="place" key="Yankton County, S. Dak.">Yankton County</name>, <name type="place" key="South Dakota">South Dakota</name>. Mattison (GP), 53–55; <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 18; MRC map 30.</note>
            <note xml:id="n40090113" n="13">These notes accompany <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> drawings of the "fortification" on <name type="place" key="Bon Homme (Good Man's) Island">Bon Homme Island</name> in Codex N (figs. 7, 8); see previous notes.</note>
            <note xml:id="n40090114" n="14">Perhaps three men, the <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph and Reubin">Field brothers</name> and <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name>, according to <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n40090115" n="15">The <name type="place" key="Niobrara (Quicurre, Rapid) River">Niobrara River</name> joins the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> in <name type="place" key="Knox County, Nebr.">Knox County</name>, <name type="place" key="Nebraska">Nebraska</name>; the party first passed
it on <ref n="1804-09-04" type="related">September 4, 1804</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n40090116" n="16">
               <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> means <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">Bois Brulé Sioux</name>; see <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> entry of <ref n="1804-08-28" type="related">August 28</ref> and <ref n="1804-09-24" type="related">September 24, 1804</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n40090117" n="17">
               <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Yankton">Yankton Sioux</name>; see <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> entries of <ref n="1804-08-28" type="related">August 28</ref>–<ref n="1804-08-31" type="related">31</ref>, 1804. <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name> here passes over some tense moments for the party, described in some detail by <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> and <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-08-31-1" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-09-02" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
