<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.sup.lavender.01.04">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Way to the Western Sea</title>
            <title type="sub">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> across the Continent</title>
            <title type="sub" level="a">Chapter 4</title>
            <author>David Lavender</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2005</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Way to the Western Sea</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">Chapter 4</title>
               <author>David Lavender</author>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>2001</date>
               <idno type="ISBN">0-8032-8003-3</idno>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Supplements</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Texts</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic"/>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-11-09</date>
            <date>2005-04-20</date>
            <name>Becky Potter</name>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Split into chapters Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="four" type="chapter">
            <head rend="center">FOUR. Trial Run</head>
            <div type="section">
               <p>
The agreement whereby the United States obtained "the Colony or Province of <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name>, with the same extent that it now has in the hands of <name type="place" key="Spain">Spain</name>," was completed on April 30, 1803. Since mail took, on the average, six weeks to travel from <name type="place" key="Paris">Paris</name> to <name type="place" key="Washington D. C.">Washington</name>, the first unofficial word of the transfer presumably reached the White House about the middle of June. Its arithmetic was startling. <name type="person" key="Livingston, Robert">Livingston</name> and <name type="person" key="Monroe, James">Monroe</name> had whittled <name type="person" key="Bonaparte, Napoleon">Napoleon's</name> asking price down from 120 million francs to 80 million—60 for the territory itself plus another 20 million to be paid by the U.S. Treasury to American citizens who held claims against <name type="place" key="France">France</name> for damages incurred during the undeclared naval war of 1798–1800.</p>
               <p>
This amounted, in U.S. money, to about $11,250,000 for <name type="person" key="Bonaparte, Napoleon">Napoleon</name> and $3,750,000 in claims. Total, $15 million, in round figures, for roughly 828,000 square miles—or a little under 3 cents an acre. During the same period the U.S. Land Office was selling off the public domain to settlers and speculators for $2 per acre. (There are 640 acres in one square mile.) So it was a dazzling bargain. Even counting interest payments on the bonds issued to <name type="person" key="Bonaparte, Napoleon">Napoleon</name> in payment for the territory, the full cost for doubling the size of the nation came to only $23,213,567.73.<ref target="n0401" n="1"/>
               </p>
               <p>
The extraordinary value of the purchase was, of course, scarcely glimpsed at the time. The Federalists, <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> correctly surmised, would argue strenuously that <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name> was not worth the price. To cast ahead: one disgruntled New Englander complained that $15 million was the equivalent of 433 tons of solid silver; a wagon train capable of moving the mass would stretch out 5⅓ miles. <name type="person" key="Otis, Harrison Gray">Senator Harrison Gray Otis</name> of <name type="place" key="Massachusetts">Massachusetts</name> brayed, "I would rather the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name> were a running stream of burning lava, over which no human being could pass, than that the treaty should be ratified."<ref target="n0402" n="2"/>
               </p>
               <p>
More prescient Northeasterners pointed out that the acquisition could be divided into so many states that political power would shift west and south, to the detriment of the <name type="place" key="Atlantic Ocean">Atlantic</name> seaboard. Of more import to <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, a strict Constitutional constructionist, was the argument that the Constitution nowhere provided for the purchase of foreign territory or its incorporation into the body of the union. Finally, there was <name type="place" key="Spain">Spain</name>, concerned not with the monetary value of the province, but with the loss of a buffer against avaricious Americans. Predictably, the Spanish minister, <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name> one-time friend, the <name type="person" key="Yrujo, Marqués de Casa">Marqués de Casa Yrujo</name>, reiterated over and over that the transfer was illegal: <name type="person" key="Bonaparte, Napoleon">Napoleon</name> had promised not to let any part of <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name> fall into American hands.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> sought for and found rebuttals to the contentions. A main part of his political base was in the West and South, and he did not grieve over the New Englanders' discomfiture. <name type="person" key="Yrujo, Marqués de Casa">Yrujo</name> was brushed aside with the retort that agreements made between <name type="place" key="France">France</name> and <name type="place" key="Spain">Spain</name> were of no concern to the United States. (Nevertheless, the possibility that resistance to the transfer might boil up in <name type="place" key="New Orleans, La.">New Orleans</name> led the administration to ask the governors of 
<name type="place" key="Mississippi">Mississippi</name>, <name type="place" key="Tennessee">Tennessee</name>, <name type="place" key="Kentucky">Kentucky</name>, and <name type="place" key="Ohio">Ohio</name> to have their militia ready if need be.)<ref target="n0403" n="3"/> Meanwhile <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name> cabinet talked away his worries about the Constitution: the right to govern a territory surely implied the right to acquire it, and <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> was pragmatic enough not to let philosophic scruples prevent him from securing for the nation a good that might never again be attainable.<ref target="n0404" n="4"/> As for value, he was personally convinced that the West would eventually be peopled by Americans devoted to his style of agrarian democracy. Yet he wanted to justify the purchase by pointing to a more immediate gain. One notion that occurred to him was the possibility of using Louisiana to help solve the stubborn Indian problem in the region north of the <name type="place" key="Ohio River">Ohio River</name> and east of the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name>.</p>
               <p>
The Indians there still held title to hundreds of thousands of acres that white tillers of the soil were eyeing with increasing covetousness. He had hoped that once the Native Americans had learned agriculture and such handicrafts as weaving and sewing, they would realize they did not need great expanses of hunting grounds and would be willing to cede part of it, at a fair price, to the nation. Not all the red men were willing to abandon their old ways, however, and they exerted enough influence on the rest to block the signing of the necessary treaties. <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name> might end this impasse. Let the Indians who wanted to retain their hunting culture swap Eastern lands for others beyond the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name>. <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> grew so enthralled with the notion that he envisioned the northern reaches of <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name> as a huge reservation protected from white trespassers by an Indian cavalry patrolling the west bank of the great river. In short, get the East solidly settled first, with both red and white families, and then slowly duplicate the program west of the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name> in a wilderness so extensive he thought it could not be filled for centuries.<ref target="n0405" n="5"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Before the program could be initiated, all whites—French, Spanish, and Americans—currently living in <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> and other towns and farms of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> country would have to be persuaded to vacate their homes and find, with government aid, new dwellings east of the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name>. Examining the feasibility of this exchange became yet another chore the president heaped, on the spur of the moment, onto the already overburdened shoulders of 
<name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name>—overburdened because what had begun as a reconnaissance had abruptly ballooned into a diplomatic mission charged with carrying word of the shift in sovereignty to every Indian tribe and foreign trader within reach from the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri River</name>.</p>
               <p>
As the president and his secretary grew aware of the expedition's increased significance, they reexamined the paragraph in <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> instructions that directed him to appoint a possible successor from his party's ranks, after it was already on the march. Reports from recruiting officers indicated that there might not be anyone among the volunteers qualified for leadership. Would it not be wise to select a suitable second-in-command before the 
group set out?</p>
               <p>
Whether <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> or <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> first proposed <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark</name> cannot be said with certainty. They both knew him. He was the sixth son and ninth child of a family of ten children.<ref target="n0406" n="6"/>
                  <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clarks</name> had long farmed and soldiered in <name type="place" key="Virginia">Virginia</name>, part of the time in <name type="place" key="Albemarle County, Va.">Albemarle County</name>, home of both <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name> and <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> progenitors. Before <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William's</name> birth, however, his family had moved close to tidewater on the <name type="place" key="Rappahannock River">Rappahannock River</name>. Red-headed <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark</name> was born there on August 1, 1770, which made him four years and two and a half weeks older than <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name>.</p>
               <p>
Five of the <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> boys fought in the Revolution. The one best remembered now was <name type="person" key="Clark, George Rogers">George Rogers Clark</name>, who commanded <name type="place" key="Virginia">Virginia's</name> troops in the <name type="place" key="Kentucky">Kentucky</name> region while <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Thomas Jefferson</name> was serving as <name type="place" key="Virginia">Virginia's</name> governor. In 1784, after the war was over, the entire <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> family crossed the <name type="place" key="Allegheny Mountains">Allegheny Mountains</name> and floated down the <name type="place" key="Ohio River">Ohio</name> to <name type="place" key="Mulberry Hill">Mulberry Hill</name>, just outside of <name type="place" key="Louisville, Ky.">Louisville</name>. During and after the migration a strong bond developed between <name type="person" key="Clark, George Rogers">George Rogers</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William</name>, with the older training the younger meticulously in natural history and wilderness skills but failing signally to do much about his grammar and spelling.</p>
               <p>
In 1789, aged nineteen, six feet tall, and heavily muscled, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William</name> joined the <name type="place" key="Kentucky">Kentucky</name> militia. Afterwards he transferred to the regular army. It was a strenuous time. As a lieutenant he drilled his men hard, and learned how to build forts, draw maps, lead pack trains through enemy country, and fight the Indians on their ground. Twice he was sent on secret missions to spy on the Spanish, who during the first half of the 1790s were pushing their 
fortifications and wooing the Indians as high up the east bank of the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name> as they dared go. On his return from the last of these missions, in November 1795, Lieutenant <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> was put in charge of a select company of riflemen at <name type="place" key="Fort Greenville, Ohio">Fort Greenville</name>, <name type="place" key="Ohio">Ohio</name>. Shortly thereafter, Ensign <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name>, fresh from the lackluster contention known as the Whiskey Rebellion, joined the group.</p>
               <p>
The two learned to respect each other while keeping their blue-ribbon company smartly drilled. During off-hours they undoubtedly went hunting together and, as dark closed in, swapped stories, revealed ambitions, and on occasion perhaps drank too much in the officers' quarters. But not for long. Peace, boredom, ill health, and his brother <name type="person" key="Clark, George Rogers">George's</name> losing struggles with alcohol and debt led <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William</name> to resign his commission and rejoin his brother at <name type="place" key="Clarksville, Ind.">Clarksville</name>, <name type="place" key="Indiana">Indiana</name>, just across the river from <name type="place" key="Louisville, Ky.">Louisville</name>.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and he kept their contact alive by occasional letters and rare visits while <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether</name> was still serving in the <name type="place" key="Ohio River">Ohio</name> country and later in <name type="place" key="Washington D. C.">Washington</name> when <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> dropped by on family business. On one of those visits the Westerner was introduced by Secretary <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> to <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">President Jefferson</name>. Surely, too, the president remembered receiving, on January 7, 1803, a letter from doughty old <name type="person" key="Clark, George Rogers">George Rogers Clark</name>, answering certain military questions. 
On closing, <name type="person" key="Clark, George Rogers">George</name> recommended voting <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William</name> as "well quallified almost for any business of Honor and profit in this [Western] country. . . . I am sure it gives you pleasure to have it in your power to do me a Service . . ."—a remark certain to remind the president of how shamefully the state of <name type="place" key="Virginia">Virginia</name> had treated <name type="person" key="Clark, George Rogers">George Rogers</name> 
by refusing to honor drafts he had signed during the Revolution. So five months later, when the question of a second-in-command arose, the name <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark</name> was close to both men's tongues.</p>
               <p>
Whatever the details, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> did make an offer to <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> on June 19. The letter's structure is worth noting.<ref target="n0407" n="7"/> After touching first on a personal business matter, he threw out a hook to keep <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> reading: what follows is secret. Congress had sanctioned the exploration of North America, and the president had entrusted him, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name>, with the enterprise. "I have the most ample and hearty support the government can give," plus "liberal passports from the Ministers both of <name type="place" key="France">France</name> and <name type="place" key="England">England</name>." (Nothing about <name type="place" key="Spain">Spain</name>.) He outlined his personnel needs and urged <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> to keep an eye open for likely recruits. He summarized his travel plans—"I do not calculate on geting further than two or three hundred miles up the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missourie</name> before the commencement of the ensuing winter." He mentioned, again with adjurations of greatest secrecy, the expectation that the United States would obtain the entire western watershed of the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name>, including the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, "in less than 12 Months from this date." It was vital, therefore, to achieve "an early friendly and intimate acquaintance with the tribes that inhabit that country, that they should be early impressed with a just idea of the rising importance of the U. States." Scientific goals, he added, were also involved.</p>
               <p>
And then, having presumably excited <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> with envy over the great good fortune that had befallen him, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> came to the point. "If therefore there is anything . . . in this enterprise, which would induce you to participate with me in it's fatiegues, it's dangers and it's honors, believe me there is no man on earth with whom I should feel equal pleasure in sharing them as with yourself." He meant sharing in its fullest sense. The president, he wrote, promised <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> a permanent commission as captain, with all the benefits that went with the rank. "Your situation will in all respects be precisely such as my own."</p>
               <p>
The guarantee was <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> way of handling a ticklish situation. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> was his friend. Lieutenant <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had also been his commanding officer at <name type="place" key="Fort Greenville (Ohio)">Fort Greenville</name> on the <name type="place" key="Ohio River">Ohio</name> seven years earlier. It would be awkward for both if <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> suddenly became his superior during a long journey with a small group of enlisted men who would be quick to notice each nuance of feeling, however small, between the commanders. To obviate the friction before it developed, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> won <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name> promise to jump <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> a full rank above the one he had held on leaving the army. Precise equality—if <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> accepted. He might not. Therefore, when <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> issued <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> his final draft of instructions on June 20, he let stand the provision about choosing a second-in-command from among the enlisted men.<ref target="n0408" n="8"/> As a matter of collateral interest, it is clear from the president's later letters to the expeditionary force that he never really considered <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> to be <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> military equal. This expedition, which he had conceived and put into motion, stayed <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> in the president's mind. Just as clearly, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> himself never felt the least superiority.</p>
               <p>
The offer made, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> asked <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> to reply to him at <name type="place" key="Pittsburgh, Pa.">Pittsburgh</name>, where a specially built keelboat would be waiting. Using seven or eight soldiers being transferred to the South as crewmen, he would float downstream to the Falls of <name type="place" key="Ohio River">the Ohio</name>, between <name type="place" key="Louisville, Ky.">Louisville</name> and <name type="place" key="Clarksville, Ind.">Clarksville</name>. There he would pick up <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> and whatever recruits for the Northwest his new co-captain had enlisted. He expected to arrive early in August.</p>
               <p>
On May 30, the <name type="place" key="Boston, Mass.">Boston</name> newspapers broke the story of the Louisiana Purchase. The <hi rend="italic">National Intelligencer</hi> of <name type="place" key="Washington D. C.">Washington</name> followed on July 4, giving a special fillip to that holiday. But newspapers weren't treaties, and until <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> held the actual documents in his hands he was not going to move openly. When <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> left <name type="place" key="Washington D. C.">Washington</name> on July 5, there was no fanfare, and he still acted as if he were bound for the upper <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name> with no more than the dozen men authorized by Secretary of War <name type="person" key="Dearborn, Henry">Dearborn</name> on July 2. But there was another order, also dated July 2, wherein the secretary directed the commanders at <name type="place" key="Fort Kaskaskia (Ill.)">Fort Kaskaskia</name>, <name type="place" key="Illinois">Illinois</name>, "to furnish a Sergeant and Eight good men who understand rowing" to haul some of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> provisions as high up the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> as they could go and still return before the onset of ice.<ref target="n0409" n="9"/> This authorization of an additional boat, even if it went only partway to the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>, is the first concrete sign that the administration was beginning to realize that <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> assignment was going to demand more muscle than the small reconnaissance party first contemplated could produce.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> long road West led him first to <name type="place" key="Harpers Ferry, W. Va.">Harpers Ferry</name>—and a good thing it did. The teamster who was supposed to pick up the iron boat frame, new-model rifles, knives, tomahawks, and other material waiting there had failed to do so. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> had to spend two days finding substitute transportation. But there was compensation. During the wait he tested the rifles. They performed beautifully, and he was relaxed as he rode on to <name type="place" key="Pittsburgh, Pa.">Pittsburgh</name>—two hundred and fifty miles in six and a half days, his new, 150-pound, black Newfoundland dog, <name type="person" key="Seaman">Seaman</name>, trotting beside his horse.<ref target="n0410" n="10"/>
               </p>
               <p>
He approached the town in high anticipation, for <name type="place" key="Pittsburgh, Pa.">Pittsburgh</name> was, in a very real sense, the true start of his journey of exploration. Here the supplies he had ordered in the East would be brought together for embarkation. Here, if he was lucky, he might pick up two or three enlisted men who met the exacting qualifications he had in mind—young, unmarried, enduring men, powerfully muscled for the work of pushing the keelboat upstream with 
oars, setting poles, and tow rope.</p>
               <p>
Much depended on that keelboat. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> had sent his order to <name type="place" key="Pittsburgh, Pa.">Pittsburgh</name>—the name of the contractor does not appear in the records—as soon as he had decided not to make <name type="place" key="South West Point, Tenn.">South West Point</name>, <name type="place" key="Tennessee">Tennessee</name>, his jumping-off place, and he expected the boat to be all but ready for loading when he reached the headwaters of the <name type="place" key="Ohio River">Ohio</name>. There is some evidence that he had even specified two masts, a highly unusual feature for a keelboat<ref target="n0411" n="11"/>—just as the iron boat he had ordered at <name type="place" key="Harpers Ferry, W. Va.">Harpers Ferry</name> was unusual in its way. Otherwise the boat was standard: fifty-five feet long, eight feet, four inches wide. A high cabin in the stern would house some of the men and some of the goods. Another covered hold filled the bow. The rowers would occupy the open space amidships.</p>
               <p>
After finding his lodgings about 2:00 <hi rend="smallcaps">P.M.</hi> on July 15, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> dashed off a note to <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> and wandered off in search of <name type="person" key="Hooke, Moses">Lieutenant Moses Hooke</name>, who, as assistant military agent for supplies, was to receive the material from the East and oversee its transfer to the keelboat. A good man, young <name type="person" key="Hooke, Moses">Hooke</name>. He was a member of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> own regiment, the First Infantry, and the two had grown friendly during <name type="person" key="Hooke, Moses">Hooke's</name> recent tour of duty in <name type="place" key="Washington D. C.">Washington</name>. Quite likely he was the one who told <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> that the keelboat, ordered for July 20, was nowhere near completion.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> stormed to the boatyard. True enough: only a skeleton stood on the ways. Two rows of timbers curved up a few feet, like a whale's ribs, from the four-by-four beam, the keel, that ran down the boat's center line and was sturdy enough, supposedly, to absorb the shock of hitting submerged rocks and logs. A few planks had been nailed and tied to the ribs on one side. That was all.</p>
               <p>
The contractor, his breath fetid with whiskey, met him with that impression of mingled candor and offended dignity that habitual drunks know so well how to use. He'd had trouble getting good timber, he said. But depend on it, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> would have the boat by the end of the month. The captain silently added five days to the estimate, eyed the dropping levels of the water—1803 was a drought year; no one in town could recall such low water—and 
settled back to wait as patiently as he could.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="place" key="Pittsburgh, Pa.">Pittsburgh</name> in those days was not conducive to patience. Summer doldrums lay on the brick houses lining the narrow, grubby streets, on the boatyards and warehouses crowded close to the banks of the uniting <name type="place" key="Allegheny River">Allegheny</name> and <name type="place" key="Monongahela">Monongahela</name> rivers, and on the small inns and dark grogshops that catered to teamsters who hauled in Eastern merchandise for transshipment down the <name type="place" key="Ohio River">Ohio</name> to the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name>. During spring, when the rivers were high, farmers poured in with corn, flour, hams, salted butter, whiskey, and brandy, all in demand at <name type="place" key="New Orleans, La.">New Orleans</name>. Hammers rang on bar 
iron of local make, and visitors stopped by to see the town's nail factory, the first in America.</p>
               <p>
Little of that activity was visible in July. Every morning <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> visited the boatyard, trying to keep the contractor sober and his workers busy. He made sure each timber destined for the boat was sound, and held forth at length on the need for thorough caulking. When he could no longer endure that, he wandered through the town, yarned with <name type="person" key="Hooke, Moses">Hooke</name>, climbed a nearby hill to see a prehistoric Indian mound, and read until it was threadbare a copy of <hi rend="italic">The Navigator</hi>, a pilot's manual for the <name type="place" key="Ohio River">Ohio</name>, updated annually by an enterprising <name type="place" key="Pittsburgh, Pa.">Pittsburgh</name> printer, <name type="person" key="Cramer, Zodak">Zodak Cramer</name>.<ref target="n0412" n="12"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Glumly he received, on time, the wagonload of supplies from <name type="place" key="Harpers Ferry, W. Va.">Harpers Ferry</name> and the seven soldiers who were to act as his crew as far as <name type="place" key="Fort Massac (Ill.)">Fort Massac</name>. (Called <name type="place" key="Fort Massac (Ill.)">Fort Massac</name>re by troops for no particular reason except the sound of the word, <name type="place" key="Fort Massac (Ill.)">Massac</name> was located on the <name type="place" key="Illinois">Illinois</name> side of the <name type="place" key="Ohio River">Ohio</name>, and eight miles downstream from the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Tennessee River">Tennessee River</name>, where many years later <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark</name> would lay out the town of <name type="place" key="Paducah, Ky.">Paducah</name>, <name type="place" key="Kentucky">Kentucky</name>.) The
bitterness caused by the timely arrivals for whom no boat awaited was increased on July 22 by a letter from <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>. Copies of the Louisiana Purchase treaty, the president wrote, had reached <name type="place" key="Washington D. C.">Washington</name>.<ref target="n0413" n="13"/> The agreement still had to be confirmed by the Senate, and the House still had to authorize bonds enough to pay for the acquisition, but history was marching—and there <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> sat, the captive of a drunken boatbuilder.</p>
               <p>
Even harder on his nerves was the lack of word from <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, to whom he had written more than a month earlier. Fearful that some disaster might have befallen his friend, he decided that while there was still time to exchange letters with <name type="place" key="Washington D. C.">Washington</name>, he should seek authority to enlist <name type="person" key="Hooke, Moses">Moses Hooke</name> to take <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> place. But then the 
sun brightened. On July 29 in came the letter <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had written in response to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> offer—a letter that had gone to <name type="place" key="Washington D. C.">Washington</name> before overtaking <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> in <name type="place" key="Pittsburgh, Pa.">Pittsburgh</name>. Another note soon followed. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> was delighted: "My friend I do assure you no man lives with whome I would perfur to undertake Such a Trip &amp;c as your self." Moreover, he was already recruiting a few men of the caliber he assumed <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> would want.<ref target="n0414" n="14"/>
               </p>
               <p>
On August 3 <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> responded with equal fulsomeness: "I could neither hope, wish, or expect from a union with any man on earth, more perfect support or further aid . . . than that, which I am confident, I shall have from being associated with yourself." He predicted, overoptimistically, that he would greet <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> at the Falls of the <name type="place" key="Ohio River">Ohio</name> by the end of the month.<ref target="n0415" n="15"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Not a chance—not with that boatbuilder. Balked by the man's apparent immovability, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> contemplated buying enough pirogues to float his supplies downstream until he could find another keelboat he could buy. Local merchants dissuaded him; the odds were strongly against a suitable craft being available at that time of year, even in <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>. In order to make sure of going up the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> at all, he would have to wait on the man he had unfortunately chosen by mail.<ref target="n0416" n="16"/>
               </p>
               <p>
The contractor's drinking and constant wrangling with his shifting crew of workers dragged on and on. To make use of his time, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> let slip word of his undertaking. (Until then he had been using the fabrication of a trip up the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name>.) Volunteers began applying for places. After telling each one that enlistment in the army was a prerequisite—it carried a twelve-dollar bonus with it—<name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> carefully interviewed those who agreed to accept the condition. Finally he chose three to go downriver with him on a trial run—no guarantees attached.</p>
               <p>
One of the three probably was <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">George Shannon</name>, either sixteen or eighteen years old. (His birth year is given variously as 1785 and 1787; in either event, he turned out to be the youngest member of the expedition.) His father, an Ohioan, had recently died and <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">George</name> seems to have been on his reluctant way to <name type="place" key="Pennsylvania">Pennsylvania</name> 
to join his mother's family when the prospect of adventure in the West diverted him. Another of the <name type="place" key="Pittsburgh, Pa.">Pittsburgh</name> trio may have been that future maker of heroic mountain-man legends, <name type="person" key="Colter, John">John Colter</name>, then about thirty years old, as strong as and considerably more nimble than an ox.<ref target="n0417" n="17"/> The indefiniteness about these men and the others who would be enlisted later is frustrating, and it reaches to the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name> and back. Neither <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> nor <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> wrote much about their men, or, for that matter, about each other, perhaps because they were oppressed by too many other duties.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> unrelenting persistence finally speeded up the boatmen. Meanwhile water levels dropped and dropped. According to reports from farther downstream, only six inches covered some of the bars he would have to cross, yet his keelboat, when loaded, would draw close to three feet. To lighten it, he hired two wagons to haul part of the cargo as far as <name type="place" key="Wheeling, W. Va.">Wheeling</name>, where he expected to find better depths.<ref target="n0418" n="18"/> When the wagons proved insufficient, he added a third carrier, a craft he called a "canoe," probably a dugout made from the trunk of a cottonwood tree, but possibly a batteau, an oversized rowboat nailed together from planks.</p>
               <p>
At 10:00 <hi rend="smallcaps">A.M.</hi> on August 31, the travelers cast off for the start of their eleven-hundred-mile journey to the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name>. In addition to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, the keelboat and its auxiliary craft carried the three volunteers whose suitability for the larger adventure was being tested, seven soldiers bound via <name type="place" key="Fort Massac (Ill.)">Fort Massac</name> to <name type="place" key="Fort Adams">Fort Adams</name> in 
<name type="place" key="Mississippi">Mississippi</name> Territory, and a pilot hired for seventy dollars to take the boat through the river's shallow, shifting channels as far as the Falls of the <name type="place" key="Ohio River">Ohio</name>, near <name type="place" key="Louisville, Ky.">Louisville</name>.<ref target="n0419" n="19"/>
               </p>
               <p>
As <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> had been warned to expect, the hardest part of the journey was the hundred miles (sixty-five by wagon) to <name type="place" key="Wheeling, W. Va.">Wheeling</name>. The <name type="place" key="Ohio River">Ohio</name> is indeed a beautiful river, but its course is serpentine and it is dotted with many islands, some of which in <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> day were the sites of prosperous orchards. Immense forests broken by frequent natural clearings covered the banks. Oaks, ash, and a scattering of pines flourished on the upper terraces; willow, honey 
locust, and hickory filled the bottoms, intermingled here and there with white-barked sycamores as much as sixteen feet in circumference. According to <name type="place" key="Cramer, Zodak">Zodak Cramer's</name>
                  <hi rend="italic">The Navigator</hi>, potential feasts abounded: turkeys, partridges, bear, and deer in the forests, ducks, pike, sturgeon, and, notably, catfish weighing up to a hundred pounds each along the river.</p>
               <p>
The islands were the travelers' bane. They "drew up" sand and small gravel at their heads. These accumulations gathered driftwood; bars began to reach toward the outer banks; during periods of shallow water they often completely blocked the river. On meeting such an obstruction, the entire crew piled out of the boat—
fortunately the water was warm—and portaged the cargo to navigable water on the lower side of the bar. Then, lifting and heaving, they skidded the boat across. On one grim day they had to fight their way over five such bars. Sometimes their labors did not suffice. When that happened, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> sent men out to find farmers with draft horses or oxen capable of pulling the boat over the hump. The owners of the animals, he discovered, "are generally lazy charge extravegently . . . and have no filanthropy or contience." One even demanded the "exorbitant" price of two dollars for his and his animals' services.</p>
               <p>
Another obstacle was fog. At night, air temperatures dropped into the sixties, but the water, as <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> determined by frequently dipping in a thermometer, stayed in the low seventies. "When the air becomes most cool," he noted in his journal, "which is about sunrise the fogg is thickest and appears to rise from the face of the water like steem from a boiling kettle," a phenomenon that delayed each morning's start until the mist burned off about eight 
o'clock.</p>
               <p>
The "canoe" he had purchased in <name type="place" key="Pittsburgh, Pa.">Pittsburgh</name> turned out to be leaky and unable to carry as much cargo as necessary. On reaching the small riverbank village of <name type="place" key="Georgetown, Pa.">Georgetown</name>, he paid eleven dollars for another canoe, probably, like the first, a dugout or small pirogue. That one leaked, too, and the journey turned into a sequence of struggles to keep his goods dry from the river underneath and the sky above, which every now and then dumped deluges onto them.</p>
               <p>
No one was very happy about the course of things, but the soldiers in the crew had to obey orders or face courtmartial. Not so the civilians, additional numbers of whom he had hired for handling the dugouts. The labors irked most of them as much as their attitudes irked <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>. At the little towns they passed, he fired and hired. Only <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name> and <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name> functioned well and so made permanent places for themselves on the expedition.</p>
               <p>
They spent eight hard days covering the hundred miles to <name type="place" key="Wheeling, W. Va.">Wheeling</name>. Mercifully the captain decided to lay over there for the better part of two days so that the men could rest, wash their clothes, and trade the flour that had been issued to them for bread already baked by women in the town. He also discovered that the depth of the river had not increased as much as he had hoped. Unable to accommodate in the keelboat the cargo that had come from <name type="place" key="Pittsburgh, Pa.">Pittsburgh</name> by wagon, he bought yet another "canoe." This one was bigger, sounder, and generally more satisfactory than the other two. Though <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> doesn't describe it, it probably resembled the most common class of pirogues on the river: close to fifty feet long, five feet of beam, and equipped with a mast and sail. It meant another hiring and a reshuffling of assignments for the men. Whether or not <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> kept one or both of the smaller, leaky vessels does not appear. He had canoes, plural, when he reached the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Ohio River">Ohio</name>, but they may have been replacements picked up along the way.</p>
               <p>
The little fleet left Wheeling at three o'clock in the afternoon of September 9 and almost immediately was engulfed in another deluge. Water dashed under and between the boats' oilcloth coverings, and the holds acted like bathtubs. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> struggled ahead anyhow—that was his nature, as Attorney General <name type="person" key="Lincoln, Levi">Levi Lincoln</name> had pointed out to <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> earlier in the year—and did not land until twilight. Stumbling around with lanterns, they bailed out the boats and readjusted the cargo and coverings. Finally, at midnight, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> wrote, "I wrung out my saturated clothes, put on a dry shirt turned into my birth," presumably in the cramped stern cabin of the keelboat.</p>
               <p>
There were pleasant interludes. On the 11th and again on the 13th, the flotilla ran into numbers of gray squirrels migrating across the river from west to east, swimming lightly and making good speed, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> noted. The creatures provided sport for the dog, <name type="person" key="Seaman">Seaman</name>, and a treat for <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>. At his master's bidding the big, black Newfoundland jumped into the water, caught a squirrel, crunched it to death, and brought it back. "They wer fat and thought them when fryed a pleasant food."</p>
               <p>
More gravel bars stood in the way, but the voyagers were far enough down the river now to breach them with relative ease. The gravel was small and loose, the current brisk. After the men had dug a small trench through the barrier with spades and paddles the water swept through, washing out a channel big enough for the boats. Only twice, when the gravel was intermixed with clay and driftwood, did the captain have to call in draft animals to help.</p>
               <p>
September 7 dawned sunny and warm. Spotting a clean bar ahead, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> decided to land and give his cargo its first thorough check. To his dismay he found some of it in bad shape despite nightly bailings of the boats, oilcloth coverings, and stowage in casks and supposedly waterproof bags. Rusty guns, tomahawks, and trade knives had to be oiled. Clothing was spread out to dry. Some "biscuit," probably hardtack, was damaged beyond salvaging.</p>
               <p>
At sundown the boats were reloaded. The next day <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> journal entries ceased and were not resumed until November 11, when the wayfarers were at <name type="place" key="Fort Massac (Ill.)">Fort Massac</name>—a gap of fifty-four days and 694 miles. Possibly he kept his log in another book that was later lost, though the appearance of the one that survives makes this seem unlikely. Or he may simply have grown bored: what point was there in describing again routines that had grown tedious, and in a well-known land whose natural history he had not been instructed to examine? Or, just possibly, the failure of his 
hard work to keep things spick and span had triggered another of his deep depressions.</p>
               <p>
A long letter written to <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> in <name type="place" key="Cincinnati, Ohio">Cincinnati</name> on October 3 helps fill the gap in the journal and demonstrates how remarkably well <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, building on his own interest in natural history, had absorbed the paleontology lessons given him during his spring training course in <name type="place" key="Philadelphia, Pa.">Philadelphia</name>.<ref target="n0420" n="20"/> A natural animal trap called the <name type="place" key="Big Bone Lick">Big Bone Lick</name> lay near the outskirts of <name type="place" key="Cincinnati, Ohio">Cincinnati</name>. Animals coming there during many centuries to lick salt sometimes became mired. Dying, they left the mud studded with bones, some quite massive. Though the existence of the lick had been known to whites since 1739, its antiquity wasn't realized until a German visitor recognized some of the bones as akin to those of the extinct Siberian mastodon.</p>
               <p>
The flurry of interest reached as far as the American Philosophical Society. It also prompted a <name type="place" key="Cincinnati, Ohio">Cincinnati</name> physician, <name type="person" key="Goforth, William">Dr. William Goforth</name>, to dig in the mud, in the spring of 1803, a pit thirty feet square and eleven deep in the hope of finding the complete skeleton of a mammoth. No luck. He did cart home, however, several huge bones plus some teeth and tusks, one of which was twenty-two inches in circumference at the base and upwards of six feet 
long. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> visited <name type="person" key="Goforth, William">Goforth</name> in <name type="place" key="Cincinnati, Ohio">Cincinnati</name>, looked over the collection, and obtained permission to have other specimens dug up and shipped to <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> via <name type="place" key="New Orleans, La.">New Orleans</name>. Unhappily the freight was lost in a shipwreck. However, the minute descriptions of tusks and teeth that he put on paper did reach and, he hoped, impressed the president.</p>
               <p>
It is not hard to believe that the long and carefully crafted letter to <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> was intended as a form of compensation for his recent failures. Before starting West he had made much of ascending the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> for many hundred miles before winter set in. Because of a drunken boatbuilder whom he, the personal representative of the 
president of the United States, had not been able to handle, that hope was blasted. He had not been able to go down the <name type="place" key="Ohio River">Ohio</name> without damaging a part of his cargo. But perhaps he could regain stature in <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name> eyes by focusing clearly and cogently on a phase of natural history in which <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> was deeply interested.</p>
               <p>
His desire to wash away the stigma of failure emerges still more explicitly in the last paragraph of that long letter. Congress was about to meet to consider the treaties implementing the Louisiana Purchase. And what would those august men think of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> progress so far? To keep them in "good humor" (<name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> words) "I have concluded to make a tour this winter on horseback of some hundred miles through the most interesting country adjoining my 
winter establishment; perhaps . . . towards Santafee." And would <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> please send him official copies of the treaties; they might induce Spanish officials in <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> to give him more information about the Western country than might otherwise be the case.</p>
               <p>
To anticipate: <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name> reply was delayed until the treaties, confirmed by the Senate on October 20, 1803, could be put into print. What he said then was crisp. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> should not undertake the proposed excursion. It might be more dangerous than the expedition up the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> "&amp; would, by an accident to you, hazard our main object . . . [finding] the direct water communication from sea to sea formed by the bed of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> &amp; perhaps the Oregon." His time would be better spent and his stores conserved if he made his headquarters in American territory near <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> and did what he could in that city to learn what awaited in the land ahead.<ref target="n0421" n="21"/>
               </p>
               <p>
So much for that rash notion of a long winter trip toward <name type="place" key="New Mexico">New Mexico</name>, a proposal that confirmed again <name type="person" key="Lincoln, Levi">Levi Lincoln's</name> estimate of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> headstrong nature.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>
Because of the gap in the 1803 journal we know nothing of how the boats were run down the Falls of the <name type="place" key="Ohio River">Ohio</name>, a two-mile-long series of cascades formed by water foaming grandly over limestone ledges. The usual route ran close to the north (<name type="place" key="Indiana">Indiana</name>) side, where <name type="place" key="Clarksville, Ind.">Clarksville</name> lay near the bottom of the turbulence. <name type="place" key="Louisville, Ky.">Louisville</name> stood opposite, in <name type="place" key="Kentucky">Kentucky</name>. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> fleet arrived at one or the other of the towns on October 14, but just where or under what circumstances the co-captains came together is also unknown, which is a cause for regret.</p>
               <p>
In some ways they were much alike. Both were over six feet tall and in superb physical condition, except that <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> suffered intermittently and painfully throughout his life from some obscure digestive ailment. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> was leaner, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> more heavily set. Both were fiercely loyal. Army discipline was deeply ingrained in them, yet they were flexible enough to improvise as frontier conditions necessitated.</p>
               <p>
There were striking differences as well. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> had a better formal education, though when he wrote rapidly his spelling was almost as unrestrained as <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>, and his sentences were even more convoluted. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> was moody, intense, and speculative; his nature seemed to require occasional times of solitude. When the occasion arose, he could be charming socially. Unlike <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, who was accompanied west by a devoted <name type="person" key="York">black slave</name>, <name type="person" key="York">York</name>, he took no 
personal servant along on the trip. He frequently sought the company of young women and seemed, especially after his return from the expedition, eager to marry. He never did.</p>
               <p>
It would be a mistake to assume <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> was the more intelligent. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> bent was simply more practical, given to dealing with things to which he could put his hands. He was bluff, hearty, and gregarious. As far as we know, his eye for girls was not as quick as <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>, but shortly after the expedition ended, when he was thirty-five, he married sixteen-year-old <name type="person" key="Clark, Julia Hancock">Julia (sometimes called Judy) Hancock</name>. He named his first child <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name>
                  <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>,
a compliment <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> probably would have returned if circumstances had allowed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>
The pause in <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clarks</name>ville lasted nearly two weeks. Many farewell parties must have held sway there and across the river in <name type="place" key="Louisville, Ky.">Louisville</name>, for the <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clarks</name> were a large, prominent, and well-liked family, and the upcoming expedition was one to attract attention. By day there were chores. The larder had to be replenished, the keelboat spruced up. Because the river remained low and there were more men to transport, the captains decided to keep the big pirogue 
<name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> had purchased in <name type="place" key="Wheeling, W. Va.">Wheeling</name>. They may also have replaced the small, leaky pair with one or two sounder craft.</p>
               <p>
Although <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had interviewed many volunteers while waiting for <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, he had selected—and only tentatively—no more than seven: William <name type="person" key="Bratton, William E.">Bratton</name>, the brothers Joseph and <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">Reuben Field</name>, <name type="person" key="Floyd, Charles">Charles Floyd, Jr.</name>, <name type="person" key="Gibson, George">George Gibson</name>, <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Nathaniel Pryor</name>, and <name type="person" key="Shields, John">John Shields</name>. <name type="person" key="Shields, John">Shields</name>, aged thirty-five, turned out to be the oldest man 
on the trip. He was married and had at least one child. This ran contrary to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> instructions about signing on only bachelors, but <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had made an exception because of <name type="person" key="Shields, John">Shields's</name> known talents as a blacksmith and gunsmith, and <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> let the enlistment stand.<ref target="n0422" n="22"/>
                  <name type="person" key="Floyd, Charles">Charles Floyd</name> was an inheritance of sorts. His father had served under <name type="person" key="Clark, George Rogers">George Rogers Clark</name> during the Revolution, and his son was enough like him that the captains later called on him to be one of the group's sergeants. Another sergeant-to-be was <name type="person" key="Floyd, Charles">Floyd's</name> cousin, <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Nathaniel Pryor</name>, who, after the expedition was disbanded, would embark on a fruitful and adventurous career in the army and as an Indian trader. The <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph and Reubin">Field brothers</name> seemed to turn up whenever trouble threatened and distinguished themselves in what followed. So <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had picked well, even though <name type="person" key="Bratton, William E.">Bratton</name> and <name type="person" key="Gibson, George">Gibson</name> were accorded no special remarks when <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> summarized the merits of the party's men in a letter to the secretary of war on January 15, 1807.<ref target="n0423" n="23"/> The two were not alone in this; only six of the twenty-nine men <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> listed drew particular praise. But everyone, the captain said, deserved "warmest approbation and thanks."</p>
               <p>
The reinforced party left <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clarks</name>ville on October 26. On November 11, at <name type="place" key="Fort Massac (Ill.)">Fort Massac</name>, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> river journal picks up again as abruptly as it left off. The post, occupied that fall by seventy-three soldiers and three officers, had a reputation as a sickly place. Perhaps this took some of the spirit out of the garrison. Although the post commander, <name type="person" key="Bissell, Daniel">Captain Daniel Bissell</name>, had been ordered by the War Department to recruit volunteers for the Corps of Discovery, as the party had been named by <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, he had managed to sign up only <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Joseph Whitehouse</name> and <name type="person" key="Newman, John">John Newman</name>—and the latter would be cashiered later on for insubordination. Another, greater disappointment was the failure of <name type="person" key="McRae, William">Major McRae</name> to send from <name type="place" key="South West Point, Tenn.">South West Point</name>, <name type="place" key="Tennessee">Tennessee</name>, to <name type="place" key="Fort Massac (Ill.)">Fort Massac</name> the six to eight volunteers he had been instructed to provide.</p>
               <p>
There was one marked gain—<name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">George Drouillard</name>, about twenty-eight, the son of a French-Canadian father and a <name type="native_nation" key="Shawnee Indians">Shawnee</name> Indian mother. When <name type="person" key="Bissell, Daniel">Bissell</name> recommended him as an expert hunter with a good knowledge of the Indians' character and their "hand talk," <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> promptly offered him twenty-five dollars a month if he would join the expedition as a civilian interpreter. <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name>, whose name was consistently given the phonetic spelling <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name> 
in the trip journals, hesitated. But he did agree to go to <name type="place" key="South West Point, Tenn.">South West Point</name>, about three hundred miles away, to pick up the volunteers there and bring them to <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>. For this he drew a thirty-dollar advance. Meanwhile the seven soldiers who had come down the <name type="place" key="Ohio River">Ohio</name> with <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> dropped out, to continue to their own destination, <name type="place" key="Fort Adams">Fort Adams</name>. The nine volunteers <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had signed up took their places at the oars.</p>
               <p>
The captains wound up their work at <name type="place" key="Fort Massac (Ill.)">Massac</name> late in the afternoon on November 13. Though <name type="person" key="Bissell, Daniel">Bissell</name> surely pressed them to stay, enough was enough. After sailing and rowing three miles, they camped on the riverbank. That night <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> came down with a violent "ague"—what else could be expected of a place like <name type="place" key="Fort Massac (Ill.)">Massac</name>? He dosed himself with some of <name type="person" key="Rush, Benjamin">Rush's</name> thunderbolt pills, probably spent the next day in and out of the boat, and by the time they 
reached the junction of the <name type="place" key="Ohio River">Ohio</name> and <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name> he was able to move about more normally, though "extreemly week."</p>
               <p>
His sense of duty was still haunting him, and the party spent six days at the confluence, making up chores for themselves. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, still very shaky, passed on some of his recently acquired knowledge of surveying techniques to <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, who calculated the width of the rivers: the <name type="place" key="Ohio River">Ohio</name>, 1,274 yards; the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name>, 1,435. Below the junction the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name> spread out to 2,002 yards, somewhat more than a mile. The junction was a prominent geographic spot, of course, and noting the geography of the expanding nation was one of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> assignments. Still, neither the river statistics nor the sketches they made of bars and islands in the vicinity proved very much, for the rivers were exceptionally low. High-water marks on the banks showed that the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name> at times reached an extraordinary fifty-two feet above the point where they stood when measuring it. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> must have wondered what would happen if he met water like that when the boats started up the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> in the spring.</p>
               <p>
To add to his sense of usefulness he practiced being an emissary. One way and another—rowing, walking—part of the group visited a few <name type="native_nation" key="Shawnee Indians">Shawnee</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Deleware Indians">Delaware</name> hunting camps, some on the west bank of the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name>. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> informed the Indians that the great father of all the tribes now lived in a city bigger than <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>, one called <name type="place" key="Washington D. C.">Washington</name>. It is unlikely that this talk of distant and unknown rulers impressed the Indians. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> big black dog, <name type="person" key="Seaman">Seaman</name>, was far more interesting. One <name type="native_nation" key="Shawnee Indians">Shawnee</name> offered three beaver skins for him. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> shook his head.</p>
               <p>
At some point along the way, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> was stricken with one of his stomach disorders. In spite of that he rowed with the others, going along with a small group that traveled down the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name> in search of a key fort that <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William's</name> brother, <name type="person" key="Clark, George Rogers">George Rogers</name>, had built in 1780 and named <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> for the then newly inaugurated governor of <name type="place" key="Virginia">Virginia</name>. It had stood near the eastern shore atop a bluff on an island called Iron Banks.<ref target="n0424" n="24"/> Not a trace remained in 1803. The disappearance was the sort of thing moody <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> might well have brooded about; how long did any work of man last?</p>
               <p>
On November 20, with <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> still ailing, they started up the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name>. Concerned for his friend, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> went out of his way to kill a grouse and make a broth he hoped <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> could keep in his stomach. It did not help. The invalid was still laid up on the 23d when the boats swung to at the <name type="place" key="Cape Girardeau, Mo.">Cape Girardeau</name> landing and <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> set forth on what can be regarded, in spite of the extemporized visits with the <name type="native_nation" key="Shawnee Indians">Shawnees</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Delaware Indians">Delawares</name>, as his first official errand in newly acquired <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name>.</p>
               <p>
Before <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> turned the northern part of the territory into a huge Indian reservation, he needed to know how many whites and, in particular, how many Americans would have to be relocated on the eastern side of the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name>. The obvious source of information about the number of those living in the <name type="place" key="Cape Girardeau, Mo.">Cape Girardeau</name> region was the man who governed them for the Spanish—a man named <name type="person" key="Lorimier, Louis">Louis Lorimier</name>.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> was not sure how <name type="person" key="Lorimier, Louis">Lorimier</name> would receive him. The fellow, who was <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">George Drouillard's</name> uncle, had fought for the British in the <name type="place" key="Ohio River">Ohio</name> country during the Revolution. This had made him fair game for a detachment of <name type="person" key="Clark, George Rogers">George Rogers Clark's</name> men. They fell on his trading post, just missed capturing <name type="person" key="Lorimier, Louis">Lorimier</name> himself, and then looted his establishment of two hundred packhorse-loads of goods. What they couldn't carry they burned; losses were estimated at twenty thousand dollars. Disliking the American jurisdiction that spread over the trans-<name type="place" key="Allegheny Mountains">Allegheny</name> region after the war, he moved to <name type="place" key="Cape Girardeau, Mo.">Cape Girardeau</name> about 1793 and somehow managed to be appointed its commander by the lieutenant governor in <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>. He had continued in that post under <name type="place" key="France">France</name> and would continue to hold it until the territory was formally transferred to the United States. He might not relish hearing of the change from an associate of <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark</name>.<ref target="n0425" n="25"/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> need not have worried. He reached <name type="person" key="Lorimier, Louis">Lorimier's</name> settlement at the close of a horse-racing celebration during which the winners took possession of the losers' animals. It was a wild scene—yelling, drinking, fighting, cavorting. The frontier Americans, who were in the majority, struck the somewhat supercilious emissary from the United States as "dissolute and abandoned . . . of desperate fortunes [with] but little to loose either character or property." Though <name type="person" key="Lorimier, Louis">Lorimier</name> had lost four horses during the meet, he greeted <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> cheerfully and invited him to dinner with his family, away from the disorders.</p>
               <p>
Two things about the man struck the explorer. One was <name type="person" key="Lorimier, Louis">Lorimier's</name> hair. He wore it in a queue that reached down his back as low as his knees and was held in place by a broad belt. (He was about five feet eight inches tall.) When he unbraided it, it touched the ground. There was not a gray strand in it, though <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> guessed him to be sixty years old. (Actually he was fifty-five.) The other notable attraction was his daughter, "much the most descent looking feemale I have seen since I left the settlement in <name type="place" key="Kentucky">Kentuckey</name> a little below <name type="place" key="Louisville, Ky.">Louisville</name>." In addition to thoroughly enjoying the family gathering, he picked up useful census figures from "a young man," probably <name type="person" key="Lorimier, Louis">Lorimier's</name> son; the comandante himself could neither read nor write. The district, which had been in existence for only ten years, already held 1,111 souls. During 1802 and the first ten months of 1803, 406 persons had arrived, some of them Americans. This headlong immigration, coupled with a high birthrate, was likely to increase the figure rapidly. Could so many people be readily uprooted and moved out of the country for the sake of the Indians? Was it his business to make suggestions after collecting more data?</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> health improved, and as the cold, weary miles of bucking the current dragged past, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> restlessness increased. He disliked being cramped in a boat under the best of circumstances. As the number of settlements on both banks of the river increased, he could no longer contain himself. Surely he could find a horse and cover ground that way much faster than by following the winding river in a cranky vessel. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> army experiences had involved boats; he could manage the flotilla better than <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> could. So why not ride ahead, check in at <name type="place" key="Fort Kaskaskia (Ill.)">Fort Kaskaskia</name> about personnel and an extra boat for carrying supplies to the upper <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, as authorized by the War Department, and afterwards continue to <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> to confront the region's lieutenant governor, <name type="person" key="Delassus, Carlos Dehault">Carlos Dehault
Delassus</name>?</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Delassus, Carlos Dehault">Delassus</name>. It was not a Spanish name. But as <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> knew by then, many enterprising French had entered Spanish service during the closing decades of the past century. <name type="person" key="Delassus, Carlos Dehault">Delassus</name> was one. He might try to end his tenure at <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> by being resistant. As far as <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> knew, no copies of the treaties had reached <name type="place" key="Missouri">Missouri</name>, and anyway the Spanish were vociferously insisting the sale of <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name> to the United States had no legal standing. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> did not even have a Spanish passport to use for gaining entrance to <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> in the event <name type="person" key="Delassus, Carlos Dehault">Delassus</name> chose to keep him out.</p>
               <p>
It could be a serious block. None of the maps he had studied in <name type="place" key="Washington D. C.">Washington</name> had been based on the knowledge of people who had actually been in most of the country he and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> proposed to enter. If such maps existed, they would be in <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>. If traders who knew the upper <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri River</name> could be run down, it would be in <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>. He had to determine, by drawing on the wisdom of such people, how many men he would need and then enlist them; he was already sure the roster would exceed the fifteen for whom he had bought guns and shirts in the East. He would need 
to recalculate and then buy and package the additional supplies he would need for his own party and as Indian gifts to be used as he urged the tribes to shift their allegiance from old friends to new. Those tedious shopping chores could be completed only in <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> and vicinity. Finally, he hoped desperately he could establish winter quarters along the lowest reaches of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, not just for convenience, but for face saving. It would be humiliating, 
after a year's work on the project, to have to admit to the world that he had not even crossed the old boundary into the new acquisition. The sooner he confronted Delassus the better.</p>
               <p>
At 8:00 <hi rend="smallcaps">A.M</hi>. on November 28 he wrote in his journal that he was turning the boat over to <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain Clark</name>.<ref target="n0426" n="26"/> Handing the journal to his partner, who would keep it until the site of the wintering was reached, he departed. The separation would last intermittently for the next five and a half months.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="notes" type="notes">
            <head rend="center">Notes</head>
            <div type="section">
               <note xml:id="n0401" n="1">DeVoto, Course, 397.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0402" n="2">McMaster, II, 638–40.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0403" n="3">Malone, IV, 324, 335. DeConde, 201–4.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0404" n="4">
                  <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> to Breckinridge, August 12, 1803, quoted in Sprague, 315.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0405" n="5">Indian removal: Jackson, <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> and Stony Mountains</hi>, 112–13, and Letters, 152–54; Esarcy, 69–73; Prucha, 213–17, 226.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0406" n="6">Steffen. Bakcicss, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>. Appleman, 52–55.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0407" n="7">
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> to <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, in Jackson, Letters, 57–60.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0408" n="8">The actual commission, a lieutenancy, contained a blank wherein <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> could enter any name he chose. (Jackson, <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, 104.) In <name type="place" key="Pittsburgh, Pa.">Pittsburgh</name>, as we will see, he came close to naming a regimental friend, <name type="person" key="Hooke, Moses">Moses Hooke</name>, rather than <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0409" n="9">Jackson, <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, 103–4.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0410" n="10">
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> dog was long called <name type="person" key="Seaman">Scammon</name> or <name type="person" key="Seaman">Scannon</name> because of errors made by Coues, Thwaites, Osgood, and others in reading the manuscript journals. The mistake was corrected by Jackson, "Call Him Good Old Dog." I assume, as do Osgood in "Our Dog <name type="person" key="Seaman">Scannon</name>" and many others, that <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> bought the dog somewhere on the East Coast, paying twenty dollars. However, I have found no mention of him before the start of the trip down the <name type="place" key="Ohio River">Ohio</name>, and <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> may have picked him up in <name type="place" key="Pittsburgh, Pa.">Pittsburgh</name>.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0411" n="11">Drawings made by <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> of a keelboat resting in a cove of the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name> show a high stern cabin and two masts. (Moulton, <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>, maps 3a, 3b.) Later, near <name type="place" key="Cahokia, Ill.">Cahokia</name>, December 7, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> reported that a violent wind blew down one of the masts. (Quaife, entry for December 7.) This suggests the unusual second mast was another of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> innovations.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0412" n="12">Extracts from <name type="person" key="Cramer, Zodak">Cramer's</name>
                  <hi rend="italic">The Navigator</hi> appear in Hulbert. See also 
 Havighurst, <hi rend="italic">Long Horizons</hi>, 165–70, and River, 135–36.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0413" n="13">Jackson, <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, 109.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0414" n="14">Ibid., 110–15.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0415" n="15">Ibid., 115–17.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0416" n="16">Appleman, 49.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0417" n="17">Lange, "<name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name>." <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name> may not have joined the expedition at <name type="place" key="Pittsburgh, Pa.">Pittsburgh</name> but at Old Limestone, now <name type="place" key="Maysville, Ky.">Maysville</name>, <name type="place" key="Kentucky">Kentucky</name>. See biographies of him: Burton Harris and the <hi rend="italic">Dictionary of  American Biography</hi>.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0418" n="18">
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> to <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, from <name type="place" key="Wheeling, W. Va.">Wheeling</name>, September 8, 1803, speaks of having hired "a waggon." <name type="person" key="Hooke, Moses">Moses Hooke</name>, the military agent who had to pay for the vehicles, says two. I follow <name type="person" key="Hooke, Moses">Hooke</name>. See Jackson, <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, 119, 122.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0419" n="19">I reconstruct the trip down the <name type="place" key="Ohio River">Ohio</name> from <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> journal in Quaife and his letters to <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, September 8 and 13 and October 3. Jackson, <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, 121–31.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0420" n="20">Jackson, <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, 126–31. Havighurst, River, 131–32.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0421" n="21">Havighurst, <hi rend="italic">River</hi>, 136–38.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0422" n="22">Lange, "Shields." <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clarke</name>, 53–54.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0423" n="23">Jackson, <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, 364–73.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0424" n="24">Bakeless, <hi rend="italic">Background to Glory</hi>, 242–48.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0425" n="25">Ibid., 295. Quaife, 59–62. Jackson, <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, 152.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0426" n="26">Quaife, 169.</note>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.lavender.01.03" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.lavender.01.00" type="contents"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.lavender.01.05" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
