<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.sup.allen.04">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">Geographical Review 62.1 (1972): 13–39</title>
            <title type="sub">An Analysis of the Exploratory Process: The Lewis and Clark Expedition of 1804–1806</title>
            <author>John L. Allen</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Supplements</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Texts</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic"/>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-11-23</date>
            <name>Jamie Tallman</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="main">An Analysis of the Exploratory Process: The <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition of 1804–1806</head>
         <p>by John Allen</p>
         <div type="article">
            <p>(This article first appeared in <hi rend="italic">Geographical Review</hi> 16.91 [1972]: 13–39.)</p>
            <p>Of the many activities that lead to the establishment of more-or-less systematized bodies of knowledge about the world or its regions, few have received as much attention, scholarly and otherwise, as exploration. Unfortunately most of the studies have concentrated on the inherent romance and adventure, on tedious re-constructions and endless arguments about routes taken, and on the historical and geographical results. Remarkably few have focused on the exploratory process itself and on the relationship between that process and man's understanding of his world.</p>
            <p>Since exploration has been (and perhaps still is) an effective instrument of national policy, with far-reaching commercial, political, and military consequences, it is an important consideration in historical analysis. And for geographers and others concerned with the ways in which man comes to know his world, it is necessary to recognize exploration as a basic step in the acquisition of geographical knowledge.</p>
            <p>The bond between exploration and geographical knowledge, however, goes beyond the simple fact that one of exploration's major contributions is an expansion of <hi rend="italic">terrae cognitae</hi>; for geographical knowledge is linked not only with the results of exploration but with the nature of the exploratory process. Exploration begins with the articulation of certain goals gleaned from the geographical lore of the time and place and with the establishment of a plan to achieve those goals. As exploration proceeds toward its objectives, field operations are implemented on the basis of the acceptance or rejection of different types of geographical information.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="_">
            <head>Geographical Knowledge and the Exploratory Process</head>
            <p>Although the relationship between geographical knowledge and the exploratory process is difficult to assess, a potentially useful concept exists for making such an assessment—that of gradations in the accuracy of regional knowledge.<ref target="n01" n="1"/> Geographical knowledge is not necessarily "accurate." That is, from it may be developed images of, or patterns of belief about, the nature of land that are not fully consistent either with geographical reality or with what consensual opinion considers to be geographical reality. The accuracy of the images that any person or group at any point in time has about the world or a distinct part of it depends on a wide range of subjective constituents that condition both the acquisition of knowledge and the transmittal of that knowledge to individuals or groups. In many cases, the accuracy of the images may be affected more by esthetic, emotional, economic and environmental biases than by the actual quantity or quality of geographical information.<ref target="n02" n="2"/>
            </p>
            <p>To illustrate this, the accuracy of the geographical knowledge of a region may be scored on two bases: first, on the basis of currently accepted geographical reality; second, as the information was perceived by those to whom it was available. The first category concerns the quality and quantity of the actual information. We can divide a region into zones of first-degree knowledge, obtained "through active, commercial, diplomatic, ecclesiastical, military, and scholarly enterprise"; second-degree knowledge, derived from travelers' accounts and/or fairly reliable hearsay; and third-degree knowledge, acquired only through rumor and conjecture (Fig. 1).<ref target="n03" n="3"/> These zones can be used to evaluate the actual quality of information available to explorers and to assess the impact of geographical knowledge on exploration itself.</p>
            <p>The absolute quality of knowledge must have an initial and continuing impact on the motives and course of exploration. But it is not the only determinant of the influence that lore exerts on the exploratory process. Equally important is the second category mentioned above, the zonation of a region into areas for which explorers believe they have information of a specific reliability. In many cases, the perceived quality of knowledge differs substantially from the actual reliability of knowledge. Rarely, prior to exploration, will the zones of perceived accuracy conform precisely to those of real accuracy.<ref target="n04" n="4"/> The

<figure>
                  <p/>
               </figure>

first and second zones of perceived knowledge (those areas considered well known and partly known, respectively) are generally more extensive than the first and second zones of real accuracy. Frequently, the first two zones of perceived knowledge extend far into what is the third zone of real knowledge (Fig. 2). In short, explorers frequently think that they know a great deal more than they actually do. This fact is of primary importance in understanding the exploratory process.</p>
            <p>While in the field explorers function, at least in part, according to their understanding of the quality of their knowledge. Since neither the actual quality of the lore nor their perception of its quality is uniform throughout the course of exploration, their exploratory behavior will also vary.<ref target="n05" n="5"/> At the outset, the explorer has certain notions about the accuracy of his information, and on them he bases his early field operations. As exploration progresses, he may change his views about the quality of his knowledge and may accordingly alter his field behavior. Such behavior generally reflects the explorer's recognition of discrepancies between zones of actual and perceived knowledge.</p>
            <p>For example, an explorer may pass from a zone of first-degree real knowledge into a zone of second-degree real knowledge. But if this boundary does not coincide with that between the zones of perceived knowledge, he may continue to act as though his information were of the highest quality. Gradually he begins to recognize the inadequacy of his information and shifts from a reliance on the macrogeographical lore obtained prior to exploration to microgeographical information, the detailed lore obtained from natives and from field observations during the course of exploration. At some later point, the explorer may again be forced to change his behavior and to select new sources of data, or, in the absence of information of any kind, he may be forced to return to some modified version of his original macrogeographical lore.</p>
            <p>These reactions to knowledge can be classified into zones of operation, areas in which acceptance of information and field behavior are based on the explorer's perceptions of the quality of knowledge. Boundaries of operational zones will most often lie somewhere between the limits of the zones of actual and of perceived knowledge (Fig. 3). The transition from one operational zone to another comes with the recognition that information about an area is not as accurate as originally assumed. In many cases, the ability to recognize changes in operational zones may determine the success of an expedition. How quickly information is recognized as inadequate and how swiftly the explorer responds determines the time between the failure of one information class to assist in making field decisions and the replacement of that class with another, possibly more adequate, framework.</p>
            <p>The <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition of 1804–1806 provides an excellent case study. In the following analysis, the quality of the geographical knowledge available to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> is examined in the light of its relationship to their behavior during the journey to the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name> and back.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="_">
            <head>The<name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition</head>
            <p>From May, 1804, to September, 1806, the Corps of Discovery of the Northwest, commanded by <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captains Meriwether Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark</name>, explored the vast trans-<name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> West.<ref target="n06" n="6"/> In their attempts to make known quantities out of partly known and unknown quantities they were guided and directed by geographical knowledge.</p>
            <p>The origins of this first transcontinental expedition in the United States may be found in men's geographical knowledge and in their reactions to it. Ever since the New World had been recognized as a barrier between Europe and Asia, men had blended their geographical theories and their teleological speculations and had spoken of a "Passage to India," an all-water route across the North American continent. The passage existed primarily because logic decreed that it should, and the force of logic, combined with the geography of desire, conditioned exploration in the three centuries between Columbus and <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>. During the long search for the passage, new information and experience, old disappointments and still older hopes, contributed to the continually changing lore of the all-water route. When the passage was found not to be a sea-level strait, it was conceived as mighty rivers draining from a huge inland sea and flowing to both the eastern and the western oceans. When the inland sea was recognized as illusory, the passage became navigable rivers whose headwaters "intermingled" somewhere in the continental interior. By the time of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition, the President of the United States of America, <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Thomas Jefferson</name>, had articulated the dream in its final and most realistic form: in the western part of North America there existed a simple height of land from which two rivers, separated at their sources by a short portage, flowed to the <name type="place" key="Atlantic Ocean">Atlantic</name> and <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name> respectively. In the mind of <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, conceiver and sponsor of the expedition, the two mighty rivers were the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> and the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>; the height of land was the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rockies</name>, a narrow, single ridge of no great height separating the waters of the East from those of the West. Backed by this interpretation, which was based on what was probably the most complete and accurate collection of geographical and cartographical materials on western America, <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> knew that the passage existed, and in 1803 he appointed his personal secretary, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name>, to locate by way of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> and <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> rivers the route which "may offer the most direct practicable water communication across this continent, for the purposes of commerce."<ref target="n07" n="7"/> Since in the minds of <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> and others what should be was indistinguishable from what was, the misconception could be erased only by exploration.</p>
            <p>When <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> left <name type="place" key="Washington D.C.">Washington</name> on the initial leg of his journey to the Pacific in early July, 1803, he carried with him knowledge from which the concept of the passage had emerged. And when he and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark</name>, his personal choice as co-commander, entered their winter camp at the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Dubois River">Wood River</name>, opposite the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>'s confluence with the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name>, they worked to augment that knowledge. During the winter of 1803–1804 at <name type="place" key="Camp Dubois (Ill.)">Camp Dubois</name>, the two men analyzed the available geographical information and developed concepts of the West and of the passage which scarcely differed from those of <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>. The single-ridge <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rockies</name> were there and from their slopes flowed the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> and <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> rivers, linked by a short portage over which American commerce would find its way to the Orient. Their belief in the passage, founded in the geographical lore of the time and in the explorers' understanding of that lore, conditioned the exploratory process and guided the course of exploration when they broke camp in May, 1804, and headed up the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri River</name> for the Pacific.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="_">
            <head>Zonation of Knowledge at <name type="place" key="Camp Dubois (Ill.)">Camp Dubois</name>
            </head>
            <p>By the time <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> left <name type="place" key="Camp Dubois (Ill.)">Camp Dubois</name> for the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>, they had accumulated considerable geographical information from a number of sources.<ref target="n08" n="8"/> But these sources varied in reliability, and since the captains' knowledge of the West was not uniformly accurate, neither was the image they constructed from it. It is therefore possible to describe, for the period immediately prior to exploration, the zonations of actual and perceived knowledge that determined the proposed course of the forthcoming journey to the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name> and back.</p>
            <p>The zone of first-degree real knowledge, well-known through active commercial and military contacts, comprised only the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri River</name> from <name type="place" key="St. Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> to the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> villages in what is now central <name type="place" key="North Dakota">North Dakota</name> and the coastal area of the Pacific Northwest from <name type="place" key="Vancouver Island">Vancouver Island</name> southward, including the valley of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name> from its mouth inland to a point near present-day <name type="place" key="Portland, Oreg.">Portland</name>, <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name> (Fig. 4). The course of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> and the distances in miles between the points of entry of the major rivers into the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, the names and settlements of the various Indian tribes, the location and character of the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> villages, and the nature of the landscape were all a part of the actual available knowledge of the West. Pretty sound information also existed for the course, width, and depth of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name> for nearly a hundred miles into the interior. Although explorers had not penetrated the <name type="place" key="Olympic Mountains">Olympic Mountains</name> and the <name type="place" key="Cascade Range">Cascade Range</name>, accurate sightings had been made of the highest 

<figure>
                  <p/>
               </figure>

peaks, and Mounts <name type="place" key="Mount Olympus">Olympus</name>, <name type="place" key="Mount Rainier">Rainier</name>, <name type="place" key="Mount St. Helens">St. Helens</name>, and <name type="place" key="Mount Hood (Timm, Falls Mountain)">Hood</name> were shown in their proper locations on the available charts.</p>
            <p>The remainder of the country through which <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> expected to travel either was only partly known through travelers' accounts and fairly reliable hearsay or was virtually unknown (Fig.4). The zones of second-degree real knowledge comprised the <name type="place" key="Mount Hood (Timm, Falls Mountain)">Missouri River</name> between the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> villages and the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky Mountains</name> and the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name> from <name type="place" key="Point Vancouver">Point Vancouver</name> to the <name type="place" key="Cascade Range">Cascades</name>. Although explorers and traders had never penetrated these regions, their maps and journals provided some data obtained from observation and from native sources. Finally, the vast tract of land between the point at which the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri River</name> flows out of the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rockies</name> and the <name type="place" key="Cascade Range">Cascade Range</name> was in the realm of third-degree real knowledge. The only information <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> possessed about this region came from speculations presented in some of their sources or from their own extrapolations from the sources.</p>
            <p>When various measures are used to determine the captains' opinions about the quality of their information, certain differences appear between the zones of real knowledge and the zones of perceived knowledge, differences that represent overoptimistic evaluations of the reliability of the data.<ref target="n09" n="9"/> Thus the areas for which <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> felt they had information of the highest quality included not only the regions of first-degree real knowledge but also areas that were only partly known in reality. The zone of first-degree perceived knowledge, then, extended beyond the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> villages to include the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> as far as the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">Great Falls</name>. Similarly, the zone of second-degree perceived knowledge included nearly all the remainder of the Northwest. At <name type="place" key="Camp Dubois (Ill.)">Camp Dubois</name> the captains were unwilling to admit that their knowledge was of less-than-intermediate quality for any region.<ref target="n10" n="10"/>
            </p>
            <p>Perhaps partly because the captains believed so firmly in a short-distance passage across the mountains, they treated the information for the Rockies and for the source regions of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> and <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> rivers which described such a passage as though it were, in fact, of no less than intermediate quality. When <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> left <name type="place" key="Camp Dubois (Ill.)">Camp Dubois</name> in May, 1804, their plans were thus predicated on the acceptance of the short-portage concept.<ref target="n11" n="11"/> They believed the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> was navigable all the way to its source on the eastern side of a narrow range of mountains; across these mountains, easily reached by a short portage, was the navigable headwater of the Great River of the West, the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>. That they perceived their information to he better than it actually was illustrates the common tendency to decrease what is actually unknown by filling it, at least partly, with what is believed to be known.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="_">
            <head>
               <name type="place" key="Camp Dubois (Ill.)">Camp Dubois</name> to <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name>
            </head>
            <p>From May 14 until October 26, 1804, the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition traveled up the great river that had held for so long the key to the mystery of the Passage to <name type="place" key="India">India</name>. As they proceeded, their views of the West, which had been shaped at <name type="place" key="Camp Dubois (Ill.)">Camp Dubois</name>, gradually began to change form. Increments to geographical knowledge extended the borders of the first zone of real knowledge beyond the banks of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> to encompass the lower reaches of such rivers as the <name type="place" key="Kansas (Decaugh, Kaw) River">Kansas</name>, the <name type="place" key="Platte River (Nebr.)">Platte</name>, and the <name type="place" key="Niobrara (Quicurre, Rapid) River">Niobrara</name>. But the additional knowledge did not influence field operations, which continued to be based on macrogeographical knowledge accumulated earlier; for the expedition was passing through a region where the fit between real and perceived knowledge was good. The mileage charts that <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had devised at <name type="place" key="Camp Dubois (Ill.)">Camp Dubois</name> closely matched their own records of the distances traveled during the spring and summer of 1804. The landmarks that they had anticipated were found where they were expected to be. And when the expedition reached the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> villages the captains found that their information about the location and nature of the villages was also accurate.</p>
            <p>But the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> villages marked the western edge of the zone of first-degree real knowledge, though the captains did not yet recognize this and still assumed that the zone extended farther. The disparity between what was actually known and what was thought to be known was unimportant, however, in terms of operational behavior. For at the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> villages a halt was made, and the party built the fort where they wintered over until April, 1805. During the winter, inputs of new information changed the zones of both real and perceived knowledge and enabled <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> to shape an almost entirely new image of the country between the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name> and the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>, an image that exerted considerable influence on the operations of the expedition during the following year.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="_">
            <head>Zonation of Knowledge at <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name>
            </head>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, with their interpreters and men, spent the winter preparing for the final assault on the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>. A steady stream of visitors, both British fur traders and <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Minnetaree (Hidatsa)</name> Indians, came to the fort, and from them the captains gathered information that enabled them to form a better idea of the country to the west.<ref target="n12" n="12"/> Between the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> villages and the <name type="place" key="Continental Divide">Continental Divide</name>, the zonation of real knowledge changed substantially as the captains received reliable data on the upper sections of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>. The new data increased slightly the zone of first-degree real knowledge, expanded the zone of second-degree real knowledge, and decreased the area that remained unknown (Fig. 5). The zone of highest-quality information encompassed the valley of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> as far as the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone</name>, including the lower courses of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>'s major tributaries below the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone</name>. Also expanded was the zone of intermediate-quality lore, which now took in the course of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> and some of its tributaries between the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone</name> and the <name type="place" key="Continental Divide">Continental Divide</name>. In this zone were several key landmarks for which generalized information was available: the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">Great</name>
               <figure>
                  <p/>
               </figure>
               <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">Falls of the Missouri</name>, the several mountain ranges through which the river ran, and the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Three Forks of the">Three Forks</name> area. Beyond the divide was the zone of third-degree real knowledge, a land of sheer fantasy that stretched front the mountains in which the westernmost parts of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> had their sources to the headwaters of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> system. On the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name> side of the <name type="place" key="Continental Divide">divide</name>, the zones of first-, second-, and third-degree knowledge remained as they had been.</p>
            <p>The expansion in the first two zones of real knowledge was accompanied by an enlargement in the first two zones of perceived knowledge. In the spring of 1805, when the expedition was preparing to leave <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name>, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> believed that their knowledge of the country between the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> villages and the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>'s source was of the highest quality." It is likely that they assumed their knowledge to be of intermediate quality for the areas drained by the tributaries of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> and for the area of the connecting portage between the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> and <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> systems. If there were any region along the line of travel for which they might possibly have thought their data to be inaccurate, this would have been confined to what was viewed as a narrow strip between the westernmost ranges of the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rockies</name> and the <name type="place" key="Cascade Range">Cascades</name>.<ref target="n14" n="14"/> But it is apparent that <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> assumed their information was fairly reliable even in this area, and thus they would probably have included it in the zone of second-degree knowledge.</p>
            <p>At <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name>, then, the zones of first- and second-degree perceived knowledge were more extensive than the corresponding zones of real knowledge, and the zone of third-degree perceived knowledge was either missing altogether or was small in comparison with the vast area about which virtually nothing was actually known. Features that were actually known or thought to be known were expanded in the minds and maps of the explorers to fill the empty spaces that remained after the first year of exploration.</p>
            <p>The single most striking example of this expansion of the known to fill the unknown was the westerly and southerly extension of the <name type="place" key="Atlantc Ocean">Atlantic</name> drainage systems, which shows up on a map drawn by <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> during the winter at <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name> (Fig. 6). <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had received quite specific data from the Indians relative to the course of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> above the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> villages: the rivers that flowed into it, the distances between them, the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">Great Falls</name>, and the division of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> into three streams of nearly equal size. They also had obtained detailed descriptions about the number and locations of the various mountain ranges through which the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> flowed, beginning with the first chain near the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">Great Falls</name> and ending with the westernmost range from which flowed a great southern branch of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>, accessible from the Upper <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> by a portage of not more than half a day's journey. This information became the basis of their image. Because it was so much more specific than earlier knowledge, because it was accepted as accurate by the captains, and because it supported their belief in the Passage to <name type="place" key="India">India</name>, it nearly filled <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>'s map. In the image, the known or believed-to-be-known filled areas for which information was lacking.</p>
            <p>But if <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>'s and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>'s view of the West as they made ready to leave their winter quarters was not fully consistent with reality, it reflected the same optimism that had cloaked earlier images of western geography. The captains remained firm in the belief that the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> continued to be navigable to its source, that the last of several ranges of the mountains still served as the source area for both the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> and the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>, and that those two mighty rivers could be linked by a simple portage of not more than a few miles. The way to the Passage to <name type="place" key="India">India</name> seemed clear, and on April 8, 1805, the men of the expedition pointed their boats—six canoes and two large pirogues—once more to the West.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="_">
            <head>
               <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name> to the <name type="place" key="Continental Divide">Divide</name>
            </head>
            <p>Although <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> were still functioning within the macrogeographical framework of the years before the expedition, most of their exploratory behavior and decisions were at first based on the microgeographical view shaped from the information obtained at <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name>. During the winter recognition of differences between what was actually known and what had been thought to be known about the country west of the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name> brought about a shift in the type of information relied on. Consequently, a new operational zone began, in which behavior was based almost entirely on the specific lore obtained at the winter camp. But during the journey to the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name> this microgeographical lore, like the more generalized lore be lore it, was found wanting and was replaced by new information as still another zone of operation was entered. At no single place along

<figure>
                  <p>Fig. 6—Tracing a map compiled by Nicholas King in 1805 from sketches provided by <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark</name>. The original is in the national archives. In this adaptation considerable detail has been omitted. 
</p>
               </figure>

the route was a sudden shift made; rather, the process was gradual and cumulative.</p>
            <p>On the first stretch of the journey above the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> villages, the explorers' opinions about the quality of their information were reinforced as they passed die mouths of the <name type="place" key="Little Missouri (E-mâh-tark',-Ah'-zhah) River">Little Missouri</name>, the <name type="place" key="White Earth (Ok-hah-Âh-zhâh) River">White Earth</name>, and the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone</name>. Each of these was found approximately where it should have been according to all reports. When the expedition reached the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone</name>, however, it passed from an area of first-degree real knowledge into an area that was only partly known. But the captains did not recognize the break point and continued to operate as if their <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name> lore was of the highest caliber. Their trust was supported when they reached the <name type="place"
                     key="Milk (Ah-mâh-tâh ru-shush-sher, River Which Scolds at All Others) River">Milk River</name> in eastern <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name> and recognized it as "<name type="place"
                     key="Milk (Ah-mâh-tâh ru-shush-sher, River Which Scolds at All Others) River">the river which scoalds at all others</name>,"<ref target="n15" n="15">15</ref> in the descriptive phrase of the Indians. According to the captains' views, this river was the only major northern tributary of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, and beyond it, at a distance of 240 miles, they expected to find the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">Great Falls</name>.<ref target="n16" n="16"/>
            </p>
            <p>Before reaching <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">the falls</name>, however, they encountered the first evidence that their Indian informants may have been less reliable than they assumed. By May 19, the captains were somewhat puzzled because mountains were sighted that did not fit the Indians' descriptions of the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rockies</name>' first chain, which was supposed to begin near the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">Great Falls</name>, still a considerable distance away according to their estimates. The expedition continued in sight of the mountains for days without reaching <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">the falls</name>, and though the slightly disturbing presence of mountains where none were supposed to exist created no major breakdown in reliance on the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> lore, the seeds of suspicion had been sown. Why had not the Indians told them about these outlying ranges?</p>
            <p>Shortly after the outliers of the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rockies</name> had been sighted a more important event shook the captains' faith in the <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name> data. On June 2, the expedition camped on the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>'s south bank opposite the mouth of "a very considerable river" that entered the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> from the north.<ref target="n17" n="17"/> This was the <name type="place" key="Marias River">Marias River</name>, a totally unexpected geographical feature; for the Indians had told them of no northern tributary between the <name type="place"
                     key="Milk (Ah-mâh-tâh ru-shush-sher, River Which Scolds at All Others) River">Milk River</name> and the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">Great Falls</name>. But here was a major steam, rivaling the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> in size (the <name type="place" key="Marias River">Marias</name> was then in flood), and the captains were not only confused by its existence but unsure about which of the rivers was the true <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, the river described to them "as approaching very near to the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia river</name>."<ref target="n18" n="18"/>
            </p>
            <p>The encounter with the <name type="place" key="Marias River">Marias</name> caused a serious erosion in the captains' confidence in the reliability of their Indian information." In solving the riddle posed by the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>-<name type="place" key="Marias River">Marias</name> junction, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> combined analysis of several different kinds of geographical data. First, they returned to their macrogeographical framework and, using information that they had possessed before they left <name type="place" key="Camp Dubois (Ill.)">Camp Dubois</name>, concluded that since the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> was believed to flow from the southwest, the southern fork was the route to be followed.<ref target="n20" n="20">20</ref> This conclusion was reinforced by the Indian information, which also indicated that the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> flowed in a northeasterly direction from its source to a point near the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">Great Falls</name>. Finally, observation of the two rivers and the surrounding topography substantiated the opinion that the southern branch was the real <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>. The southern stream was clear and ran with a swift current and, in the light of the captains' understanding of physical geography, must therefore flow from mountainous areas (as the true <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> was believed to do). The waters of the northern fork, on the other hand, were muddy and sluggish and thus probably headed in open plains country and flowed through it for a considerable distance.</p>
            <p>Based on the combination of these three different kinds of lore the captains made their decision, and the expedition turned up the south fork (the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>). The fact that <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> made the correct choice shows that they had begun to recognize the disparity between the zones of their real and their perceived knowledge. In becoming hesitant about the Indian data and in beginning to use other sources, they had entered a transition area between operational zones. Evidence of the beginnings of a shift into a new operational zone lies in the fact that the captains determined to cache "all the heavy baggage which we could possibly do without" before proceeding up the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>.<ref target="n21" n="21"/>
            </p>
            <p>Still another increment in the growing distrust of the microgeographical lore came at the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">Great Falls</name>. Discovery of that critical landmark on June 13 confirmed the Indian descriptions, and the captains felt confident that they were traveling the route that the Indians had said would lead to the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>. But whereas the Indians at <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name> had contended that the portage around <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">the falls</name> was not more than half a mile, the actual portage proved to be a tortuous, eighteen-mile traverse that consumed more than a month of a traveling season already far gone. Still, <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">the falls</name> were relatively close to where they should have been, and they lay in the proper geographical relationship with the first ranges of what the explorers recognized the true <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky Mountains</name>. In spite of the growing evidence that their microgeographical lore was less than perfect, the leaders continued to place more faith iii the <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name> data than in anything else.</p>
            <p>The section of the journey from the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">Great Falls</name> to the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Three Forks of the">Three Forks</name> did still more to erode confidence in the Indian lore. The <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> bore south and southeast from the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">Great Falls</name> instead of southwest as the captains had expected. And although it flowed through the several ranges of the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rockies</name>, as described by the Indians, those ranges were not the narrow, parallel ridges that the natives at <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name> had drawn on their buffalo-hide maps. Both captains began to be discouraged over the prospects of reaching the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Three Forks of the">Missouri's Three Forks</name> and of locating the portage to <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbian</name> waters that lay beyond. In late July, however, the party reached the junction of the three rivers, which they named the <name type="place" key="Gallatin (South, Southeast Fork) River">Gallatin</name>, the <name type="place" key="Madison River (Middle Fork)">Madison</name>, and the <name type="place" key="Jefferson (North, Southwest) River">Jefferson</name>. Their arrival at the forks reaffirmed, for a time, the explorers' original assessment of the quality of the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> lore. The three rivers that join to form the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> were much as the natives had described them, and the expedition turned up the western branch, the <name type="person" key="Jefferson River (North, Southwest Fork) River">Jefferson</name>, believing the natives' assertions that it would lead to the final dividing ridge of the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rockies</name> and across a short portage to navigable <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbian</name> waters.</p>
            <p>Although the captains' faith in the possibilities of long-range commercial navigation did not flag, travel up the <name type="place" key="Jefferson River (North, Southwest Fork)">Jefferson</name> proved to he more difficult than they had expected. They were learning to recognize the limitations of the term "navigability" as it applied to plains rivers and mountain streams. Travel across the mountains via the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>'s western branch, long assumed to be easy, was proving incredibly difficult.</p>
            <p>Somewhere along the <name type="place" key="Jefferson (North, Southwest Fork) River">Jefferson</name>, during the torturous struggle up. stream and the futile search for the <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshone</name> tribe that the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> had described as living in the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Three Forks of the">Three Forks</name> area and as having the horses necessary to assist the expedition across the divide, the ultimate breakdown in the captains' dependence on their microgeographical lore began. But the precise point at which they finally realized the inadequacies of their <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name> zonation of knowledge and shifted their sources of information accordingly is problematical. It may have come when <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, in desperation, determined to take a small party ahead of the main force to the source of the <name type="place" key="Jefferson River (North, Southwest Fork)">Jefferson</name>, to cross the divide to a river that he believed would be a major southern branch of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>, and then to proceed down that river until the <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshones</name> were found. It is more likely, however, that the final shift from the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>-<name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Minnetaree</name> information to acceptance of other kinds of data occurred at the <name type="place" key="Continental Divide">Continental Divide</name> itself, at <name type="place" key="Lemhi Pass">Lemhi Pass</name> in the <name type="place" key="Beaverhead Mountains">Beaverhead Mountains</name> of southwestern <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>.</p>
            <p>On August 9, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and three men separated from the main body of the expedition. They continued to follow the Indians' directions and trusted that a route up the <name type="place" key="Jefferson River (North, Southwest Fork)">Jefferson</name> would lead to the final dividing ridge and to Pacific slope waters. By the middle of the next day they had come to the junction of the <name type="place" key="Jefferson River (North, Southwest Fork)">Jefferson</name> and <name type="place" key="Horse Prairie Creek (West Fork Jefferson River)">Horse Prairie Creek</name> and, recognizing that navigation beyond this point would be futile, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> left a note instructing <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> to begin making a cache of supplies at the junction and to await his return. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> then turned up <name type="place" key="Horse Prairie Creek (West Fork Jefferson)">Horse Prairie Creek</name>, following an Indian trail that he assumed was the route to <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbian</name> waters described to him the previous winter. On August 12 the small party reached the spring that is the source of <name type="place" key="Horse Prairie Creek (West Fork Jefferson)">Horse Prairie Creek</name> and saw beyond it the gentle ascent to <name type="place" key="Lemhi Pass">Lemhi Pass</name>. Thus far the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> lore was proving correct, and <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> climbed to the crest of what, in his image, was the final range of the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rockies</name>. He expected to see open plains through which a large navigable river flowed. No such view awaited him. To the west loomed immense ranges of snow-covered mountains, and in the valley below there ran not a mighty river but a small stream, the <name type="place" key="Lemhi Pass">Lemhi</name>, one of the upper tributaries of the <name type="place"
                     key="Salmon (Lewis's, Main Fork Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">Salmon River</name>. Here the cumulative effect of all the small erosions in the quality of the Indian lore became complete. From <name type="place" key="Lemhi Pass">Lemhi Pass</name> the expedition would operate without regard for the <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name> data.</p>
            <p>With the realization that the dream of reaching navigable <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbian</name> waters within easy portage of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> was no more came the prospect of a long overland journey, and the discovery of the <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshone</name> nation with their horse herds became more important. The Indians must be found, and <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> led his men northward down the valley of the <name type="place" key="Lemhi Pass">Lemhi</name>, hoping to locate the elusive tribe. In his search for the <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshones</name>, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> was no longer guided by the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>-<name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Minnetaree</name> information but followed only his own geographical intuition and awareness. The distinction between real and perceived zones of knowledge had been made at the top of <name type="place" key="Lemhi Pass">Lemhi Pass</name>, and the expedition entered a new operational zone. From here on the macrogeographical lore of preexploratory days, combined with field observations, served as a guide to the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="_">
            <head>The <name type="place" key="Continental Divide">Divide</name> to the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>
            </head>
            <p>By the time <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had crossed the <name type="place" key="Continental Divide">divide</name>, they were fully aware that they had virtually no good information about the country through which they had to travel by land. During the trek from <name type="place" key="Lemhi Pass">Lemhi Pass</name> to the <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Clearwater River</name> in western <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>, therefore, the captains accepted and used field information within the frame. work of their macrogeographical knowledge that some rivers did flow west into the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>, and they did not attempt to fit in the <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name> microgeoggraphical lore.</p>
            <p>The day after <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and his men crossed the <name type="place" key="Continental Divide">divide</name>, they made contact with the <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshones</name> near their summer camp on the <name type="place" key="Lemhi (East Fork Lewis's) River">Lemhi River</name>. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> negotiated with the chief for the purchase of horses and endeavored to learn as much as he could about the easiest route to the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>. The <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshones</name> informed him that the <name type="place" key="Lemhi (East Fork Lewis's) River">Lemhi</name> was unnavigable, and that although it flowed into a larger river (the <name type="place"
                     key="Salmon (Lewis's, Main Fork Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">Salmon</name>) north of the <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshone</name> camp, this stream also was impassable for canoes; moreover, the country through which it flowed was too rugged for foot travel.</p>
            <p>Before acting on this information, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> traveled back across the <name type="place" key="Continental Divide">divide</name> to link up with the rest of the party. The captains were reunited on August 17 and held a brief conference on what course of action to take in the light of the Indian information that neither the Lemhi nor the <name type="place"
                     key="Salmon (Lewis's, Main Fork Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">Salmon</name> was navigable. It was determined that <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> would remain at the mouth of <name type="place" key="Horse Prairie Creek (West Fork Jefferson River)">Horse Prairie Creek</name> and complete the cache of canoes and other equipment. He would then portage across the pass the materials needed for the remainder of the journey, using the horses that he had purchased from the <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshones</name>. Meanwhile, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> and eleven men were to cross the mountains to the <name type="place" key="Lemhi (East Fork Lewis's) River">Lemhi</name> and proceed downstream to the <name type="place"
                     key="Salmon (Lewis's, Main Fork Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">Salmon</name> in order to determine whether it was, as the <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshones</name> had claimed, unnavigable. It is clear that the captains were now unwilling to accept Indian information without testing it. This is firm evidence of their entry into a new operational zone. Since Indian data had earlier proved unreliable, local lore must be examined and tested within the structure of earlier, more generalized knowledge and the captains' own physical-geographical understanding. The transition that had begun east of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>-<name type="place" key="Marias River">Marias</name> junction was complete.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> and his party crossed the <name type="place" key="Continental Divide">divide</name> to the <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshone</name> camp where they paused for conversations with the natives, hoping to get additional information on the surrounding country. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> learned essentially the same things that <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> had about the impassability of the country to the west and the impossibility of navigating its rivers. But, unlike <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> was told of other routes to the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>.</p>
            <p>One of these routes was recommended by an Indian from a tribe that lived to the south. His suggested route led south across a divide between the headwaters of the <name type="place" key="Lemhi (East Fork Lewis's) River">Lemhi</name> and a large river that flowed from southeast to northwest through a barren desert. Beyond this river, still further south, was another large stream that ran in the same direction and had its source near streams that flowed to the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>. The best route, the Indian suggested, would be to follow the second river to its headwaters and then travel to the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name> by way of streams heading near it. This suggested passage, of course, was pure fantasy, and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> rejected it, but not on those grounds. Returning to the macrogeographical concepts of preexploratory days, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> thought that the streams described by the Indian as flowing to the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name> were the Rio Colorado and the mythical Rio des los Apostolos, both of which were believed to flow into the <name type="place" key="Gulf of California">Gulf of California</name> and were much too far south for his purposes.</p>
            <p>A second route was suggested by the <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshones</name>, who described it as difficult but better than following the <name type="place"
                     key="Salmon (Lewis's, Main Fork Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">Salmon</name>. This route led north from their camp on the <name type="place" key="Lemhi (East Fork Jefferson River) River">Lemhi</name>, over huge mountains to a large river that flowed in a northerly direction and, as far as the Indians knew, entered the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> believed this river to be the <name type="place"
                     key="Salmon (Lewis's, Main Fork Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">Salmon</name> after it had emerged from the mountains to the west and then (conjecturally) turned toward the north. He considered this to be the best passage, if the original plans to navigate the <name type="place" key="Lemhi (East Fork Jefferson River) River">Lemhi</name>-<name type="place"
                     key="Salmon (Lewis's, Main Fork Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">Salmon</name> proved unfeasible.<ref target="n22" n="22"/>
            </p>
            <p>The process of decision making at this point illustrates the nature of operations in the new operational zone. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> knew of three possible ways to the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>: the one to the west via the rivers immediately adjacent to the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>'s headwaters; the one recommended by the Indian from the south; and the one to the north to a river believed to be a tributary of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>. If <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had been operating within the same type of operational structure that had characterized the course of exploration from <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name> to the <name type="place" key="Continental Divide">divide</name>, he would probably have accepted the Indians' word that the route to the west was impassable and the one to the north was the best. But he had learned to mistrust the Indian lore; the zones of real and perceived knowledge were no longer as disparate as they had been east of the <name type="place" key="Continental Divide">divide</name>. The method of decision making was therefore based on a combination of macrogeographical knowledge and on the explorer's own conception of the physical features of the region. The route to the west was part of the macrogeographical view, and though the Indians insisted it was impassable, it must be tested. The route to the south was rejected because <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> thought that the waters flowed into the <name type="place" key="Gulf of California">Gulf of California</name>. And the route to the north could be an alternative to the <name type="place" key="Lemhi (East Fork Jefferson River) River">Lemhi</name>-<name type="place"
                     key="Salmon (Lewis's, Main Fork Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">Salmon</name> passage if the latter proved to be impossible.</p>
            <p>By August 24, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had gone far enough down the <name type="place"
                     key="Salmon (Lewis's, Main Fork Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">Salmon</name> to affirm the hopelessness of the passage. Knowing that haste was necessary if the party were successfully to negotiate the mountains before the winter snows, he sent a message to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> suggesting two plans for the crossing. The first was to purchase as many horses as possible from the <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshones</name> and follow the northern route, which the Indians had recommended. The second plan suggested dividing the party into two groups for a double assault on the <name type="place"
                     key="Salmon (Lewis's, Main Fork Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">Salmon River</name> route, one by canoe and one by land. Of the two plans, however, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> preferred the first, since the <name type="place"
                     key="Salmon (Lewis's, Main Fork Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">Salmon</name> country was so extraordinarily difficult.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> concurred with <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>'s choice, and the party began the trek across the massive uplands between the <name type="place" key="Anaconda Mountains">Anaconda</name> and <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Snow) Mountains">Bitterroot</name> ranges of western <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>. The road was a hard one, made treacherous by late-summer snows, but the crossing was made. On September 5 the expedition reached the northward-flowing river, flanked on both east and west by high mountains. Here they made contact with the <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Flathead</name> Indians and began to seek information, knowing that if the river (the <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">Bitterroot</name>) could not be navigated guides must be sought to cross the rugged mountains to the west.</p>
            <p>The captains were quick to recognize that the <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">Bitterroot</name> was not the <name type="place"
                     key="Salmon (Lewis's, Main Fork Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">Salmon</name>, since their course after leaving the <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshone</name> camp had been almost due north and the <name type="place"
                     key="Salmon (Lewis's, Main Fork Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">Salmon</name>'s course had been almost due west. However, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> believed that the <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">Bitterroot</name> was a tributary of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>; the question was, could it he navigated? The Indians could provide little help on this point, but the captains suspected that the river was not navigable. Since there were no salmon in its waters, the existence of a great fall or a long stretch of extremely rough water downstream was, they deduced, quite likely. A trip to the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> by water would have been eminently preferable, but since the chances of navigating the <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">Bitterroot</name> were, in the captains' view, slim, they had no choice but to cross the mighty uplands to the west.</p>
            <p>Before leaving the valley of the <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">Bitterroot</name>, the explorers gained new information from the <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Flathead</name> Indians. Although this provided no directives for the passage to the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>, it changed the captains' understanding of western geography and the nature of their operations during the return journey in 1806. Somewhere along the <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">Bitterroot</name>, according to the Indians, that river was joined by one that came from the east and had its source near a stream that flowed into the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>.<ref target="n23" n="23"/> Only four days, they said, would be necessary to make the crossing from the <name type="place" key="Biitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">Bitterroot</name> to the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> if this route were used. Here was the short portage the captains had been looking for, and though it was not the half-day journey they had anticipated at <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name>, it was much better than the long, circuitous way up the <name type="place" key="Jefferson River(North, Southewest Fork)">Jefferson</name>.<ref target="n24" n="24"/> This knowledge transformed their ideas and testing it was the major objective of the return trip.</p>
            <p>Of more immediate interest, however, was the finding of navigable waters to the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>. Operating on the basis of a combination of Indian directions and their own geographical instincts, the expedition made the long and arduous ascent up the eastern slopes of the <name type="place" key="Bitterroot Range">Bitterroot Range</name> and the equally difficult descent down the western flank into the valley of the <name type="place" key="Lochsa (Upper Kooskooske) River">Lochsa River</name>. By September 22 they had emerged from the mountains, and five days later, after traveling down the <name type="place" key="Lochsa (Upper Kooskooske) River">Lochsa</name> to the <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Clearwater</name> and then down that river to the mouth of its north fork, they began to build dugout canoes. The short portage, so long hoped for and expected, had turned into a month-and-a-half journey of more than four hundred miles over some of the most difficult terrain in North America.</p>
            <p>From the junction of the <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Clearwater</name> and the North Fork, however, travel became much easier. The captains began to feel more confident about reaching the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>, since they began to encounter Indians who possessed objects that obviously derived from European and American sailors on the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name> coast. The <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Clearwater</name> carried them into the <name type="place"
                     key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Snake River</name> and thence to the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>. When on October 19 they recognized the mountains on the western horizon as those shown on the charts of the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name> coast, they were back in a zone of second degree real knowledge. Confidence in their macrogeographical lore of the coastal area of the Northwest increased correspondingly. When they passed through the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> gorge and reached the farthest 

<figure>
                  <p/>
               </figure>

inland penetration of British exploration, they re-entered the real world of first-degree knowledge.<ref target="n25" n="25">25</ref> By early November the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name> was in view, and the expedition prepared to winter on its gray and sodden shores.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="_">
            <head>Zonation of Knowledge at <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name>
            </head>
            <p>On December 24, 1805, the officers and men moved into the small log structure they had erected near the entry of the <name type="place" key="Lewis (Cahwahnakiooks) River">Lewis River</name> into the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>. Here at <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name> they prepared for the long journey home the following spring. Like the winter at <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name>, the winter at <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Clatsop</name> was a time of evaluation of knowledge. But whereas the camp of 1804–1805 had been one in which geographical ideas were formed, the camp of 1805–1806 was one in which the accuracies were sorted out from the inaccuracies of earlier views.</p>
            <p>Throughout the winter the captains worked at making sense out of the lands through which they had traveled. Out of this process of summation came the realization that, with the possible exception of the areas between the <name type="place" key="Bitterroot Valley">Bitterroot Valley</name> and the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> and between the upper <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> and the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone</name>, their knowledge of the country through which they had passed was of the highest quality. Unlike the zonation of knowledge at <name type="place" key="Camp Dubois (Ill.)">Camp Dubois</name> and at <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name>, the picture from <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name> shows a near merging of the zones of real and perceived knowledge (Fig. 7).<ref target="n26" n="26"/> And as the captains wiped out many of the inaccuracies of their earlier views, they came to the conclusion that was the most important outcome of their winter on <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name> shores and, in terms of geographical knowledge, the most important of the entire expedition.</p>
            <p>"We now discover," wrote <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> on February 14, 1806, "that we have found the most practicable and navigable passage across the Continent of North America."<ref target="n27" n="27"/> For all its positive sound, this statement was a negative one. The key to the most practicable passage was the route between the <name type="place" key="Bitterroot Valley">Bitterroot</name> and <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> valleys, which the explorers had learned about from the <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Flatheads</name> the previous September. And in that key was the final destruction of the age-old myth of the
water passage. The core of misconception—the short portage—had been effectively demolished. The captains had made correlations between the zones of real and perceived knowledge, and on the return journey these correlations were tested. The macrogeographical concepts that had guided the trek to the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name> were replaced by more specific lore derived from exploration, lore that could be fitted into the framework of a new image of the West. The new image, though generalized, was much more detailed than any previous image. It is clear from the journals that the captains had begun to think of the West in distinct regional terms, referring to the prairie areas of the lower <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> Valley, the <name type="place" key="Great Plains">Great Plains</name>, the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rockies</name>, the "<name type="place" key="Great Columbian Plain">Great Columbian Plain</name>," the <name type="place" key="Cascade Range">Cascades</name>, and the coastal plain. Earlier views of the West had tended to blur or obliterate any regional differences.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="_">
            <head>The Return</head>
            <p>In late March, 1806, the expedition departed from dreary <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name> to begin a new crossing of the continent. Sometimes by water, more often by land, since the feasibility of a water passage was no longer relevant, the party traveled up the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> to the <name type="place"
                     key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Snake</name>, up the <name type="place"
                     key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Snake</name> to the <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Clearwater</name>, and then to the massive <name type="place" key="Bitterroot Range">Bitterroot Range</name>. Once across the range and down into the valley of the <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">Bitterroot River</name>, testing began of the conclusions worked out at <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name>.</p>
            <p>The expedition separated in the <name type="place" key="Bitterroot Valley">Bitterroot Valley</name>, hoping to eliminate the only segments of the area covered on their outward journey that still were, and were recognized to be, regions of second- or third-degree knowledge. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and nine men crossed the mountains east of the <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">Bitterroot River</name> and steered for the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> by the route that the <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Flatheads</name> had told them was the shortest and best way from the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> to the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> and the rest of the force retraced the route of the previous summer to the cache at the mouth of <name type="place" key="Horse Prairie Creek (West Fork Jefferson River)">Horse Prairie Creek</name>. Here some of the men took canoes and supplies down the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> to meet <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, while <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> and his party crossed the <name type="place" key="Continental Divide">divide</name> between the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> and the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone</name> and traveled down that river to its junction with the Missouri.</p>
            <p>Near the middle of August, the captains were reunited. The return journey had accomplished its purpose. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>'s trip across the <name type="place" key="Continental Divide">divide</name> had confirmed the nature of the shortest route across the mountains. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>'s journey had added knowledge about the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone</name>, filling in the last remaining gaps in the captains' understanding of the upper <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> drainage.<ref target="n28" n="28"/> From the reunion near the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone</name>, the trip was all downhill, both literally and figuratively, and the expedition reached <name type="place" key="St. Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> on September 23, 1806.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> returned to civilization with information about the area along their traverse that was both accurate and understood to be so. Their journey added immeasurably to geographical knowledge of the West, an achievement that would not have been possible had it not been for the captains' ability to distinguish between the accuracy of the imagination and the accuracy of reality, and thus to make their expedition an effective agent in the expansion of geographical knowledge. Preexisting and generalized lore, earlier believed to be accurate, had been modified and replaced by specific knowledge, which in turn was eventually interpreted in the light of a new set of generalized concepts about the Northwest and fitted into it. The zones of real knowledge and of perceived knowledge were merged through effective exploration.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had gone west in search of a macrogeographical dream. They had believed in the components of the dream—the navigability of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> to its source, the short portage across a narrow ridge of mountains, and the teleological certainty of finding navigable waters on the Pacific slope. But experiences during the exploratory process had eroded the dream elements and had helped to fill the map. In the new image of the West were explicit notions about the impossibility of navigation on mountain rivers, the bounty of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> Valley and the <name type="place" key="Great Plains">Great Plains</name>, the snow and ice of the high passes, and the massive complex of mountains that resembled the dream range of earlier days only in name. But perhaps the most important feature of the new image was something that was not there—the Passage to <name type="place" key="India">India</name>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="_">
            <note xml:id="n01" n="1"> This concept was introduced in John K. Wright's seminal study of medieval science and tradition, "Geographical Lore of the Time of the Crusades," <hi rend="italic">Amer. Geogr. Soc. Research Ser. No. 15</hi> (New York, 1925): 256–257.</note>
            <note xml:id="n02" n="2"> John K. Wright. "Terrae Incognitae: The Place of the Imagination in Geography", <hi rend="italic">Annals Assn. of Amer. Geogrs</hi> (1947): 37, 1–15; Yi-Fu Tuan. "Attitudes toward Environment: Themes and Approaches", in <hi rend="italic">Environmental Perception and Behavior</hi> ed. David Lowenthal, (Chicago: Univ. of Chicago, Dept. of Geography), (1967): Research Paper No. 109, 4–17.</note>
            <note xml:id="n03" n="3"> Wright, "Geographical Lore of the Time of the Crusades" [see footnote 1 above]: 257. Operating from the vantage point of the present, Wright used this classification to describe the knowledge available to the reasonably well-informed Western European during the period A.D. 1100–1250.</note>
            <note xml:id="n04" n="4"> Research findings that support this statement may be found in recent psychological literature; see, for example, Jerome Bruner. "On Going Beyond the Information Given", in <hi rend="italic">The Cognitive Processes: Readings</hi> ed. Robert J. Harper and others; (Englewood Cliffs, N. J., 1964), 293–510; and John R. Kirk: "The Distortion of Information", <hi rend="italic">Etc.: A Review of General Semantics</hi> 17 (1959): 5–27.</note>
            <note xml:id="n05" n="5"> The term "exploratory behavior," as used in this paper, refers to the field operations during exploration. Field operations include the manner in which information is acquired; establishment of proposed routes and courses; decisions made about the sources of food, types of transportation, and locations for campsites and caches of materials; and on-site observations and conclusions relative to landmarks, distances, and proposed routes of travel.</note>
            <note xml:id="n06" n="6"> The basic sources for the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition are Reuben Gold Thwaites, ed.: <hi rend="italic">Original Journals of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition, 1804–1806</hi> (8 vols.; New York: Dodd, Mead, &amp; Company, 1904–1905); [<name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Nicholas Biddle</name>] and Paul Allen, eds.: <hi rend="italic">History of the Expedition under the Command of Captains <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>
               </hi> (2 vols., Philadelphia: Bradford and Inskeep; New York: A. H. Inskeep, 1814); Ernest Staples Osgood, ed.: <hi rend="italic">The Field Notes of <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain William Clark</name>, 1803–1805</hi> (New Haven: Yale University Press, 1964). Both the Thwaites and the so–called <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name> journals are available in more recent editions: the Thwaites journals were reissued in 1959 by Antiquarian Press of New York; the <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name> journals, re-edited by Elliot Coues, were published in 1893 (and reissued by Dover Press, 1965); another edition of the <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name> journals (reprinted directly from the 1814 edition) is available in the Keystone Western Americana Series (3 vols., Philadelphia: Lippincott, 1961). Also of considerable interest is Bernard DeVoto's masterfully edited condensation of the Thwaites journals (with some added material from <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>), "The Journals of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>" (Boston: Houghton Mifflin, 1953). No listing of source material would be complete without reference to Donald Jackson's compilation of nearly all the known correspondence and documentary material relating to the expedition ("Letters of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition: With Related Documents, 1783–1854" [Urbana, Ill.: University of Illinois Press, 1962]).</note>
            <note xml:id="n07" n="7">
               <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>'s instructions to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, June 19, 1803 (<name type="place" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> Papers, Library of Congress Manuscripts Division, Vol. 132, folios 22884–22887).</note>
            <note xml:id="n08" n="8"> The source materials available to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> prior to May, 1804, are in three categories: those supplied by <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>; those acquired by <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> before his departure from <name type="place" key="Washington D.C.">Washington</name>; and those gathered by <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> during the winter at <name type="place" key="Camp Dubois (Ill.)">Camp Dubois</name> (for a complete, documented list, see John I. Allen: <hi rend="italic">Geographical Images of the American Northwest, 1673–1806</hi> [unpublished Ph.D. dissertation, Graduate School of Geography, Clark University, 1969]). In addition, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> must have obtained oral data from residents of the <name type="place" key="St. Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> area, from fur trappers and traders, and from others, but it is impossible to determine the nature of this material.</note>
            <note xml:id="n09" n="9"> The assessment of the captains' opinions about the quality of their information must rest on the documentary materials of the expedition. The two cardinal measures of perceived knowledge that I have used are content analysis of the daily journals and correspondence for references to specific items of information and for indications that certain materials were being used, and definite statements by either <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> or <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> on the merits of the information. Where such information is lacking, inferences have been based on extensive research.</note>
            <note xml:id="n10" n="10"> Good evidence for this statement can be found in the distance calculations for the country between the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name> and the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name> that <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> drew up during the winter at <name type="place" key="Camp Dubois (Ill.)">Camp Dubois</name> (Osgood, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.</hi> [see footnote 6 above] pp. 19–20). In estimating the distances between the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name> and the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> villages, between the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name> and the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rockies</name>, and between the mountains and the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>, it is clear that <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> was relying on cartographic and documentary materials presenting only conjectural data on the interior.</note>
            <note xml:id="n11" n="11"> Their belief in the short portage appears in the distance calculations. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> allowed no mileage for crossing the mountains. He assumed that the distance from the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> villages to the mountains was the same as the distance from the villages to the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>'s source. He assumed as well that the distance from the mountains to the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>, via some river flowing toward the west, was the same as the distance from the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name> "to the river" (the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>). Further substantiation may be found in estimates of the time that would be required to reach the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name> (<hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., 19–21).</note>
            <note xml:id="n12" n="12"> Employees of the Northwest Fur Company who lived at the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> villages were able to provide accurate information that was of high quality for the country as far west as the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone</name>. A more important source of information were the <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Minnetaree</name> Indians who carried out raids as far west as the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rockies</name> and beyond, primarily to steal horses from the <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshones</name>. Because of their familiarity with the area of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>'s source waters, they were able to describe many landmarks and to give rather precise instructions on a route across the mountains (Thwaites, <hi rend="italic">op. cit</hi>. [sec footnote 6 above], Vol. 1, 209, 227, 238, 245–246). The information was good but must he considered as intermediate in quality because of the difficulties that the captains had in translating Indian concepts of distance and direction into their own conceptual framework.</note>
            <note xml:id="n13" n="13">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> commented that the information obtained had been carefully compared and was "entitled to some confidence" (Thwaites, <hi rend="italic">op. cit</hi>. [see footnote 6 above], Vol. 6, 50).</note>
            <note xml:id="n14" n="14">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> noted that they had not been able "to acquire any information further West than" just beyond the dividing range of the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rockies</name> (Thwaites, <hi rend="italic">op. cit</hi>. [see footnote 6 above], Vol. 6, 55).</note>
            <note xml:id="n15" n="15"> Thwaites, <hi rend="italic">op. cit</hi>. [see footnote 6 above], Vol. 2, 10.</note>
            <note xml:id="n16" n="16"> Their distance estimates were based on the calculations that <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had made at <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name> for mileages between the villages and the <name type="place" key="Continental Divide">Continental Divide</name> (<hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., Vol. 6, 60).</note>
            <note xml:id="n17" n="17">
               <hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>., Vol. 2. p. 109. Sec also John L. Allen: <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> on the Upper <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>: Decision at the <name type="place" key="Marias River">Marias</name>, <hi rend="italic">Montana: The Magazine of Western History</hi>. 22: 3, (1971): 2–17.</note>
            <note xml:id="n18" n="18"> Thwaites, <hi rend="italic">op. cit</hi>. [see footnote 6 above], Vol. 2, 112–113.</note>
            <note xml:id="n19" n="19"> "What astonishes us a little is that the Indians who appeared to be so well acquainted with the geography of this country should not have mentioned this river" (<hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., Vol. 2, 115).</note>
            <note xml:id="n20" n="20"> Basic to their decision here was the course of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> as shown on their Arrowsmith map and as described in the Mackay–Evans journals. Both sources indicated a southwestern source for the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> (<hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., Vol. 2, 132).</note>
            <note xml:id="n21" n="21">
               <hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>., Vol. 2, 134.</note>
            <note xml:id="n22" n="22"> "My rout was instantly settled in my own mind, p[r]ovided the account of this river should prove true on an investigation of it" (Thwaites, <hi rend="italic">op. cit</hi>. [see footnote 6 above], Vol. 2, 382).</note>
            <note xml:id="n23" n="23"> The river flowing from the east is the main branch of <name type="place"
                     key="Clark Fork (Clark's, East Fork Clark's, Flathead) River">Clark Fork</name> of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>, called the <name type="place" key="Missoula, Mont.">Missoula</name> where it is joined by the <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">Bitterroot</name> and the <name type="place" key="Hellgate River">Hellgate</name> and <name type="place" key="Big Blackfoot River">Big Blackfoot</name> in its upper reaches. It heads near the <name type="place" key="Dearborn River">Dearborn River</name>, which (lows into the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> above the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">Great Falls</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24" n="24"> To get from the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">Great Falls</name> to the <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Flathead</name> camp on the <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">Bitterroot</name>, the expedition had traveled more than 700 miles. The route the Indians suggested from the <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">Bitterroot</name> to the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">Great Falls</name> was approximately 170 miles.</note>
            <note xml:id="n25" n="25"> After the coastal ranges were sighted a behavioral change becomes apparent in the journals; for geographical description and commentary diminished considerably. The captains now knew exactly where they were, and consequently they no longer sought geographical data from the Indians.</note>
            <note xml:id="n26" n="26"> This statement is true only for the areas that they had traversed. They still had a fuzzy and inaccurate picture of the southern waters of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> and of the entire Southwest.</note>
            <note xml:id="n27" n="27"> Thwaites, <hi rend="italic">op. cit</hi>. [see footnote 6 above], Vol. 4, 70.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28" n="28"> It must be noted that although <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> determined the nature of the divide area between the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> and <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone</name> valleys, a great deal of the information he presented on the upper parts of the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone</name> was simply a restating of descriptions obtained from the Indians at <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name> more than a year earlier.</note>
            <p>Dr. Allen is assistant professor of geography at the University of Connecticut, Storrs.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
