<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.sup.johnsgard.01.preface">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Lewis and Clark on the Great Plains</title>
            <title type="sub">A Natural History</title>
            <title type="sub" level="a">Preface</title>
            <author>Paul A. Johnsgard</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title level="m" type="main">Lewis and Clark on the <name type="place" key="Great Plains">Great Plains</name>
               </title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">Preface</title>
               <author>Paul A. Johnsgard</author>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <publisher>Center for Great Plains Studies, University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
               <date>2003</date>
               <idno type="ISBN">0-8032-7618-4</idno>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Supplements</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Plant and Animal Images</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic"/>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-10-07</date>
            <date>2004-10-26</date>
            <name>Becky Potter</name>
            <name>Andrew Jewell</name>Split into chapters Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="preface" type="preface">
            <head rend="center">Preface</head>
            <p>The purpose of this book is to identify and describe the <name type="place" key="Great Plains">Great Plains</name> animals and
plants that were encountered and described by <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> and their Corps
of Discovery two centuries ago during their famous exploratory expedition of
the Louisiana Purchase territories. It also attempts to place both the organisms
they discovered in an ecological framework and these two explorers in a historical
context as biologists. It is intended to serve as a bicentennial tribute to this
remarkable exploration of the then-unknown lands comprising the Louisiana
Purchase. The bicentennial of this epic journey seems an especially appropriate
time to review and marvel at the expedition's accomplishments, and to reflect
on the changes in the land and its associated biota that have occurred during
the subsequent two hundred years of American history. </p>
            <p>The animals selected for inclusion in this survey represent as many as possible
of the identifiable species of vertebrates that were initially described, or at
least apparently discovered, by the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> expedition while crossing
the <name type="place" key="Great Plains">Great Plains</name> as well as those previously known species that were described
in sufficient detail to permit identification with some degree of confidence.
Special attention has been given to those animal species encountered by the
Corps of Discovery that were previously unknown, or ones for which important
new biological information was obtained during the expedition. However,
a few distinctly western and montane-adapted animals such as the blue grouse
(<hi rend="italic">Dendragapus obscurus</hi>) and pinyon jay (<hi rend="italic">Gymnorhinus cyanocephalus</hi>) were excluded.
Both of these forest-adapted birds were encountered at the very edge
of the <name type="place" key="Great Plains">Great Plains</name> in western <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>. A few additional western or northern
species, such as the Columbian ground squirrel, lynx, and moose, were likewise
deemed to be of doubtful species identification or of questionable geographic
affinities. These species have been included in the survey, but their names are
set off by parentheses. </p>
            <p>The plants chosen for inclusion in the text represent all those species collected
on the <name type="place" key="Great Plains">Great Plains</name> and preserved as herbarium specimens that are
known to be still extant. Selecting the western limits of the <name type="place" key="Great Plains">Great Plains</name> in order
to decide which plant species to include was a subjective exercise, but those
species whose ranges fall largely or entirely outside the coverage of the <hi rend="italic">Atlas of
the Flora of the <name type="place" key="Great Plains">Great Plains</name>
               </hi> were excluded. These include antelope bush (<hi rend="italic">Purshia
tridentata</hi>), golden currant (<hi rend="italic">Ribes aureum</hi>), moundscale (<hi rend="italic">Atriplex gardneri</hi>),
and common monkey-flower (<hi rend="italic">Mimulus guttatus</hi>). The comments made
in the text as to Native American ritual or medicinal uses of plants derive mostly
from Gilmore (1977) and Kindscher (1992); the latter reference is especially valuable
as to plant medicinal properties. </p>
            <p>This summary of the animals and plants encountered by <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>
is organized in three parts, corresponding to three broad and roughly equal
geographic regions, at least in terms of river distances traveled. Accompanying
the summary are maps of the major campsites and associated dates spent by the
Corps of Discovery in each of these three regions. The Corps spent much more
time exploring during the upstream, outward-bound phase in 1804 and 1805
than during the return journey, and this first part of the expedition was by far
the richest from a biological standpoint. Almost no new species were discovered
during the return trip in 1806, and the associated campsites are not mapped. </p>
            <p>In general, the animals and plants that the expedition encountered are described
only for that phase of the expedition where they were first encountered.
However, a few especially important mammals (e.g., bison, pronghorn, elk,
wolf, and grizzly bear) are discussed in two or all three of the geographic regions
recognized here. Names of present-day states or counties as well as current
town locations have often been used to provide convenient geographic reference
points for the reader. Included are drawings of all the certainly discovered or initially well-
described vertebrates, as well as some representative plants, especially
species of genera having special ritual or medicinal value for Native Americans,
such as <hi rend="italic">Artemisia</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Juniperus</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Nicotiana</hi>. The names used in the text for Native
American tribes are modern ones, although alternate names used by <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>
and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> are typically shown parenthetically. </p>
            <p>When this book had nearly gone to press, H. Wayne Phillips's <hi rend="italic">Plants of the
<name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition</hi> (2003) appeared. He illustrated more than 80 tallgrass
and high-plains species, including some that are not included here because
herbarium specimens are not known to exist. </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.johnsgard.01.ill" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.johnsgard.01.00" type="contents"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.johnsgard.01.ack" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
