<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.sup.lavender.01.20">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Way to the Western Sea</title>
            <title type="sub">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> across the Continent</title>
            <title type="sub" level="a">Chapter 20</title>
            <author>David Lavender</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2005</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Way to the Western Sea</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">Chapter 20</title>
               <author>David Lavender</author>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>2001</date>
               <idno type="ISBN">0-8032-8003-3</idno>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Supplements</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Texts</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic"/>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-11-09</date>
            <date>2005-04-20</date>
            <name>Becky Potter</name>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Split into chapters Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="twenty" type="chapter">
            <head rend="center">TWENTY. Endings</head>
            <div type="section">
               <p>
The captains began their reportage with three letters whose differing contents and tones indicate careful thinking about how and to whom they wanted to spread the word of their discoveries. (Actually four such letters have survived. The first, however, dated September 21, 1806, and written in a wobbly hand that suggests it was composed on a moving boat, is very pedestrian and breaks off abruptly, as if the author, probably <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name>, decided 
its style would not meet requirements.) The first of the other calculated letters was, not surprisingly, a preliminary report to <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">President Jefferson</name>.<ref target="n2001" n="1"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Dated <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>, September 23, 1806, it announced the party's safe arrival and stated that <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> had held up the regular mail in order to dispatch the missive without delay. Its handwriting is shaky, too, as if <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> had started composing it on the pirogue before the expedition reached <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> journal fleshes out the skeleton somewhat. It says that after learning the mail for the East had already left, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> rushed a note across the river to <name type="place" key="Cahokia, Ill.">Cahokia</name> with a request that the postmaster there, <name type="person" key="Hay, John">John Hay</name>, hold the rider for twenty-four hours. With the need for hurry somewhat relieved, the captains found storage space for their baggage and rooms for themselves. They then called on the Chouteaus and sat up late, talking and talking. "however we rose early [on the 24th, says <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>] and commenced wrighting our letters. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt Lewis</name> wrote one to the presidend . . ." after which the ever-dependable <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">George Drouillard</name> delivered the correspondence, posthaste, to <name type="person" key="Hay, John">Hay</name> in <name type="place" key="Cahokia, Ill.">Cahokia</name>.</p>
               <p>
The first really informative letter about the new land—it couldn't cover everything. So what would <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> like to learn first?</p>
               <p>
We can imagine <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> mentally reviewing the formal list of instructions <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> had handed him on June 20, 1803, more than three years before. We can imagine his memory latching onto this: "The object of your mission is to explore the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri river</name>, &amp; such principal stream of it, as, by it's course &amp; communication with the waters of the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific Ocean</name>, may offer the most direct &amp; practicable water communication across this continent, for the purpose of commerce."</p>
               <p>
And so the second sentence of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> letter reads, "In obedience to your orders we have penitrated the continent of North America to the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific Ocean</name>, and sufficiently explored the interior of the country to affirm with confidence that we have discovered the most practicable rout which does exist across the continent by means of the navigable branches of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> and <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> Rivers." He described the route as modified by his return over <name type="place" key="Lewis and Clark Pass">Lewis and Clark Pass</name>. Travelers should go by boat 2,575 miles up the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> past caving banks and difficult snags to the foot of the rapids below the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">Great Falls</name>. There they would leave the river for 340 miles of land travel. Two hundred of those miles were not particularly difficult. But then came 140 miles across "tremendious mountains which for 60 miles are covered with eternal snow"—though not so eternal they couldn't be surmounted during the summer months. Fortunately the horses needed for the land section of the journey could be obtained from the Indians at trifling cost. The last leg of the journey consisted of 640 boat miles down the <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Clearwater</name>, <name type="place"
                        key="Snake (Ki-moo-enim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Snake</name>, and <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia river</name>s to the ocean, a stretch broken only by the three roaring cascades of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> could imagine <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name> expression on reading all that. The president had presupposed an easy passage across a low <name type="place" key="Continental Divide">continental divide</name> to a short run down the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>, with no intervening falls, to the sea. The explorers had sent him nothing from <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name> in April 1805 to prepare him for reality. And so <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> tried to soften the blow. Although he granted that merchants handling bulky or brittle Oriental goods consigned to either the East Coast of the United States or Europe would continue using the sea lanes around the <name type="place" key="Cape of Good Hope">Cape of Good Hope</name>, still "we view this passage across the Continent as affording immence advantages to the fur trade."</p>
               <p>
How valuable was that trade? <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> dashed off what became the most frequently quoted sentence he ever wrote: "The <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> and all it's branches from the <name type="native_nation" key="Cheyenne Indians">Chyenne</name> upwards abound in more beaver and Common Otter, than any other streams on earth, particularly that proportion of them lying within the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky Mountains</name>." He also flattered <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name> perspicacity. The president had suggested in his secret message to Congress on January 18, 1803, 
the possibility of diverting Canadian furs to America's Eastern ports by way of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> and <name type="place" key="Ohio River">Ohio</name> rivers. His instructions to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> had, in effect, asked the explorer to study the feasibility of the idea. In the part of the letter that reported on the study, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> suggested reversing the pattern. A run of fewer than a thousand miles down the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> and its tributaries was preferable to one of four thousand or more miles down the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> and on across the <name type="place" key="Appalachian Mountains">Appalachian Mountains</name> to the <name type="place" key="Atlantic Ocean">Atlantic</name>. After all, one of the best markets for furs, as Yankee ship traders had learned many years before, was China and the <name type="place" key="East Indies">East Indies</name>. "If the government," he concluded, "will only aid, even in a very limited manner, the enterprize of her Citizens I am fully convinced that we shal shortly derive the benefits of a most lucrative trade from this source, and that in the course of ten or twelve years a tour across the Continent by the rout mentioned will be undertaken by individuals with as little concern as a voyage across the <name type="place" key="Atlantic Ocean">Atlantic</name> is at present."</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> did not mention that <name type="person" key="Mackenzie, Alexander">Alexander Mackenzie</name> was also proposing that the British government support a similar export route by way of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>.<ref target="n2002" n="2"/> (He did not have to. Both <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> and he had read <name type="person" key="Mackenzie, Alexander">Mackenzie's</name> book.) However, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> did warn the president about the expanded activities of <name type="place" key="Canada">Canada's</name> North West Company on the upper <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>. "The strides of this company ... cannot be too vigorously watched nor too firmly and speedily opposed by our government." The more truculent Indians along the way, he added, also needed attention, a matter he would go into more fully when he saw <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>.</p>
               <p>
So there it was: the route, its potential value, and something of its problems. That letter on its way, he turned his attention to composing, with <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, another letter aimed at different readers. The best way to disseminate information in those days was through local newspapers. <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> might not see fit to show the press <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> letter to him, peppered as it was with anti-British sentiments. (<name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> already knew from what he had learned on the 
<name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> that relations between the countries were strained again.) But other recipients could be counted on to pass along a more circumspect letter to frontier editors they knew would be friendly. Accordingly <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> drafted and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> copied, also under date of September 23, 1806, a letter to "Dear Brother," an addressee who may have been either <name type="person" key="Clark, George Rogers">George Rogers Clark</name> or <name type="person" key="Clark, Jonathan">Jonathan Clark</name>, both of whom lived near <name type="place" key="Louisville, Ky.">Louisville</name>, <name type="place" key="Kentucky">Kentucky</name>. This letter repeated most of what <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> had told <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> about the route but went into more detail about what they had experienced along the way. It mentioned the help given the expedition by some of the Indians, briefly described <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name>, and brushed off the return journey with a statement that familiarity with the land and people had greatly lessened the kind of hunger and fatigue they had experienced on the outward journey. There was no mention of either British competition or of Indian hostilities. Such a letter, landing in a <name type="place" key="Kentucky">Kentucky</name> newspaper, would spread to other frontier papers and put pressure on the government as a whole to pay more attention to the feat than might otherwise be the case. More attention would mean more credit and perhaps greater rewards to all the Corps's personnel, captains and enlisted men both.</p>
               <p>
The third letter, written by <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> under the date September 29, 1806, is much longer than the others and something of a mystery. The addressee is unknown, the original document has been lost, and only a garbled replica survives. Even so, it may reveal more about <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> fatal character flaws than its predecessors do.</p>
               <p>
The purpose of this letter almost surely was like that of the others—to bring the accomplishments of the expedition to the attention of a particular class of readers. The chief difference between it and the others is a long account of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> experiences with <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfoot</name> Indians along the <name type="place" key="Marias River">Marias River</name>. In accounting for that bloody northern detour, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> does not refer even indirectly to the hope, dwelt on in his journals, of bringing about peace between the <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name> and the Western Indians. Instead he says he went there, "at every hazard," to find out whether the <name type="place" key="Marias River">Marias River</name> extended as far north as latitude 49°37'N.</p>
               <p>
Latitude 49°37' seems a curious figure to pop up here. It arose originally because of the geographic ignorance of the diplomats who, in 1783, hammered out the Treaty of Paris, which officially closed the American Revolution. After much haggling, the negotiators specified that the boundary between the United States and Britain's North American possessions should follow a complex of canoe waterways from <name type="place" key="Lake Superior">Lake Superior</name> to <name type="place" key="Lake of the Woods">Lake of the Woods</name>; "then through the said lake to the northwestern point thereof [later determined to be latitude 49°37' and still later as 49°24'], and from thence on a <hi rend="italic">due west</hi> course [emphasis added] to the river <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name>." The south-flowing <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name> would then serve as the boundary between the United States and Spanish Louisiana.</p>
               <p>
The trouble with this was that the headwaters of the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name> lay <hi rend="italic">south</hi>, not west, of <name type="place" key="Lake of the Woods">Lake of the Woods</name>. Some day some kind of rectification would have to be made. Until that happened, the handful of Indian traders who ranged through the area would have to conduct their business as best they could, meanwhile suggesting lines of demarcation that would suit their own interests.</p>
               <p>
The North West Company wanted the boundary line drawn south from the northwest corner of the lake to the headwaters of the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name>—or at least as far south as the forty-ninth parallel of latitude. In 1797 the partners in that firm sent their great geographer and explorer, <name type="person" key="Thompson, David">David Thompson</name>, into the area to find the forty-ninth parallel and learn where the company's southernmost trading posts stood in respect to that line. For it seems the Canadian company had (or <name type="person" key="Thompson, John B.">Thompson</name> thought it had) an understanding with <name type="place" key="Spain">Spain</name> that the forty-ninth parallel should serve as an arbitrary boundary separating the northern watershed of Upper <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name> from the southern watershed of the <name type="place" key="Saskatchewan River">Saskatchewan</name>.<ref target="n2003" n="3"/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> must have learned many of these things during their frequent conversations with North West Company traders during the winter of 1804–5 while they were in the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> towns collecting information about the upper <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> for <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> map. Surely <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> felt that as an official explorer of Upper <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name>, he should follow through by discovering where the bounds of the territory were.</p>
               <p>
He had made a start of sorts when scouting the <name type="place" key="Marias River">Marias</name> in the summer of 1805 to determine whether it was the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>. On his return in 1806 he had crowded his luck to go there with only three companions on a double errand: to urge peace on the <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name> and to determine whether the <name type="place" key="Marias River">Marias</name> reached as high as 49°37'. If he 
found that some of the river's tributaries did reach that far north, he would peg the place on <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> map. It would be a figure for negotiators to work with when deciding on the boundary between British and American holdings. If his finding was accepted as the line, it would bring the United States a little more territory than a line drawn along the forty-ninth parallel. Best of all, it would push his country close to the tributaries of the <name type="place" key="South Saskatchewan River">South Saskatchewan</name>, which he had come to regard as a magic gateway to the prime fur country of northwestern Canada. Foreign pelts pouring through his native land for transshipment down the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> to the Orient and the rest of the world-that, too, would be part of the trade picture he eventually presented to <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Thomas Jefferson</name>.</p>
               <p>
The <name type="place" key="Marias River">Marias</name>, however, did not reach that high. He candidly admitted as much in his letter to the unknown correspondent. Perhaps to assuage his disappointment, he let the addressee know his quest for truth had not been without peril. His small party, he wrote, ran into <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name> who "treacherously seized on &amp; made themselves masters of all our Guns—in which Situation we engaged them with our Knives &amp; our Pistol recovered our guns &amp; killed two of them &amp; put the others to flight, pursued them retook our Horses. . . . Fearing pursuit from 2 large Bands whom the Indians had informed us on the evening before were in our neighborhood, we hastened to the <name type="place" key="Marias River">Rivers Maria</name> &amp; <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missesourii</name>."</p>
               <p>
The <name type="place" key="Marias River">River Maria</name>. The <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missesourii</name>. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> never used either form. He would never have made other mistakes in proper nouns, mileage figures, and so on that appear in the letter that has survived. In other words, the original had been copied by someone—probably by several people—before one of the duplicates landed in the hands of <name type="person" key="Thompson, David">David Thompson</name>, from whose papers in the public library of <name type="person" key="Vancouver, George">Vancouver</name>, <name type="place" key="British Columbia">British Columbia</name>, it was abstracted by researchers. <name type="person" key="Thompson, David">Thompson</name> and other Nor'Westers, incidentally, did habitually use the spelling Missisourie or slight variations thereof. Almost surely Canadians were among those who copied the original.</p>
               <p>
To whom was the original addressed? Donald Dean Jackson, close student of the expedition, has suggested, among others, <name type="person" key="Hay, John">John Hay</name>, postmaster of <name type="place" key="Cahokia, Ill.">Cahokia</name>.<ref target="n2004" n="4"/> I agree. <name type="person" key="Hay, John">Hay</name>, a former Canadian trader, was also a supplier of goods to fur traders working along the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name> and <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, many of whom had taken out American citizenship papers in order to obtain licenses. He had provided <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> with translations, goods, and geographic information while they were preparing to embark from <name type="place" key="Camp Dubois (Camp Wood, River Dubois) (Ill.)">Camp Wood</name> in 1804. Jackson, however, does not feel <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, aware of the anti-British sentiments of the time, would have given <name type="person" key="Hay, John">Hay</name> a letter that might be passed on to Canadians. I wonder. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> had left a U.S. medal hanging around the neck of one of the <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name> his party had slain so the Indians—and, inevitably, their white traders along the <name type="place" key="Saskatchewan River">Saskatchewan</name>—"might be informed who we were." <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> and he had carved their names on several trees on both sides of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia's</name> estuary so that whoever came along later would be informed of the American presence. I think he would have liked Britons to know he had been investigating potential boundary lines as a part of his assignment. American traders should know it, too, for they would expect that sort of information as they spread out through the fur paradise he was reporting. The third letter he wrote in <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>, then, may well have been intended for the trading fraternity, a group unlikely to be reached by his other initial correspondence concerning the expedition's accomplishments.</p>
               <p>
Letters, of course, contained only a small part of what the captains hoped to put before the public. They planned to draw from their journals one volume of narrative about their travels, another about the Indians of the West, and a third about their scientific investigations of the terrain, the climates they encountered, botany, zoology, and so on. Plus a large map drawn by <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, showing details never before recorded about the American West and some 
of its contiguous lands. All this was in their minds when they left <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> for the East late in October. A big cavalcade accompanied them: various important <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> figures; <name type="person" key="Big White (Sheheke)">Sheheke's</name> family (in <name type="place" key="Washington D. C.">Washington</name> the chief and his wife would be called the King and Queen of the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>); <name type="person" key="Jusseaume, René">Jessaume's</name> family; a delegation of <name type="native_nation" key="Osage Indians">Osage Indians</name> shepherded by <name type="person" key="Chouteau, Pierre">Pierre Chouteau</name>; and <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> and <name type="person" key="Labiche, François">Labiche</name> in charge of a packtrain loaded with the party's baggage and whatever plants, seeds, bird skins, animal skeletons, and furs had not been ruined in water-soaked caches.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> and <name type="person" key="York">York</name> halted in <name type="place" key="Louisville, Ky.">Louisville</name> for a reunion with <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> family; afterwards <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> continued to <name type="place" key="Fincastle, Va.">Fincastle</name>, <name type="place" key="Virginia">Virginia</name>, north of <name type="place" key="Roanoke, Va.">Roanoke</name>, to see how <name type="person" key="Hancock, Julia">Julia Hancock</name>, who had delighted him when she was a child of twelve, had developed. He had named the <name type="place" key="Judith River">Judith River</name> in <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name> for her, which prompts an interesting speculation. How well had he known her when he was thirty-three and she had first made an impression on him? Had he heard her nickname Julie as Judy?</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> pressed on to his home at <name type="place" key="Ivy Creek (Va.)">Ivy Creek</name>, <name type="place" key="Albemarle County, Va.">Albemarle County</name>, <name type="place" key="Virginia">Virginia</name>, near <name type="place" key="Monticello (Va.)">Monticello</name>. After spending Christmas with his mother, he continued to <name type="place" key="Washington D. C.">Washington</name>, where <name type="person" key="Chouteau, Pierre">Chouteau</name> had already arrived with his Usages. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, his mind dazzled with thoughts of <name type="person" key="Hancock, Julia">Julia</name>, rejoined him in the capital city sometime after the middle of January. They had a great deal of business to do and debriefings to attend, though the sessions weren't called that then. There were 
fetes, banquets, balls, and less formal dances at which <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> may well have consumed more liquor than was good for him.<ref target="n2005" n="5"/> Then came the climactic rewards. Like the enlisted men of the expedition, each captain (they would soon resign their commissions) received double pay while on service with the Corps—it came to $1,228 apiece. They also received warrants to 1,600 acres each as compared to the 320 acres awarded the soldiers. If they chose not to select their allotments from the public domain, they could sell the warrants for whatever land speculators would pay, sometimes as much as $2 an acre.<ref target="n2006" n="6"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Much more important was <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> double appointment as brigadier general of militia and superintendent of Indian affairs for the Territory of Upper <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name>. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> was named governor of the same territory.<ref target="n20unnumbered" n="*"/> The territorial secretary and, in effect, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> lieutenant governor was <name type="person" key="Bates, Frederick">Frederick Bates</name>, whose brother, <name type="person" key="Bates, Tarleton">Tarleton Bates</name>, had been a close friend of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> during pre-expedition days. The appointments came through early in March 1807. On March 10, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> and <name type="person" key="Bates, Frederick">Bates</name> left <name type="place" key="Washington D. C.">Washington</name> for <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> by way of <name type="place" key="Fincastle, Va.">Fincastle</name> and <name type="person" key="Hancock, Julia">Julia Hancock's</name> home. Clearly the brigadier general of militia was smitten by the young woman, by then sixteen or close to it.</p>
               <p>
Not so <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name>. He caught a raging fever in <name type="place" key="Washington D. C.">Washington</name> while helping nurse <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name> son-in-law, <name type="person" key="Randolph, Thomas">Thomas Randolph</name>. On recovering he traveled to <name type="place" key="Philadelphia, Pa.">Philadelphia</name> to find a publisher for his and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> joint venture into literary production. For a time the business went swimmingly. He obtained the services of a reputable publisher, C. and A. Conrad &amp; Co., lined up the famed doctor and philosopher, <name type="person" key="Barton, Benjamin">Benjamin Barton</name>, to act as editor of the scientific volume, and hired a battery of famous artists and naturalists to illustrate the animals, plants, birds, and natural wonders that would he discussed in the tome.</p>
               <p>
While he was engaged in those affairs and also sitting for at least three portraits, two other accounts of the expedition were announced. One was by <name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">Private Robert Frazer</name> and the other by <name type="person" key="McKeehan, David">David McKeehan</name>, who had purchased <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Sergeant Gass's</name> journal and proposed to bring it out in refined, heavily edited prose. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> promptly defended his and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> interests by running paid newspaper stories depreciating all such efforts as being written by 
unqualified men. Nothing more was heard of <name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">Frazer's</name> proposal, perhaps because of financial difficulties. <name type="person" key="McKeehan, David">McKeehan</name>, however, responded with stinging sarcasm. "Did your Excellency never attend to the advice given those who have glass houses? Were you afraid that some persons affected by your publication might inform the public that you were not a man of science, that you were not a man of letters, and that you were not qualified for scientific research?"<ref target="n2007" n="7"/> And he went right ahead with <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass's</name> book, pretty well drowning in long sequences of bland sentences whatever individuality the sergeant's rough-hewn account might have had.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="McKeehan, David">McKeehan's</name> long and scurrilous letter was printed in the <name type="place" key="Pittsburgh, Pa.">Pittsburgh</name>
                  <hi rend="italic">Gazette</hi> on April 14, 1807. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> may never have seen it. If he did, he took no public notice of either it or <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass's</name> volume. And so probably it was not shock over this unexpected threat to his and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> plans that caused him to suddenly quit working on their joint project. For the sad truth is that <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name>, having allowed a stirring prospectus to be issued about the forthcoming work, never provided the publishers with a single line of the promised manuscript.<ref target="n2008" n="8"/>
               </p>
               <p>
At first he may have been frozen by plain old writer's block, rising from a deep, inner fear of the inadequacies that <name type="person" key="McKeehan, David">McKeehan</name> chanced to hit on without <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> being aware (probably) of the hack writer's charges. The same feelings of inadequacy may have kept him loafing around <name type="place" key="Philadelphia, Pa.">Philadelphia</name> when he should have been following <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> to <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>, where his duties as governor awaited. Later, drink may have added its chains to his paralysis of will, for it is known that by 1809 he was indulging heavily. As far as that goes, he never had been a teetotaler.<ref target="n2009" n="9"/>
               </p>
               <p>
He was floundering during that unhappy summer, and he desperately sought a wife in the hope that matrimony might fill the restless, unquiet, indescribable void in his heart, as he put his despair to his friend <name type="person" key="Dickerson, Mahlon">Mahlon Dickerson</name>. Nothing worked out. His cousin, <name type="person" key="Wood, Maria">Maria Wood</name>, for whom he had named <name type="place" key="Marias River">Maria's River</name>, had married during his absence. One unnamed charmer put his head to spinning, but he found out she was already engaged. Something, we do not know what, ended his pursuit of a Miss E-B-y, "whose memory still remains provokingly <hi rend="italic">important</hi> in spite of all my philosophy."<ref target="n2010" n="10"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Sometime late in July he drifted from <name type="place" key="Philadelphia, Pa.">Philadelphia</name> to <name type="place" key="Washington D. C.">Washington</name> and then on to <name type="place" key="Abermarle County, Va.">Albemarle</name>. Along the way he took deep offense at something <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> did or said—certainly <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> had reasons for scolding him about his book, about his delay in going to <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>, and perhaps about his drinking—and thereafter, during the 
rest of his life, he wrote only three or four curt business letters to the man who had done so much for him.<ref target="n2011" n="11"/> Toward the end of November he and his brother <name type="person" key="Lewis, Reuben">Reuben</name> appeared in <name type="place" key="Fincastle, Va.">Fincastle</name>, the home of <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> fiancée. There <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> was smitten by <name type="person" key="Breckinridge, Letitia">Letitia Breckinridge</name>, whom <name type="person" key="Lewis, Reuben">Reuben</name> declared was "one of the most beautiful women I have ever seen, both as to form and feature." <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether</name> immediately laid siege, but he had scarcely begun to fight when off she went, leaving him with only one more memory to cling to. When <name type="person" key="Preston, William">William Preston</name>, <name type="person" key="Hancock, Julia">Julia Hancock's</name> brother-in-law, later suggested he pay court to <name type="person" key="Breckinridge, Letitia">Letitia's</name> sister <name type="person" key="Breckinridge, Emily">Emily</name>, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> rejected the plan: "Such was my passion for her sister that my soul revolts at the idea of attempting to make her [<name type="person" key="Breckinridge, Emily">Emily</name>] my wife."<ref target="n2012" n="12"/> Which sounds more than a little like overblown rhetoric from a man who, in his despondency, had decided not to risk being spurned again.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark</name> married <name type="person" key="Hancock, Julia">Julia</name> in <name type="place" key="Fincastle, Va.">Fincastle</name> on January 5, 1808. Presumably <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> hung around waiting for the ceremony, in which one supposes he played a major role. (<name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> later named his eldest son for him.) What he did after the wedding is unknown. He did not reach <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> until March 8, 1808, a full year after his appointment as governor. For that matter, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> did not return there until July. Territorial officials, it would seem, did not take their responsibilities very seriously.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> should have. He had landed in a turbulent milieu. <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> was awash with opportunists of every sort. Politics was violently partisan. Indian unrest sent continual ripples of alarm down the rivers. Land speculation was rife; land titles were in a mess because of old Spanish grants. Dueling was common, violent crime all but unchecked. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> could maintain discipline in a company of soldiers when he had the weight of the army behind him. He could not do it in a disorderly community while being constantly undercut and sniped at by a jealous territorial secretary, <name type="person" key="Bates, Frederick">Frederick Bates</name>, who had grown used to being top dog during the year of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> absence. Turning to the bottle, as <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether</name> apparently did, simply compounded his problems.</p>
               <p>
His collapse was precipitated by the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> chief, <name type="person" key="Big White (Sheheke)">Sheheke</name>, whose trip to <name type="place" key="Washington D. C.">Washington</name> was supposed to salvage something from the wreckage of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> Indian diplomacy on the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>. Having been taken from their homes, <name type="person" key="Big White (Sheheke)">Sheheke's</name> and <name type="person" key="Jusseaume, René">Jessaume's</name> families had to be returned so the chief could spread word of the wonders he had seen. By the time <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> reached <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>, a military escort of fifteen men was on the point of setting forth. In charge was one of the Corps of Discovery's former sergeants, <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Nathaniel Pryor</name>, promoted to ensign for this purpose. 
Among his fourteen soldiers were <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">George Shannon</name> and <name type="person" key="Gibson, George">George Gibson</name>, formerly of the Corps. Accompanying the soldiers were twenty-three traders bound for the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> towns. As soon as the new superintendent of Indian affairs appeared on the scene, the mission became his responsibility.<ref target="n2013" n="13"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Traveling ahead of <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Pryor's</name> group was a larger party of traders led by <name type="person" key="Lisa, Manuel">Manuel Lisa</name>, hurrying upstream to exploit, ahead of everyone else, the beaver streams revealed by <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>. <name type="person" key="Lisa, Manuel">Lisa's</name> passage alerted the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara Indians</name> that a second party was following. The <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> were resentful still of the death of their chief in the United States and had abused <name type="person" key="Gravelines, Joseph">Joseph Gravelines</name> for bringing them the bad news. Now here came a live <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>—a <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>!—under the protection of the nation who had let the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> die. After some confused posturing and maneuvering by both sides, they and several <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name> allies attacked. They killed three whites and wounded seven, one of whom later died. <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">George Shannon</name>, who had been the youngest member of the Corps of Discovery, had to have a leg amputated because of his wound. (He later married and became a successful lawyer and a <name type="place" key="Missouri">Missouri</name> state senator.) Thoroughly shaken by the experience, <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Pryor</name> reported that four hundred armed men would be needed to get <name type="person" key="Big White (Sheheke)">Sheheke</name> past the 
<name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name>. His letter about the incident caught <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> while he was on his way to <name type="place" key="Fincastle, Va.">Fincastle</name> for his wedding. If <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> was there, as he almost surely was, they undoubtedly talked the problem over.</p>
               <p>
Responsibility for the return now fell to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Lisa, Manuel">Manuel Lisa</name> arrived back in <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> from his own upriver excursion late in the summer of 1808, afire to raise enough capital for expanding his activities. As a means to this end he formed, during the winter of 1808–9, the St. Louis Missouri Fur Company, more popularly the Missouri Fur Company. He took in as partners a representative of every important commercial interest in <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>, plus <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark</name> and <name type="person" key="Lewis, Reuben">Reuben Lewis</name>, brother of the governor. In order to obtain collateral for necessary loans he signed with <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name>, acting on behalf of the United States government, a seven-thousand-dollar contract for escorting <name type="person" key="Big White (Sheheke)">Sheheke</name>, <name type="person" key="Jusseaume, René">Jessaume</name>, and their wives and children to their homes. Clearly a conflict of interests was involved that would not be tolerated today and was looked at askance even then.</p>
               <p>
The contract required the company to go upriver with no fewer than 120 men. Forty of them were to be a militia unit of expert American riflemen (not French voyageurs). Hunters, boatmen, and so on lifted the total to more than three hundred. They would travel, at intervals, in thirteen barges and on an unknown number of horses. To help the ponderous force get underway, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> signed a number of vouchers, some of them without proper bureaucratic authorization. Insofar as <name type="person" key="Big White (Sheheke)">Sheheke</name> was concerned, the effort was successful. The show of force cowed the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> and 
<name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>, and the chief was delivered safely to his tribesmen, who did not seem to care very much, anyway.<ref target="n2014" n="14"/>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, however, did not live to learn these things.</p>
               <p>
The new administration in <name type="place" key="Washington D. C.">Washington</name> refused to honor some of his vouchers. Learning this and fearing he might face bankruptcy if all the vouchers were rejected, land speculators to whom he was indebted for about five thousand acres of supposedly get-rich-quick property closed in on him. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> panicked, whether rightly or wrongly cannot be said. Late in the summer he gathered together the papers he hoped would save his economic life and added to them his journals, bound by then in red morocco leather, as if he could belatedly use them for justifying his worth to his countrymen. Thus laden, he departed early in September 1809 for the East to plead his case before the new secretary of war, <name type="person" key="Eustis, William">William Eustis</name>.</p>
               <p>
Would such a man, who had helped lead a small expedition farther west than any other American had yet gone, commit suicide?</p>
               <p>
Yes, under a certain conjunction of circumstances: If he suffered chronically from melancholia, as <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> did. If he could find no one to help fill the void he felt in his life. If the clarity of his mind and feelings were blurred by alcohol. And if, now that his great adventure was over, he dreaded the blackness of life more than the blackness of death. Psychiatrists tell us, furthermore, that such persons often reveal their proclivities, long before the event, by the reckless way with which they embrace danger.<ref target="n2015" n="15"/> Thus <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name>. If <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> had not intervened, he would have taken a most risky winter trip to <name type="place" key="Santa Fe, N. Mex.">Santa Fe</name> to compensate for his delays in reaching <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> in 1803. The Corps's expedition had barely gotten underway when he unnecessarily climbed a dangerous cliff beside a place called the <name type="place" key="Tavern Rock">Tavern</name> and very nearly fell to destruction. He went alone past the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">Great Falls of the Missouri</name> into country he knew was filled with grizzlies and came close to paying for his recklessness. With only two companions he forged ahead of the expedition's boats to find <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name> Indians and buy horses, although he had no idea how the tribe would receive the first white man they had ever seen. With only three companions he ventured into the country of the <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name>, although he had been forcefully warned not to. But so far death, if he really wanted death, however subconsciously, had eluded him.</p>
               <p>
On September 4, 1809, attended by his free mulatto servant, <name type="person" key="Pernier, John">John Pernier</name>, he caught a riverboat for <name type="place" key="New Orleans, La.">New Orleans</name>, intending to finish his journey East by sea. For some reason the trip south past the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Ohio River">Ohio</name> was slow. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> had too much time in which to brood, drink—and twice attempt to take his life. It seems likely he was urged off the boat at <name type="place" key="Fort Pickering (Tenn.)">Fort Pickering</name>, <name type="place" key="Chickasaw Bluffs">Chickasaw Bluffs</name> (now <name type="place" key="Memphis, Tenn.">Memphis</name>)—or so implied <name type="person" key="Russell, Gilbert">Major Gilbert Russell</name>, the 
commander at that fort, into whose charge <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> was delivered. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> himself says he landed because of an "indisposition."<ref target="n2016" n="16"/> Conceivably, another subconscious wish was involved. In 1797, as a young ensign, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> had supervised the building of, and had been briefly in command at, <name type="place" key="Fort Pickering (Tenn.)">Fort Pickering</name>. Did he welcome being put ashore in a blurred hope of again gaining command, this time of himself?</p>
               <p>
He needed help. He was incoherent and well soaked. <name type="person" key="Russell, Gilbert">Major Russell</name> put him in whatever served the fort as sick bay and deprived him of all spirits except occasional sips of claret or white wine. Under solicitous treatment his remarkable constitution reasserted itself, and within a week he was chafing to continue his journey, this time by land, promising the while "never to drink any more spirits or use snuff again."<ref target="n2017" n="17"/> When <name type="person" key="Neelly, James">James Neelly</name>, Indian agent for the <name type="native_nation" key="Chickasaw Indians">Chickasaw</name> tribe, showed up, hound for the interior, and agreed to lend <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> riding horses and pack animals and keep an eye on him, <name type="person" key="Russell, Gilbert">Russell</name> reluctantly let the governor go. There was little else, actually, that he could have done.</p>
               <p>
Somewhere in the <name type="native_nation" key="Chickasaw Indians">Chickasaw</name> nation <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> apparently got hold of more liquor and became incoherent again. They rested for two days and on either October 8 or 9 crossed the <name type="place" key="Tennessee River">Tennessee River</name> and intersected the once-notorious <name type="place" key="Natchez Trace">Natchez Trace.</name> They turned northeast along it. At their first camp beyond the river, they lost two horses. Ever-restless <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>: while <name type="person" key="Neelly, James">Neelly</name> hunted for the horses, the governor, his servant, and <name type="person" key="Neelly, James">Neelly's</name> servant (charged with watching the ailing man?) went ahead, after "promising to wait for me at the first house he came to that was inhabited by white people; he reached the house (and tavern] of a <name type="person" key="Mr. Grinder">Mr. Grinder</name> about sun set, the man of the house being from home, and no person there but a woman who discovering the governor to be deranged, gave him up the house &amp; slept herself in one near it."<ref target="n2018" n="18"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Because no one saw what actually happened thereafter, circumstantial reports of the killing vary in detail. Suffice it here to say that sometime during the night <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> loaded his pistols and shot himself twice, first in the forehead and, after that ball had glanced off his skull without killing him, a little below the breast. All accounts agree he died slowly. In his agony he called for water but received none until dawn, when <name type="person" key="Mrs. Grinder">Mrs. Grinder</name>, who had heard the shots and was in abject terror of him, summoned his and <name type="person" key="Neelly, James">Neelly's</name> servants from the barn where they had been sleeping.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> died shortly after sunrise. During the day, <name type="person" key="Neelly, James">Neelly</name> reached the house, heard the stories of <name type="person" key="Mrs. Grinder">Mrs. Grinder</name> and the servants, and buried the body as best he could beside the road. (There it stayed. Today the site is marked by a monument, erected in 1846.) Taking charge of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> personal possessions, <name type="person" key="Neelly, James">Neelly</name> sent them with a letter, by <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> man, to <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>. There was no doubt in <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name> mind—or in <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>, who heard the news in <name type="place" key="Louisville, Ky.">Louisville</name> while on another trip East with <name type="person" key="Hancock, Julia">Julia</name> and their eldest son, the infant <name type="person" key="Clark, Meriwether Lewis">Meriwether Lewis Clark</name>—that the death was suicide and not murder, a theory that keeps insistently cropping up to explain, in more palatable form, the death of a national hero.<ref target="n2019" n="19"/>
               </p>
               <p>
After learning of his friend's death, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> continued to <name type="place" key="Fincastle, Va.">Fincastle</name>. There he left his wife and son while he visited <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> and some of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> family. Gathering up the journals, he went to <name type="place" key="Philadelphia, Pa.">Philadelphia</name> to arrange with <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Nicholas Biddle</name> to rewrite them in two volumes as a coherent, smooth-flowing narrative. After being given a final polishing by Paul Allen, they were issued in 1814, with <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> map as a supplement. Although that chronic procrastinator, <name type="person" key="Barton, Benjamin">Benjamin Barton</name>, renewed his promise to edit the scientific volume, he died before getting around to it. With no one in charge of the specimens the captains had either sent back down the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> on the keelboat from <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name> or had brought with them, the materials became scattered and many were lost.</p>
               <p>
Not long after <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> death, <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name>, <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name>, and <name type="person" key="Jean Baptiste">Pomp</name>, the child well weaned by then, came down the river to visit <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>. They stayed about a year. The parents then returned to the <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> villages beside the <name type="place" key="Knife River">Knife River</name>, leaving little <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Jean Baptiste">Jean Baptiste</name> with <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> to be educated, as the captain had promised. His benefactions continued. Late in 1811, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Reuben">Reuben Lewis</name> of the Missouri Fur Company built a post, named for <name type="person" key="Lisa, Manuel">Manuel Lisa</name>, beside the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri River</name>. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> was well aware of this, of course, and it was perhaps through his influence that <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name> got a job at the new establishment as interpreter. He moved there with <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name>, who was pregnant, in early 1812. A daughter, <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Lizette">Lizette</name>, was born to them in August. Four months later, on December 20, <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name> died of what the post trader called putrid fever. She was about twenty-three.<ref target="n2020" n="20"/>
               </p>
               <p>
As soon as circumstances allowed, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> assumed guardianship of the girl and, later, of <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau's</name> son <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint, Jr.">Toussaint</name> by a second <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name> wife. As for <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Jean Baptiste">Jean Baptiste</name>, he went back among the Indians in 1816 or so. In 1824, when he was twenty, he caught the attention of <name type="person" key="Prince Maximilian">Prince Maximilian</name> of Wied, who was touring the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri River</name> country on an elaborate sightseeing junket. The prince took <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Jean Baptiste">Pomp</name> to <name type="place" key="Germany">Germany</name>, where he stayed for five years before returning to the American West to make a commendable name for himself as a mountain man and army guide.</p>
               <p>
When <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Thomas Jefferson</name> died on July 4, 1826 (his predecessor as president and sometime enemy, <name type="person" key="Adams, John">John Adams</name>, died on that same day), America's fabled fur trade had been firmly and profitably established throughout the area <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had known as Upper <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name>. Curiously, the man who had presided over the purchase of that territory had little to say about either the land or its burgeoning commerce, at least in public. In his introduction to <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name> and Allen's <hi rend="italic">History of the Expedition under the Command of Captains <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>
                  </hi>, he outlined his own early interest in trans-<name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name> explorations, repeated the instructions he had given <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> before <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had been decided on as the party's co-commander, mentioned the excitement caused by the Corps's return, and closed by mourning <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> untimely suicide. That death, the president finished, had kept his fellow Americans from receiving from <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> own hands their first knowledge of "that vast and fertile country, which their sons are destined to fill with arts, with science, with freedom and happiness."</p>
               <p>
As to the United States' share of that vast and fertile land he was quite definite and quite conservative. His nation, he believed, should not make any effort to extend itself politically across the <name type="place" key="Continental Divide">Continental Divide</name>, the country's western boundary as arbitrarily established by the purchase itself. The communications of the time were too slow to allow the quick responses between voters and their government needed by a democracy, and <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> despised the thought of his country becoming masters of a distant colonial empire. The <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name> country should become, in his opinion, a neighboring nation "of independent Americans, unconnected with us but by the ties of blood and interest, and employing like us the right of self-government."<ref target="n2021" n="21"/> No more territory (except West <name type="place" key="Florida">Florida</name>), he said in effect, not sensing the energy <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had helped impart to the westward dynamics of the young nation. If the British and Spanish—both of them empires—could be forestalled, that was enough.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> concluding years were the antithesis of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>. In 1813 he was named territorial governor and held that office until the state of <name type="place" key="Missouri">Missouri</name> was created in 1820. Though defeated in the first election for state governor, he continued as superintendent of Indian affairs. Whether dealing with whites or Indians or both together, he sought to settle controversies by conciliation. He was imposingly proportioned, dignified, trustworthy, and respected. Most Indians liked him, called him Red Head Chief and, whenever circumstances brought them to <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>, eagerly visited him and the Indian Hall he had erected on his estate.</p>
               <p>
Maintaining his contacts with traders and trappers, he utilized the information they brought him to regularly update his master map of the West. The white spaces shrank, the Indians retreated, the vast herds of game became mere ghosts of what they had been. When <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark</name> died peacefully in 1838, the face of the nation was changing at a rate that neither <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> nor he could have imagined when they returned to <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> in 1806, bursting with news. Luck! That, too, was part of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis's</name> heritage, in spite of the manner of his death. The West was bound to be crossed sooner or later by—who knows, acting with what motives? But through good fortune <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, twenty-seven white soldiers, a black slave, an Indian woman, an infant, and a man of mixed races were the first. Acting for the government and hence for the people, and following plans laid down by the president of the United States, they saw the grandeur and space and felt the freshness, and returned successful. The imprint stayed. This was the people's West, the public domain, in ways not quite matched anywhere else. That domain has been sadly abused—and gloriously used—over the years, but the ideal, the sense of newness and promise with which the names <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> have always been identified, has not yet been lost.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="notes" type="notes">
            <head rend="center">Notes</head>
            <div type="section">
               <note xml:id="n2001" n="1">The four letters: Jackson, <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, 317–43. Jackson's notes describe their appearance, provenance, and so forth. He is not to blame for my interpretations, however.</note>
               <note xml:id="n2002" n="2">
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> suggestions raise the question of the effect the Corps of Discovery had on <name type="person" key="Astor, John Jacob">John Jacob Astor's</name> plans for a vast fur-trade base, <name type="place" key="Asortia, Oreg.">Astoria</name>, at the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>. It is true <name type="person" key="Astor, John Jacob">Astor</name> was aware of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> crossing and wrote <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> about his intentions. For some years, however, the trader's orientation had been toward <name type="place" key="Canada">Canada</name>. He knew of <name type="person" key="Mackenzie, Alexander">Alexander Mackenzie's</name> drive to use the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> as the key point in a fur and fisheries plan embracing the entire Northwest. Before embarking on his own venture, therefore, <name type="person" key="Astor, John Jacob">Astor</name> entered into 
arrangements with the Canadians that he hoped would preclude their competition—only to have the War of 1812 ruin his Pacific Fur Company. So, except perhaps for <name type="person" key="Hunt, Wilson Price">Wilson Price Hunt's</name> harrowing overland trip, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> example probably was no more than confirmation of plans already underway. (Lavender, <hi rend="italic">Fist</hi>, 118–45, passim.)</note>
               <note xml:id="n2003" n="3">Thompson, 131. Thompson, writing from memory, errs in saying that in 1792 the forty-ninth parallel formed the boundary between the British dominions and the United States as far west as the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rockies</name>. The United States had no claims that far west until 1803.</note>
               <note xml:id="n2004" n="4">Jackson, Letters, 343.</note>
               <note xml:id="n2005" n="5">
                  <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> to <name type="person" key="Russell, Gilbert">Major Gilbert Russell</name>, April 18, 1810: "He [<name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>] was much afflicted &amp; habitually so with hypochondria. This was probably increased by the habit into which he had fallen"—i.e., intemperance. <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> could have noticed the intemperance only during 1807, for he did not see <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> after that. Apparently he did get occasional reports of it later on, but chronic alcoholism probably would have taken a while to 
develop.</note>
               <note xml:id="n2006" n="6">Reimbursement affairs: Jackson, Letters, II, 377–84.</note>
               <note xml:id="n2007" n="7">Ibid., 385–85, 394–97, 399–408. The <name type="person" key="McKeehan, David">McKeehan</name> quotation: ibid., 406.</note>
               <note xml:id="n2008" n="8">Jackson, <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>. See last sentence of C. and A. Conrad to <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, 
468–69. Also 459 and last sentence of <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, July 17, 1808, ibid., 445.</note>
               <note xml:id="n2009" n="9">Ibid., 575n. Cutright, "Rest, Rest," passim.</note>
               <note xml:id="n2010" n="10">Jackson, <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, II, 720. See also <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, undated, 388.</note>
               <note xml:id="n2011" n="11">Ibid., 444–45 and especially Jackson's note 1.</note>
               <note xml:id="n2012" n="12">Ibid., 721.</note>
               <note xml:id="n2013" n="13">Appleman, 237. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> reached <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> either at the end of June or early in July 1807. Writing <name type="person" key="Dearborn, Henry">Dearborn</name>, under date <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>, May [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>] 18, 1807, he says the party "will set out this evening." I cannot explain the contradiction in dates. For a summary of the affair: Oglesby, 50–54.</note>
               <note xml:id="n2014" n="14">Oglesby, 69–76.</note>
               <note xml:id="n2015" n="15">Kushner, 470–80.</note>
               <note xml:id="n2016" n="16">
                  <name type="person" key="Russell, Gilbert">Russell</name>, "Statement," and <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> to <name type="person" key="Stoddard, Amos">Stoddard</name>, Jackson, <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, II, 573–75, 466. It is said <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> switched to land travel because he feared, given the international tensions of the time, that his ship from <name type="place" key="New Orleans, La.">New Orleans</name> might be seized by a British man-of-war. (<name type="person" key="Neelly, James">Neelly</name> to <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, ibid., 
467–68.)</note>
               <note xml:id="n2017" n="17">Ibid., 748.</note>
               <note xml:id="n2018" n="18">Ibid., 467.</note>
               <note xml:id="n2019" n="19">Among those arguing, sometimes with great intensity, that <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> was murdered are Elliott Coues, ed., <hi rend="italic">History of the Expedition under the Command of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>
                  </hi> (New York, 1893); Bakeless, <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>
                  </hi>; Vardis Fisher, <hi rend="italic">Suicide or Murder? The Strange Death of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name>
                  </hi> (Denver, 1962); and Dillon. The case for suicide is put forth by Phelps; Kushner; Cutright, "Rest, Rest"; and Donald Jackson, who in his <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> moves from tentative to firm support of the suicide theory. (1962 ed., 486n; 1978 ed., 474n.)</note>
               <note xml:id="n2020" n="20">I refer those who persist in believing, against all evidence, that <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name> lived to a ripe old age and is buried on an Indian reservation near <name type="place" key="Lander, Wyo.">Lander</name>, <name type="place" key="Wyoming">Wyoming</name>, to Irving Anderson, "Probing the Riddle of the 
<name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Bird Woman</name>," <hi rend="italic">Montana, the Magazine of Western History</hi>, XXIII (Autumn 1973), 2–17.</note>
               <note xml:id="n2021" n="21">Merk, 4–5, 116–17. The quotation is from a letter, <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> to <name type="person" key="Astor, John Jacob">John Jacob Astor</name>, May 24, 1812, 117.</note>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <note xml:id="n20unnumbered" n="*" type="footnote">
                  <name type="place" key="Missouri">Missouri</name> Territory would be carved out of <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name> in 1812.</note>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.lavender.01.19" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.lavender.01.00" type="contents"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.lavender.01.app1" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
