<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.lc.editorial.procedures">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">Editorial Procedures</title>
            <title type="sub"/>
            <author>Gary E. Moulton</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 2</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">August 30, 1803–August 24, 1804</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1986</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">49-54</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-04-05</date>
            <date/>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>
            <name/>Initial creation Transcribed</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="main">Editorial Procedures</head>
         <head type="sub"/>
         <div type="introduction">
            <p>The primary goal of this edition of the journals of the Lewis and Clark expedition 
is to present users with a reliable text that is largely uncluttered with editorial 
interference. The editorial procedures designed to provide such an authentic 
text have necessitated certain modifications in the original text due to the demands of modern typography and the inconsistent usage of the journalists, but 
every effort has been made to furnish a transcription that is true to the original. 
Difficulties that have worked against producing a printed transcript that nearly 
duplicates handwritten words have also prevented establishing foolproof and 
unchanging principles of editing. Readers have been advised when deviations 
from the following procedures occur.</p>
            <p>There are usually two parts to each journal entry by Lewis or Clark. One is a
narrative text describing the day's events; the other gives the course of travel and 
distance covered for the day, which the captains usually called "courses, distances, and references." These two sections are here called "text" and "course." 
The format for the text and course has been somewhat normalized. The course 
has been set in smaller type than the text in keeping with Lewis's and Clark's practice of writing in a smaller hand for this portion of the journal. The course has 
been printed in closely aligned columns, one for courses, one for distances, and 
one for references, after Clark's usual ordering. Lewis's style is somewhat different at the beginning so adjustments have been made in those instances. When 
the course material is run as a continuous line, as Clark occasionally wrote it in 
his Field Notes, it has been converted to columns for clarity. In the captains' entries the text sometimes precedes the course and sometimes follows it. Here the 
order of the text and course follows the journalists' changing arrangement. 
Where confusion might exist, a date has been given in brackets. The dateline has 
been set to the right margin whenever it appears on the line above the entry to 
allow the name of the journalist to be placed consistently on the left margin above 
the entry. Repeated dates above sections within an entry are placed as they appear on the original.</p>
            <p>Grammatical consistency is a vexing problem to any historical editor but particularly to an editor of Lewis and Clark materials. The men's erratic, but delightful 
and ingenious, manner of spelling and capitalizing creates the most perplexing 
difficulties of all. "This is expecially true of Clark," one investigator noted, "who
was not only the master misspeller of them all, but also displayed dazzling virtuosity in his approach to punctuation, capitalization, and simple sentence structure."<ref target="nge000001" n="1"/> In this edition the spelling and capitalization have been retained as nearly 
as possible, but some conventionalizing has been necessary. Uncrossed <hi rend="italic">t'</hi>s and undotted <hi rend="italic">i'</hi>s and the like have been silently corrected. Misspelled words have been 
corrected in brackets when necessary for clarity. When letters or words defy comprehension, conjectural readings have been given in brackets with a question 
mark signifying the editor's uncertainty. With ambiguous spelling, the journalist's 
typical spelling has been taken as a guide, or the modern spelling has been 
adopted in disputed cases. With Clark that is nearly impossible. One researcher 
discovered that Clark spelled the word Sioux "no less than <hi rend="italic">twenty-seven</hi> different
ways."<ref target="nge000002" n="2"/> Little can be promised in the way of consistency, for no rule can stand 
against Clark's inimitable style.</p>
            <p>For capitalization some consistencies of the writers have been discovered;
otherwise, individual letters have been judged against their rise along the line of 
writing and compared to the writer's normal usage. This procedure has generated a great number of capital letters. Clark again has confounded any system. 
One historian who struggled with his handwriting wrote: "In the matter of capitalization, one man has utterly bested me. William Clark, a creative speller, is also
a versatile capitalizer—especially in handling words beginning with <hi rend="italic">s.</hi> After 
many attempts to work out a sane norm I have retired in confusion. Clark uses 
four kinds of initial s and each can be interpreted as a capital."<ref target="nge000003" n="3"/>
            </p>
            <p>Several alterations from the original punctuation occur in the text. Periods have
been retained mostly in their currently accepted context. Incidental and random 
periods, which may be pen rests, have been dropped. Spaced periods (leaders), 
used frequently in the course material, have also been discarded. Periods at the 
end of lines have been retained. When periods have not been supplied by the 
writer at the end of a sentence, none have been added. Rather, extra spacing has 
been used at the end of a sentence where no punctuation appears. If some other 
punctuation occurs at the end of a sentence (such as a comma or a semicolon), 
it has been retained and normal spacing follows. Random lines and dashes, occasionally used to separate entries, have been omitted. Multiple or lengthy dashes 
have been shown as a single dash. Underscoring has been retained, but occasional pen marks that are questionable underlining have been dropped. Multiple 
underscoring has been dropped except where double underlining has been used 
with a figure that represents a total from a column of figures, such as in the 
mileage column of a day's course. Quotation marks have been discarded when 
they appear before every line; only beginning and ending marks have been used. 
When beginning or ending quotation marks are missing, they have been supplied in brackets at the most logical place.</p>
            <p>Paragraphing follows the writer's usage, except that when a paragraph ends
and a new one begins without indentation, the new line has been silently indented. When words and phrases are scattered across a page with no apparent order 
(as in Clark's Field Notes), the text has been printed in the most logical fashion. 
Otherwise, items have been printed as they appear from left to right and from 
top to bottom on the page. Signs, symbols, and abbreviations have been handled 
in this fashion. Signs and symbols found on a modern typewriter have been retained, and unidentified symbols have been dropped. Superscript letters have 
been brought down to the line of type. Lewis and Clark used a variety of marks 
under the superscript letters <hi rend="italic">st</hi>, <hi rend="italic">th</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">nd</hi> of their ordinal numbers. Those have 
been lowered, marks beneath the letters have been discarded, and no punctuation has been added. Abbreviated and contracted words have been spelled out 
within brackets only if it seems that the word might not be understood. Most often 
they are unaltered. Scored-out, torn, and blotted passages have been handled in 
this way. Where words have been crossed out by the author for the apparent purpose of word choice, with no significant change in the text, the words have been 
silently omitted. Where words scored out by the author add new meaning, or 
convey a different sense to the passage, the deleted words have been placed 
between angle brackets. If it appears that someone other than the author has 
crossed out words, the affected passage has been restored and the action noted 
in the annotation. When a passage is unclear due to the condition of the paper, 
or because the writer has disfigured the page, a conjectural reading followed by a 
question mark has been given in brackets; otherwise, a note on the condition of 
the paper appears between brackets with the words italicized, such as [<hi rend="italic">torn</hi>], 
[<hi rend="italic">blotted</hi>], [<hi rend="italic">erased</hi>], or [<hi rend="italic">unable to read</hi>].</p>
            <p>Over the years, persons besides the original authors have written on the pages
of the journals. Nicholas Biddle was the first, about 1810, as he prepared a paraphrase of the journals. Some of Biddle's emendations were made for his own 
purposes and some perhaps were made on the advice of Clark, with whom Biddle 
occasionally collaborated during his labors. During the collaboration, Clark may 
have added his own postexpeditionary interlineations. Elliott Coues worked with 
the manuscripts at his Washington home in December 1892 and made numerous 
and long interlinear notations upon the pages. Perhaps one other, unknown person has also added words here and there in the journals. Those emendations and 
interlineations have been retained and have been handled in this way. Interlineations by the original author have been added to the line of type without editorial 
comment. Writings by Lewis or Clark that are interjections in one another's journals or perhaps later writings (usually in ink of a different shade), by Biddle 
(usually in red ink), by Coues, and by the unknown person have been placed in 
the text between brackets, with the emended words italicized and with the author's initials placed ahead of the words, such as: [<hi rend="italic">WC:</hi> ], [<hi rend="italic">ML:</hi> ], [<hi rend="italic">NB:</hi> ], [<hi rend="italic">EC:</hi> ], 
and [<hi rend="italic">X:</hi> ]. The letter <hi rend="italic">X</hi> stands for the unknown or any unidentified person. Extremely complex or lengthy emendations have been explained in the annotation. 
Bracketed material without identifying initials and in italics is that of the editor. 
Where confusion might exist the following scheme has been used to identify the 
editor's remarks: [<hi rend="italic">Ed:</hi> ].</p>
            <p>The format follows the plan adopted by Thwaites in the first edition of the
journals. Thwaites printed Lewis's and Clark's entries together but separated the 
remaining diaries. When the writing of the enlisted men significantly alters or 
adds to information provided by Lewis and Clark, it has been abstracted and 
placed in footnotes to the captains' entries. This procedure should reduce annotation in later volumes by combining editorial work under a single entry or 
two rather than across several volumes. Under this plan the subordinates' journals will not be as heavily annotated and some comparison of volumes may be 
necessary. Readers have traditionally turned to the words of Lewis and Clark first  
and used the enlisted men's diaries as supplements—this plan will facilitate such 
practice. A comprehensive, synoptic index that coordinates all journal entries 
will be placed in the final journal volume. In the footnotes, subordinates' journals have been noted by dates of entry rather than by their published sources, 
thus anticipating their eventual publication in this series.</p>
            <p>The chapter divisions used in Biddle's edition and maintained by Thwaites
and Osgood have also been employed with only minor changes. Thwaites's remarks for this decision are appropriate: "They are convenient chronological and
geographical divisions; they are familiar to scholars, and thus have acquired a 
certain historical and bibliographical standing; moreover, comparisons between 
the Biddle paraphrase and the Original Journals will be facilitated by their retention."<ref target="nge000004" n="4"/> Comparisons between the new edition and Thwaites's volumes will also be 
facilitated by the retention of the chapter divisions.</p>
            <p>Annotation in the new edition will be full but not discursive. Although footnotes will be kept within bounds, it is not the intention to produce a barebones 
transcription with little or no analysis. The explication of the journals is basic to 
the purpose of this edition, but the work is primarily the preparation of source 
material, meant to be borrowed from and enlarged upon by other scholars; 
there is no mandate to compose essays as footnotes. In general, the amount of 
information included in the annotations depends upon the importance placed 
on the subject by Lewis and Clark, or upon the significance of the subject to the 
expedition. In some cases where the information is controversial, conjectural, or 
confusing, the length of annotation may be disproportionate to the item's relevance to the expedition.</p>
            <p>The design for annotation in this edition is similar to the method used in editions of letters, where footnotes are placed at the end of each letter rather than at 
the bottom of a page. Here the annotation follows each dated entry, and the 
numbers run consecutively within an entry. Since Lewis's and Clark's entries have 
been placed together, the annotation comes after the final entry for a day, regardless of the number of journal versions for that day. Lewis's entries, when 
available, always precede Clark's, and the author's name is given in brackets at the 
head of each entry. The text material takes priority over the course material for 
annotation, whatever its order in an entry. If items have been annotated in the 
text, similar matter has been ignored for annotation in the course. If items have 
been annotated from Lewis's entry and Clark has much the same material in his 
entry for that day, Clark's points have not been noted. The same is true if either 
writer has more than one version for a day's entry. The versions have been placed 
in the apparent order of their preparation. Annotation is to the first mention of 
a point and usually only to that mention. References to previous or later notes 
in this edition are to dated journal entries rather than volume, chapter, and note 
numbers.</p>
            <p>Words defined in modern standard college dictionaries are not annotated,
although archaic, regional, unusual, and misleading usages are noted. Variant or 
incorrect spellings that could mislead the reader sometimes need annotation. 
I have supplied definitions from the <hi rend="italic">Oxford English Dictionary</hi> in such cases, but I 
have not cited it in the notes. Common or well-known places or things are not 
annotated unless their status in Lewis and Clark's time is significant.</p>
            <p>Geographic features mentioned by the explorers are annotated in the journals, except in cases where such notations are too obscure to allow proper identification. Their trail, still doubtful in some areas, has been laid out as accurately as 
possible and campsites have been identified. The status and signficance of places 
and the state of geographical knowledge in Lewis and Clark's time are important 
considerations in the annotations.</p>
            <p>Scientific information gained by the expedition—in botany, zoology, geology,
medicine, and ethnology—all receive fuller treatment in this edition. Plants and 
animals are identified by their popular labels and scientific names, with questionable species so noted. Sources cited are primarily the most up-to-date scientific 
references available; earlier historical sources such as Coues, Gilmore, Criswell, 
or Cutright are also cited secondarily in some instances.</p>
            <p>American Indian groups are identified by tribal names and linguistic affiliations; the latter can demonstrate patterns of historical connections between 
groups that sometimes cannot be learned either from tribal traditions or from 
historical records. Information on the location of tribes at the time of Lewis and 
Clark's visit, the basis of their economy, archaeological sites, other relevant points, 
and further references are provided in the notes. Significant Indian personalities 
are portrayed as fully as possible.</p>
            <p>Members of the expedition have received the fullest biographical treatment
possible within the limits of available information in the notes and in Appendix A. General biographical dictionaries have not been cited in the annotations. 
Although scholars and enthusiasts will be disappointed to learn that some persons still remain unidentified, persons, places, or things 
for which research has failed to provide an identification have not been annotated. Exceptions involve cases where the lack of information is itself significant 
or creates problems, such as the identity of the expedition member La Liberté.</p>
            <p>The most important considerations in the annotations have been to substantiate statements in the text and to provide additional information immediately 
relevant to the expedition. In many areas the editorial staff has turned to the vast 
literature on the expedition and to numerous scholars and lay people who have 
graciously offered their assistance in their respective areas of expertise. Our 
hope is that the new edition will offer the same service to future students of the 
Lewis and Clark expedition.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="nge000001" n="1">Belts (WCW), 10.</note>
            <note xml:id="nge000002" n="2">Ibid.</note>
            <note xml:id="nge000003" n="3">Jackson (LLC) 1:ix.</note>
            <note xml:id="nge000004" n="4">Thwaites (LC), 1:lviii.</note>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>