<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.1803-12-13">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">December 13, 1803</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2003</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 2</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">August 30, 1803–August 24, 1804</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1986</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">133</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc/>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2003-12-18</date>
            <date/>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>
            <name/>Initial creation Transcribed</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date>December 13, 1803</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>
                  <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>
                  <ref target="n03121301" n="1"/>
               </speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Tuesday—on the 13th    fixed on a place to build huts    Set the men to Clearing land &amp; Cutting Logs—    a hard wind all day—    flying Clouds, Sent to the neghbourhood, Some Indians pass.

	
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n03121301" n="1">Here begin the Field Notes, kept by <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> during the five months spent at the <name type="place" key="Camp Dubois (Camp Wood, River Dubois) (Ill.)">Wood River winter camp</name>. The <name type="place" key="Camp Dubois (Camp Wood, River Dubois) (Ill.)">Dubois</name> Journal consists of twelve loose sheets of different sizes, on which are found not only dated entries but other miscellaneous, undated material; the thrifty captains used the same sheets for a variety of purposes. In Osgood's edition of the Field Notes, each sheet was given a document number, and the material was arranged largely according to the document on which it occurs. The same document numbers are used here in reference to the sheets. In this edition, chronological order is followed wherever possible; thus, entries that bear a date before December 13, 1803, have been placed with the Eastern Journal material. Material that cannot be dated is placed according to the sheet on which it occurs. In determining order, the sheets are read from left to right and top to bottom insofar as possible, allowing for the fact that on many sheets the writing runs in several different directions. Obverse and reverse of each sheet are determined by the dates of the entries. Apparently the captains did not regard this journal as an official document because they were not traveling and the expedition had not actually begun; hence it is extremely sketchy and disorganized. On both sides of this first sheet are drawings of squares and rectangles, apparently representing plans for the <name type="place" key="Camp Dubois (Camp Wood, River Dubois) (Ill.)">River Dubois camp</name> (see fig. 5). It is not clear which plan was eventually adopted. There are also many jottings on this sheet that are illegible or that seem unworthy of adding to this text, words like "Perogues" or "take off the Deed [dead?]." Doodles are also present. Facsimiles of these documents are accessible in Osgood's edition.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1803-12-12" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1803-12-14" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>