<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.1806-03-31">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
March 31, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 7</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">March 23–June 9, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1991</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">38-42</biblScope>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">283-284</biblScope>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">204</biblScope>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 11</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of Joseph Whitehouse, May 14, 1804–April 2, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1997</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">437</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc/>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-09-27</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date>March 31, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Monday March 31st 1806</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
We set out early this morning and proceeded until 8 A. M.    when we Landed on the N. side opposite one large wooden house of the <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Shâh-ha-la</name>
                  </hi> nation<ref target="n31033101" n="1"/> and took breakfast.    when we decended the river in November last there were 24 other lodges formed of Straw and covered with bark near this house; these lodges are now distroyed and the inhabitants as the indians inform us have returned to the <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Cascades (Great Rapids, Great Shute)">great rapids</name>
                  <ref target="n31033102" n="2"/> of this river which is their permanent residence; the house which remains is inhabited; soon after we landed two canoes came over from this house with 4 men and a woman.    they informed us that their relations who were with them last fall usuly visit them at that season for the purpose of hunting deer and Elk and collecing wappetoe and that they had lately returned to the rapids I presume to prepare for the fishing season as the Salmon will begin to run shortly.—    this morning we overtook the man who had visited our camp last night he had a fine sturgeon in his canoe which he had just taken.    the Sagittaria Sagittifolia dose not grow on this river above the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbian</name> valley.—    These indians of the rapids frequently visit this valley at every season of the year for the purpose of collecting wappetoe which is abundant and appears never to be out of season at any time of the year.    at 10 A. M. we resumed our march accompanyed by three men in a canoe; one of these fellows appeared to be a man of some note among them; he was dressed in a salor's jacket which was decorated in this own fassion with five rows of large and small buttons in front and some large buttons on the pocket flaps.    they are remarkably fond of large brass buttons.    these people speak a different language from those below<ref target="n31033103" n="3"/> tho' in their dress habits manners &amp;c they differ but little from the <name type="native_nation" key="Cathlapotle Indians">quathlahpohtles</name>.    their women wear the truss as those do of all the nations residing from the <name type="native_nation" key="Cathlapotle Indians">quathlahpohtles</name> to the entrance of <name type="place" key="Lewis (Cahwahnakiooks) River">Lewis's river</name>.    they differ in the manner of intering their dead.<ref target="n31033104" n="4"/>    they lay them horizontally on boards and cover them with mats, in a valt formed with boards like the roof of a hose supported by forks and a single pole laid horizontally on those forks.    many bodies are deposited in the same valt above ground.    these are frequently laid one on the other, to the hight of three or for corps.    they deposit with them various articles of which they die possessed, and most esteem while living.    their canoes are frequently broken up to strengthen the vault.—    these people have a few words the same with those below but the air of the language is intirely different, insomuch, that it may be justly deemed a different language. their women wear longer and larger robes generally, than those below; these are most commonly made of deer skins dressed with the hair on them.    we continued our rout along the N. side of the river passed <name type="place" key="Government (Diamond, White Goose, Swan) Island">diamond Island</name> and <name type="place" key="Lady (White Brant) Island">whitebrant island</name>
                  <ref target="n31033105" n="5"/> to the lower point of a handsom prarie opposite to the upper entrance of the <name type="place" key="Sandy (Quicksand) River">Quicksand river</name>;<ref target="n31033106" n="6"/> here we encamped having traveled 25 miles today.    a little below the upper point of the <name type="place" key="Lady (White Brant) Island">White brant Island</name>
                  <name type="place" key="Washougal (Seal) River">Seal river</name> discharges itself on the N. side.    it is about 80 yards wide, and at present discharges a large body of water. the water is very clear.    the banks are low and near the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> overflow and form several large ponds.    the natives inform us that it is of no great extent and heads in the mountains just above us.    at the distance of one mile from the entrance of this stream it forks, the two branches being nearly of the same size.    they are both obstructed with falls and innumerable rappids, insomuch that it cannot be navigated.    as we could not learn any name of the natives for this stream we called it <name type="place" key="Washougal (Seal) River">Seal river</name> from the great abundance of those animals<ref target="n31033107" n="7"/> which we saw about it's entrance. we determined to remain at our present encampment a day or two for the several purposes of examining <name type="place" key="Sandy (Quicksand) River">quicksand river</name> [<hi rend="italic">NB: which <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt Clark</name> could not believe to be the river watering the Country to the Sth &amp; for the purpose of</hi>] making some Celestial observations, and procuring some meat to serve us as far as the falls or through the Western mountains where we found the game scarce as we decended.—    the three indians who accompanied us last evening encamped a little distance above us and visited our camp where they remained untill 9 P. M.    in the entrance of <name type="place" key="Washougal (Seal) River">Seal river</name> I saw a summer duck or wood duck<ref target="n31033108" n="8"/> as they are sometimes called.    this is the same with those of our country and is the first I have seen since I entered the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">rocky mountains</name> last summer.—    our hunters who had halted a little below <name type="place" key="Washougal (Seal) River">Seal river</name> in consequence of the waves being too high for their small canoe did not join us untill after dark. <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name> who was out below <name type="place" key="Washougal (Seal) River">Seal river</name> informed us that game was very scarce in that quarter, a circumstance which we did not expect.
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Monday March 31st 1806</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
we Set out this morning and proceeded untill 8 oClock when we landed on the N. Side opposit one large House of the <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Shah-ha-la</name>
                  </hi> Nation    near this house at the time we passed on the 4th of November last was Situated 25 houses, 24 of them were built of Straw &amp; Covered with bark as before mentioned.    those [of] that description are all distroyed, the one built of wood only remains and is inhabited.    we overtook the man whome came to our Camp last night and Soon after we landed two canoes Came over from the opposit Side with 5 men &amp; a woman    those people informed us that their relations who was with them last fall reside at the <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Cascades (Great Rapids, Great Shute)">Great rapids</name>, and were down with them last fall gathering Wappato which did not grow above, and also killing deer, that they Secured the bark of the houses which they then lived in against their return next fall.    they also inform us that their relations also visit them frequently in the Spring to collect this root which is in great quantities on either Side of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>.    at 10 A. M we proceeded on accompanied by one Canoe and three men, one of them appeared to be a man of Some note, dressed in a Salors jacket which had 5 rows of large &amp; Small buttons on it. Those people Speak a differant language from those below, with Some fiew Words the Same, the accent entirely different.    their dress and Manners appear very Similar.    the women ware the truss or breach clout and Short robes, and men roabs only    passed up on the N. Side of <name type="place" key="Lady (White Brant) Island">White brant Island</name> near the upper point of Which a Small river falls in about 80 yards wide and at this time discharges a great quantity of water.    the nativs inform us that this river is very Short and heads in the range of mountains to the N E of its enterance into the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>    the nativs haveing no name which we could learn for this little river we Call it <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="place" key="Washougal (Seal) River">Seal</name>
                  </hi>
                  <ref target="n31033109" n="9"/> river from the great number of those Animals which frequents its mouth.    this river forks into two nearly equal branches about 1 mile up and each branch is crouded with rapids &amp; falls.    we proceeded on about 2 miles above the enterance of this <name type="place" key="Washougal (Seal) River">Seacalf river</name> and imedeately opposit the upper mouth of the <name type="place" key="Sandy (Quicksand) River">quick Sand river</name> we formed a Camp in a Small Prarie on the North Side of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> where we intend to delay one or two days to make Some Selestial observations, to examine <name type="place" key="Sandy (Quicksand) River">quick sand river</name>, and kill Some meat to last us through the Western Mountains which Commences a fiew miles above us and runs in a N. N. W. &amp; S. S. E. derection. The three Indians encamped near us and visited our fire    we entered into a kind of a Conversation by signs, of the Country and Situation of the rivers.    they informed us that <name type="place" key="Washougal (Seal) River">Seal river</name> headed in the mountains at no great distance.    <name type="place" key="Sandy (Quicksand) River">quick Sand river</name> was Short only headed in <name type="place" key="Mount Hood (Timm, Falls Mountain)">Mt. Hood</name> which is in view and to which he pointed.    this is a circumstance we did not expect as we had heretofore deemed a comsiderable river. <name type="place" key="Mount Hood (Timm, Falls Mountain)">Mount Hood</name> bears East from this place and is distant from this place about 40 miles.    this information if true will render it necessary to examine the river below on the South Side behind the <name type="place" key="Hayden (Image Canoe) Island">image canoe</name> and <name type="place" key="Sauvie (Wapato) Island">Wappato islands</name> for some river which must water the Country weste of the western mountains to the <name type="place" key="Gulf of California">Waters of California</name>.<ref target="n31033110" n="10"/> The <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> is at present on a Stand and we with dificuelty made 25 miles to day—.
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Monday 31st March 1806.    a clear pleasant morning.    we Set out eairly and proceed. on    passd. a village<ref target="n31033111" n="11"/> which was a large one when we went down last fall but the Savages are more Scattered along the River in fishing parties &amp;C.    only 2 cabbins left at this village on the South Shore in a large bottom.    the wind rose from the Southward.    a number of the Savages followed us with their canoes.    one of our hunters<ref target="n31033112" n="12"/> killed a deer &amp; Saw a great number more Deer &amp; Elk in these bottoms &amp;c. this morning.    in the evening we passed the mo of <name type="place" key="Washougal (Seal) River">Seal River</name>
                  <ref target="n31033113" n="13"/> on N. Side    the waves high.    we Encamped<ref target="n31033114" n="14"/> a Short distance above Sd. River on a handsom high plain of rich land &amp; timber    near this is opposite the mouth of <name type="place" key="Sandy (Quicksand) River">Quick Sand River</name>
                  <ref target="n31033115" n="15"/> which puts in on South Side &amp; is high at this time.


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Monday 31st.</hi>    This was a beautiful clear morning, and we proceeded on early. One of the men went along shore, and in a short time killed a deer: the deer are very plentiful on this part of the river.— We proceeded on, and passed a large village which was full of people as we went down, but is now all deserted except one lodge.<ref target="n31033116" n="16"/> In the evening, we came to a small prairie, opposite the mouth of <name type="place" key="Sandy (Quicksand) River">Quicksand river</name>, where we encamped.
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry">
            <sp who="jw">
               <speaker>Whitehouse</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Monday March 31st    A clear pleasant morning, We set out early and proceeded on, &amp; passed a Village which lay on the So. side of the River.    This Village when we descended the River was large, but the greater part of the houses were removed &amp; lay scattering along the Shore, for the convenience of the Inhabitants fishing.    One of our hunters killed a deer, &amp; mention'd that he had seen a number of them, Elk &amp;ca    Several of the natives followed us from the last Indian Village, in small Canoes.    In the Evening we passed the Mouth of a river lying on the North side of the River &amp; encamped a short distance above it, on a handsome high Priari laying on the North Side of the River &amp; Opposite to <name type="place" key="Sandy (Quicksand) River">Quick sand River</name>.




</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n31033101" n="1">
               <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Shah-ha-la</name> is from Chinookan <hi rend="italic">
                  <seg n="u353">š</seg>á<seg n="uxu803">x̣</seg>l(a),</hi> "upriver, above," and <hi rend="italic">
                  <seg n="u353">š</seg>á<seg n="uxu803">x̣</seg>latk<seg n="u353">š</seg>,</hi> "those upriver." For the people and the village see <ref n="1805-11-02" type="related">November 2</ref> and <ref n="1805-11-04" type="related">4</ref>, 1805.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31033102" n="2">The later <name type="place" key="Cascade Range">Cascades</name>, in the vicinity of present <name type="place" key="Bonneville Dam">Bonneville Dam</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31033103" n="3">On this portion of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> the inhabitants were of the Upper Chinook division of the Chinookan linguistic family, living below <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The Dalles</name>. The Lower <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinooks</name>, consisting of <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinooks</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsops</name>, lived near the mouth of the river. There were various dialectal differences within the division.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31033104" n="4">This is the farthest downstream occurrence of burial vaults on the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31033105" n="5">A combination of <name type="place" key="Government (Diamond, White Goose, Swan) Island">Government</name> and <name type="place" key="McGuire (Diamond, Swan, White Goose) Island">McGuire islands</name>, <name type="place" key="Multnomah County, Oreg.">Multnomah County</name>, <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>, and <name type="place" key="Lady (White Brant) Island">Lady (White Brant) Island</name>, <name type="place" key="Clark County, Wash.">Clark County</name>, <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 79. See also <ref n="1805-11-03" type="related">November 3, 1805</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31033106" n="6">
               <name type="place" key="Sandy (Quicksand) River">Sandy River</name>, in <name type="place" key="Multnomah County, Oreg.">Multnomah County</name>, <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>. The camp, where the main party would remain until April 6, was in <name type="place" key="Clark County, Wash.">Clark County</name>, <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>, above the entrance of the <name type="place" key="Washougal (Seal) River">Washougal (Seal) River</name> in the vicinity of present <name type="place" key="Washougal, Wash.">Washougal</name>. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 79.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31033107" n="7">The harbor seal, <hi rend="italic">Phoca vitulina richardii.</hi>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="n31033108" n="8">The wood duck, <hi rend="italic">Aix sponsa</hi> [AOU, 144]; see <ref n="1805-07-29" type="related">July 29, 1805</ref>. Burroughs, 191–92; Holmgren, 29. A vertical line runs through this passage, perhaps <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle's</name> mark.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31033109" n="9">This word appears to have replaced another, erased word.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31033110" n="10">The <name type="place" key="Willamette (Multnomah) River">Willamette River</name>, reaching the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> below <name type="place" key="Portland, Oreg.">Portland</name>, <name type="place" key="Multnomah County, Oreg.">Multnomah County</name>; the "<name type="place" key="Willamette (Multnomah) River">Multnomah R</name>" of <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 79. It does not drain nearly as great an area as the captains imagined, nor does any western river. They could not, of course, know of the existence of the <name type="place" key="Great Basin">Great Basin</name>, the huge area west of the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rockies</name> that has no exterior drainage. The concept of this mighty river would persist among geographers until fully dispelled by <name type="person" key="Frémont, John C.">John C. Frémont's</name> exploration in the 1840s. See <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> maps 123, 125. Allen (PG), 334–36, 394.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31033111" n="11">A village of the <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Watlala Indians</name>, <name type="place" key="Portland, Oreg.">Portland</name>, <name type="place" key="Multnomah County, Oreg.">Multnomah County</name>, <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>. See <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>
entries of <ref n="1805-11-02" type="related">November 2</ref> and <ref n="1805-11-04" type="related">4</ref>, 1805.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31033112" n="12">Perhaps <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name>; see <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> entry of this day.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31033113" n="13">
               <name type="place" key="Washougal (Seal) River">Washougal River</name>, <name type="place" key="Clark County, Wash.">Clark County</name>, <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31033114" n="14">In <name type="place" key="Clark County, Wash.">Clark County</name>, <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>, above the entrance of <name type="place" key="Washougal (Seal) River">Washougal River</name> (the party's <name type="place" key="Washougal (Seal) River">Seal River</name>), near <name type="place" key="Washougal, Wash.">Washougal</name>, where the party remained until April 6.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31033115" n="15">
               <name type="place" key="Sandy (Quicksand) River">Quicksand River</name> is present <name type="place" key="Sandy (Quicksand) River">Sandy River</name>, <name type="place" key="Multnomah County, Oreg.">Multnomah County</name>, <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31033116" n="16">The captains called the people <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Shahalas</name>; they were probably <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Watlalas</name>. The village was 
within <name type="place" key="Portland, Oreg.">Portland</name>, <name type="place" key="Multnomah County, Oreg.">Multnomah County</name>, <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>, probably on the site of the airport.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-03-30" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-03-31-1" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>