<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.introduction.v09">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">Introduction to Volume 9</title>
            <title type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
            <author>Gary E. Moulton</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">xi-xix</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-03-02</date>
            <date/>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>
            <name/>Initial creation Transcribed</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="main">Introduction to Volume 9</head>
         <head type="sub"/>
         <div type="introduction">
            <p>
The essential, definitive record of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> expedition is contained in
the journals and observations of the two captains, "the writingest explorers of their
time," in the words of Donald Jackson.<ref target="n01" n="1"/> If no one else associated with the enterprise had written a word we would still have a marvelous narrative replete with geographic, zoological, botanical, and ethnographic information. In fact, however, at
least four other members of the party did set down their own daily accounts. This
edition brings them together with those of their commanders for the first time.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">President Thomas Jefferson</name> did not order the actual keeping of separate journals by anyone other than the captains. In his final instructions to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, however, he did suggest that "several copies of these as well as of your other notes should be made at leisure times, &amp; put into the care of the most trust-worthy of your attendants, to guard, by multiplying them, against the accidental losses to which they will
be exposed."<ref target="n02" n="2"/> All this would seem to require is that some of the "attendants" copy
the captains' journals verbatim. Apparently <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, at an early stage, decided to do something else. On May 26, 1804, less than two weeks out from <name type="place" key="Dubois River">River
Dubois</name>, the captains noted that "The sergts . . . are directed each to keep a separate
journal from day to day of all passing accurences, and such other observations on
the country &amp;c. as shall appear to them worthy of notice.—"<ref target="n03" n="3"/>
            </p>
            <p>
In his last communication to <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> from <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name> in April 1805, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>
wrote: "We have encouraged our men to keep journals, and seven of them do so, to
whom in this respect we give every assistance in our power."<ref target="n04" n="4"/>
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> had a sense of
history; in departing westward from the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> villages he compared his little fleet
of pirogues and canoes to the vessels of <name type="person" key="Cook, James">Captain Cook</name>.<ref target="n05" n="5"/> The significance of his enterprise warranted as complete a record as possible. It might be too much to ask any
enlisted men to copy their officers' voluminous journals, but those so inclined could
be encouraged to add their bit to the record.</p>
            <p>
At least some of the men who went with <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> seem to have shared that
sense of history. They were volunteers, after all, and although some of them no
doubt simply hoped to escape from irksome military discipline or to find good beaver streams, others evidently knew very well that this was the chance of a lifetime,
that they were involved in something that would survive them, something greater
than their individual contribution. The combination of that sense of history with a
degree of literacy and considerable diligence made a few of them journal keepers.</p>
            <p>
To appreciate the work of these men, let us remember the conditions under
which they wrote. Most days of the voyage involved hard physical labor, working
canoes upstream, loading and unloading bulky equipment, hunting and butchering, tanning leather, making moccasins, cooking, chopping and shaping wood, caring for horses and searching for strays, mounting guard, portaging around falls and rapids, all of it while exposed to every kind of weather and to the attacks of insects
and grizzly bears, with the constant danger of physical injury from accidents. At the
end of such a day, perhaps while others were dancing to <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Pierre Cruzatte's</name> fiddle, a
journal keeper would have to write by the light of a campfire in notebooks somehow
kept safe from the elements. According to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, seven of the thirty-odd men had
the perseverance and the sense of the destiny to try.</p>
            <p>
They wrote under the same conditions as the captains, and like them wrote not
only for themselves. It seems probable that they examined each other's journals,
and perhaps <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> read them, too. We know that on July 14, 1804, having
lost his notes for the previous day, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had "to refur to the . . . Journals of Serjeants." The enlisted men's journals were intended as part of the record; they were
public documents and we cannot expect any deep psychological revelations. No one
recorded explicitly, for example, his opinion of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> or <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> or <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name>.</p>
            <p>
Literacy was the first requirement. It is probable that some of the men could not
even write their own names. Historians have expressed considerable humor over
<name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> awkward grammar and his versatility as a speller, but he was little worse than
many contemporaries who like him were men of affairs, government officials, and
army officers. Comparison of <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> journal with those of the enlisted men should
keep us from laughing too much at <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>. Nor should we be overly amused at the
enlisted men, for none of their journals suggests stupidity or dullness. They tried to
the best of their ability to record an extraordinary experience.</p>
            <p>
Sergeants in the army had to be literate, since they kept records for their companies, and it is not too surprising that three of the four enlisted men's journals that
we now have are those of sergeants. <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">John Ordway</name> and <name type="person" key="Floyd, Charles">Charles Floyd</name> held that rank
from the start of the trip, and <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Patrick Gass</name> was promoted some three months out to
fill the place of the deceased <name type="person" key="Floyd, Charles">Floyd</name>. <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Joseph Whitehouse</name> is the only private whose
journal we now have. <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway's</name> spelling and grammar are, if anything, better than
<name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>. We cannot judge <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass's</name> performance for we do not have his original writing.
<name type="person" key="Floyd, Charles">Floyd</name> and <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse</name> apparently struggled with writing, but there is rarely doubt
about what they meant.</p>
            <p>
We have four enlisted men's journals, in one form or another. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> indicated
that seven men were keeping journals, and the discrepancy requires some notice,
although few hard conclusions can be made. Since the other sergeants were expected to keep journals, one would assume that <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Sergeant Nathaniel Pryor</name> would
also do so, but no document demonstrating this has come to light. <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Pryor</name> served later
on as an army officer and an Indian agent, but other men filled those posts on the
frontier who could barely sign their names. On August 12, 1806, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> noted that
<name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Pryor</name> had left behind saddlebags containing his "papers," but <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Pryor</name> had just returned from being separated from the main party, and the papers could have consisted only of letters he was supposed to deliver to a Canadian trader, and perhaps
a journal of his separate trip, which began barely three weeks before. In any case,
<name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Pryor</name> went back and recovered the saddlebags, so the papers, whatever they were,
were not then lost. There is simply no clear evidence to show that <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Pryor</name> was one of
the seven journal keepers mentioned by <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>.</p>
            <p>
It is fairly certain that one private besides <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse</name> kept some sort of journal,
because <name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">Robert Frazer</name> announced his intention to publish by issuing a prospectus
soliciting subscribers barely a month after the party returned to <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>, promising
"An accurate description of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> and its several branches; of the mountains
separating the Eastern from the Western waters; of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia river</name> and the Bay
it forms on the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific Ocean</name>; of the face of the Country in general; of the several
Tribes of Indians on the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> and <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> rivers . . . ," and with all this "a
variety of Curious and interesting occurrences during a voyage of two years four
months and nine days." The account, <name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">Frazer</name> made clear, was "Published by Permission of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captn. Meriwether Lewis</name>."<ref target="n06" n="6"/> If the journal was anything like what <name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">Frazer</name>
promised, that it was never published is a great pity. Given the importance of the
expedition this is surprising, especially since <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Patrick Gass</name> was able to secure publication of his work the next year and since there were six further editions of his book
in six years. Clearly it was not lack of public interest in <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> discoveries
that held <name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">Frazer's</name> work back. Whatever the problem was, <name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">Frazer</name> passed from view
and so did his journal; we have no clue as to its fate.</p>
            <p>
In April 1805, when <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> wrote that seven men were keeping journals, <name type="person" key="Floyd, Charles">Floyd</name> was
already dead. If we accept <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Pryor</name> and <name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">Frazer</name> as journal keepers, along with <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name>,
<name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, and <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse</name>, we still have two others to account for. It is possible that
<name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> counted <name type="person" key="Floyd, Charles">Floyd</name>, whose journal was sent back from <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name>, even though
his record had ceased the previous August. There is a possibility that <name type="person" key="Willard, Alexander">Private Alexander Willard</name> kept a journal, and with <name type="person" key="Willard, Alexander">Willard</name> and <name type="person" key="Floyd, Charles">Floyd</name> we would have <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> seven journal keepers.<ref target="n07" n="7"/> One way or another a considerable part of the record appears to be lost, perhaps forever.</p>
            <p>
The journals that remain belong with those of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, supporting them
to the best of their ability as they did during the voyage. After the return <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>
evaluated his men, each according to his individual merits, and then wrote of them
all: "the Ample support which they gave me under every difficulty; the manly firmness which they evinced on every necessary occasion; and the patience and fortitude
with which they submitted to, and bore, the fatigues and painful sufferings incident to my late tour to the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific Ocean</name>, entitles them to my warmest approbation
and thanks."<ref target="n08" n="8"/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="center">
                  <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">JOHN ORDWAY</name>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Sergeant John Ordway</name> clearly made an important contribution to the success of the
expedition, and he has left us in many ways the fullest of the enlisted men's records.
Yet we know frustratingly little about him. Virtually every mention of him in the
captains' journals refers simply to his performance of some duty, with no other comment. There could be no better evidence that he did his job well. Born in <name type="place" key="New Hampshire">New
Hampshire</name> in about 1775, apparently he had some of the qualities often attributed
to New Englanders, including steadiness, diligence, and dependability. He was serving in <name type="person" key="Bissell, Russell">Captain Russell Bissell's</name> company of the First Infantry Regiment when he
joined <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, and the captains apparently made him a sergeant before
any of the others who held that rank with the Corps of Discovery. He was left in
charge at <name type="place" key="Camp Dubois (Camp Wood, River Dubois) (Ill.)">Camp Dubois</name> on various occasions when the two officers had to be absent.<ref target="n09" n="9"/> In other words, he was the "top sergeant" of the outfit, expected to preserve
discipline and see that things ran smoothly. He probably had a regular army way of
doing things that pleased <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> but perhaps did not sit too well with some
of the newly enlisted frontiersmen. At any rate, on returning to <name type="place" key="Camp Dubois (Camp Wood, River Dubois) (Ill.)">Camp Dubois</name> on
one occasion, the captains reprimanded <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">Reubin Field</name> and <name type="person" key="Shields, John">John Shields</name> for disobeying <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> who, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> noted, "has during their necessary absence been charged
with the execution of their orders; acting from those orders expressly, and not from
his own capriece, and who, is in all respects accountable to us for the faithfull observance of the same."<ref target="n10" n="10"/> That <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> continued as a sergeant indicates that his performance was satisfactory.</p>
            <p>
Since <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, like the other members of the Corps, was a volunteer, we might
assume that he had a sense of adventure and wanted to do something more than
serve out his enlistment. More insight into his character can be gained from some
family letters written before he left on the voyage of discovery. In September 1803
he wrote to his brother <name type="person" key="Ordway, Stephen">Stephen</name> of his homesickness, denying a rumor that he had
become engaged, and asking his brother to present his compliments to a young lady
named <name type="person" key="Crosby, Betsey">Betsey Crosby</name>, saying, "the probability is, that if She remains in a State of
celibacy till my return I may perhaps join hands with hir yet."<ref target="n11" n="11"/>
               <name type="person" key="Crosby, Betsey">Miss Crosby</name> apparently found <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway's</name> promises too indefinite, or the state of celibacy too irksome,
and married someone else. <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> probably joined the Corps of Discovery when
the captains passed <name type="place" key="Kaskaskia, Ill.">Kaskaskia</name>, <name type="place" key="Illinois">Illinois</name>, where he was stationed, in November 1803.
In April 1804 he wrote to his "Honored Parence" telling them of his new enlistment: "I am now on an expidition to the westward, with <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt.
Clark</name>. . . .  We are to ascend the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri River</name> with a boat as far as it is navigable
and then to go by land, to the western ocean, if nothing prevents, &amp;c." He also told
them that "I am So happy as to be one of them pick'd men from the armey, and I
and all the party are if we live to Return, to Receive our Discharge when ever we
return again toe the united States if we chuse it." He expected to be gone eighteen
months to two years and to receive a "great Reward," of "15 dollars pr. month and
at least 400 ackers of first Rate land, and if we make Great Discoveries as we expect,
the united States, has promised to make us Great Rewards more than we are promised, &amp;c."<ref target="n12" n="12"/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> was the most faithful of all the party's journal keepers; even <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> missed
a few days, but the sergeant has an entry for every day from May 14, 1804, when the
Corps left <name type="place" key="Dubois River">River Dubois</name>, to September 23, 1806, when they returned to <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>—
863 days in all. He perhaps waited a day or two to fill in entries in especially trying
times, but he cannot have waited long. Even during the most difficult periods, such
as the journey over the <name type="place" key="Lolo Trail">Lolo Trail</name> in September 1805, his entries are fair-sized paragraphs. During the uneventful days at <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name> and <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name>, he contented
himself with a few lines. His grammar, spelling, and vocabulary are at least as good
as <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> did not record the detailed courses and distances of each day's journey,
as the captains did, nor the wealth of scientific data; the events of each day were his
primary concern, yet he shows evidence of curiosity and an interest in the things
and people around him. On May 5, 1805, he noted that the grizzly "bair" killed
that day was one "which the natives and the french tradors call white but all of the
kind that we have seen is of a light brown only owing to the climate as we suppose."
The captains have no such thoughts about the animal's color that day, although they
give a more detailed description. While among the <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Flathead Indians</name> on September 5, 1805, <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> observed, "these natives have the Stranges language of any we
have ever yet seen. they appear to us as though they had an Impedement in their
Speech or brogue on their tongue. we think perhaps that they are the <name type="native_nation" key="Welsh Indians">welch Indians</name>,
&amp;. C." <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, the only one of the officers keeping a journal at this point, said only
that the <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Flathead</name> (<name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Salish</name>) tongue "is a gugling kind of language Spoken much thro
the Throught." <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> also reconsidered the old legend of the elusive <name type="native_nation" key="Welsh Indians">Welsh Indians</name> when he was among the <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Flatheads</name>.</p>
            <p>
On July 16, 1805, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> both tell us that they sent a man back for an
axe forgotten at their previous night's camp, their standard procedure when such a
lapse occurred. They do not mention the man's name, and it is to <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway's</name> honesty
that we owe the knowledge that he was the culprit. On the return journey, when
<name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> and <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> made separate explorations, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> sent <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> with nine other
men in canoes down the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> from the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Three Forks of the">Three Forks</name> to the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">Great Falls</name>. The
sergeant was on his own and provides the only record of this part of the expedition
from July 13 to July 19, 1806, when he joined the party under <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Sergeant Gass</name> that
<name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> had left at the <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Great Falls of the">Great Falls</name>. <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> then promptly recorded the events of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> party when they were separated from <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, and after meeting <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> on July 28
he described the tragic events of the captain's party. Describing <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">Reubin Field's</name> killing of a <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name> Indian on July 27 he became almost poetic: "he drew but one
breath    the wind of his breath followed the knife &amp; he fell dead."</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> did not choose any more than did the other journal keepers to provide
much information about the day-to-day personal relationships within the party. 
The nature of his office surely caused special strains and frustrations, but he said
nothing of this; there is no hint of the incidents of disobedience at <name type="place" key="Camp Dubois (Camp Wood, River Dubois) (Ill.)">Camp Dubois</name>,
which occurred before he began his journal. We would like to know how the top
sergeant of the Corps of Discovery evaluated the men who served with him, and the
two men who commanded him, but the New Hampshireman maintained his discretion. Like the captains he was writing a public document, not a private record of
emotions. Even the desertion of <name type="person" key="Reed, Moses B.">Moses Reed</name>, which aroused <name type="person" key="Floyd, Charles">Floyd's</name> indignation, is
reported by <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> in the most matter-of-fact way, on August 6, 1804.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway's</name> life following the return to <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> is nearly as obscure as it was before.
He accompanied <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and a party of Indians to <name type="place" key="Washington D.C.">Washington, D.C.</name>, in late 1806,
took his discharge from the army, and returned to <name type="place" key="New Hampshire">New Hampshire</name>. In 1809 he
settled in <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, where he married and became prosperous, acquiring "two plantations under good cultivation peach and apple orchards, good buildings &amp;c &amp;c."
He did not enjoy them for long, however, for both he and his wife were dead by
1817.<ref target="n13" n="13"/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway's</name> journal is in three notebooks. The first, handstitched sheets covered by
loose boards, apparently started out as the Orderly Book of the Corps, which the
sergeant would have kept as part of his duties, and became his journal on May 14,
1804, when the expedition set out. This book lasted him until the end of September 1805. The next day, October 1, at the <name type="place" key="Canoe Camp (Idaho)">Canoe Camp</name> on the <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Clearwater River</name> in
<name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>, he commenced writing in a notebook bound in stiff boards and covered with
marbled paper that lasted until May 15, 1806, when he was back on the <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Clearwater</name>
some miles upstream at <name type="place" key="Camp Chopunnish (Idaho)">Camp Chopunnish</name>. A collection of uncovered sheets then
served him until September 23, 1806, when he closed: "the party all considerable
much rejoiced that we have the Expedition Completed and now we look for boarding in Town and wait for our Settlement an then we entend to return to our native
homes to See our parents once more as we have been so long from them.—    finis."</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> turned his journal over to the captains in return for $300. It was among
the papers that <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> provided <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Nicholas Biddle</name> for use in preparing his history of
the expedition. <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name> found it very useful and judged it much better than <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass's</name>
journal, which he also examined, probably in its printed form. Indeed he was so
fond of it that he never returned it to <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, as he was supposed to, nor did he turn
it over to the American Philosophical Society with other expedition documents in
1816, as <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> wished. His grandsons found it among his papers in 1913, and it
was edited by Milo Milton Quaife for publication with <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> Eastern
Journal by the State Historical Society of Wisconsin.<ref target="n14" n="14"/> It now appears together with
the other expedition journals for the first time.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="center">
                  <name type="person" key="Floyd, Charles">CHARLES FLOYD</name>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Floyd, Charles">Sergeant Charles Floyd</name>, according to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, was "a young man of much merit."<ref target="n15" n="15"/>
We do not know a great deal more about him. He has the tragic fame of being the
only man of the party to die on the expedition, and an impressive monument rises
over his remains at <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux City, Iowa">Sioux City</name>, <name type="place" key="Iowa">Iowa</name>, near the place where he died. Born in 1782, he
was one of the "nine young men from <name type="place" key="Kentucky">Kentucky</name>" who joined <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> at the Falls of
the <name type="place" key="Ohio River">Ohio</name>. He may have been a relative of <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>; at any rate, on hearing of his death
his brother <name type="person" key="Floyd, Nathaniel">Nathaniel</name> wrote to their sister <name type="person" key="Floyd, Nancy">Nancy</name> that "he was well cared for as <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>
was there." We do know that he was a cousin of <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Sergeant Pryor</name>. Although he enlisted
from civilian life, the captains made him a sergeant over men who were older, had
much more frontier experience, and had served in the regular army. This elevation
must have reflected his education, his character, and perhaps his family connections. Writing shortly after the sergeant's death, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> said that <name type="person" key="Floyd, Charles">Floyd</name> "had at All
times given us proofs of his impatiality Sincurity to ourselves and good will to Serve
his Countrey."<ref target="n16" n="16"/> There is little mention of <name type="person" key="Floyd, Charles">Floyd</name> in the captains' journals, which is
probably an indication that he did his duty efficiently and caused no trouble. Starting with the official beginning of the expedition on May 14, 1804, he kept his journal faithfully until two days before his death on August 20, 1804, although he must
have been feeling the effects of his illness well before then.<ref target="n17" n="17"/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Floyd, Charles">Floyd</name> kept his journal in a small notebook with marbled paper over the covers,
in which there are also a few notes by <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>. He had filled most of it by the time of
his death. The captains of course preserved it during the winter at <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name> and
apparently sent it back to his relatives in <name type="place" key="Kentucky">Kentucky</name> with the returning party in the
spring of 1805. In 1893 Reuben Gold Thwaites discovered it among the papers of
Lyman Draper, former head of the State Historical Society of Wisconsin. Draper, an
assiduous collector of historical documents, had acquired a large number of <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>
papers from the captain's nephew, <name type="person" key="Croghan, John">John Croghan</name>, and had also corresponded with
<name type="person" key="Floyd, Charles">Floyd's</name> sister, <name type="person" key="Walton, Mary Lee">Mary Lee Walton</name>. He kept no records of his own acquisitions, and the
exact source of this find is unknown. It remains in the Draper Collection in the State
Historical Society of Wisconsin, Madison.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Floyd, Charles">Floyd's</name> entries are generally brief and factual; they resemble <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> at his most
laconic. His spelling and grammar are also reminiscent of <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, and like the captain his vocabulary and phrasing suggest a man who had done some reading. In
some cases it is clear that he had copied passages verbatim from <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, in the spirit
of <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name> instructions. It may be that much of his writing was simply a condensation of <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> field notes, but occasionally he provides information that <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>
does not. On July 9, 1804, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> notes a spot in <name type="place" key="Doniphan County, Kans.">Doniphan County</name>, <name type="place" key="Kansas">Kansas</name>, "where
Several french men camped two years ago to hunt.—" <name type="person" key="Floyd, Charles">Floyd</name> describes it as "a prarie
on the South Side whare Seveal French famileys had Setled and made Corn Some
Years ago Stayed two years." The next day <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> tells us that <name type="place" key="Cedar (Pape, Pappie) Creek (Kans.)">"R. <hi rend="italic">Pape</hi>"</name> (present
<name type="place" key="Cedar (Pape, Pappie) Creek (Kans.)">Cedar Creek</name> in <name type="place" key="Doniphan County, Kans.">Doniphan County</name>) was "called after a Spanierd who killed himself
at th[e] mouth." <name type="person" key="Floyd, Charles">Floyd</name> clarifies this somewhat by noting that "it is Called after a
man who by drawning his Gun out of the Boat Shot him Self."</p>
            <p>
In reporting the desertion of <name type="person" key="Reed, Moses B.">Private Moses Reed</name>, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> is entirely matter-of-fact;
<name type="person" key="Floyd, Charles">Floyd</name> records details not found elsewhere and expresses the indignation that perhaps they all felt: "pon examining his nap-Sack we found that he had taken his Cloas
and all His powder and Balles, and had hid them out that night and had made that
an excuse to Desarte from us with out aney Jest Case." <name type="person" key="Floyd, Charles">Floyd</name> apparently had an eye
for such details, which makes us regret all the more that he did not live to complete
a record of the whole journey. As it is, the two captains have made it clear that he
did his duty as long as he could.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n01" n="1">Donald Jackson, ed., <hi rend="italic">Letters of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition with Related Documents</hi>, <hi rend="italic">1783–1854</hi> (2d ed., 2 vols. Urbana: University of <name type="place" key="Illinois">Illinois</name> Press, 1978), 1:vii.</note>
            <note xml:id="n02" n="2">
               <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name> Instructions to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> [June 20, 1803], ibid., 1:62.</note>
            <note xml:id="n03" n="3">See the Orderly Book entry for <ref n="1804-05-26" type="related">May 26, 1804</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n04" n="4">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> to <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, April 7, 1805, Jackson, ed., <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, 1:232.</note>
            <note xml:id="n05" n="5">See <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> journal entry for April 7, 1805.</note>
            <note xml:id="n06" n="6">The <name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">Robert Frazer</name> Prospectus [October 1806], Jackson, ed., <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, 1:345–46.</note>
            <note xml:id="n07" n="7">On <name type="person" key="Willard, Alexander">Willard's</name> journal, see Olin D. Wheeler, <hi rend="italic">The Trail of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>
               </hi>, <hi rend="italic">1804–1806</hi> (2
vols. <name type="place" key="New York">New York</name>: G. P. Putnam's Sons, 1904), 1:124; and Robert B. Betts, " 'The writingest
explorers of their time': New Estimates of the Number of Words in the Published Journals of
the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition," <hi rend="italic">We Proceeded On</hi> 7 (August 1981): 7–8, 8 n.34.</note>
            <note xml:id="n08" n="8">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> to <name type="person" key="Dearborn, Henry">Henry Dearborn</name>, January 15, 1807, Jackson, ed., <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, 1:369.</note>
            <note xml:id="n09" n="9">See <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> Detachment Orders for <ref n="1804-02-20" type="related">February 20, 1804</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n10" n="10">See the Detachment Orders for <ref n="1804-03-03" type="related">March 3, 1804</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n11" n="11">
               <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">John Ordway</name> to <name type="person" key="Ordway, Stephen">Stephen Ordway</name>, September 5, 1803, Jackson, ed., <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, 1:120–21.</note>
            <note xml:id="n12" n="12">
               <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">John Ordway</name> to His Parents, April 8, 1804, ibid., 1:176–77.</note>
            <note xml:id="n13" n="13">Milo Milton Quaife, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Journals of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Meriwether Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Sergeant John Ordway</name> Kept on the Expedition of Western Exploration, 1803–1806</hi> (Madison: State Historical Society of Wisconsin, 1916), 28; Charles G. Clarke, <hi rend="italic">The Men of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition: A Biographical Roster of the Fifty-one Members and a Composite Diary of Their Activities from All Known
Sources</hi> (Glendale, Calif.: Arthur H. Clark, 1970), 40–41.</note>
            <note xml:id="n14" n="14">Paul Russell Cutright, <hi rend="italic">A History of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Journals</hi> (Norman: University of Oklahoma Press, 1976), 128–29; <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Nicholas Biddle</name> to <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, July 7, 1810, Jackson, ed., <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, 2:551; Quaife, <hi rend="italic">Journals of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>
               </hi>, 25–26.</note>
            <note xml:id="n15" n="15">Jackson, ed., <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, 1:366. See also <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clarke</name>, <hi rend="italic">The Men of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition</hi>, 39.</note>
            <note xml:id="n16" n="16">See <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> first entry for <ref n="1804-08-20" type="related">August 20, 1804</ref>, in the Field Notes. The Codex B entry, perhaps written some time later, says much the same.</note>
            <note xml:id="n17" n="17">On the nature of <name type="person" key="Floyd, Charles">Floyd's</name> illness see Eldon G. Chuinard, <hi rend="italic">Only One Man Died: The Medical Aspects of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition</hi> (Glendale, Calif.: Arthur H. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, 1979), 238–39.</note>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>