<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.lc.blake.01">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
               <hi rend="italic">Great Plains Quarterly</hi> 24:4 (2004): 263–82.</title>
            <title type="sub">Great Plains Native American Representations
Along The <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> And Clark Trail</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="Blake, Kevin S.">Kevin S. Blake</name>
            </author>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-6-13</date>
            <name>Beth Burke</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="main">Great Plains Native American Representations Along The <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> And <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Trail</head>
         <p>by <ref target="http://www.k-state.edu/geography/kblake/">Kevin S. Blake</ref>
         </p>
         <div type="article">
            <p>(This article first appeared in the <hi rend="italic">
                  <ref target="http://www.unl.edu/plains">Great Plains Quarterly</ref>
               </hi> 24:4 (2004): 263–82.)</p>
            <p>Memorializing history in the landscape reflects deep-seated cultural needs. This process not only pays homage to the actions, events, or persons deemed significant at a particular point in time, but it also offers a chance for the creators of the historic marker to write their version of history and to use an interpretive format that highlights their own understanding and values. Cultural geographer <name type="person" key="Foote, Kenneth">Kenneth Foote</name> observes in a study of American memorials, "What is accepted as historical truth is often a narrative shaped and reshaped through time to fit the demands of contemporary society."<ref target="nlc.blake.0101" n="1"/> The significance of selecting particular historical interpretations for commemoration is that the impress of these upon the landscape plays a key role in shaping social memory, as "nations rewrite their history, forgetting much, denying more, and replacing past perspectives with new national images and explanations."<ref target="nlc.blake.0102" n="2"/> Ironically, some of the peoples central to American identity—Native Americans—are often memorialized with markers that "mistreat" them, creating a contested landscape of social memory that stands "in desperate need of revision."<ref target="nlc.blake.0103" n="3"/>
            </p>
            <p>In the midst of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> bicentennial commemorations, the significance of American Indians in the social memory of the expedition is strongly debated. Some American Indians express concern over the interpretation of their people and see the bicentennial as an opportunity "to tell their own story of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, an epic about Indians hailing out whites, showing them where to go, what to eat, whom to avoid along the way, and how to get hack home in one piece."<ref target="nlc.blake.0104" n="4"/>
               <name type="person" key="Conner, Roberta">Roberta Conner</name>, a member of the Confederated Tribes of the <name type="native_nation" key="Umatilla Indians">Umatilla</name> Indian Reservation in Oregon and director of its Tamástslikt Cultural Institute, notes that although the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition is only a "tiny story" within the context of American Indian history, it is one with "tremendous impact" because it "is a story about land, the places we call home."<ref target="nlc.blake.0105" n="5"/>
            </p>
            <p>The purpose of this article is to examine the portrayal of American Indians at the interpretive sites along the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> National Historic Trail (NHT) in the <name type="place" key="Great Plains">Great Plains</name> to see to what extent multicultural awareness exists. My central thesis is that many of the representations of Great Plains Native Americans along the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Trail are stereotyped and give little or no voice to Native peoples. This is problematic not only because of the slanted messages about American Indians and social memory that increased numbers of visitors during the bicentennial are receiving along the trail landscape, but also because these poorly drawn interpretations should not be the model for new interpretive sites developed during the spate of bicentennial commemorations. Similar to the perspective of cultural historian <name type="person" key="Dennis, Matthew">Matthew Dennis</name>, I question the meaning of commonly accepted representations of the past and examine them from multiple viewpoints in the belief that this process is essential for all groups to gain meaningful interpretations of the complete cultural and historical significance of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>.<ref target="nlc.blake.0106" n="6"/>
            </p>
            <p>The underlying cause of the desire for a Native American voice in the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> drama goes beyond historical events and the ethnocentric perspective of the expedition journals, it also springs from the privileged status of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition in American social memory. The expedition helped America invent its identity, even while the story grows and changes through each generation.<ref target="nlc.blake.0107" n="7"/>Some of the recent interpretations of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> portray them as proto-ecologists and multicultural diplomats, but all stories have two sides and it strips the expedition of meaning to exclude the American Indian perspective.<ref target="nlc.blake.0108" n="8"/> Examining the misguided interpretations has another benefit, too, since "distorted or oversimplified images of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> are not only inescapable . . . they provide a fascinating index of changes in American society and culture over time."<ref target="nlc.blake.0109" n="9"/>  A more inclusive depiction of Great Plains Native Americans along the NHT (the "Trail Tribes") is a critical element in understanding the rich multicultural heritage of places along the trail and the Native role in helping the expedition travel to the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name> and back.</p>
            <p>This study examines the cultural aftermath of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition through a previously untapped source—the landscape of the interpretive sites on the trail itself. Established in 1978 under the administration of the National Park Service, the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> NHT involves dozens of partnering federal, state, and local agencies, nonprofit organizations, American Indian nations, and private landowners. Even the information centers operated by the federal government along the Great Plains portion of the NHT are under multiple jurisdictions, including the US Army Corps of Engineers, Bureau of Land Management, US Forest Service, and National Park Service. To think of the expedition route as the "<name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Trail" is somewhat of a misnomer since <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> did not typically blaze a new trail. For the most part, the expedition traveled routes previously used by traders or Native Americans, yet the signs of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> pointing the way fix this image in the NHT interpretation.</p>
            <p>GREAT PLAINS PERSPECTIVES</p>
            <p>The Great Plains segment of the NHT is the focus of this study for several reasons. Foremost, this is the "home of the peoples who gave to most of the world the current perception of what an American Indian is."<ref target="nlc.blake.0110" n="10"/> The <name type="native_nation" key="Plains Indians">Plains Indians</name> encountered by <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> also were culturally and linguistically distinct (<name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Siouan</name>, <name type="native_nation" key="Algonquian Indians">Algonquian</name>, <name type="native_nation" key="Caddoan Indians">Caddoan</name>) from the <name type="native_nation" key="Rocky Mountain Indians">Rocky Mountain Indians</name>, with a unique set of intertribal relations and interracial dealings with white traders. Furthermore, the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition expressed a different message to <name type="native_nation" key="Plains Indians">Plains Indians</name> than to those in the mountains or coastal regions because much of the <name type="place" key="Great Plains">Great Plains</name> had recently been claimed by the <name type="place" key="United States">United States</name> in the Louisiana Purchase.</p>
            <p>For the purposes of this study, the <name type="place" key="Great Plains">Great Plains</name> extends from <name type="place" key="Kaw Point">Kaw Point</name> (the confluence of the <name type="place" key="Kansas River">Kansas</name> and <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> rivers in <name type="place" key="Kansas City, Missouri">Kansas City</name>) to the Gates of the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky Mountains</name> in the <name type="place" key="Big Belt Mountains of Montana">Big Belt Mountains of Montana</name>.<ref target="nlc.blake.0111" n="11"/> Even though the mountains are not always in close proximity to the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri River</name> upstream of Gates of the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky Mountains</name>, here the character of the expedition became focused ever more strongly on crossing the <name type="place" key="Great Divide">Great Divide</name>, and for the first time the expedition felt it was <hi rend="italic">in</hi> the mountains as opposed to <hi rend="italic">viewing</hi> mountains. River travelers today also see the <name type="person" key="Rocky Mountain Gates">Gates</name> as the place at the foot of the mountains where the <name type="place" key="Great Plains">Great Plains</name> has been left behind.<ref target="nlc.blake.0112" n="12"/>
            </p>
            <p>One of the Native American messages along the trail is that, to at least some <name type="place" key="Great Plains">Great Plains</name> tribes in 1804, the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition was just one more party of outsiders interested in trade, continuing an already well-established trend. <name type="person" key="King, Tracy">Tracy King</name> of the <name type="native_nation" key="Gros Ventre Indians">Gros Ventre</name> (A'Aninin) Nation says, "If it wasn't <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, it would have been somebody else."<ref target="nlc.blake.0113" n="13"/> Indeed, the incursions of whites had already wreaked radical change with the introduction of horses, weapons, and smallpox and other diseases, as well as the subsequently altered power relations. Yet American Indians easily could have eliminated the expedition at numerous points, and without the aid and accommodation of <name type="native_nation" key="Plains Indians">Plains Indians</name> the expedition would have foundered long before reaching the <name type="person" key="Rocky Mountains">Rockies</name>.<ref target="nlc.blake.0114" n="14"/> The Native American message also tells of how <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> entered an advanced society, not a wilderness, exemplified by the sophisticated agricultural society of the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> nations with large earthlodge towns.<ref target="nlc.blake.0115" n="15"/> To relate their story during the bicentennial commemoration, the tribes have developed tour packages and resource materials for visitors. In <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>, for example, the <name type="native_nation" key="Chippewa Cree Indians">Chippewa Cree</name> run a store marketing tribal arts and crafts, the <name type="native_nation" key="Lower Brule Sioux Indians">Lower Brule Sioux</name> in <name type="place" key="South Dakota">South Dakota</name> tell their tribe's history through tipi and buffalo hide tanning displays, and the Three Affiliated Tribes of the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>, <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name>, and <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> offer overnight stays in <name type="place" key="North Dakota">North Dakota</name> earthlodges. More than a desire to cash in on <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> tourists, this is a prime opportunity for the tribes to educate the public about American Indian culture of two hundred years past.<ref target="nlc.blake.0116" n="16"/>
            </p>
            <p>Although I have made repeated visits to portions of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Trail, this study relies extensively on detailed fieldwork completed in June 2003 along the entire <name type="place" key="Great Plains">Great Plains</name> segment of the route. In the <name type="place" key="Great Plains">Great Plains</name> it is impossible to separate the physical character of land and the season of the year from the way in which its sense of place is interpreted. Open vistas begin to dominate the landscape north and west of <name type="place" key="Kaw Point">Kaw Point</name>, where trees seek "the river valleys, as though to escape a limitless expanse of wind-whipped grass," cottonwoods begin to dominate riparian woodlands, and the expedition first encountered American Indians and bison.<ref target="nlc.blake.0117" n="17"/> In the <name type="place" key="North and South Dakota">Dakotas</name> at this time of year the trail strikes through a mostly treeless, rolling green prairie in a big sky country of endless summer thunderheads. In <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name> the dappled sunlight on the broad expanses of the shortgrass prairie and river lowlands, and the mountains towering into the cumulus, make for unforgettable images along the trail.</p>
            <p>I visited the interpretive sites accessible by automobile within the <name type="place" key="Great Plains">Great Plains</name>, and closely examined those that have interpretation of American Indians in the context of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>.<ref target="nlc.blake.0118" n="18"/> Locations visited by a large number of tourists were deemed most central to this study of how American Indians are represented along the NHT. The absence of any single compendium containing every site on the NHT, coupled with the various routes taken by different members of the expedition, resulted, no doubt, in this study's omission of some sites with on-site interpretation of American Indians. Visiting every single interpretive site, however, would not be a feasible nor necessarily meaningful goal given that at any point in time some interpretive sites along the NHT will be closed due to construction, renovation, or decay. Observations were included from nearly all of the major NHT sites, such as national historic landmarks, national historic sites, and places designated as national signature events in 2004–6 by the National Council of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Bicentennial. An attempt was also made to include observations from interpretive sites representing each of the <name type="native_nation" key="Trail Tribes">Trail Tribes</name>.</p>
            <p>Forty-eight locations with on-site interpretation were examined for this study. Detailed notes about the textual and pictorial interpretation of American Indians were taken, along with photographs where permitted.<ref target="nlc.blake.0119" n="19"/> The sites were then analyzed based on (1) American Indian nations interpreted, (2) date of interpretive site development, (3) funding agency and/or management organization, (4) location, (5) interpretation format (e.g., marker or statue), and most importantly, (6) nature of the American Indian portrayal. The interplay of landscape and memory at these interpretive sites along the trail is important to analyze in this manner since "the very durability of the landscape and the memorials placed in the landscape makes these modifications effective for symbolizing and sustaining collective values over long periods of time."<ref target="nlc.blake.0120" n="20"/> As much as from wood, plastic, and steel, the interpretive sites are built "from strata of memory."<ref target="nlc.blake.0121" n="21"/> Some markers may last only a couple decades, while statues and monuments made of steel or stone may interpret a version of events to multiple generations.</p>
            <p>The findings are categorized into four major thematic representations of American Indians, each having some connection to specific expedition events and places along the trail:  <hi rend="italic">Councils of Power</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Hostile Encounters</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Good Neighbors</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Sacagawea Reinterpreted</hi>. These themes are presented in a westward sequence because each one is shaped by prior events, yet a purely linear or chronological structure would not account for repetition of the representations along the trail. <hi rend="italic">Councils of Power</hi> relates to the councils held with the eastern and central <name type="native_nation" key="Plains Indians">Plains Indians</name>. <hi rend="italic">Hostile Encounters</hi> encompasses the expedition confrontations with American Indians, primarily with the Teton <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name> (<name type="native_nation" key="Lakota Indians">Lakota</name>) in <name type="native_nation" key="South Dakota">South Dakota</name> and the <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name> (<name type="native_nation" key="Pikuni Indians">Pikuni</name>) in <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>. <hi rend="italic">Good Neighbors</hi> relates to the winter spent with the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> (<name type="native_nation" key="Neuidia Indians">Neuidia</name>) and <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> (<name type="native_nation" key="Nuxbaaga Indians">Nuxbaaga</name>) Nations and the expedition's study of <name type="native_nation" key="Plains Indians">Plains Indians</name>. <hi rend="italic">Sacagawea Reinterpreted</hi> includes the multiple archetypes attributed to her, such as guide, interpreter, peace symbol, and Madonna of the trail.</p>
            <p>Interwoven throughout the four themes of American Indian representations is a cameo role that is typically reserved for the Natives. American Indian interpretations consistently receive less space than is devoted to any other major aspect of the expedition, such as the transportation, naturalist observations, and camp life displays in the Chamberlain <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Information Center (opened in 2000 by the <name type="place" key="South Dakota">South Dakota</name> Department of Tourism and the State Historical Society). The Western Historic Trails Center in <name type="place" key="Council Bluffs, Iowa">Council Bluffs</name> (built by the National Park Service in 1997 and operated by the State Historical Society of <name type="place" key="Iowa">Iowa</name>) pays only token attention to Native Americans, noting a few general ethno-historical events, such as decimation by disease. American Indians break out of the cameo role most significantly at the Blackbird Scenic Overview in northeastern <name type="place" key="Nebraska">Nebraska</name>; Atka Lakota Museum in <name type="place" key="Chamberlain, South Dakota">Chamberlain, South Dakota</name>; <name type="place" key="North Dakota">North Dakota</name>
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether"> Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Interpretive Center in <name type="place" key="Washburn">Washburn</name>; Knife River Indian Villages National Historic Site in central <name type="place" key="North Dakota">North Dakota</name>; and the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> NHT Interpretive Center in <name type="place" key="Great Falls, Montana">Great Falls, Montana</name>, but even at these locations some interpretation fits within one of the four dominant themes.</p>
            <p>COUNCILS OF POWER</p>
            <p>The primary objective of the expedition, ascertaining the practicability of a water route across the continent for the purposes of commerce, was bundled with numerous other objectives, including scientific observation and collection of plant, animal, and mineral specimens, observation of weather data, study of Indian cultures, mapping geographic features, promoting American trade, and conducting councils with the Indians.<ref target="nlc.blake.0122" n="22"/> The <hi rend="italic">Councils of Power</hi> representation of American Indians in trail interpretation dominates from <name type="place" key="Kansas City">Kansas City</name> to <name type="place" key="Calumet Bluff">Calumet Bluff</name> at <name type="place" key="Gavins Point Dam, Nebraska">Gavins Point Dam</name> on the <name type="place" key="Nebraska">Nebraska</name>-<name type="place" key="South Dakota">South Dakota</name> border.<ref target="nlc.blake.0123" n="23"/>
            </p>
            <p>Throughout this stretch the explorers were on the lookout for Indians with whom to meet. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> eventually were able to hold council with the <name type="native_nation" key="Otoe Indians">Otoe</name> (<name type="native_nation" key="Jiwere Indians">Jiwere</name>) and <name type="native_nation" key="Missouria Indians">Missouria</name> (<name type="native_nation" key="Nutachi Indians">Nutachi</name>), <name type="native_nation" key="Yankton Sioux Indians">Yankton Sioux</name> (<name type="native_nation" key="Nakota Indians">Nakota</name>), <name type="native_nation" key="Teton Sioux Indians">Teton Sioux</name>, <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> (<name type="native_nation" key="Sahnish Indians">Sahnish</name>), and <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan-Hidatsa Indians">Mandan-Hidatsa</name>, with an intent to promote peaceful trade along the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, inform the Indian children of the replacement of their late Spanish father with a new great white father, andawe the Indians with the military might of the expedition.<ref target="nlc.blake.0124" n="24"/> Although several NHT sites mention Indian trade, including at Case Park in Kansas City, Missouri, where a marker recently erected by the Choteau Society notes that the Kansa had traded with the French, and at the 1980s-era Sergeant Floyd Riverboat Museum (operated by the Sioux City, Iowa, Museum and Historical Association) with a mention of the trading presence of Indians on the river, the overall American Indian interpretation in this segment of the trail is heavily slanted toward the first Otoe-Missouria council on August 3, 1804.</p>
            <p>Images of American Indian acquiescence dominate the <hi rend="italic">Councils of Power</hi> representation, such as at the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Monument in Council Bluffs, Iowa, Nebraska's Fort Atkinson State Historical Park (established in 1963 on the western bank of the river at the site of the first council), and the interpretive centers in Chamberlain and Great Falls (opened in 1998). Displays frequently refer to the American Indian desire for peace and ex-tending the hand of friendship. Replica and authentic peace medals are ubiquitous, implying tribal acceptance of the United States as the sovereign power. The North Dakota <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Interpretive Center, opened in 1997 by the North Dakota <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Bicentennial Foundation in Washburn, informs of the American Indian desire for peaceful trade, which is also a major theme at the Knife River and Fort Union National Historic Sites, but the Washburn center also interprets that Indians were unwilling to part with their war rituals, and the diplomacy of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> "never imagined the Indians as true partners." <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>'s gift-giving is another standard element in <hi rend="italic">Councils of Power</hi>, with displays on this at the interpretive centers in Chamberlain, Calumet Bluff, and Sioux City.</p>
            <p>In the <hi rend="italic">Councils of Power</hi> representation, American Indians are rarely portrayed as equals to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>. The <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Monument in Council Bluffs, erected in 1935 by the Colonial Dames of America and re-dedicated in 1993 to commemorate "the meeting between famed explorers <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> and area Native Americans," has two large relief panels depicting American Indians presenting the expedition with melons (a rare instance of interpretation showing gift-giving by the tribes) and shaking hands with the explorers, but there is no further depth to the tribal interpretation. Not only are the indigenous peoples nameless, the <hi rend="italic">Councils of Power</hi> representation also renders them land-less in a 1990s-era NHT marker at the monument, with a map showing the expedition route in the western portion of the continent passing through lands either designated Oregon Country, Louisiana Purchase, or New Spain, but not Indian lands. The depiction of American Indian land claims as nonexistent or subservient to other powers is repeated in the interpretative maps at Sioux City's Southern Hills Mall (produced for display in 2003 by Split Rock Studios, a museum outfitting company based in Arden Hills, Minnesota), the interpretive center in Sioux City (opened in 2003 by the Missouri River Historical Development, Inc., a nonprofit organization funded by the local riverboat casino), and the 1960s-era Fort Leavenworth Frontier Army Museum. These representations are ironic given that <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>'s 1814 map acknowledged an Indian presence while ignoring Spanish and British claims.<ref target="nlc.blake.0125" n="25"/>
            </p>
            <p>The geographic imprint of the Trail Tribes is consistently absent from many interpretive maps along the NHT, and the <hi rend="italic">Councils of Power</hi> representations are consistent across multiple media and decades. The Council Bluffs monument seemed to set the dominant representation nearly seven decades ago with noble yet stylized depictions of the Otoe-Missouria. Left unsaid is the great change over the past two hundred years for these peoples. Dispossessed of their Platte River homeland in southeastern Nebraska, the Otoe-Missouria eventually relocated to Oklahoma.<ref target="nlc.blake.0126" n="26"/> Rhonda Dent of the Otoe Nation observes, "We were the first to greet <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, and look what happened to us."<ref target="nlc.blake.0127" n="27"/> Bicentennial commemorations and interpretive sites containing a Native American voice would provide these peoples a chance to "reconnect to their homeland."<ref target="nlc.blake.0128" n="28"/> Literally putting the tribes on the maps reinforces the message that the Native peoples, despite overwhelming odds, are still in place to offer their unique perspective.<ref target="nlc.blake.0129" n="29"/>
            </p>
            <p>HOSTILE ENCOUNTERS</p>
            <p>The transition from the <hi rend="italic">Councils of Power</hi> to <hi rend="italic">Hostile Encounters</hi> representation begins in <name type="place" key="Sioux City, Iowa">Sioux City</name> and is complete by central <name type="place" key="South Dakota">South Dakota</name>. The <name type="native_nation" key="Teton Sioux Indians">Teton Sioux</name> encounter is perhaps the signature event in the interpretation of American Indians in the <name type="place" key="Great Plains">Great Plains</name> portion of the trail. This episode is recounted at every interpretive site from <name type="place" key="Sioux City, Iowa">Sioux City</name> to <name type="place" key="Pierre, South Dakota">Pierre, South Dakota</name>, and in the Pierre area this story is usually the sole focus of the interpretation, such as at <name type="place" key="Farm Island Recreation Area">Farm Island Recreation Area</name>, <name type="place" key="LaFramboise Island Nature Area">LaFramboise Island Nature Area</name>, and the confluence of the <name type="place" key="Bad River">Bad</name> and <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> rivers. Interpretive sites in <name type="place" key="North Dakota">North Dakota</name> and <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name> also focus on this encounter, reflecting its drama and the fixation of the expedition on the Teton Sioux dominance of Missouri River trade.<ref target="nlc.blake.0130" n="30"/> The significance of the <hi rend="italic">Hostile Encounters</hi> representation is indicated on the National Park Service standard map panel installed many places along the NHT. It mentions<name type="native_nation" key=" Plains Indians"> Plains Indians</name> only three times: first council, <name type="native_nation" key="Teton Sioux Indians">Teton Sioux </name>encounter, and <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name> encounter (the other major event in <hi rend="italic">Hostile Encounters</hi>).</p>
            <p>The <hi rend="italic">Hostile Encounters</hi> representation is well illustrated by several versions of the <name type="native_nation" key="Teton Sioux Indians">Teton Sioux</name> encounter. At <name type="place" key="LaFramboise Island Nature Area">LaFramboise Island Nature Area</name> in <name type="person" key="Pierre, South Dakota">Pierre</name>, on the east bank of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri River</name>, the 1990s-era NHT marker reads:</p>
            <p>The expedition had its first meeting with the <name type="native_nation" key="Teton Sioux Indians">Teton Sioux</name> on September 25, 1804, at the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Teton River">Teton River</name> (today's <name type="place" key="Bad River">Bad River</name>), just across from here. The captains met on shore with three chiefs: Black Buffalo, Partisan and Buffalo Medicine, then took them out to the keelboat. When <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> returned the Chiefs to shore, several <name type="native_nation" key="Teton Sioux Indians">Tetons</name> attempted to detain him. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> drew his sword, the <name type="native_nation" key="Teton Sioux Indians">Tetons</name> strung their bows, and <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> readied the men for action. <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo">Black Buffalo</name> moved to diffuse the situation by ordering his men to back off. Eventually, they allowed <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> to return to the keelboat; two of the chiefs went with him.</p>
            <p>This text attributes the initiation of hostilities to the <name type="native_nation" key="Teton Sioux Indians">Tetons</name> with an attempted detainment of <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, although it notes Black Buffalo was a calming influence. The Washburn interpretive center expounds on the hostile nature of the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name> by stating:</p>
            <p>Even gift-giving became a disaster when they gave one chief, named the <name type="person" key="Partisan">Partisan</name>, fewer gifts than his rival, <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo">Black Buffalo</name>. Highly offended, the <name type="person" key="Partisan">Partisan</name> hijacked a pirogue.</p>
            <p>The Great Falls interpretive center rationalizes the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name> action this way:</p>
            <p>The open trade advocated by <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> would wipe out the <name type="native_nation" key="Lakota Indians">Lakota</name> monopoly. No wonder they treated the Expedition with hostility.</p>
            <p>Although the Great Falls center at least places the encounter in the context of power relationships, the <hi rend="italic">Hostile Encounters</hi> interpretations are silent on other possible causes for the tense negotiations, such as preconceived notions on the part of the captains, or how the <name type="native_nation" key="Teton Sioux Indians">Teton Sioux</name> were insulted by the expedition's poor diplomacy in offering mere trinkets as gifts, or how the tribe was offended at the idea of subjugation to yet another new great father.<ref target="nlc.blake.0131" n="31"/> The aggressive theme is oft repeated at other sites: the 1990s-era Calumet Bluff visitor center calls the <name type="native_nation" key="Teton Sioux Indians">Teton Sioux</name> "one of the most aggressive of the Sioux bands"; the Chamberlain information center contains text on how the captains reacted with firmness to the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name> warnings and threats; and the South Dakota Cultural Heritage Center (built in 1989 and operated by the State Historical Society) features text about how the expedition was always on its guard after the <name type="native_nation" key="Teton Sioux Indians">Tetons</name> tried seizing one of the expedition's canoes as toll. The murals and accompanying text at the Southern Hills Mall in <name type="person" key="Sioux City, Iowa">Sioux City</name> also echo the greedy interpretation of the <name type="native_nation" key="Teton Sioux Indians">Teton Sioux</name> by stating that they "demanded more than the expedition could afford."</p>
            <p>The same event may be interpreted from several different perspectives, however, and while the <name type="native_nation" key="Teton Sioux Indians">Teton Sioux</name> encounter is dominated by interpretation with hostile overtones, a nonattributed west-bank marker of indeterminate age in Lilly Park at the <name type="place" key="Bad River">Bad River</name> confluence reads, in part:</p>
            <p>President <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Thomas Jefferson</name> commissioned Captains William <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> and Meriwether <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> to explore the Louisiana Purchase and make peaceful contact with the native nations. Here where the <name type="place" key="Bad River">Bad River</name> meets the <name type="person" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, the Corps of Discovery held council, feasting, and celebration with the <name type="native_nation" key="Teton Sioux Indians">Teton Sioux</name>. Language barriers led to an armed confrontation, diffused largely through the efforts of <name type="person" key="Chief Black Buffalo">Chief Black Buffalo</name>. The expedition continued peacefully to the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific Ocean</name>.</p>
            <p>Without casting blame on either party or portraying the <name type="native_nation" key="Teton Sioux Indians">Tetons</name> as aggressive or greedy, this marker offers a neutral rendition that avoids the <hi rend="italic">Hostile Encounters</hi> archetype.</p>
            <p>The <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name> encounter in northern <name type="person" key="Montana">Montana</name> was the most violent of any of the <hi rend="italic">Hostile Encounters</hi>. All the National Historic Trail interpretations of this event follow approximately the same script, illustrated with this text at the Great Falls center:</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, <name type="person" key="Drouillard">Drouillard</name>, and the <name type="person" key="Field brothers">Field brothers</name> rode deep into <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name> (<name type="native_nation" key="Pikuni Indians">Pikuni</name>) country. On July 26 near the <name type="place" key="Two Medicine River">Two Medicine River</name>, eight <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name> men rode towards them. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> presented three among them with a flag, a medal, and a handkerchief. That evening he described America's intentions to trade guns with the <name type="native_nation" key="Salish (Sells) Indians">Salish (Sells)</name>, <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone (Aqui-Dika) Indians">Shoshone (Aqui-Dika)</name>, and <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce (Nimiipu) Indians">Nez Perce (Nimiipu)</name>. This news may have alarmed the <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name> because these tribes were their traditional enemies. At dawn the warriors attempted to steal the party's guns and horses. In the ensuing fight, <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">Reubin Field</name> mortally stabbed an Indian and <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> shot another, narrowly escaping being killed himself. The <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name> beat a hasty retreat. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> quickly burned the warriors' abandoned shields and reclaimed the flag given the previous day. He left a peace medal around the dead warrior's neck and fled the scene.</p>
            <p>The Montana Historic Expedition Trail Map produced in the past few years by the Bureau of Land Management (exhibited at <name type="place" key="Pompeys Pillar National Monument and Decision Point">Pompeys Pillar National Monument and Decision Point</name>) enhances this representation by showing <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> shooting the "thieving" <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name>. The <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name> are also represented as hostile in the interpretation at the Washburn center and the Great Falls Ryan Island Day Use Area (developed in 1976 by Montana Power Company). The most biased portrayal of the hostile, powerful <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name>, however, is in a mural at the Southern Hills Mall in <name type="person" key="Sioux City, Iowa">Sioux City</name>.</p>
            <p>As is typical with any narrative, verbal or written, multiple versions of the encounter exist in <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name> oral tradition. The only in-stance of this viewpoint presented along the NHT is in the Great Falls interpretive center:</p>
            <p>A <name type="native_nation" key="Pikuni Indians">Pikuni</name> raid near the <name type="place" key="Two Medicine River">Two Medicine River</name> in 1806 ended in tragedy. <name type="person" key="Wolf Calf">Wolf Calf</name>, a member of the <name type="native_nation" key="Pikuni Indians">Pikuni</name> party, recalled the incident years later. He said a war party was roaming the southern bounds of their territory when they met the first white men to ever visit the area (<name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and his men). The <name type="native_nation" key="Pikuni Indians">Pikuni</name> greeted the white men in a friendly way, but later the chief directed the young men to steal their guns. In the attempt, a <name type="native_nation" key="Pikuni Indians">Pikuni</name> named <name type="person" key="Side Hill Calf">Side Hill Calf</name> was killed with the white men's "big knives."</p>
            <p>Yet another <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name> version, although absent from on-site interpretations, is far different:</p>
            <p>Two <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name> boys-12 and 13-were on their way home when the men of the expedition spotted them and invited them to camp. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> kept insisting they camp with them. He said we have a gift for you, and they had hands on guns at all times. In the middle of the night the boys tried to leave. One of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>'s men woke up and stabbed one boy. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> shot the other.<ref target="nlc.blake.0132" n="32"/>
            </p>
            <p>Significantly, this is the version that is taught in a <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name> school, and thus it may be assumed to have more resonance with the <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name> than <name type="person" key="Wolf Calf">Wolf Calf</name>'s account. Horse stealing, a common action among <name type="native_nation" key="Plains Indians">Plains Indians</name> and a recognized war honor,<ref target="nlc.blake.0133" n="33"/> is also transformed by some NHT interpretations into a degenerate act. The portrayal of the <name type="native_nation" key="Crow (Apsaalooka) Indians">Crow (Apsaalooka)</name> theft of horses on the return trip, seen in the Chamberlain and Washburn centers, also fits within the <hi rend="italic">Hostile Encounters</hi> theme.</p>
            <p>The unflattering <hi rend="italic">Hostile Encounters</hi> portrayal of American Indians would be expected from an outdated source rather than in so many displays created in the past two decades. The pictorial reinforcement to the written text of this theme in the <name type="place" key="Sioux City, Iowa">Sioux City</name> Southern Hills Mall murals and the <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name> trail map is particularly disturbing and runs strongly counter to achieving even a modicum of multicultural awareness along the trail. <hi rend="italic">Hostile Encounters</hi> may be so firmly entrenched in popular thought because of its portrayal in <name type="person" key="DeVoto, Bernard">Bernard DeVoto</name>'s generally highly regarded and widely read abridgment of <hi rend="italic">The Journals of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>
               </hi>. It refers to the <name type="native_nation" key="Teton Sioux Indians">Teton Sioux</name> as "among the most warlike of Indians, swaggerers and bullies," and it notes that <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> handled the <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name> encounter "with an expertness that no one could have surpassed."<ref target="nlc.blake.0134" n="34"/> The journal entries of the expedition members cement this impression; <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, for example, used words like "vilenous [sic], hostile, and treacherous" to describe the <name type="native_nation" key="Teton Sioux Indians">Teton Sioux</name>, who "ill treated us."<ref target="nlc.blake.0135" n="35"/> Yet cause for hope exists in suggestions for balanced portrayals of American Indians, such as one published by the Montana Governor's <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Bicentennial Commission. It says that to improve <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>'s <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> interpretation, interpretive signs should "emphasize the Native American point of view."<ref target="nlc.blake.0136" n="36"/>
            </p>
            <p>GOOD NEIGHBORS</p>
            <p>In the vicinity of <name type="place" key="Washburn, North Dakota">Washburn, North Dakota</name>, the dominant representations of American Indians change direction in a manner reminiscent of river travelers turning westward at the dramatic <name type="person" key="Missouri River">Great Bend of the Missouri</name>, as the <hi rend="italic">Good Neighbors</hi> theme arises to a primary position among Native American interpretations. The "Good Neighbors" exhibit at the Washburn center discusses at length the mutually beneficial relationship of hospitality, friendship, and military alliance between the expedition and the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>. American Indian assistance to the expedition is rarely interpreted in detail elsewhere, with the exception of the Sioux City interpretive center and <name type="place" key="Knife River Indian Villages National Historic Site">Knife River Indian Villages National Historic Site</name> (designated in 1974, with most interpretation development in the past fifteen years).</p>
            <p>The NHT interpretations of the expedition's ethnography are also inherent in the representation of Native Americans as <hi rend="italic">Good Neighbors</hi>. <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> instructed the expedition to study "seventeen areas of Indian life and culture," from "language and law to trade and technology," all with a watchful eye toward business enterprise, national expansion, and the empire of knowledge. <ref target="nlc.blake.0137" n="37"/> The <hi rend="italic">Good Neighbors</hi> representation is manifest throughout the NHT in the elementary interpretation of American Indians as static, passive culture groups worthy of study, such as with artifacts on display in the <name type="place" key="Sioux City, Iowa">Sioux City</name> and <name type="place" key="Pierre, South Dakota">Pierre</name> centers and the Sergeant Floyd Riverboat Museum; displays on farming and hunting habits at Calumet Bluff, West Whitlock, and Knife River; signs about Indian words or legends providing place names at the Chamberlain center and Big Sky Wayside Exhibit in Terry, Montana; and interpretation of Indian plant use at Pompeys Pillar. While in aggregate <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> assembled a valuable ethnographic record, in practice along the NHT it is generally presented piecemeal and in a way that conflates Native American cultures, with the notable exception of the Great Falls NHT center.</p>
            <p>The earthlodge exhibit at the Great Falls NHT center notes the role of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> as ethnographers but also recognizes that their views were prejudiced, often describing "only external features and events, neglecting the spiritual and cultural significance of what they saw." This statement aptly illustrates the limited perspectives offered by a <hi rend="italic">Good Neighbor</hi>s archetype of <name type="native_nation" key="Plains Indians">Plains Indians</name>. The interpretation of the expedition's ethnography is visually oriented toward Native American dwellings, especially tipis and earthlodges. A tipi dominates the Indian display inside the Chamberlain center, and a stylized tipi outside is the signature architectural feature of the center. Tipi replicas are also on display at the Atka Lakota Museum, Fort Union Trading Post, and Southern Hills Mall. Earthlodges are even more frequent on the trail, with displays about their construction or replicas at <name type="place" key="Blackbird Scenic Overview">Blackbird Scenic Overview</name>, <name type="place" key="Calumet Bluff">Calumet Bluff</name>, <name type="place" key="West Whitlock">West Whitlock</name>, <name type="place" key="Double Ditch">Double Ditch</name>, <name type="place" key="Great Falls NHT center">Great Falls NHT center</name>, and <name type="place" key="Knife River">Knife River</name>.</p>
            <p>Although the <name type="place" key="Knife River">Knife River</name> site offers a great deal of ethnographic interpretation, it still lacks a Native American voice that goes beyond the material culture of tools and housing, to religion and governance, for example. This absence is common among a variety of sites, all developed within the past twenty-five years. <name type="person" key="Mossett, Amy">Amy Mossett</name>, a <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan-Hidatsa Indians">Mandan-Hidatsa</name>, wants the commemorations to recognize that "Indians have the strongest sense of place of anyone in the world." Of the sophistication of her society she adds, "<name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> wanted to make Indians into farmers and traders. But we were already doing all of that. The difference is, we were doing it without slave labor."<ref target="nlc.blake.0138" n="38"/> Quotations of American Indian perspectives about their own identity, civilization, or beliefs are used liberally at the Great Falls NHT center to add a Native voice.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">SACAGAWEA</name> REINTERPRETED</p>
            <p>Changing interpretations of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition reflect changes in society, such as the increasing interest in <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name> concurrent with the women's movement.<ref target="nlc.blake.0139" n="39"/> Included in the expedition for her ability to interpret with <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshones</name>, <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name> is the most instantly recognizable individual in displays along the trail since she is the only woman and usually the only depicted Native American.<ref target="nlc.blake.0140" n="40"/> Her image has transcended her original role in multiple reinterpretations of what she meant to the expedition. Like the <hi rend="italic">Good Neighbors</hi> representation, the <hi rend="italic">Sacagawea Reinterpreted</hi> theme is a widespread element in the NHT interpretation, but it is strongest from northern <name type="place" key="South Dakota">South Dakota</name> to <name type="place" key="Great Falls">Great Falls</name>.</p>
            <p>The easternmost and westernmost Great Plains sites on the NHT with on-site interpretation both feature statues: Kansas City's Case Park (erected circa 2000) and the Broadwater Portage Overlook in Great Falls (erected 1989). Sacagawea is a sculpture staple along the trail, featured in Kansas City, Missouri; Bismarck, North Dakota; and Miles City, Fort Benton, and inside the Great Falls NHT interpretive center in Montana.<ref target="nlc.blake.0141" n="41"/> Sacagawea faces west on all five statues, which points to the emphasis of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> trail interpretation on the westward adventure rather than the return and to Sacagawea's multiple roles in that westward progress. Her absence from statues in Sioux City, Washburn, and at the Broadwater Portage Overlook symbolically suggests the ambivalence of the American Indian portrayal along the NHT in the Great Plains. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>'s dog, Seaman, on the other hand, appears on both the Sioux City and Broadwater Portage statues as well as in <name type="place" key="Kansas City">Kansas City</name>.</p>
            <p>So many meanings have been layered upon <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name> that her true self could well be unrecognizable in her mythic interpretation. Even her name changes as one moves among the interpretation sites. <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacajawea</name> is often the preferred spelling in <name type="place" key="Wyoming">Wyoming</name> and <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>, a reflection of the phonetic <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshone</name> pronunciation for a name meaning Boat Launcher. <name type="person" key="Sakakawea">Sakakawea</name> is used in northern <name type="place" key="South Dakota">South Dakota</name> and in <name type="place" key="North Dakota">North Dakota</name> because of the phonetic <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> pronunciation for a name meaning <name type="person" key="Bird Woman">Bird Woman</name>. Because <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name>'s name is usually spelled in this fashion along the trail and in the literature, I use this spelling except for when it is spelled differently at a particular interpretive site. <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name> is portrayed as the expedition's "indomitable and unerring" guide in the earliest interpretations of her extant along the NHT, dating back to 1910 at the Bismarck statue (erected by the Federated Clubwomen and schoolchildren of <name type="place" key="North Dakota">North Dakota</name>) and 1920 at the <name type="person" key="Sakakawea">Sakakawea</name> Monument in <name type="place" key="South Dakota">South Dakota</name> (erected by the Mobridge Hickory Stick Club). The unerring guide representation is repeated many times along the trail in later interpretive efforts, including on the 1928 Daughters of the American Revolution plaque at <name type="place" key="Pompeys Pillar">Pompeys Pillar</name>, the 1972 marker at the <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan">Fort Mandan</name> reconstruction, and on the recent <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name> trail map at Decision Point and Pompeys Pillar that indicates, "<name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name> points the way." At the <name type="place" key="Washburn">Washburn</name> and <name type="place" key="Great Falls">Great Falls</name> centers her role as a guide is reinterpreted to say, "She did not guide the Expedition as romanticized accounts claim, but she did provide crucial help in several instances."</p>
            <p>According to several reinterpretations of <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name> in the <name type="place" key="Great Plains">Great Plains</name>, this "crucial help" was either as an interpreter for <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> or a harbinger of the peaceful intent of the expedition. Both of these perspectives are quoted from the journals of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> at the <name type="person" key="Sakakawea">Sakakawea</name> statue interpretive marker in <name type="place" key="Bismarck">Bismarck</name>, and they are repeated in the <name type="place" key="Sioux City, Iowa">Sioux City</name> and <name type="place" key="Great Falls">Great Falls</name> interpretive centers.<ref target="nlc.blake.0142" n="42"/> The <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name> interpreter role is also elaborated in a NHT marker at the Jedediah Smith Monument near <name type="place" key="Mobridge, South Dakota">Mobridge, South Dakota</name>, and <name type="person" key="Sakakawea">Sakakawea</name> as a symbol convincing local tribes that the expedition came in peace is reiterated in the Washburn center. Building upon the <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name> archetypes of guide, interpreter, and token of peace, she is also portrayed as a heroic Madonna of the trail, uncomplainingly dealing with the hardships of travel while caring for an infant;<ref target="nlc.blake.0143" n="43"/> every statue and depiction of her along the trail includes her son, <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Jean Baptiste">Jean Baptiste Charbonneau</name>. Statues and earlier memorials favor the interpretation of <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name> as a guide or Madonna, whereas her reinterpretations as interpreter or harbinger of peace come in later displays along the trail.</p>
            <p>NATIVE AMERICAN VOICES</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Spence, Mark">Mark Spence</name> highlights the challenges of interpreting American Indians within the context of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, noting that current commemoration efforts are rooted in old ideas that cloud understanding of the expedition and perpetuate a set of cultural burdens that are increasingly problematic. The interpretation of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> "as exemplary models of multiculturalism" is even "less accurate" than that of a century ago when they were hailed "as champions of industrial growth and resource exploitation."<ref target="nlc.blake.0144" n="44"/> According to <name type="person" key="Spence, Mark">Spence</name>, the danger is that the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> bicentennial will portray excitement and adventure but not all of the expedition's legacies. He calls for "an honest assessment of the expedition as a long, difficult, imperial venture with tragic consequences for the peoples and homelands that <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> described and evaluated."<ref target="nlc.blake.0145" n="45"/> The dependence of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> on resident communities in making their way across the continent is still under-emphasized along the trail. How can we recover what has been lost since the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition if we do not receive a comprehensive view of who they encountered?</p>
            <p>Although the <hi rend="italic">Councils of Power</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Hostile Encounters</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Good Neighbors</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Sacagawea Reinterpreted</hi> representations dominate the Native American interpretation along the Great Plains portion of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Trail, eleven of the forty-eight places with on-site interpretation lack even a brief mention of American Indians. In almost every case of omission, the tribes could have been interpreted as part of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> journey, since American Indians were rarely completely separate from the expedition. The construction and renovation of interpretive sites for the bicentennial commemoration offered a chance to end the silence of Native American voices and the recycling of old themes.<ref target="nlc.blake.0146" n="46"/>
            </p>
            <p>The persistence of poorly drawn Native American representations along the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Trail likely emanates from a variety of circumstances, including the influence of <name type="person" key="DeVoto, Bernard">DeVoto</name>'s seminal work mentioned earlier in <hi rend="italic">Hostile Encounters</hi>, and the power of the heroic <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> myth. A lag time in either the ability or inclination to replace semipermanent markers contributes to the presence of outdated perspectives, as could the lack of a single management directive to include the Native voice. The variability in American Indian cultures and in the versions of Native oral histories also is a contributing factor. Yet it is also clear from some recent biased interpretations that some organizations are at best uninformed by recent scholarship, or at worst unwittingly racist.<ref target="nlc.blake.0147" n="47"/>
            </p>
            <p>Rarely do the NHT interpretations attempt comprehensive summaries of the legacy of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> (especially pertaining to Native Americans), but a comparison of two examples illustrates the potential voice versus silence of indigenous peoples in the expedition drama. At the South Dakota Cultural Heritage Center a recent interpretive display called the "Explorers' Legacy" reads, "The <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition made the West real for Americans. . . . The Corps of Discovery brought back a wealth of information about land, plants, animals, and native tribes." This passage perpetuates the cameo role for American Indians and implies they had no sense of place prior to the expedition. Conversely, the Atka Lakota Museum (opened in 1991 by St. Joseph's Indian School) strips the journey of its heroic drama and instead focuses on the changes to the people and place:</p>
            <p>The <name type="native_nation" key="Lakota Indians">Lakota</name> met <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> in 1804. Subsequently, increasing contact with the white world included traders, explorers, missionaries, the US Army, Indian Agents, miners, and settlers, bringing sweeping changes to the Great Plains. Thousands of Indians died from diseases, setting off a struggle for the people to retain what was theirs amid the seemingly endless tide of the wasicu (white men). Eighty years after the encounter with <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> the buffalo were gone, forever changing the <name type="native_nation" key="Lakota Indians">Lakota</name> way of life.</p>
            <p>Because no one organization has had total control over the NHT interpretation, there are multiple layers of meaning regarding American Indians. Given the varied and constantly changing perspectives on American Indian interpretation, however, the existing decentralized NHT interpretation model may be best.</p>
            <p>Historian <name type="person" key="Schama, Simon">Simon Schama</name> notes that "not all cultures" embrace the myths produced by the interplay of landscape and memory "with equal ardor."<ref target="nlc.blake.0148" n="48"/> Skewed interpretations apparently resulted in the defacement of several <name type="person" key="Smith, Jedediah">Jedediah Smith</name> plaques and the Sakakawea Monument plaque near <name type="place" key="Mobridge, South Dakota">Mobridge, South Dakota</name>, on the <name type="place" key="Standing Rock Reservation">Standing Rock Reservation</name>. The damage is at two different locations separated by several miles of paved and dirt roads, and it is selective at each site, targeting specific language as opposed to random or senseless destruction. Even the choice of the medium for the vandalism seems purposeful and symbolic, as it consists of red paint sprayed over some text in a neat circle. It is not hard to imagine why someone in this area would disagree with the heroic portrayal of <name type="person" key="Smith, Jedediah">Jedediah Smith</name>, but less immediately evident is why some text at the Sakakawea Monument received the same treatment. An explanation may lie within the Native American perspective that urges teachers to "avoid materials which illustrate Native American heroes as only those who helped Euro-Americans."<ref target="nlc.blake.0149" n="49"/> The Sakakawea Monument interpretive text places her significance entirely within the context of a noble savage helping the expedition: "Sakakawea won her place in history as the indomitable guide of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> on their trip to the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name> in 1805. . . . By her courage, endurance, and unerring instinct she guided the expedition over seemingly insuperable obstacles. . . . <name type="person" key="Sakakawea">Sakakawea</name> is, beyond question, the most illustrious feminine representative of the Indian race." On the site of the Sakakawea Monument, a bronze relief picturing her and <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Jean Baptiste">Jean Baptiste Charbonneau</name> is undamaged, as is the nearby <name type="person" key="Sitting Bull">Sitting Bull</name> Monument. Likewise, at the <name type="person" key="Smith, Jedediah">Jedediah Smith</name> Monument site the text is untouched that interprets Sacagawea as the trip's only female and a key interpreter with the <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshone</name>.</p>
            <p>Enhancing the contemplative mindset of visitors along the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Trail could at times be equally important as creating the right tone in American Indian interpretation, however.<ref target="nlc.blake.0150" n="50"/>
               <name type="place" key="Spirit Mound, South Dakota">Spirit Mound, South Dakota</name>, offered a powerful opportunity for personal contemplation about the meaning of the place to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> and Native Americans during my fieldwork, but that was by accident, since the site recently was acquired by the state, with the old interpretation mostly removed and the new interpretation not yet installed. Furthermore, road construction forced me to approach the summit from an unconventional direction, making my own path across the prairie; therefore, I drew a sense of place through my own touch, smell, sight, hearing, <hi rend="italic">and spirit</hi>. Had I visited <name type="place" key="Spirit Mound, South Dakota">Spirit Mound</name> even a few weeks later the interpretive signs would likely have been in place and the visit highly structured, all to the possible detriment of a contemplative experience.</p>
            <p>Nevertheless, interpretive sites along the NHT can offer an insightful portrayal of Native Americans. <name type="place" key="Blackbird Scenic Overview">Blackbird Scenic Overview</name>, a relatively unknown <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> site in northeastern <name type="place" key="Nebraska">Nebraska</name>, developed over perhaps the last fifteen years jointly by the Papio-Missouri River Natural Resources District and the <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Omaha</name> Tribe, illustrates an exception to the overall pattern and provides a possible model for future interpretations. The significance of this site accrues from its sacredness to the <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Omaha</name> due to the proximity of <name type="person" key="Chief Blackbird">Chief Blackbird</name>'s grave, not just because <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> visited the grave. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> are portrayed as a small part of the <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Omaha</name> story in the detailed signs about <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Omaha</name> history, earthlodges, social structure, symbols, and contributions to American society and the expedition. Another sign asks visitors to "respect this sacred area." The inclusion of American Indian partners is a key in breaking the mold of the typical Native representations. Including the perspectives of the Trail Tribes would likely lead to interpretation of contemporary issues related to the legacies of the expedition, such as "sacred site protection and the return of human remains and burial goods."<ref target="nlc.blake.0151" n="51"/> Too often in America an "anti-historical habit of thought" intrudes on the representations of the valued past, with history "merely museumized, not integrated with the present."<ref target="nlc.blake.0152" n="52"/> Places like <name type="place" key="Blackbird Scenic Overview">Blackbird Scenic Overview</name> and the Great Falls NHT center offer a sharp and refreshing contrast to this tendency.</p>
            <p>Analyzing the date, creator, and format of interpretation leads to several conclusions. Surprisingly, the newest interpretive efforts and those by federal agencies do not always offer the most culturally aware interpretations of Native Americans in the context of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, as evidenced by the <hi rend="italic">Hostile Encounters</hi> tone of the 2003 mural display at <name type="place" key="Sioux City, Iowa">Sioux City</name>'s Southern Hills Mall or the <hi rend="italic">Hostile Encounters</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Good Neighbors</hi> tropes perpetuated at <name type="place" key="Decision Point">Decision Point</name> and <name type="place" key="Knife River">Knife River</name>. The media used in American Indian interpretation tend to characterize certain themes. Reconstructions, for example, typically focus on material culture, reminiscent of <hi rend="italic">Good Neighbors</hi>. Signposts and statues are mixed in their messages of <hi rend="italic">Councils of Power</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Sacagawea Reinterpreted</hi>, which largely seems a function of whether American Indians were consulted in the interpretation process. Pictorial representations of the Trail Tribes are the most problematic in the portrayals of <hi rend="italic">Hostile Encounters</hi>.</p>
            <p>It could be unrealistic to expect to see the American Indian voice in the textual interpretation of the trail, since this voice is traditionally oral, not written, and the storyteller tone of voice and listener reaction are elemental to sharing ideas and interpreting meaning.<ref target="nlc.blake.0153" n="53"/> But to craft new or revise old representations of Native Americans along the trail, recordings of tribal voices, or at least written quotations, and an end to the recycling of insensitive representations would be an appropriate start. Just as some members of the expedition undoubtedly became more attuned to American Indian cultures during their journey, the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> trail interpretation should further evolve toward including the Native American voice.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Blake, Kevin S.">Kevin S. Blake</name> is an Associate Professor of Geography at Kansas State University. His research interests include nature-society interactions, Native American geography, landscape symbolism, and place identity. Thanks to <name type="person" key="Blake, William R.">William R. Blake</name> for assistance during the fieldwork and to John P. Harty for suggestions on the data analysis. This study was funded in part by a Kansas State University Small Research Grant.</p>
            <p>KEY WORDS: <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name>, cultural resources, interpretive sites, <name type="native_nation" key="Lakota Indians">Lakota</name>, landscape, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, Native Americans, <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name>.</p>
            <p>NOTES</p>
            <note xml:id="nlc.blake.0101" n="1">
               <name type="person" key="Foote, Kenneth E.">Kenneth E. Foote</name>, <hi rend="italic">Shadowed Ground: America's Landscapes of Violence and Tragedy</hi> (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1997), 29.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.blake.0102" n="2">Quote from p. 109 of <name type="person" key="Lowenthal, David">David Lowenthal</name>, "The Place of the Past in the American Landscape," in <hi rend="italic">Geographies of the Mind: Essays in Honor of <name type="person" key="Wright, John Kirtland">John Kirtland Wright</name>
               </hi>, ed. <name type="person" key="Lowenthal, David">David Lowenthal</name> and <name type="person" key="Bowden, Martyn J.">Martyn J. Bowden</name> (New York: Oxford University Press, 1976), 89–117. See also <name type="person" key="Schama, Simon">Simon S[c]hama</name>, <hi rend="italic">Landscape and Memory</hi> (London: HarperCollins, 1995), 15.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.blake.0103" n="3">
               <name type="person" key="Loewen, James W.">James W. Loewen</name>, <hi rend="italic">Lies Across America: What Our Historic Sites Get Wrong</hi> (New York: New Press, 1999), 443–47. Although the label "Native American" is often generically attributed to the indigenous peoples of the Great Plains, many tribes also identify with "American Indian," the typical term at many interpretive sites along the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Trail. This article uses terminology similar to that used in <name type="person" key="Heck, Suzanne">Suzanne Heck</name>, ed., <hi rend="italic">Native American Resource Handbook</hi> (Atchison: Kansas <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Bicentennial Committee Native American Sub-committee, 2002), which interchangeably describes American Indians, Native Americans, and the individual tribes.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.blake.0104" n="4">
               <name type="person" key="Egan, Timothy">Timothy Egan</name>, "Two Centuries Later, a Moment for Indians to Retell the Past," <hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi>, June 15, 2003.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.blake.0105" n="5">Ibid. See also <name type="person" key="Conner, Roberta">Roberta Conner</name>, "The <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Bicentennial: Putting Tribes Back on the Map," in <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>: Legacies, Memories, and New Perspectives</hi>, ed. <name type="person" key="Fresonke, Kris">Kris Fresonke</name> and <name type="person" key="Spence, Mark">Mark Spence</name> (Berkeley: University of California Press, 2004), 265–73, and <name type="person" key="Eckert, Christie Appelhanz">Christie Appelhanz Eckert</name>, "Focusing on Inclusion: American Indian Perspective," <hi rend="italic">Kansas!</hi> no. 4 (2003): 21–22, for discussions of the varying American Indian points of view on the bicentennial.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.blake.0106" n="6">
               <name type="person" key="Dennis, Matthew">Matthew Dennis</name>, <hi rend="italic">Cultivating a Landscape of Peace: Iroquois-European Encounters in Seventeenth-Century America</hi> (Ithaca, NY: Cornell University Press, 1993), 2–5. <name type="person" key="Hudson, John C.">John C. Hudson</name>, "The Big Empty," <hi rend="italic">Historical Geography</hi> 31 (2003): 61–67, also promotes the value of a multicultural perspective. This study does not primarily focus on telling the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> story from the American Indian point of view since that is already the perspective of <name type="person" key="Ronda, James P.">James P. Ronda</name>, <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> among the Indians</hi>, rev. ed. (Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, [1984] 2002), and this perspective is also best related by Plains Indian storytellers. Instead, this article examines the NHT portrayal of Native Americans who were encountered by <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.blake.0107" n="7">The significance of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> to national myth and identity is explained by <name type="person" key="DeVoto, Bernard">Bernard DeVoto</name>, <hi rend="italic">The Course of Empire</hi> (Boston: Houghton Mifflin, 1952); <name type="person" key="Allen, John Logan">John Logan Allen</name>, <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> and the Image of the American Northwest</hi> (New York: Dover, 1991); <name type="person" key="Hendrix, James P. Jr.">James P. Hendrix Jr.</name>, "A New Vision of America: <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> and the Emergence of the American Imagination," <hi rend="italic">Great Plains Quarterly</hi> 21, no. 3 (2001): 211–32; and <name type="person" key="Kirn, Walter">Walter Kirn</name>, "<name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>: The Journey that Changed America Forever," <hi rend="italic">Time</hi>, July 8, 2002, 36–41.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.blake.0108" n="8">
               <name type="person" key="Spence, Mark">Mark Spence</name>, "Historical Commentary: The Unnatural History of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Bicentennial," <hi rend="italic">Montana: The Magazine of Western History</hi> 53, no. 2 (2003): 56–63.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.blake.0109" n="9">Quote from p. 160 of <name type="person" key="Spencer, John">John Spencer</name>, "`We Are Not Dealing Entirely with the Past': Americans Remember <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>," in <name type="person" key="Fresonke, Kris">Fresonke</name> and <name type="person" key="Spence, Mark">Spence</name>, <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>
               </hi>, 159–83.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.blake.0110" n="10">
               <name type="person" key="Heat-Moon, William Least">William Least Heat-Moon</name>, <hi rend="italic">River-Horse: The Logbook of a Boat across America</hi> (Boston: Houghton Mifflin, 1999), 263.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.blake.0111" n="11">
               <name type="place" key="Kaw Point">Kaw Point</name> is also known as <name type="place" key="Kawsmouth">Kawsmouth</name>, a place that takes it name from the <name type="place" key="Kansas (Kaw) River">Kansas (or Kaw) River</name>, which was named for the people alternately called the <name type="native_nation" key="Kaw Indians">Kaw</name>, <name type="native_nation" key="Kansa Indians">Kansa</name>, or <name type="native_nation" key="Kanza Indians">Kanza</name>. For more on the <name type="native_nation" key="Kansa Indians">Kansa</name>, see <name type="person" key="Heck, Suzanne">Heck</name>, <hi rend="italic">Native American Resource Handbook</hi>, 9–12, and <name type="person" key="Wright, Muriel H.">Muriel H. Wright</name>, <hi rend="italic">A Guide to the Indian Tribes of Oklahoma</hi> (Norman: University of Oklahoma Press, 1986), 160–64.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.blake.0112" n="12">
               <name type="person" key="Wright, John B.">John B. Wright</name>, "The Dearborn River Confluence: Montana's Northwest Passage," <hi rend="italic">Historical Geography</hi> 31 (2003): 89–96, writes that <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, who named the <name type="place" key="Gates of the Rocky Mountains">Gates of the Rocky Mountains</name>, refers to this place in his journal as towering, remarkable, and dark, with gloomy rock cliffs. See <name type="person" key="Lavender, David">David Lavender</name>, <hi rend="italic">The Way to the Western Sea: <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> across the Continent</hi> (Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 2001), 229–44, for a description of how the dramatic landscape change at the <name type="place" key="Gates of the Rocky Mountains">Gates</name> caused <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> to underline his journal entry for added emphasis, and also for how the expedition focused on crossing the <name type="place" key="Great Divide">Great Divide</name> after the <name type="place" key="Gates of the Rocky Mountains">Gates</name>. <name type="person" key="Heat-Moon, William Least">Heat-Moon</name>, <name type="person" key="River-Horse">River-Horse</name>, 360, 382, comments on leaving the Great Plains behind and being at the foot of the <name type="person" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky Mountains</name> once he reaches the Gates.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.blake.0113" n="13">
               <name type="person" key="Wagner, Angie">Angie Wagner</name>, "Indians Want Their Side of Story Told," <hi rend="italic">Topeka Capital-Journal</hi>, May 4, 2003. I use the tribal names that are commonly seen in the interpretation along the trail, in the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> literature, or by the tribe today, although other tribal names are provided in parentheses.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.blake.0114" n="14">The shifts in power relations are discussed in <name type="person" key="Wishar, David J.">David J. Wishart</name>, <hi rend="italic">The Fur Trade of the American West, 1807–1840: A Geographical Synthesis</hi>, rev. ed. (Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, [1979] 1992), 19–22; Spence, "Historical Commentary," p. 59; and <name type="person" key="Ewers, John C.">John C. Ewers</name>, "Plains Indian Reactions to the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition," in <hi rend="italic">Voyages of Discovery: Essays on the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition</hi>, ed. <name type="person" key="Ronda, James P.">James P. Ronda</name> (Helena: Montana Historical Society Press, 1998), 171–82.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.blake.0115" n="15">The Native American perspective can be sampled in <name type="person" key="Oko, Dan">Dan Oko</name>, "Honoring the First Discoverers," in <hi rend="italic">Living in the Runaway West</hi>, ed. <hi rend="italic">High Country News</hi> (Golden, CO: Fulcrum, 2000), 45–46; <name type="person" key="Roosevelt, Margot">Margot Roosevelt</name>, "Tribal Culture Clash," <hi rend="italic">Time</hi>, July 8, 2002, 66–68; and <name type="person" key="Ronda, James P.">Ronda</name>, <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> among the Indians</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.blake.0116" n="16">
               <name type="person" key="Heck, Suzanne">Heck</name>, <hi rend="italic">Native American Resource Handbook</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.blake.0117" n="17">
               <name type="person" key="Cutright, Paul Russell">Paul Russell Cutright</name>, <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>: Pioneering Naturalists</hi> (Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1989), 62.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.blake.0118" n="18">Three guidebooks that proved valuable in identifying sites with American Indian interpretation were <name type="person" key="Fifer, Barbara">Barbara Fifer</name> and <name type="person" key="Soderberg, Vicky">Vicky Soderberg</name>, <hi rend="italic">Along the Trail with <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>
               </hi>, 2nd ed. (Helena, MT: Farcountry, 2001); <name type="person" key="Appleman, Roy E.">Roy E. Appleman</name>, <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>: Historic Places Associated with Their Transcontinental Exploration (1804–06)</hi>, <hi rend="italic">National Survey of Historic Sites and Buildings</hi>, vol. 13, ed. <name type="person" key="Ferris, Robert G.">Robert G. Ferris</name> (Washington, DC: US Department of Interior, National Park Service, 1975); and <name type="person" key="Schmidt, Thomas">Thomas Schmidt</name>, <hi rend="italic">National Geographic Guide to the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Trail</hi> (Washington, DC: National Geographic, 2002). Dozens of tourism pamphlets published by federal, state, and local agencies were also consulted. This study only examines interpretive sites extant in June 2003; thus, new sites under construction at that time, such as the Missouri-Yellowstone Confluence Center, are excluded.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.blake.0119" n="19">Interpretation center videos were excluded because often a choice of videos is offered or a fixed schedule is in place, thus it was impractical to consider them as part of the permanent exhibits. Furthermore, obtaining a transcript of every video for content analysis was unfeasible. Living interpretation is also outside the context of this study for similar reasons.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.blake.0120" n="20">
               <name type="person" key="Foote, Kenneth">Foote</name>, <hi rend="italic">Shadowed Ground</hi>, 33.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.blake.0121" n="21">
               <name type="person" key="Schama, Simon">Schama</name>, <hi rend="italic">Landscape and Memory</hi>, 7.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.blake.0122" n="22">
               <name type="person" key="Wishart, David J.">Wishart</name>, <hi rend="italic">Fur Trade</hi>, 18; <name type="person" key="Ronda, James P.">Ronda</name>, <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> among the Indians</hi>, 35.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.blake.0123" n="23">The US Army Corps of Engineer Visitor Center at <name type="person" key="Gavins Point Dam">Gavins Point Dam</name> is on the remnants of <name type="person" key="Calumet Bluff">Calumet Bluff</name> (named for the French word for a ceremonial peace pipe), most of which was excavated for the dam and power plant.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.blake.0124" n="24">
               <name type="person" key="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</name>, <hi rend="italic">An Unspeakable Sadness: The Dispossession of the Nebraska Indians</hi> (Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1994), 1–4; <name type="person" key="DeVoto, Bernard">Bernard DeVoto</name>, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Journals of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>
               </hi> (Boston: Houghton Mifflin, 1953), xliii; <name type="person" key="Ronda, James P.">Ronda</name>, <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> among the Indians</hi>, 17–23.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.blake.0125" n="25">
               <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>'s 1814 map is discussed in <name type="person" key="Ronda, James P.">James P. Ronda</name>, <hi rend="italic">Finding the West: Explorations with <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>
               </hi> (Albuquerque: University of New Mexico Press, 2001), 54–55, and in <name type="person" key="Allen, John">John Allen</name>, "The Maps of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition," in <hi rend="italic">Mapping the West: America's Westward Movement 1524–1890</hi>, ed. Paul E. Cohen (New York: Rizzoli, 2002), 74–96. Maps in the interpretive centers at Great Falls and Calumet Bluff do depict <name type="native_nation" key="Plains Indians">Plains Indian</name> lands, but the standard NHT map on display at many sites does not.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.blake.0126" n="26">
               <name type="person" key="Wishart, David J.">Wishart</name>, <hi rend="italic">An Unspeakable Sadness</hi>, 216–26; <name type="person" key="Wright, John B.">Wright</name>, <hi rend="italic">Indian Tribes of Oklahoma</hi>, 199–200.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.blake.0127" n="27">
               <name type="person" key="Egan, Timothy">Egan</name>, "Two Centuries Later."</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.blake.0128" n="28">Ibid.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.blake.0129" n="29">
               <name type="person" key="Conner, Roberta">Conner</name>, "The <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Bicentennial," 268–69.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.blake.0130" n="30">
               <name type="person" key="Ronda, James P.">Ronda</name>, <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> among the Indians</hi>, 7.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.blake.0131" n="31">
               <name type="person" key="Roosevelt, Margot">Roosevelt</name>, "Tribal Culture Clash."</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.blake.0132" n="32">This version is attributed to <name type="person" key="DesRosier, Jesse">Jesse DesRosier</name>, a fourteen-year-old in the Piegan Institute in <name type="place" key="Browning, Montana">Browning, Montana</name>, in <name type="person" key="Wagner, Angie">Wagner</name>, "Indians Want." <name type="person" key="Slaughter, Thomas P.">Thomas P. Slaughter</name>, <hi rend="italic">Exploring <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and C<name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>: Reflections on Men and Wilderness</hi> (New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 2003), 180–85, also provides alternative versions of the <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name> encounter.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.blake.0133" n="33">
               <name type="person" key="Ewers, John C.">Ewers</name>, "Plains Indians Reactions," 172.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.blake.0134" n="34">
               <name type="person" key="DeVoto, Bernard">DeVoto</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journals of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>
               </hi>, 1, <name type="person" key="Ronda, James P.">Ronda</name>, <hi rend="italic">Voyages of Discovery</hi>, xiv, observes that although <name type="person" key="DeVoto, Bernard">DeVoto</name>'s use of some terms is "regrettable," <name type="person" key="DeVoto, Bernard">DeVoto</name> was also the first <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> historian to call for a fuller treatment of Indian perspectives on the journey.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.blake.0135" n="35">
               <name type="person" key="Moulton, Gary E.">Gary E. Moulton</name>, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Journals of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition</hi> (Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1987, 1993), 3:121; 8:329–30.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.blake.0136" n="36">Montana Governor's <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Bicentennial Commission and the Montana Tourism and Recreation Initiative, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> in <hi rend="italic">Montana: Interpretive Sign Strategy</hi> (Helena, MT: <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Bicentennial Commission and Montana Tourism and Recreation Initiative, 2000).</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.blake.0137" n="37">Quoted from <name type="person" key="Ronda, James P.">Ronda</name>, <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> among the Indians</hi>, 3–4. See also <name type="person" key="Jackson, Donald">Donald Jackson</name>, <hi rend="italic">Letters of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition with Related Documents, 1783–1854</hi>, 2nd ed. (Urbana: University of Illinois Press, [1962] 1978), 1:165–66.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.blake.0138" n="38">
               <name type="person" key="Egan, Timothy">Egan</name>, "Two Centuries Later."</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.blake.0139" n="39">
               <name type="person" key="Sullivan, Christopher">Christopher Sullivan</name>, "Retracing History: On the 200th Anniversary of the Cross-Country Journey of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, a Look Back Enables a Critical Examination of the United States," <hi rend="italic">Topeka Capital Journal</hi>, January 12, 2003. The nuances and mysteries of the name and life of <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name> are addressed in <name type="person" key="Allen, John Logan">Allen</name>, <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> and the Image</hi>, 211–12; <name type="person" key="Ronda, James P.">Ronda</name>, <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> among the Indians</hi>, 256–59; and Slaughter, <hi rend="italic">Exploring <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>
               </hi>, 86-113.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.blake.0140" n="40">Two members of the expedition, Pierre Cruzatte and Francois Labiche, were half Omaha and George Drouillard, another member of the corps, was half Shawnee, yet travelers on the expedition other than <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, Sacagawea and child, York, and <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>'s dog, Seaman, are rarely depicted in statues.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.blake.0141" n="41">Andrew Gulliford notes that there are "more statues erected to her honor than any other American woman" on p. 245 of "On the Tourist Trail with <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>: Issues of Interpretation and Preservation" in Fresonke and Spence, <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>
               </hi>, 239–64.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.blake.0142" n="42">Moulton, <hi rend="italic">Journals of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition</hi>, 1988, 4:11, 299; 5:111, 122, 268.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.blake.0143" n="43">Joanna Brooks, "Sacajawea, Meet Cogewea: A Red Progressive Revision of Frontier Romance" in Fresonke and Spence, <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>
               </hi>, 184–97.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.blake.0144" n="44">
               <name type="person" key="Spence, Mark">Spence</name>, "Historical Commentary," 58.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.blake.0145" n="45">Ibid., 62.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.blake.0146" n="46">The basic themes are present in DeVoto, <hi rend="italic">Journals of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>
               </hi>, in his focus on councils announcing the new great father (p. xliii), hostile encounters with Indians (p. 1), and American Indians as good neighbors (p. lv).</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.blake.0147" n="47">
               <name type="person" key="Limerick, Patricia Nelson">Patricia Nelson Limerick</name>, <hi rend="italic">The Legacy of Conquest: The Unbroken Past of the American West</hi> (New York: W.W. Norton, 1987).</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.blake.0148" n="48">
               <name type="person" key="Schama, Simon">Schama</name>, <hi rend="italic">Landscape and Memory</hi>, 15.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.blake.0149" n="49">
               <name type="person" key="Heck, Suzanne">Heck</name>, <hi rend="italic">Native American Resource Handbook</hi>, 27.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.blake.0150" n="50">
               <name type="person" key="Sax, Joseph">Joseph Sax</name>, <hi rend="italic">Mountains without Handrails: Reflections on the National Parks</hi> (Ann Arbor: University of Michigan Press, 1980).</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.blake.0151" n="51">Gulliford, "On the Tourist Trail," 251.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.blake.0152" n="52">Lowenthal, "Place of the Past," 110.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.blake.0153" n="53">Eckert, "Focusing on Inclusion," 21; <name type="person" key="Slaughter, Thomas P.">Slaughter</name>, <hi rend="italic">Exploring <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>
               </hi>, 8.</note>
            <p>This article was reproduced with the permission of the <hi rend="italic">Great Plains Quarterly</hi>.  The <hi rend="italic">Great Plains Quarterly</hi> is published by the Center for Great Plains Studies at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln.  <hi rend="italic">
                  <ref target="http://www.unl.edu/plains">www.unl.edu/plains</ref>
               </hi>.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>