<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.lc.lavender.01.01">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Way to the Western Sea</title>
            <title type="sub">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> across the Continent</title>
            <title type="sub" level="a">Chapter 1</title>
            <author>David Lavender</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2005</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Way to the Western Sea</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">Chapter 1</title>
               <author>David Lavender</author>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>2001</date>
               <idno type="ISBN">0-8032-8003-3</idno>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-11-09</date>
            <date>2005-04-20</date>
            <name>Becky Potter</name>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Split into chapters Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="one" type="chapter">
            <head rend="center">ONE. Beginner's Luck</head>
            <div type="section">
               <p>
Luck! It began for <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Meriwether Lewis</name>, paymaster of the First Infantry Regiment, United States Army, when he reached his regimental headquarters in <name type="place" key="Pittsburgh, Pa.">Pittsburgh</name> on March 5, 1801, after a rough trip from <name type="place" key="Detroit, Mich.">Detroit</name>, and found in his mail a letter from <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Thomas Jefferson</name>, recently elected president of the United States.</p>
               <p>
His thin, long-nosed face must have shown his mingled delight and astonishment. <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> needed a private secretary with unusual qualifications. "Your knolege of the Western country," he wrote, "of the army and of all it's interests and relations have rendered it desirable for public as well as private purposes that you should be engaged in that office."<ref target="n0101" n="1"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Pay would be five hundred dollars a year. Not much even then, but <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> could retain his rank as job insurance and save living expenses as a member of the president's household. Now, that was exciting! <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, who was given to quick exhilarations and, balancing them, occasional deep depressions, dashed off a boastful note to an army friend—he would now be in a position to "inform you of the most important political occurrences of our government or such of them as I may feel myself at liberty to give"<ref target="n0102" n="2"/>—and then wrote a more circumspect letter to <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> accepting the appointment. After settling his accounts, he requisitioned three fresh horses, one for riding and two for packing, and shortly after March 10 started for the new federal city of <name type="place" key="Washington D. C.">Washington</name>. It was a miserable trip. Flat gray skies, leafless trees, the <hi rend="italic">plop-suck, plop-suck</hi> of hooves in the thawing mire, followed by long nights in dreary wayside inns.</p>
               <p>
Some of the phrases in <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name> letter kept returning to puzzle him. Knowledge of the Western country, of the army and all its interests and relations . . . He knew army procedures and could get along in the wilderness, but surely there was nothing in that to command national interest. Indian affairs? Hardly. The tribes of the Northwest had been quiet since their crushing defeat at Fallen Timbers in 1794 by <name type="person" key="Wayne, Anthony">General Anthony Wayne</name>. Military defense? 
That seemed just as unlikely. British fur traders were no longer occupying posts on American soil and stirring up trouble. Another tension had ended in 1795 when <name type="place" key="Spain">Spain</name> had opened the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name> to the flatboats of the pioneers surging across the <name type="place" key="Allegheny Mountains">Allegheny Mountains</name>. The undeclared naval war with revolutionary <name type="place" key="France">France</name> was winding down. Peace, in short, seemed assured for many years.</p>
               <p>
Yet <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> wanted his special talents. Strange, strange. Well, he'd learn eventually. On he plodded, losing still more time because one of his horses went lame.</p>
               <p>
He reached <name type="place" key="Washington D. C.">Washington</name> shortly after April 1, to find that <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> had departed for a short rest at his home, <name type="place" key="Monticello (Va.)">Monticello</name>, in <name type="place" key="Albemarle County, Va.">Albemarle County</name>, <name type="place" key="Virginia">Virginia</name>. He had left behind, in the leaky, unfinished hull of the President's House (now called the White House), a steward, a housekeeper, and three servants whose chief responsibility, until <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> returned, would be taking care of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name>.<ref target="n0103" n="3"/> Gratifying enough after a winter on the Northern frontier. Yet probably <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> would rather have gone south, too, for <name type="place" key="Albemarle County, Va.">Albemarle County</name> was home to him as well as to the president.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>
The <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> plantation, Locust Hill, named for the big locust trees that sheltered the main buildings, was only eight or nine miles from <name type="place" key="Monticello (Va.)">Monticello</name>. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether</name> had been born there August 18, 1774, the second child and first son of <name type="person" key="Lewis, William">William</name> and <name type="person" key="Marks, Lucy Meriwether Lewis">Lucy Meriwether Lewis</name>. He scarcely remembered his father, for <name type="person" key="Lewis, William">William Lewis</name>, a lieutenant in the Continental Army, had died in November 1779 from injuries and exposure suffered when his horse fell in an icy stream while he was homeward bound on leave.</p>
               <p>
The death left <name type="person" key="Marks, Lucy Meriwether Lewis">Lucy</name> with three small children to raise, a thousand-acre plantation to manage, additional lands in the wilderness to fret about, and sharp worries over British raiders in the vicinity. She solved the problems in part by marrying, six months after her husband's death, another army officer and a man she had known for some time, <name type="person" key="Marks, John">Captain John Marks</name>. By him she bore two more children.</p>
               <p>
In 1784 a friend of <name type="person" key="Marks, John">Marks's</name> persuaded him and his family to join a speculative land rush to the <name type="place" key="Broad River (Ga.)">Broad River</name> in the wilds of northern <name type="place" key="Georgia">Georgia</name>. There is no direct evidence that young <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether</name> did not get along with the stepfather who had twice changed his life. Still, he became, during those years, a moody lad who often went alone into the woods with his dogs, frequently at night to hunt raccoons and opossums. He had an eye for plants and one way or 
another taught himself a good deal about the vegetation he encountered. His mother probably encouraged him. She was a noted herb doctor, and it is not hard to imagine them going into the forest together on collecting trips.</p>
               <p>
Almost certainly <name type="person" key="Marks, Lucy Meriwether Lewis">Lucy Marks</name> taught her children the rudiments of writing, reading, and doing sums. Within three years, however, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether</name> had surpassed his mother's capabilities and those of the neighborhood schools. Whether at her urging or his, he was sent back to Locust Hill in 1787. For a little more than two years he attended a sequence of schools run by impoverished divines. The uncles who were acting as his guardians then set him to work 
on the plantation at the age of fifteen or so. It was an exacting practical education—learning to oversee the slaves who performed the labor in the almost self-sufficient plantation. Herding, butchering, milling, planting; spinning thread and making clothes; erecting buildings and fences; extemporizing repairs, hauling. Setting up goals and schedules. Keeping accounts. Learning the jargon of the neighboring planters who stopped by to trade news.</p>
               <p>
After Marks died either late in 1791 or early in 1792, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether</name> went to <name type="place" key="Georgia">Georgia</name> and brought the family back to Locust Hill, using for the journey a carriage said to have been built by <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name> slaves at <name type="place" key="Monticello (Va.)">Monticello</name>.<ref target="n0104" n="4"/> Apparently he stayed restless, however, and if <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Thomas Jefferson</name> is to be believed, he tried to seize the first big opportunity for adventure that came his way.</p>
               <p>
The circumstances are suggested in a letter <name type="person" key="Wistar, Caspar">Caspar Wistar</name>, a professor of anatomy at the University of Pennsylvania, wrote to the American botanist <name type="person" key="Marshall, Moses">Moses Marshall</name>. <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Thomas Jefferson</name>, <name type="person" key="Wistar, Caspar">Wistar</name> said, and "some other gentlemen," mostly members of the American Philosophical Society, were proposing to raise a prize of one 
thousand guineas to be awarded to anyone who, after following the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri River</name> to its source, brought back proof that he had continued to the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>.<ref target="n0105" n="5"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Years later, on August 18, 1813, the anniversary of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> birth and four years after his death by suicide, <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, then seventy, wrote a short memoir of the young man's life. In it he stated that <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, who in 1792 had been stationed in <name type="place" key="Charlottesville, Va.">Charlottesville</name>, <name type="place" key="Virginia">Virginia</name>, on recruiting service for the army, somehow learned of the transcontinental proposal and "warmly solicited me to obtain for him the execution of that object." <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> declined, implying the venture was too dangerous for a youth of eighteen.<ref target="n0106" n="6"/>
               </p>
               <p>
There are problems with this recollection. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> had not yet joined the army in 1792 and would not be stationed in <name type="place" key="Charlottesville, Va.">Charlottesville</name> until 1798. Donald Jackson, who has studied the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> expedition as deeply as anyone, is inclined to believe the aging <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> made a mistake and the episode may, in fact, never have occurred. Certainly there is no mention of it in any other surviving document.<ref target="n0107" n="7"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Be that as it may, another candidate soon appeared. This was the highly trained French botanist, <name type="person" key="Michaux, André">André Michaux</name>, aged forty-six. <name type="person" key="Michaux, André">Michaux</name> had been in the United States since 1785, searching for useful plants he could introduce into <name type="place" key="France">France</name>. He established one nursery near <name type="place" key="Charleston, S.C.">Charleston</name>, <name type="place" key="South Carolina">South Carolina</name>, and another at <name type="place" key="Hackensack, N.J.">Hackensack</name>, <name type="place" key="New Jersey">New Jersey</name>, and stocked them with specimens he found in the mountains of the <name type="place" key="North Carolina, South Carolina">Carolinas</name> and the hazardous swamps of <name type="place" key="Florida">Florida</name>. In 1792 he traveled with <name type="place" key="Montreal">Montreal</name> fur traders into the harsh lands near the southern tip of <name type="place" key="Hudson Bay">Hudson Bay</name>. In <name type="place" key="Montreal">Montreal</name>, quite possibly, he learned that <name type="person" key="Mackenzie, Alexander">Alexander Mackenzie</name> of the North West Company had just passed through the city on an exciting errand—crossing <name type="place" key="Canada">Canada</name> to the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name> by canoe in order to show that far western trading posts could be supplied from harbors on the distant coast.</p>
               <p>
The thought was bound to stir a man of <name type="person" key="Michaux, André">Michaux's</name> temperament. And though there is no evidence to prove this, he may well have heard of the thousand-guinea prize from his fellow botanist, <name type="person" key="Marshall, Moses">Moses Marshall</name>. In any event he applied to <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> for the position.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> and the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>: we need to digress in order to place his interest in perspective. Heritage, predilections, and circumstances all inclined him that way, though he himself never traveled physically more than fifty miles west of <name type="place" key="Monticello (Va.)">Monticello</name>. His father had been a pioneer land speculator and mapmaker. The son had touched on 
the West in one of the few books he wrote, Notes on <name type="place" key="Virginia">Virginia</name>. While in <name type="place" key="France">France</name> from 1784 to 1789 as American minister to the court of <name type="person" key="Louis XVI">Louis XVI</name>, he began assiduously collecting books on the West until he owned more volumes on the topic than any other collector in the world.<ref target="n0108" n="8"/>
               </p>
               <p>
That the West would be peopled by Americans, though <name type="place" key="Spain">Spain</name> then owned almost all of it, <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> had no doubt. Even during the Revolution, citizens of the eastern regions and immigrants from Europe had persisted in crossing the <name type="place" key="Allegheny Mountains">Alleghenies</name> in defiance of violent Indian opposition. When the war ended, the stream became a flood. In 1785, for a single instance, a thousand river craft, scores of them huge flatboats loaded with entire families, their goods, and livestock, went down the <name type="place" key="Ohio River">Ohio</name>. Roads split the forests: the Forbes Road through <name type="place" key="Pennsylvania">Pennsylvania</name>, the Wilderness 
Trail blazed through <name type="place" key="Cumberland Gap">Cumberland Gap</name> by <name type="person" key="Boone, Daniel">Daniel Boone</name>, and a dozen more. By 1800, three hundred thousand people lived in the trans-<name type="place" key="Allegheny Mountains">Allegheny</name> region, as compared to thirty thousand at the close of the Revolution.</p>
               <p>
In <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name> fanciful moments the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name> disappeared as the boundary with <name type="place" key="Spain">Spain</name>, and the human tide flowed unrestrained. In 1786 he wrote in a private letter, "Our confederacy must be viewed as the nest from which all America, North and South, is to be peopled." Others, stirred by the same prospect, shared the view. <name type="person" key="Morse, Jedediah">Jedediah Morse</name>, writer of geography textbooks, proclaimed in 1789, "We cannot but anticipate the period, as not far distant, 
when the AMERICAN EMPIRE will comprehend millions of souls, west of the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name>." The poet <name type="person" key="Dwight, Timothy">Timothy Dwight</name> sang, 
"Soon shall thy sons across the mainland roam / And claim on far <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name> shores their home."<ref target="n0109" n="9"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Savants of the American Philosophical Society, of which <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> was a member, loved to speculate on what venturesome settlers might find in the uncharted landmass. Did mammoths, long extinct in Europe, still wander there? How far north did the strange llamas of Peru range? Were there active volcanoes, as rumored? Mountains of undissolved salt? Above all, was there a central "height of land" from which the West's principal rivers 
extended like rays—the Red-Nelson system toward <name type="place" key="Hudson Bay">Hudson Bay</name>, the <name type="place" key="Rio Grande">Rio Grande</name> southward, the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> eastward, and, interlocking with the headwaters of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, a navigable, west-flowing stream already named "Oregon" by two early army officers and traders, <name type="person" key="Rogers, Robert">Robert Rogers</name> and <name type="person" key="Carver, Jonathan">Jonathan Carver</name>?</p>
               <p>
Should members of the Philosophical Society foster private attempts to find a westward crossing? Some thought so. In 1783, when garbled rumors reached <name type="place" key="Philadelphia, Pa.">Philadelphia</name> that a group of Britons proposed to explore the country from the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name> to <name type="place" key="California">California</name>, <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> wrote <name type="person" key="Clark, George Rogers">George Rogers Clark</name>, the military hero of the trans-<name type="place" key="Allegheny Mountains">Allegheny</name> West and one of <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark's</name> elder brothers, that "some of us here are talking in a feeble way of making the attempt to search that country. How would you like to lead such a party?" The offer was too feeble, and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> declined. No Britons appeared, either.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Ledyard, John">John Ledyard</name> came next. He was a Connecticut Yankee who had been with <name type="place" key="England">England's</name> great navigator, <name type="person" key="Cook, James">James Cook</name>, as a corporal of marines when <name type="person" key="Cook, James">Cook</name> had visited the Northwest Coast of America in 1778 on his last voyage of discovery. <name type="person" key="Ledyard, John">Ledyard</name> had seen how easily sea-otter pelts could be obtained from the natives and then resold in <name type="place" key="China">China</name> at an enormous profit. Eager to set up trading posts in the region, he sought backing first in the East and then in 
<name type="place" key="France">France</name>. After every financial prospect had failed him, he sought out <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, then residing in <name type="place" key="Paris">Paris</name>. To the minister the would-be explorer expounded one of the zaniest ideas in the history of exploration. He would cross <name type="place" key="Siberia">Siberia</name> to the <name type="place" key="Kamchatka Peninsula">Kamchatka Peninsula</name> and embark for <name type="place" key="Alaska">Alaska</name> on a Russian fur ship. From there he would walk to the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name>, buoyed by two large hunting dogs, an Indian peace pipe, and a hatchet for chopping firewood. What he 
hoped to achieve by the incredible effort, beyond publicity and material for another book, is impossible to say.</p>
               <p>
There was no chance he could succeed. "He has too much imagination," <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> wrote, and added wistfully that if he should get through, "he will give us new, curious &amp; useful information."<ref target="n0110" n="10"/> On <name type="person" key="Ledyard, John">Ledyard's</name> behalf he wrote the empress of <name type="place" key="Russia">Russia</name> for a passport. She refused it; the notion, one of her officers explained, was wholly chimerical. Grimly <name type="person" key="Ledyard, John">Ledyard</name> went ahead anyway and came within seven hundred miles of <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">the Pacific</name> before he was arrested and dragged back.</p>
               <p>
Now hardly five years later, here was <name type="person" key="Michaux, André">André Michaux</name>, eager for fame and a thousand guineas. Embarrassed—apparently the talk of the prize had been only talk—a few members of the Philosophical Society scrambled to rectify matters. On January 22, 1793, they drew up an agreement about payments: one-fourth down and other installments according to the explorer's progress. Simultaneously they set about trying to raise the necessary funds.<ref target="n0111" n="11"/>
               </p>
               <p>
The arrival of Citizen <name type="person" key="Genet, Edmond Charles">Edmond Charles Genet</name>, <name type="place" key="France">France's</name> new minister to the United States, at <name type="place" key="Charleston, S.C.">Charleston</name>, <name type="place" key="South Carolina">South Carolina</name>, on April 8, 1793, put a severe crimp in the program. By then it was known in America that <name type="place" key="France">France</name> had just abolished the monarchy and war had broken out again between that country and most of the rest of Europe. <name type="place" key="Genet, Edmond Charles">Genet's</name> assignment was to stir up trouble in the New World for <name type="place" key="France">France's</name> principal enemies by outfitting privateers in American harbors to prey on British shipping and by forming an army of insurgents to attack Spanish Louisiana.</p>
               <p>
The reception <name type="person" key="Washington, George">Washington</name> and the pro-British Federalists in the cabinet granted <name type="person" key="Genet, Edmond Charles">Genet</name>, who reached <name type="place" key="Philadelphia, Pa.">Philadelphia</name> on April 22, was noticeably cool. The Francophile <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, then serving as secretary of state, was more amiable. He listened to the schemer's bombast and, although the Frenchman was already in contact with <name type="person" key="Michaux, André">Michaux</name>, went ahead with plans for the exploration. He drew up, under the date of April 30, detailed instructions, the main one of which was for <name type="person" key="Michaux, André">Michaux</name> to "seek for &amp; pursue that route which shall form the shortest &amp; most convenient communication between the higher parts of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> &amp; the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific ocean</name>." Another society member was appointed to collect the first installment of the subscriptions specified in the agreement. Results are suggestive. Only twenty persons paid up. Amounts ranged from $2.00 to $25.00 from <name type="person" key="Washington, George">George Washington</name>, who had subscribed the previous January. <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> paid $12.50, as did his enemy <name type="person" key="Hamilton, Alexander">Alexander Hamilton</name>. Total: $128.25.<ref target="n0112" n="12"/> Hardly enough for crossing the continent (he surely planned to take a crew along), and it is difficult to suppose that <name type="place" key="France">France's</name> flagrant breaches of neutrality did not help account for the shortage.</p>
               <p>
On July 15, 1793, <name type="person" key="Michaux, André">Michaux</name> started West to further <name type="person" key="Genet, Edmond Charles">Genet's</name> plans, not the Philosophical Society's. It was not a fruitful trip. On <name type="person" key="Washington, George">Washington's</name> demand, the French government recalled <name type="person" key="Genet, Edmond Charles">Genet</name>, <name type="person" key="Michaux, André">Michaux</name> drifted back to <name type="place" key="Philadelphia, Pa.">Philadelphia</name>, and the disturbance lost its punch, although <name type="person" key="Clark, George Rogers">George Rogers Clark</name>, whom <name type="person" key="Genet, Edmond Charles">Genet</name> had commissioned "Major General of the Independent and Revolutionary Legion of the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name>," kept fussing with it well into 1794.<ref target="n0113" n="13"/>
               </p>
               <p>
The episode left scars, for it exacerbated the feuding between Federalists and Antifederalists (Jeffersonian Republicans) in Congress and in the cabinet. Weary of turmoil, <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> resigned as secretary of state on December 31, 1793, and returned home to restore his neglected plantation and to resume work on his domed, pillared, airy mansion. He would not return officially to the capital at <name type="place" key="Philadelphia, Pa.">Philadelphia</name> until he challenged <name type="person" key="Adams, John">John Adams</name> for the presidency in 1796.</p>
               <p>
To jump ahead: In those days voters cast their ballots for electors pledged to the presidentail candidate of one party or the other. Those chosen then met in <name type="place" key="Philadelphia, Pa.">Philadelphia</name> (later in <name type="place" key="Washington D. C.">Washington</name>) and voted according to their pledges. The man who received the most electoral votes became president and the runner-up vice-president. In 1796, <name type="person" key="Adams, John">John Adams</name>, a Federalist, won. <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, a Republican, became his puntative successor, an uneasy situation. Well, there would be another election in 1800 and <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> was determined that then he would be second to no one. That, too, bacame part of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis's</name> luck.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, meanwhile had let his yearning for adventure draw him into military service. The proximate cause was an excise tax of seven cents a gallon on distilled spirits, which commonly retailed on the frontier for twenty-five cents a gallon. Since making whiskey was almost the only way backwoods farmers had of disposing of their surplus grain, the West was outraged, particularly since no tax was imposed on any Eastern product. Antitax riots—the so-called Whiskey Rebellion—erupted in western <name type="place" key="Pennsylvania">Pennsylvania</name>; revenue agents were tarred and feathered.</p>
               <p>
To demonstrate that the federal government could not be trifled with, <name type="person" key="Washington, George">Washington</name>, at <name type="person" key="Hamilton, Alexander">Hamilton's</name> behest, asked the governors of <name type="place" key="Virginia">Virginia</name>, <name type="place" key="Maryland">Maryland</name>, <name type="place" key="New Jersey">New Jersey</name>, and <name type="place" key="Pennsylvania">Pennsylvania</name> to provide thirteen thousand militiamen for restoring order. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name> joined the <name type="place" key="Virginia">Virginia</name> contingent and quickly became an ensign, the equivalent today of second lieutenant. The oversized force—a blunderbuss to kill a flea—marched through the brilliant reds and golds of fall to the <name type="place" key="Pittsburgh, Pa.">Pittsurgbh</name> area. The ringleaders among the insurgents fled. Only eighteen protesters were captured and tried. Two were convicted, and <name type="person" key="Washington, George">Washington</name> pardoned them. In spite of the clemency, the overkill turned many resentful frontiersmen into voters—Antifederalist voters—for the first time in their lives.</p>
               <p>
At the expiration of his enlistment, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> transferred, still an ensign, into what became the First Regiment of the regular army. Either late that year (1795) or early the next, he served for a few months at <name type="place" key="Fort Greenville, Ohio">Fort Greenville</name>, <name type="place" key="Ohio">Ohio</name>, in a rifle company commanded by Lieutenant <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark</name>, four years older than he and a veteran of the ferocious Indian wars of the first half of the 1790s. A strong friendship developed between them, but actual association ended, except for occasional letters, when <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> left the service to salvage what he could of the muddled affairs of his alcoholic brother <name type="person" key="Clark, George Rogers">George</name>.</p>
               <p>
Unlike <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> saw no action in the army. He drilled his men punctiliously in the Northwest's dreary stockades and supervised the building of <name type="place" key="Fort Puckering (Tenn.)">Fort Puckering</name> on a bluff above the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name> where <name type="place" key="Memphis, Tenn.">Memphis</name> now stands. Then in 1798, he was placed on recruiting duty at <name type="place" key="Charlottesville, Va.">Charlottesville</name>, <name type="place" key="Virginia">Virginia</name>, near his home—and <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name>. He stayed there well into 1799. Certainly he saw the vice-president during that period. They could hardly have been close friends, for there was a thirty-one-year difference in their ages. Still, they were neighbors. <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> bought beautifully cured hams from <name type="person" key="Marks, Lucy Meriwether Lewis">Lucy Marks</name>, and the presidential aspirant would have enjoyed talking to the younger man about the mood of the settlers in the Northwest, and about the region's natural history, a subject that fascinated both. Before long <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> would have sensed that <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> was an ardent Republican, though most of his fellow officers were Federalists.</p>
               <p>
As the new century approached, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> was moved back to the Northwest. Late in 1800, aged twenty-six, he was promoted to captain and stationed at Detroit. Shortly thereafter he was made regimental paymaster, an assignment that involved arduous journeys down the <name type="place" key="Ohio River">Ohio</name> by boat and through the dense forests by horse. Or, more accurately, it would have involved many such journeys if the election of 1800 had not intervened.</p>
               <p>
When the campaign, the most slanderous in American history, was over the Federalists had been defeated—but two Republicans, <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> and <name type="person" key="Burr, Aaron">Aaron Burr</name>, were tied at seventy-three votes each. This threw the contest into the House of Representatives. Thirty-six ballots, each preceded by intense maneauvering, were cast before the deadlock splintered, with <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> as president and Burr as vice-president.</p>
               <p>
The triumph came February 17, only two weeks before the inauguration. A whole new administration had to be given shape, and yet <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, ignoring qualified applicants near at hand, took time enough to reach out into the wilderness and hire <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Meriwether Lewis</name> as his private secretary.</p>
               <p>
For a long time many people have wondered why. Because <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> eventually did lead the first American expedition to reach the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name> by land, some historians have assumed the choice was in <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name> mind before the election.<ref target="n0114" n="14"/>
               </p>
               <p>
The conjecture just won't wash. It is true <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> had speculated at length about what lay beyond the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name>. It is true he envisioned a continental destiny for the United States. As a private individual, acting generally on behalf of the American Philosophical Society, he had involved himself in three ill-conceived plans. 
But there is no evidence that as a public leader, whether as secretary of state or vice-president, he had endeavored to set into motion a government-sponsored, carefully prepared enterprise.</p>
               <p>
Consider. The Spanish empire was losing its grip. Maintaining <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name> even in a halfhearted way was endured only in the hope that the vast region would serve as a topographical buffer protecting <name type="place" key="New Mexico">New Mexico</name> and, especially, <name type="place" key="Mexico">Mexico</name>, rich in silver. But that hope, <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> believed, was fatuous. The <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name> Valley was filling with aggressive, energetic Americans. Some, taking advantage of <name type="place" key="Spain">Spain's</name> offer of land grants to adult males who would 
embrace Spanish citizenship and Roman Catholicism (no inconvenient attention was paid to the way the "converts" observed their new faith), were already crossing the river. <name type="person" key="Boone, Daniel">Daniel Boone's</name> family was among them. So were <name type="person" key="Austin, Moses">Moses Austin</name> and his young son <name type="person" key="Austin, Stephen F.">Stephen</name>, later the "fathers" of American Texas. <name type="place" key="Spain">Spain</name> hoped, of course, that these and other rugged, naturalized Spaniards would leap to the defense of their property in case of invasion.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> thought not. The emigrants, he believed, would remember their origins and work for eventual annexation by the United States. So why stir up a hornet's nest by sending a government-sponsored expedition into alien territory? Why rouse French and British curiosity: what were those Americans doing? Better let nature take its course. Let the plum ripen until it was ready to fall without friction into American hands.</p>
               <p>
Then why did he hire <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name>? The reasons were immediate, pragmatic, and political. Dressed in a dark uniform crisscrossed with white belts, and wearing a cocked hat with an eagle medallion in its front, the captain would lend dignity to the confidential messages he carried. He could serve as a decorative and charming host at presidential dinners—a real need, for <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> was a widower and his daughters could not often leave their 
own growing households to help. More important, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> was a stalwart Republican. The spoils system of appointing party faithful to government positions had not yet attained the lush growth it would achieve under Andrew Jackson, but it was on the way. The excise tax had provided openings for Federalist agents, and just before leaving office <name type="person" key="Adams, John">John Adams</name> had created several "midnight" judges. During the expansion of the armed forces while the undeclared naval war with <name type="place" key="France">France</name> was under way (1798–1800), most officers had been picked according to party allegiance. Now it was the Republicans' turn. One of <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name> campaign promises had been to cut the size of the army, but he wanted to be careful not to remove dependable Republicans.<ref target="n0115" n="15"/>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, whom he knew to be trustworthy, could guide the endeavor and also work over long, dull lists of postmasterships.<ref target="n0116" n="16"/>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>
Toward the end of April 1801, <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> returned to swampy <name type="place" key="Washington D. C.">Washington</name> (population 3,210) from <name type="place" key="Monticello (Va.)">Monticello</name> and, with his new secretary, tackled the problem of making the huge, white-painted sandstone presidential mansion habitable. Its twenty-three rooms were big and cold; <name type="person" key="Adams, Abigail">Abigail Adams</name> had said it was impossible to keep warm in such a place. Because the Adamses had removed most of the furniture—it was their own property—more had to be provided. An unsubstantial partition was built in the East Room, on the second floor, to provide <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> with two chambers. <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> had more suitable quarters in the west wing. The unkempt grounds were tidied up and surrounded by a rail fence, but little could be done about the approach to the entry hall; the outside steps and porch were still made of planks.<ref target="n0117" n="17"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Because the new secretary of state, <name type="person" key="Madison, James">James Madison</name>, and his wife, <name type="person" key="Madison, Dolley">Dolley</name>, were temporarily without housing, <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> invited them to stay in the mansion until their own quarters were ready. <name type="person" key="Madison, James">Madison</name> was wizened and sharp-eyed; <name type="person" key="Madison, Dolley">Dolley</name>, plump, pretty, and addicted to snuff.<ref target="n0118" n="18"/> Both were sparkling conversationalists and lent elan to the dinner parties the president launched as soon as a proper cook had been found for him by the <name type="person" key="Yrujo, Marqués de Casa">Marqués de Casa Yrujo</name>, the Spanish ambassador. <name type="person" key="Yrujo, Marqués de Casa">Yrujo</name> was a dashing, handsome, curly-haired cavalier given to resplendent uniforms. Fluent in English, he had married the daughter of that sound Republican, <name type="person" key="McKean, Thomas">Thomas McKean</name>, the governor of <name type="place" key="Pennsylvania">Pennsylvania</name>, and was a favorite of <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name>.</p>
               <p>
Though <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, six feet tall, angular, red-headed, and always poised, could have matched the sartorial splendor of some of his guests, he chose not to. He saw himself as the representative of the nation's sturdy tillers of the soil. He dressed accordingly, appearing at his own parties in ordinary clothing, occasionally wearing slippers. The food he served did not match his costume. One diarist, <name type="person" key="Dickerson, Mahlon">Mahlon Dickerson</name>, who became a close friend of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether 
Lewis</name>, wrote after one dinner that "however [<name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>] may neglect his person, he takes good care of his table. No man in America keeps a better." It should have been good. <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, whose salary as president was $25,000 a year, spent that first year $6,508 on groceries and provisions, $2,797.28 on wine, and $2,700 on servants, some of them in livery.<ref target="n0119" n="19"/> Laborers, it might be pointed out, earned, at that period, $10.00 a month.</p>
               <p>
After several weeks, the Madisons moved to their own house, and the president and his secretary were left, <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> wrote one of his daughters, as lonely as two mice in a church.<ref target="n0120" n="20"/> Did that lonesomeness break down some of his habitual reserve? "Secrecy," according to his biographer Saul Padover, "was his strategy and his predilection."<ref target="n0121" n="21"/> Still, it would be strange if he did not let slip, during that summer, occasional remarks that revealed to his secretary some of his uneasiness about French intentions in the West.</p>
               <p>
The matter began innocuously. Shortly after the inauguration <name type="person" key="Pichon, Louis André">Louis André Pichon</name>, French chargé d'affaires in <name type="place" key="Washington D. C..">Washington</name>, told the president that <name type="person" key="Bonaparte, Napoleon">Napoleon</name> was planning to retake the island of <name type="place" key="Santo Domingo">Santo Domingo</name> from <name type="person" key="L'Ouverture, Toussaint">Toussaint L'Ouverture</name> and black insurrectionists. Could the French government count on American help?</p>
               <p>
The proposal awoke <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name> strongest biases—his love for France, where he had spent some of his happiest years; his desire not to ruffle the new Convention of 1800, which had ended America's undeclared naval war with that nation; and his dread, as a Southern slaveholder, of an independent black republic near the borders of the United States. If the spirit of black rebellion spread . . . Chilled by the thought—his own state of <name type="place" key="Virginia">Virginia</name> had just authorized the arming of fifteen thousand men as a defense against possible insurrection—<name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> told <name type="person" key="Pichon, Louis André">Pichon</name> the United States would halt shipments of food to <name type="place" key="Santo Domingo">Santo Domingo</name>, hoping this would help starve <name type="person" key="L'Ouverture, Toussaint">Toussaint</name> into submission.</p>
               <p>
So far, so good. But then rumors leaked across the <name type="place" key="Atlantic Ocean">Atlantic</name> that <name type="place" key="Spain">Spain</name> had retroceded all <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name> to <name type="place" key="France">France</name>!<ref target="n0122" n="22"/> If they were true, America's hope of eventually absorbing the vast territory by slow and peaceful osmosis from moribund <name type="place" key="Spain">Spain</name> was ended.</p>
               <p>
Rumor. But as <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> paced his office, talking to his cabinet members and with <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name> quite possibly listening, he found it a rumor all too easy to believe. <name type="place" key="France">France</name> had long dreamed of reclaiming her lost colonial empire in the New World. The <name type="person" key="Genet, Edmond Charles">Genet</name>–<name type="person" key="Michaux, André">Michaux</name>–<name type="person" key="Clark, George Rogers">George Rogers Clark</name> conspiracy of 1792–93 had been part of the cloak-and-dagger game. Later, in 1796, the French general, <name type="person" key="Collot, George Victor">George Victor Collot</name>, had traveled through the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name> Valley, studying its topography in more detail than befitted an ordinary tourist. And now <name type="place" key="Santo Domingo">Santo Domingo</name>.</p>
               <p>
Plus other matters that <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> could not have known at the time, though the outlines soon enough took shape. In 1798, <name type="place" key="France">France's</name> lame, shrewd, unscrupulous foreign minister, <name type="person" key="Talleyrand, Charles">Talleyrand</name>, had baldly told his Spanish counterpart that <name type="place" key="Spain">Spain</name> could not hold the westward-pushing Americans away from <name type="place" key="Mexico">Mexico's</name> silver mines, but <name type="place" key="France">France</name> could. So why not let <name type="person" key="Bonaparte, Napoleon">Napoleon</name> take over <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name>, together with East and West <name type="place" key="Florida">Florida</name>, and create from them "a wall of Brass forever impenetrable to the combined efforts of <name type="place" key="England">England</name> [working out of <name type="place" key="Canada">Canada</name>] and the Americans"?<ref target="n0123" n="23"/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Carlos IV">Carlos IV</name> of <name type="place" key="Spain">Spain</name> refused to negotiate—until <name type="person" key="Bonaparte, Napoleon">Bonaparte</name> so thoroughly mauled an Austrian army at <name type="place" key="Marengo, Italy">Marengo</name>, <name type="place" key="Italy">Italy</name>, in 1800 that the Austrian-Russian-British coalition pledged to subduing him began to break apart. Arrogantly then he put more pressure on <name type="person" key="Carlos IV">Carlos</name>, helped by the Spanish king's wife, who wanted a duchy for her brother's then-propertyless family. At San Ildefonso, on October 1, 1800—one day after <name type="person" key="Bonaparte, Napoleon">Napoleon's</name> ministers had removed 
another roadblock by signing the convention that brought peace with the United States—he promised to give <name type="person" key="Carlos IV">Carlos</name> the Grand Duchy of Tuscany with its bejeweled cities of Florence, Pisa, and Siena. In exchange he was to receive six warships and the territory of <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name>, its boundaries only fuzzily known even along the lower <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name>. (Whether or not West <name type="place" key="Florida">Florida</name> could be considered a part of the territory would trouble American policymakers for years.)</p>
               <p>
Secretary of State <name type="person" key="Madison, James">James Madison</name> carried the administration's worries to <name type="person" key="Pichon, Louis André">Louis Pichon</name>. What, exactly, was going on in Europe? The French minister smiled blandly. Why the excitement? Was the United States planning to cross the river into territory it did not own? Not at all, <name type="person" key="Madison, James">Madison</name> said, just as blandly. He was concerned over the free navigation of the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name> and the right of deposit at <name type="place" key="New Orleans, La.">New Orleans</name>—rights, granted by <name type="place" key="Spain">Spain</name>, that allowed 
the entire export business of the valley to flow smoothly to docks and warehouses in the southern city. Sailing ships then landed at the same docks to pick up the merchandise for ocean transport. The lifeline was vital. The <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name>, <name type="person" key="Madison, James">Madison</name> would write later, was as important in the American view of things as "the <name type="place" key="Hudson River">Hudson</name>, the <name type="place" key="Delaware River">Delaware</name>, the <name type="place" key="Potomac River">Potomac</name>, and all the navigable rivers of the Atlantic states formed into one stream."<ref target="n0124" n="24"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Would <name type="place" key="France">France</name> observe <name type="place" key="Spain">Spain's</name> customs?</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Pichon, Louis André">Pichon's</name> hands described a Gallic spread. How could Mr. <name type="person" key="Madison, James">Madison</name> ask such a question when not a Frenchman was anywhere near <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name>?</p>
               <p>
The maddening uncertainties were still plaguing <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>—and, by association, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name>—when <name type="person" key="Livingston, Robert">Robert Livingston</name>, the new American minister to <name type="place" key="France">France</name>, sailed for <name type="place" key="Paris">Paris</name> on November 11, 1801. His instructions were to block the retrocession if it was actually contemplated. If the exchange had taken place he should try to obtain land in West <name type="place" key="Florida">Florida</name> where an American port could be built. At the very least he should obtain a guarantee of free navigation and unimpeded deposit—all without offending the French.</p>
               <p>
Confirmation of the retrocession did not have to wait on <name type="person" key="Livingston, Robert">Livingston's</name> report. <name type="person" key="King, Rufus">Rufus King</name>, minister to <name type="place" key="England">Great Britain</name>, passed on the news in a letter to <name type="person" key="Madison, James">Madison</name> dated November 20, 1801. Two days later <name type="person" key="Leclerc, Charles">General Charles Leclerc</name> sailed for <name type="place" key="Santo Domingo">Santo Domingo</name> with twenty thousand soldiers jammed into thirty transports. And <name type="place" key="England">England</name>, the last holdout of the coalition that had begun crumbling after the battle of Marengo, signed the Treaty of Amiens with <name type="place" key="France">France</name>. At least it was called a treaty, although most observers believed it was a truce only and would end as soon as the British had recuperated. Finally—<name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> was back in the field of rumor again—fresh reports said that a second French fleet was slowly assembling in <name type="place" key="Holland">Holland</name>. British strategists feared it was aimed at <name type="place" key="Canada">Canada</name>, or perhaps even at <name type="place" key="England">England</name> itself. American informants said no: its goal was <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name>.</p>
               <p>
Furious, <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> realized he had been tricked. <name type="place" key="France">France</name>, it seemed now, was attacking <name type="place" key="Santo Domingo">Santo Domingo</name> not for itself but for use as a staging area for further adventures in the Caribbean and, probably, for a push against <name type="place" key="New Orleans, La.">New Orleans</name>. By occupying the city, through which three-eighths of America's commerce passed, <name type="person" key="Bonaparte, Napoleon">Napoleon</name> could make the young United States dance to whatever tune he called. He could push upstream against <name type="place" key="Canada">Canada</name>. He might 
even persuade the impatient American West to detach itself from the Union and thus destroy one of the world's great experiments in the viability of self-government.</p>
               <p>
A grim <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> worked out his responses slowly, carefully, and secretly—secretly lest his political enemies, the Federalists, disturb the country by crying out that his plans were inadequate and that they could do better. The key element he proposed was a colossal bluff that he outlined on April 18, 1802, in a long letter to
<name type="person" key="Livingston, Robert">Robert Livingston</name>. The minister, <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> directed, should convince <name type="person" key="Bonaparte, Napoleon">Bonaparte</name> that <name type="place" key="France">France</name> would be sealing her own doom by trying to take possession of <name type="place" key="New Orleans, La.">New Orleans</name>. For the United States would immediately counter by seeking an alliance with <name type="place" key="England">Great Britain</name> and creating a naval force strong enough to keep <name type="place" key="France">France</name> from reinforcing whatever settlements <name type="person" key="Bonaparte, Napoleon">Napoleon</name> sought to plant in the New World—a world that was henceforth to be held "for the common purposes of the United British and American nations." The only way out, for <name type="place" key="France">France</name>, would be the ceding of <name type="place" key="New Orleans, La.">New
Orleans</name> and the <name type="place" key="Florida">Floridas</name> to the United States. (Other letters suggested that in return for those critical areas the U.S. would assume two million dollars in claims American shipowners held against <name type="place" key="France">France</name> for damages sustained in the quasi war just ended.)</p>
               <p>
Negotiating with the French while groping toward an alliance with the British would take time, the president admitted to <name type="person" key="Livingston, Robert">Livingston</name>. But time would be available. The French could not move into the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name> until <name type="place" key="Santo Domingo">Santo Domingo</name> was subdued, and that, <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> predicted, "will not be a short work."<ref target="n0125" n="25"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Just contemplating an alliance with <name type="place" key="England">Great Britain</name> was a wrench for <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, for he despised that nation as an insufferable aristocracy. He could not be certain, moreover, that the self-centered Anglos, as he considered them to be, would play his game for him—or that <name type="person" key="Bonaparte, Napoleon">Napoleon</name> would be swayed by the bluster if a treaty did appear. So, though he was hoping to avoid war with his bluff, he had to prepare for war as best he could—still secretly because of the Federalists.</p>
               <p>
One of his long-range plans was to gain, as quickly as possible, title to Indian lands bordering the east bank of the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name>. White settlers pouring into the vacated areas would automatically create a strong defensive militia and relieve him of the necessity of reneging on his campaign promise to reduce the size of the country's standing army. He also ordered <name type="person" key="Claiborne, William C. C.">Governor William C. C. Claiborne</name> of newly formed <name type="place" key="Mississippi Territory">Mississippi Territory</name> to ready other militia units strong enough to swarm across the border and seize <name type="place" key="New Orleans, La.">New Orleans</name> at the first sign the French were moving into the river. Still other contemplated steps included strengthening <name type="place" key="Fort Adams (Florida)">Fort Adams</name>, which overlooked the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name> just north of the point where West <name type="place" key="Florida">Florida's</name> northern boundary touched the river, and the building of an entirely new fort at <name type="place" key="Cahokia, Ill.">Cahokia</name>, across the stream from <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>.<ref target="n0126" n="26"/>
               </p>
               <p>
So much for a French invasion. But what of the powder keg he was proposing to cuddle up to—<name type="place" key="England">Great Britain</name>? Its redoubtable fur traders, turned out of their posts south of the <name type="place" key="Great Lakes">Great Lakes</name>, were finding rich new sources of beaver in what is now the <name type="place" key="Minnesota">Minnesota</name>-<name type="place" key="Iowa">Iowa</name> region and along the upper <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> in <name type="place" key="North Dakota">North Dakota</name>. <name type="place" key="Spain">Spain</name> had not been able to check the trespasses, though its governors in <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> had tried after a fashion, but the French would have more muscle. To get the jump on them in the event of war, the Britishers might come swarming out of the north, take possession of all northern <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name>, and then sit back to dicker about territorial divisions.</p>
               <p>
They'd not use an army for the invasion: logistics were too formidable. Small ranger forces led by men who knew the Indians would be more logical. And so small forces were what <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> prepared to meet them with. During the planning, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis's</name> "knolege of the Western country, of the army and all it's interests and relations" surely proved useful.</p>
               <p>
First, the secretary of war, <name type="person" key="Dearborn, Henry">Henry Dearborn</name>, was directed to study means of stockpiling supplies and enlisting reinforcements for the forts along the <name type="place" key="Great Lakes">Great Lakes</name> frontier. But the big gap was in the unmapped wilderness farther west. Certainly it would be prudent for the Americans to learn something about its transportation routes, sites for army posts, and places where the topography made ambushes possible. Even more important would be convincing the Indians that the Americans would make better allies than the grasping Britons.</p>
               <p>
As the talk went on, the president's glance, it can be surmised, rested more and more speculatively on his young secretary. He was aware of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> faults, particularly his tendency to give way at times to deep depressions, a characteristic <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, who knew the Lewis family, attributed to heredity. But he also knew, as he wrote later, that <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> was "brave, prudent, habituated to the woods &amp; familiar with Indian manners &amp; character."<ref target="n0127" n="27"/> He had served six years in the frontier army. He knew discipline and as a captain could presumably handle a group of soldiers specially selected for a military reconnaissance in foreign territory. Why search farther for a leader? And at that moment the seed that would grow into the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> expedition was planted.<ref target="n0128" n="28"/>
               </p>
               <p>
(Assumptions. Nearly three years later, on April 7, 1805, at the beginning of the final push to the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> wrote exultantly in his journal of what had been "a da[r]ling project of mine for the last ten years." If taken literally "ten years" could not refer to the <name type="person" key="Michaux, André">Michaux</name> scheme of 1792–93, which he supposedly tried to join, but it could refer to his early years in the regular army when he served for a time with Lieutenant <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark</name>. Probably, though, the "ten" was a general statement. As we have noted, a refrain of the 1790s told of an American nation reaching from sea to sea. As soon as the Spanish barrier vanished, and most people believed the time 
was near, the army would take its place in the vanguard of the western surge. Speculation filled the barracks, and that may be what <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> meant. But since neither he nor <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> left a word about the actual genesis of the darling project, we can only speculate in our turn. Anyway, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name> was still lucky—the right man in the right place.)</p>
               <p>
In spite of the leaky post office and slow communications of the time, no political enemy detected what was up. Smugly <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> wrote <name type="person" key="Monroe, James">James Monroe</name> some months later, "They [the Federalists] would be truly mortified if they could see our files. . . . They would see that though we could not say when war would take place, yet we said with energy what would take place when it should arise."<ref target="n0129" n="29"/>
               </p>
               <p>
The jolt, when it came, was from the outside. On November 23, 1802, couriers raced into <name type="place" key="Washington D. C.">Washington</name> with word that the Spanish intendant of <name type="place" key="New Orleans, La.">New Orleans</name>, <name type="person" key="Morales, Juan Venture">Juan Ventura Morales</name>, had revoked the right of deposit the previous October 18. (<name type="place" key="Spain">Spain</name> still held sway; <name type="person" key="Carlos IV">Carlos</name> had refused to sign the treaties of retrocession because of <name type="person" key="Bonaparte, Napoleon">Napoleon's</name> dilatoriness in handing over Tuscany.) <name type="person" key="Morales, Juan Ventura">Morales</name> justified his action on the grounds of blatant bribery and smuggling by American shippers. Corruption existed, of a certainty. But few Americans accepted the explanation. French trickery, many thought, lay behind the revocation.</p>
               <p>
The angry surmise was wrong. Many years later scholars learned that <name type="person" key="Carlos IV">Carlos</name> himself had sent the order across the <name type="place" key="Atlantic Ocean">Atlantic</name> to <name type="person" key="Morales, Juan Ventura">Morales</name> as a final way to embarrass the French before he signed the treaties giving up <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name>. But at the time no one knew this truth. Roars went up for retaliatory measures—meaning, as far as the more jingoistic Federalists were concerned, an immediate declaration of war against <name type="place" key="France">France</name>.</p>
               <p>
To keep from disturbing the country more than it already was, <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> went about his ordinary business as if nothing untoward had occurred. Privately, however, he pushed his defense measures. One of his first moves was to visit his longtime friend, the <name type="person" key="Yrujo, Marqués de Casa">Marqués de Casa Yrujo</name> (the Spaniard might be more amenable than the 
French representative who would soon replace him) and ask permission for a small "literary" expedition—today we would call it a scientific trip—to cross Spanish <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name> to the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name> slope.</p>
               <p>
The request, which he had invented to disguise the group's military errand, was logical. <name type="person" key="Yrujo, Marqués de Casa">Yrujo</name> knew, and so told <name type="place" key="Spain">Spain's</name> minister of foreign affairs in <name type="place" key="Madrid, Spain">Madrid</name>, that <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> had long fantasized about the day when America might extend its influence to the South Sea, as Spaniards often called the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>.<ref target="n0130" n="30"/> Immediacy had been lent to the dream by the great accomplishment of <name type="person" key="Mackenzie, Alexander">Alexander Mackenzie</name>, who had crossed <name type="place" key="Canada">Canada</name> to those distant shores in 1793 
with a single canoe manned by eight or ten voyageurs. Since then an account of <name type="person" key="Mackenzie, Alexander">Mackenzie's</name> voyages had been published, first in <name type="place" key="London">London</name> in 1801 and in the United States a year later. <name type="person" key="Mackenzie, Alexander">Mackenzie</name> closed his narrative by urging the British government to take steps that would place the beaver and sea-otter commerce of the far Northwest firmly in the hands of private Canadian traders, to the exclusion of the <name type="place" key="Boston, Mass.">Boston</name> seafarers who were already scouring those 
distant, fog-shrouded waters for pelts that could be sold in <name type="place" key="China">China</name>.</p>
               <p>
One way for <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> to hold a line on the British would be to strengthen the American claim to the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>, whose mouth had been discovered in May 1792 by the Yankee sea captain <name type="person" key="Gray, Robert">Robert Gray</name>. For that matter, <name type="place" key="Spain">Spain</name> also had shadowy claims to the region, based on a handful of landings made along the coast by its own early navigators. Other nations paid little heed to these Spanish pretensions. Still, <name type="person" key="Yrujo, Marqués de Casa">Yrujo</name> reasoned, they might be of some deterrence if the British, the Russians (already busy in <name type="place" key="Alaska">Alaska</name>), or the Americans developed notions of advancing on <name type="place" key="Mexico">Mexico</name> through Spanish-occupied <name type="place" key="California">California</name>. Why weaken the Spanish position by facilitating the approach of Americans into the region?</p>
               <p>
As for letting a scientific expedition thread Louisiana by way of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri River</name>—well, <name type="person" key="Yrujo, Marqués de Casa">Yrujo</name> was no fool. Whatever scientific knowledge about Indians or geography its personnel gleaned could easily be adapted to military purposes if the need ever arose. Suavely he turned down the president's request.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> remained unruffled. He had done what protocol demanded. Now he would follow the dictates of necessity. He called <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name> into his office and told him the expedition would go ahead regardless, providing Congress appropriated enough money to get it started. Inasmuch as the Constitution gave the lawmakers no expressed right to finance exploration outside the nation's own boundaries, he would lay the project before them as a preliminary step to extending commerce in furs. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> should start the ball rolling by drawing up a cost estimate not to exceed 
$2,500. A larger amount might frighten the legislators and would not sit well with <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name> repeated statements about economizing. Both men realized the voyage's costs would soar far higher than $2,500 (eventually the amount reached $38,722.25, not counting services and materials furnished by the War Department) but at the time that was not the point.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> must have felt like a blindfolded child trying to pin the tail on the donkey. He could count on very few givens. For instance, he could avoid paying wages by recruiting army personnel whose pay and rations would continue wherever they were. As far as the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name>, army posts would render some assistance in the way of transportation and lodgings. But otherwise . . . what could he draw on, except things he remembered from his experiences as 
a regimental paymaster and from reading <name type="person" key="Mackenzie, Alexander">Alexander Mackenzie's</name> book about crossing the continent far to the north in 1793?</p>
               <p>
Stabbing blindly, the captain produced such items as $217 for scientific instruments, $255 for "camp equipage," $430 for transportation, $696 (the largest item) for Indian presents, $55 for medicine, $87 for contingencies, and so on—$2,500 right on the button.</p>
               <p>
Congress convened on December 15. <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name> original plan had been to spring the adventure on the legislators during his annual message. His secretary of the treasury, the tall, balding, brilliant <name type="person" key="Gallatin, Albert">Albert Gallatin</name>, though enthusiastic about the expedition itself, talked him out of a public declaration.<ref target="n0131" n="31"/> Such exposure would draw the world's attention to the fact that the United States was planning a deliberate trespass on alien territory. Surmise would fly. Would it not be wise to ask for funds behind closed doors? <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> complied and presented a public State of the Union address so bland that the leading Federalist war hawk, <name type="person" key="Hamilton, Alexander">Alexander Hamilton</name>, denounced it as a "lullaby."<ref target="n0132" n="32"/>
               </p>
               <p>
He next placated the angry voters west of the <name type="place" key="Allegheny Mountains">Allegheny Mountains</name> by appointing <name type="person" key="Monroe, James">James Monroe</name>, who was popular in that turbulent region, as special envoy to <name type="place" key="Paris">Paris</name> to help <name type="person" key="Livingston, Robert">Robert Livingston's</name> quest for the <name type="place" key="Florida">Floridas</name> and <name type="place" key="New Orleans, La.">New Orleans</name>. The negotiators were authorized to offer <name type="place" key="France">France</name> as much as ten million dollars for the desired lands.</p>
               <p>
He scheduled his secret message for January 18, 1803. He began it with an indirect approach to another of his defensive measures, obtaining more land along the east bank of the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name> from the Indians. Some years earlier, he reminded Congress, the government had established trading houses among the tribes. Their purpose was to defend the Indians against unscrupulous white traders. The question now was whether or not the act authorizing the 
government houses should be renewed.</p>
               <p>
He recommended an affirmative vote. Augmenting the trading-house program would create a desire in uncivilized breasts for many items of "domestic comfort." The yearners would realize they would have more goods to trade if they embraced agriculture and simple manufacturing. The need for hunting grounds would vanish, and they would be happy to dispose of the excess acres to the government at a favorable price. The U.S. would then parcel out the acquisitions to land-hungry Americans, who would promptly form themselves into militia units. In that way the country could plant "on the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Missisipi</name> itself the means of its own safety."</p>
               <p>
Only a few envious white traders, he continued, would object to this governmental interference with private enterprise, and their losses could be more than offset by extending the fur trade beyond the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name>, perhaps as far as the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>. The ultimate aim would be to make friends and allies of the far Western Indians while at the same time diverting valuable pelts from the rugged northern routes used by another nation—obviously <name type="place" key="England">Great Britain</name>, though not named in the message—and bringing the harvest down the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> to the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name> and thence eastward by a variety of routes. In the process the explorers would gain much information about the continent's geography.</p>
               <p>
In this elucidation <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> did not say a word about military reconnaissance, and probably none was needed by his listeners. Unctuously he finished, "The nation claiming this territory [<name type="place" key="Spain">Spain</name>] regarding this as a literary pursuit . . . would not be disposed to view it with jealousy, even if the expiring state of its interest did not render it a matter of indifference"<ref target="n0133" n="33"/>—a surprising statement in view of <name type="person" key="Yrujo, Marqués de Casa">Yrujo's</name> flat refusal only a few weeks before.</p>
               <p>
Bemused by <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name> adroit presentation, Congress overwhelmingly authorized an inquiry whose extraordinary scope 
they could not yet anticipate. From then on matters would rest largely in the hands of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name>, mostly because good fortune had brought him onto the scene, with his particular talents, when the opportunity was in the making.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="notes" type="notes">
            <head rend="center">Notes</head>
            <div type="section">
               <p>
Because Reuben C. Thwaites's <hi rend="italic">The Original Journals of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition</hi> is the basic reference book for the expedition itself, references to it are frequent and therefore limited, in all the following notes, to volume and page number. For an example, see note 12 below.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <note xml:id="n0101" n="1">
                  <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, February 23, 1801, in Jackson, <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, 2–3.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0102" n="2">
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> to F. Claibourne, March 7, 1801, in ibid., 11, 675.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0103" n="3">Malone, IV, 40.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0104" n="4">Dillon, 16.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0105" n="5">
                  <name type="person" key="Wistar, Caspar">Wistar</name> to <name type="person" key="Marshall, Moses">Marshall</name>, January 20, 1792, in Jackson, <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, II, 675–77.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0106" n="6">
                  <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, "Life of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Lewis</name>," in <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>, xviii.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0107" n="7">Malone, III, 109. Jackson, <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> and Stony Mountains</hi>, 157.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0108" n="8">Jackson, <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> and Stony Mountains</hi>, 86–96, discusses <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name> library.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0109" n="9">Boyd, IX, 218. Both Morse and Dwight are quoted in DeConde, 39–40. 
 See also Smith, 10–12.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0110" n="10">Quoted in DeVoto, <hi rend="italic">Course of Empire</hi>, 416. For an analysis of <name type="person" key="Ledyard, John">Ledyard's</name> 
 proposal, 595–98.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0111" n="11">Jackson, Letters, 11, 668–69.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0112" n="12">VII, 204.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0113" n="13">Bakeless, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, 86.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0114" n="14">Ibid., 3–5. Burroughs, 2. DeVoto, <hi rend="italic">Course</hi>, 608.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0115" n="15">The army's authorized strength when <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> took office was 5,438 officers and men, but only a few more than 4,000 were actually in office. On March 16, 1802, the authorized strength was cut to 3,312. Malone, IV, 248. Ganoe, 104.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0116" n="16">Jackson, <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> and Stony Mountains</hi>, 120. Malone, IV, 248.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0117" n="17">Malone, IV, 248.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0118" n="18">Ibid., 40.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0119" n="19">Jackson, <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, II, 667. "<name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name> Analysis of Expenditures ... ," in Mayo (ed.), 236.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0120" n="20">Malone, IV, 40.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0121" n="21">Padover, 115.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0122" n="22">My account of the events leading to the Louisiana Purchase is based on DeConde; Malone, IV; DeVoto, <hi rend="italic">Course</hi>; Sprague; Johansen and Gates; Morison and Commager; and McDonald, Decker, and Govan. More iconoclastic is Philbrick. For appropriate pages consult the indexes in the different books.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0123" n="23">Quoted in DeConde, 87.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0124" n="24">Malone, IV, 266.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0125" n="25">The full letter, <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> to <name type="person" key="Livingston, Robert">Livingston</name>, is in Sprague, 362–63.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0126" n="26">
                  <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name> military preparations: Adams; DeConde, 132–37. There is a reference to the proposed fort at <name type="place" key="Cahokia, Ill.">Cahokia</name> in Jackson, Letters, 41 n. 4.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0127" n="27">Jackson to <name type="person" key="Rush, Benjamin">Rush</name>, February 28, 1803, in Jackson, <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, 18–19.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0128" n="28">This runs counter to the common convention that the expedition, with <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> at its head, had been in <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name> mind for years. But the first actual step westward was taken as a <hi rend="italic">defensive</hi>, not expansionist, measure. To quote Johansen and Gates, 93, "It was to counteract this [British] influence, to win over the Indians, and to conduct a military reconnaissance against a possible war that <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> originally projected the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> expedition." See also Adams, 174–75, 184–85.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0129" n="29">Mayo, 249. Malone, IV, 272–73.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0130" n="30">Nasatir, <hi rend="italic">Before <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>
                  </hi>, 712–16.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0131" n="31">"<name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name> Message to Congress," in Jackson, <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, 4–8.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0132" n="32">Ibid., 12.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0133" n="33">Ibid., 13.</note>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.lavender.01.ack" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.lavender.01.00" type="contents"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.lavender.01" type="entire"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.lavender.01.02" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>