<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.lc.furtwangler.01">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
               <hi rend="italic">Oregon Historical Quarterly</hi> 102.3 [2001]: 290–315.</title>
            <title type="sub">Sacagawea's Son as a Symbol</title>
            <author>Albert Furtwangler</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>eburke3@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-05-26</date>
            <name>Beth Burke</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="main">Sacagawea's Son as a Symbol</head>
         <p>
            <name type="person" key="Furtwangler, Albert">by Albert Furtwangler</name>
         </p>
         <div type="Article">
            <p>(This article first appeared in <hi rend="italic">
                  <ref target="http://www.ohs.org/publications/about_ohq.cfm">Oregon Historical Quarterly</ref>
               </hi> 102:3 [2001]: 290–325.)</p>
            <p>In recent months, <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name>'s child has come out of the footnotes of history to an enduring fame around the world. His image — or the image of a baby representing him — now shines on a brightly minted dollar coin, and his story is sure to be publicized and retold often through the coming bicentennial celebrations of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> expedition of 1803–1806. Here in <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>, a re-dedication took place on June 24, 2000, at his grave site near <name type="place" key="Jordan Valley, Oregon">Jordan Valley</name> in the southeast corner of the state. It was an occasion for clearing and improving the site as a tourist attraction and for highlighting <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>'s claim to an important person in the expedition. The grave site has long been a pilgrimage destination for <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> devotees. It has been on the National Register of Historic Places since 1971, after the site was developed and dedicated through the efforts of local people and <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name> members of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Trail Heritage Foundation.</p>
            <p>But what can we say about the person whose life ended there in 1866? The signboard at the site outlines a tantalizing history. The child was born on February 11, 1805, at the winter camp of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> on the Upper <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> (in what is now <name type="place" key="North Dakota">North Dakota</name>). Just a few weeks later the party headed west and the child came along, survived risks and hardships over thousands of miles, and returned safely in 1806. Just days after <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark</name> parted down river, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> sent a letter back to the boy's father, <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Toussaint Charbonneau</name>, making an offer to educate the child and treat him as his own. After an interval, the child (by now named <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Jean Baptiste">Jean Baptiste Charbonneau</name> and nicknamed Pomp) was brought to <name type="place" key="St. Louis, Missouri">St. Louis</name> and educated at <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>'s expense. A further turn of fortune lay ahead. In 1822, a European prince, <name type="person" key="Paul Wilhelm of Wurttemberg">Paul Wilhelm of Wurttemberg</name>, ascended the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> on an expedition of scientific curiosity. He met the youth, still in his teens, near the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Kansas River">Kansas River</name> and agreed to carry him along to <name type="place" key="Europe">Europe</name> on his return. From 1824 to 1829, the young man lived at a palace in</p>
            <p>The first page of this essay is reproduced with the permission of The Oregon Historical Society.  Please click <ref target="http://www.ohs.org/publications/ohq-single-or-back-issue-orders.cfm">
                  <hi rend="bold">here</hi>
               </ref> to go directly to the Oregon Historical Society webpage to purchase an offprint of this article.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>