<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.lc.images_chippewa">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">Texts</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2005</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic
        Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl></bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh">
               <term/>
               <term/>
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-11-18</date>
            <name>Becky Potter</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-04-12</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="main">Chippewa (
      <hi rend="italic">anishinaabe</hi>)</head>
         <div type="additional">
            <p>To the northeast of the route taken by the Corps of Discovery lived the many
        communities making up the Ojibwe or 
        <hi rend="italic">anishinaabe</hi>people (Chippewa is a name not preferred by most
        anishinaabe today but it is part of the official designation of a number of their current
        reservations). Pushed westward by conflicts with Iroquoian peoples, the 
        <hi rend="italic">anishinaabe</hi>in the early nineteenth century occupied a vast region,
        from the shores of Lake Huron and Lake Superior westward to the Turtle Mountains of
        present day North Dakota. Much of the homeland of the 
        <hi rend="italic">anishinaabe</hi>was heavily wooded with a great deal of surface
        water—quite different from the environments of many of the Native peoples encountered by
        the Corps of Discovery. Dwelling in bark-covered domed lodges, they fished, harvested wild
        rice, hunted and trapped a variety of small game animals, and made sugar from tapping
        maple trees. In the decades following the Corps of Discovery, the leadership of such
        individuals as Flatmouth (pictured here), from the Leech Lake Reservation, helped the 
        <hi rend="italic">anishinaabe</hi>for the most part to coexist peacefully with the United
        States government. The 
        <hi rend="italic">anishinaabe</hi>were placed on reservations scattered across North
        Dakota, Minnesota, Wisconsin, and Michigan and reserves in Canada. Today many of these
        various reservation communities, although struggling economically, are actively involved
        in writing their own histories, protecting treaty rights, and preserving and teaching
        their traditional language and culture. 
        <lb/>
               <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <p>Chippewa head chief Flatmouth, 1897</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>