<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.lc.images_arapaho">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">Texts</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2005</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic
        Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl></bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh">
               <term/>
               <term/>
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-11-18</date>
            <name>Becky Potter</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-04-12</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="main">Arapaho</head>
         <div type="additional">
            <p>When the Corps of Discovery made its way to the Pacific Ocean, the Arapahos lived
        between the Yellowstone and Platte rivers, moving across a large region of what is today
        northern Wyoming and southern Montana. Former planters of corn, the Arapahos by the
        nineteenth century led a more nomadic way of life, being accomplished horse riders,
        hunting buffalo, and living in portable tepees much like the later ones pictured here.
        They were allied with (and related in language and culture to) the Cheyennes, who are
        shown here living with Southern Arapahos on the Washita River in Oklahoma. External
        pressures from settlers, miners, and soldiers helped to divide the Arapahos in the years
        after the Corps of Discovery: the northern Arapahos were resettled to the Wind River
        Reservation in Wyoming while the Southern Arapahos, after fighting, were moved southward
        to the Cheyenne-Arapaho Reservation in western Oklahoma. Both communities survived decades
        of federal government neglect, poverty, sickness, and threats to their traditional way of
        life, and today are dedicated to preserving and revitalizing their language and
        culture.</p>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>
            <table rows="1" cols="5">
               <row role="data">
                  <cell role="desc" rows="1" cols="1">
                     <figure>
                        <p>Arapaho camp, ca. 1870</p>
                     </figure>
                  </cell>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/>
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/>
                  <cell role="desc" rows="1" cols="1">
                     <figure>
                        <p>Arapaho camp, 1868</p>
                     </figure>
                  </cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <table rows="1" cols="1">
               <row role="data">
                  <cell role="desc" rows="1" cols="1">
                     <figure>
                        <p>Cheyennes and Arapahos
                <lb/>at Seger Colony, 1886</p>
                     </figure>
                  </cell>
               </row>
            </table>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>