<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.about.links">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">Links</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2005</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic
        Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl/>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>About</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Links</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07-20</date>
            <date>2008-11-24</date>
            <date>2005-06-17</date>
            <date>2005-06-17</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Old links deleted Old links deleted New links added Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-04-12</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="main">Links</head>
         <div type="additional">
            <p>
               <hi rend="bold">Educational Sites</hi>
               <lb/>
               <lb/>
               <ref target="http://www.lewisandclark200.org/" rend="new">National Lewis &amp; Clark
        Bicentennial Commemoration</ref>
               <lb/>Cartographic, ethnographic, and natural history materials. Includes a complete
        schedule of National signature events as well as recommended links in the areas of
        American Indian nations, trail information, and student and teacher resources. The
        National Council of the Lewis and Clark Bicentennial aims to promote educational programs,
        cultural sensitivity and harmony, and the sustaining stewardship of natural and historical
        resources along the route of the Expedition.
        <lb/>
               <lb/>
               <ref target="http://www.trailtribes.org/" rend="new">Trail Tribes</ref>
               <lb/>Cartographic and ethnographic materials. Produced by the Lifelong Learning Project
        at the University of Montana, a group who works collaboratively with tribes to produce top
        quality, primary resource materials about Native American culture and history. Features
        material on the tribes located along the Lewis and Clark trail route and provides
        information on relevant maps and films.
        <lb/>
               <lb/>
               <ref target="http://www.loc.gov/exhibits/lewisandclark/virtualtour/"
                    rend="new">Rivers,
        Edens, and Empires: Lewis and Clark and the Revealing of America</ref>
               <lb/>Cartographic and ethnographic materials. A virtual tour of the Rivers, Edens, and
        Empires exhibit from the Northwest Gallery of the Library of Congress's Thomas Jefferson
        Building. Draws upon the Library's rich collections of exploration material to feature the
        trek of the Corps of Discovery as a culmination in the quest to connect the East and the
        West by means of a waterway passage. Includes materials related to the Native groups,
        animals, and plants that Lewis and Clark encountered.
        <lb/>
               <lb/>
               <ref target="http://www.pbs.org/lewisandclark/" rend="new">PBS Online: Lewis and
        Clark</ref>
               <lb/>Cartographic and ethnographic materials. Features articles on sixteen Native
        American tribes who had the most interaction with the expedition. Contains audio files
        from a panel of experts offering their responses to various expedition issues. Includes
        lesson plans and an interactive trail map.
        <lb/>
               <lb/>
               <ref target="http://www.lewis-clark.org/" rend="new">Discovering Lewis and Clark</ref>
               <lb/>Cartographic, ethnographic, and natural history materials. Developed by numerous
        individuals with funding from the Montana Committee for the Humanities, Montana Cultural
        Trust, Lee Enterprises, National Endowment for the Humanities, Oregon Council for the
        Humanities, and the National Park Service. Features journal excerpts, natural history
        lessons, aerial photos of the trail, discussions of important issues in the history of the
        American West, and information about modern-day Native American tribes.
        <lb/>
               <lb/>
               <ref target="http://www.mnh.si.edu/lewisandclark" rend="new">Lewis and Clark as
        Naturalists</ref>
               <lb/>Cartographic and natural history materials. The Smithsonian Institution site
        portrays the expedition's interaction with the natural world. Browse by state, species, or
        date collected. Includes lesson plans for elementary through high school students.
        Features an interactive map.
        <lb/>
               <lb/>
               <ref target="http://www.sierraclub.org/lewisandclark/" rend="new">Sierra Club</ref>
               <lb/>Natural history materials. The Sierra Club's Lewis and Clark Campaign Web site helps
        visitors enjoy and protect the lands explored by the expedition. Contains essays,
        photographs, and maps that compare the environment of the expedition with today's world.
        <lb/>
               <lb/>
               <hi rend="bold">Resources for Research</hi>
               <lb/>
               <lb/>
               <ref target="http://www.westernhistoryassociation.org" rend="new">Western History
        Association</ref>
               <lb/>Promotes the study of the American West.
        <lb/>
               <lb/>
               <ref target="http://www.historycooperative.org/home.html" rend="new">History
        Cooperative</ref>
               <lb/>Provides access to history journals, full-text articles, and a discussion board.
        <lb/>
               <lb/>
               <ref target="http://www.lewisandclark.org/?p=proceeded_on&amp;n=publications"
                    rend="new">
                  <hi rend="italic">We Proceeded On</hi>
               </ref>
               <lb/>The official publication of the Lewis and Clark Trail Heritage Foundation, Inc.
        <lb/>
               <lb/>
               <ref target="http://mhs.mt.gov/pub/default.asp" rend="new">
                  <hi rend="italic">Montana The Magazine of Western History</hi>
               </ref>
               <lb/>Information about the Montana Historical Society's publication.
        <lb/>
               <lb/>
               <ref target="http://www.usu.edu/history/whq/" rend="new">
                  <hi rend="italic">The Western Historical Quarterly</hi>
               </ref>
               <lb/>Information about Utah State University's journal.
        <lb/>
               <lb/>
               <ref target="http://gallery.unl.edu/" rend="new">The Gallery of the Open Frontier</ref>
               <lb/>Digital library of images of the American West drawn primarily from the National
        Archives.
        <lb/>
               <lb/>
               <ref target="http://www.archives.gov/" rend="new">U.S. National Archives and Records
        Administration</ref>
               <lb/>Information about the agency that manages all federal records. Includes lesson plans
        based on documents of the expedition.
        <lb/>
               <lb/>
               <ref target="http://www.lewisandclarkpictures.com" rend="new">Lewis and Clark
        Pictures</ref>
               <lb/>A stock image resource dedicated to providing designers, publishers, researchers,
        and the general public with photographs of the Lewis and Clark Trail and subject matter
        related to the Lewis and Clark Expedition.
        <lb/>
               <lb/>
               <hi rend="bold">Travel Sites</hi>
               <lb/>
               <lb/>
               <ref target="http://www.lewisandclark.org/" rend="new">Lewis and Clark Trail Heritage
        Foundation, Inc.</ref>
               <lb/>This foundation—the largest and oldest organization dedicated to Lewis and
        Clark—works to promote the expedition's story and protect the trail.
        <lb/>
               <lb/>
               <ref target="http://www.nps.gov/lecl/" rend="new">Lewis &amp; Clark National Historic
        Trail</ref>
               <lb/>Produced by the National Park Service, this site promotes Lewis and Clark events and
        provides contact information for visitor centers, historic sites, national parks, and
        attractions along the trail. Includes curriculum guides and learning activities for
        children.
        <lb/>
               <lb/>
               <ref target="http://lewisclark.geog.missouri.edu/index.shtml" rend="new">Lewis and Clark
        Historic Landscape Project</ref>
               <lb/>A Web site developed by the University of Missouri's Geographic Resources Center, in
        partnership with the Missouri State Archives and the Office of the Missouri Secretary of
        State with the primary goals to geo-reference, digitize, and map all retrievable
        information from the Lewis and Clark journals and the 18th and 19th century land survey
        notes along the Big River Corridors of the state of Missouri. Contains rich geographic
        material and interactive maps.
        <lb/>
               <lb/>
               <ref target="http://lewisandclarkmo.com" rend="new">Missouri Lewis and Clark Bicentennial
        Commission</ref>
               <lb/>The official site of the Missouri Lewis and Clark Bicentennial Commission. Provides
        information on featured attractions and an interactive map of the expedition trail,
        campsites, and historical markers throughout Missouri. Includes information on a
        curriculum guide for Missouri educators.
        <lb/>
               <lb/>
               <ref target="http://lewisandclark.state.mt.us/" rend="new">Lewis &amp; Clark in
        Montana</ref>
               <lb/>Sponsored by Travel Montana, Department of Commerce, and State of Montana. Features
        an interactive map with points of interest as well as information on accommodations,
        events, and guided tours. Includes children's activities and information on Montana's
        Native American tribes.
        <lb/>
               <lb/>
               <ref target="http://www.lcbo.net/" rend="new">Lewis &amp; Clark Bicentennial in
        Oregon</ref>
               <lb/>Oregon's official Lewis and Clark Bicentennial Web site. Includes a complete
        calendar of Oregon events and classroom resources. Features a detailed map of Oregon sites
        and advice on conducting a self-guided tour.
        <lb/>
               <lb/>
               <ref target="http://www.fortmandan.com/" rend="new">Lewis &amp; Clark Fort Mandan
        Foundation</ref>
               <lb/>Provides visitor information for Fort Mandan and the North Dakota Lewis and Clark
        Interpretive Center. The Corps of Discovery spent the winter of 1804 in this part of North
        Dakota.
        <lb/>
               <lb/>
               <ref target="http://www.lewisandclarkidaho.org/" rend="new">Lewis and Clark in Idaho</ref>
               <lb/>Idaho's official Web site commemorating the Lewis and Clark expedition. Plan a trip
        along the Lewis and Clark trail in Idaho, the homeland of Sacajawea. Includes maps and
        information on the Nez Perce, Lemhi Shoshoni, and Salish tribes.
        <lb/>
               <lb/>
               <ref target="http://www.museumofidaho.org" rend="new">Museum of Idaho</ref>
               <lb/>Beginning October 12, 2004, the Museum of Idaho will be hosting a 2000 sq. ft.
        exhibit, featuring a Lemhi Shoshone village and other Indian and Lewis and Clark items.
        The exhibit will run through 2006.
        <lb/>
               <lb/>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
