<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.lc.advisoryboard">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">Advisory Board</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2005</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic
        Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl></bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh">
               <term/>
               <term/>
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-11-07</date>
            <date>2005-11-18</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>
            <name>Becky Potter</name>Updated content Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-04-12</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="main">Advisory Board</head>
         <div type="additional">
            <p>
               <list type="simple">
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="bold">Dee Ann Allison</hi>(2003-present) is director of Computing Operations
            and Research Services at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln Libraries.
            <lb/>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="bold">Roberta Leigh Conner</hi>(2003-present) is an enrolled member of the
            Confederated Tribes of the Umatilla Indian Reservation-Cayuse, Umatilla, and Nez
            Perce, and director of the Tamastslikt Cultural Institute of the Cayuse, Umatilla, and
            Walla Walla tribes. Conner is a board member of the Wallowa Band Nez Perce Trail
            Interpretive Center and a board member of the National Council of the Lewis and Clark
            Bicentennial. She is co-chair of the Circle of Tribal Advisors of the National Council
            of the Lewis and Clark Bicentennial and a board member of the Oregon Lewis and Clark
            Bicentennial.
            <lb/>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="bold">Kathleen Johnson</hi>(2003-present) is professor and humanities
            librarian at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln, vice-chair of the Literature in
            English section of the Association for College and Research Libraries, and past
            president of the Nebraska Center for the Book, an affiliate of the Center for the Book
            at the Library of Congress.
            <lb/>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="bold">Gary Moulton</hi>(2003-2005), the Thomas C. Sorensen Professor
            Emeritus of American History at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln, is known for his
            work as editor of the award-winning 
            <hi rend="italic">Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition</hi>. Moulton's project
            began in 1979 with support from the UNL Center for Great Plains Studies, the American
            Philosophical Society, and the National Endowment for the Humanities; publication of
            the thirteen-volume set was completed in 1999. Moulton was a consultant for Ken
            Burns's 1997 film, 
            <hi rend="italic">Lewis and Clark: The Journey of the Corps of Discovery</hi>, and
            served as an advisor to the National Geographic Society's IMAX film on Lewis and
            Clark. Moulton served on the U.S. Mint's design selection committee for the one-dollar
            Sacagewea coin in 1998, assisted in the development of the online project pilot site,
            and served on the advisory board from its inception until April 2005.
            <lb/>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="bold">James P. Ronda</hi>(2003-present), the H. G. Barnard Chair in Western
            American History at the University of Tulsa, is past president of the Western History
            Association and author of numerous books, essays, and papers, including 
            <hi rend="italic">Lewis and Clark Among the Indians</hi>(University of Nebraska Press,
            1984; Bicentennial edition, 2003); 
            <hi rend="italic">Jefferson's West: A Journey with Lewis and Clark</hi>(2000); 
            <hi rend="italic">Finding the West: Explorations with Lewis and Clark</hi>(2001); 
            <hi rend="italic">Beyond Lewis and Clark: The Army Explores the West</hi>(2003); and 
            <hi rend="italic">Finding Lewis and Clark: Old Trails, New Directions</hi>(2004).
            Ronda has served as a consultant for many museum projects, such as the Lewis and Clark
            Exploration exhibition at the Library of Congress, and is a member of the board of
            advisors for the National Lewis and Clark Bicentennial Exhibition. In January 2003
            Ronda gave the keynote address at Monticello for the official opening of the National
            Lewis and Clark Bicentennial.
            <lb/>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="bold">James Stubbendieck</hi>(2003-present) is director of the Center for
            Great Plains Studies and professor of grassland ecology at the University of
            Nebraska-Lincoln.
            <lb/>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="bold">Germaine White</hi>(2003-present) is an enrolled member of the
            Confederated Salish and Kootenai Tribes and has served as their information and
            education specialist, public programs manager, education director, and cultural
            specialist. While a member of the Salish-Pend d'Oreille Culture Committee, White
            contributed to the development of the book 
            <hi rend="italic">The Salish People and the Lewis and Clark Expedition</hi>(University
            of Nebraska Press, 2005). She served on the Circle of Tribal Advisors to the National
            Council of the Lewis and Clark Bicentennial and on the Montana Lewis and Clark
            Commission.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>