<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.about.sponsors">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">Sponsors</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2005</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
              <term>About</term>
            </keywords>
           <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
             <term>About the Site</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-06-14</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="main">Sponsors</head>
         <div type="additional">
            <table>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell role="desc" rows="1" cols="1">
                     <figure/>
                  </cell>
                  <cell role="desc" rows="1" cols="1">This website has been made possible in part by a<lb/> major grant from the<ref target="http://www.neh.gov/" rend="new"> National Endowment for the<lb/> Humanities</ref>, promoting excellence in the humanities.




<lb/>
                     <lb/>
Any views, findings, conclusions, or recommendations<lb/>expressed on this website do not necessarily<lb/>represent those of the National Endowment for the<lb/> Humanities.</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <lb/>
            <p>

The <ref target="http://www.nebraskapress.unl.edu/" rend="new">University of Nebraska Press</ref>, founded in 1941, seeks to encourage, develop, publish, and disseminate research, literature, and the publishing arts. The Press is the largest academic publisher in the Great Plains and a major publisher of books about that region.<lb/>
               <lb/>

The purpose of the <ref target="http://www.unl.edu/plains/" rend="new">Center for Great Plains Studies</ref> is to promote a greater understanding of the people, culture, history, and environment of the Great Plains through a variety of research, teaching, and outreach programs.<lb/>
               <lb/>

A joint initiative of the University of Nebraska–Lincoln Libraries and the UNL College of Arts and Sciences, the <ref target="http://cdrh.unl.edu" rend="new">Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</ref> advances collaborative, interdisciplinary research by creating unique digital content, developing text analysis and visualization tools, and encouraging the use and refinement of international standards for humanities computing.<lb/>
               <lb/>

The preparation and publication of the print editions of the <hi rend="italic">Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition</hi> were assisted by grants from the <ref target="http://www.neh.gov/" rend="new">National Endowment for the Humanities</ref> and private donations from individuals.


</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
