<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-06-20">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">June 20, 1805</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic
        Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            4</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">April7–July 27, 1805</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1987</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">317-321</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">170-171</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">104</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jw">Joseph Whitehouse</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            11</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of Joseph Whitehouse, May 14, 1804–April 2,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1997</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">204-206</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journal Entries</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-02-04</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-04-12</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1805-06-20">June 20, 1805</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-06-20.01" ref="">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Thursday June 20th 1805.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>This morning we had but little to do; waiting the return of 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name>; I am apprehensive from his
          stay that the portage is longer than we had calculated on. I sent out 4 hunters this
          morning on the opposite side of the river to kill buffaloe; the country being more
          broken on that side and cut with ravenes they can get within shoot of the buffaloe with
          more ease and certainty than on this side of the river.    my object is if
          possible while we have now but little to do, to lay in a large stock of dryed meat at
          this end of the portage to subsist the party while engaged in the transportation of our
          baggage &amp;c, to the end, that they may not be taken from this duty when once
          commenced in order to surch for the necessary subsistence. 
          <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">The Indian woman</name>is qute free from pain and
          fever this morning and appears to be in a fair way for recovery, she has been walking
          about and fishing. In the evening 2 of the hunters returned and informed me that they
          had killed eleven buffaloe eight of which were in very fine order, I sent off all hands
          immediately to bring in the meat    they soon returned with about half of the
          best meat leaving three men to remain all night in order to secure the ballance.
             the buffaloe are in immence numbers, they have been constantly coming down
          in large herds to water opposite to us for some hours sometimes two or three herds
          wartering at the same instant and scarcely disappear before others supply their places.
             they appear to make great use of the mineral water, whether this be owing
          to it's being more convenient to them than the river or that they actually prefer it I
          am at a loss to determine for they do not use it invaryably, but sometimes pass at no
          great distance from it and water at the river.    brackish water or that of a
          dark colour impregnated with mineral salts such as I have frequenly mentioned on the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>is found in small quantities in
          some of the steep ravenes on the N. side of the river opposite to us and 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">the falls</name>. 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name>and party returned late this
          evening when he gave me the following relation of his rout and the occurrences which had
          taken place with them since their departure.
          <ref target="n15062001" n="1"/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name>now furnished me with the
          field notes of the survey which he had made of the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>and it's Cataracts cascades
          &amp;c. from the entrance of 
          <name type="place" key="Belt (Portage) Creek">portage Creek</name>to the South
          Eastwardly bend of the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>above the 
          <name type="place" key="White Bear Islands">White bear Islands</name>, which are as
          follow.
          <ref target="n15062002" n="2"/>
               </p>
               <p>June 20th 1805    At our camp below the entrance of 
          <name type="place" key="Belt (Portage) Creek">portage creek</name>observed Meridian
          Altd. of 
          <seg n="u9737">☉</seg>'s L. L. with Octant by the back Observtn. 53° 10'</p>
               <p>Latitude deduced from this observation 47° 7' 10.3"</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-06-20.02" ref="">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">June 20th Thursday 1805</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>a Cloudy morning, a hard wind all night and this morning, I direct Stakes to be Cut
          to Stick up in the prarie to Show the way for the party to transport the baggage &amp;c.
          &amp;c.    we Set out early on the portage, Soon after we Set out it began to
          rain and continued a Short time    we proceeded on thro' a tolerable leavel
          plain, and found the hollow of a Deep rivein to obstruct our rout as it Could not be
          passed with Canos &amp; baggage for Some distance above the place we Struck it
             I examined it for Some time and finding it late deturmined to Strike the
          river &amp; take its Course &amp; distance to Camp which I accordingly did   
          the wind hard from the S. W.    a fair after noon, the river on both Sides Cut
          with raveins Some of which is passes thro Steep Clifts into the river, the Countrey
          above 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">the falls</name>&amp; up the
          
          <name type="place" key="Sun (Mah-pah-pah,-ah-zhah, Medicine) River">Medison
          river</name>is leavel, with low banks, a chain of mountains to the west Some part of
          which particuler those to the N W. &amp; S W are Covered with Snow and appear verry
          high—    I Saw a rattle Snake in an open plain 2 miles from any Creek or wood.
          When I arrived at Camp found all well with great quantites of meet, the Canoes 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name>had Carried up the Creek 1
          ¾ 〈of an〉 mile to a good place to assend the band &amp; taken up. Not haveing Seen
          <ref target="n15062003" n="3"/>the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Snake</name>Indians or knowing in fact
          whither to Calculate on their friendship or hostillity, we have Conceived our party
          Sufficiently Small, and therefore have Concluded not to dispatch a Canoe with a part of
          our men to 
          <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>as we have intended early in
          the Spring.    we fear also that Such a measure might also discourage those
          who would in Such Case remain, and migh possibly hazard the fate of the expedition.
             we have never hinted to anyone of the party that we had Such a Scheem in
          contemplation, and all appear perfectly to have made up their minds, to Succeed in the
          expedition or perish in the attempt.    we all believe that we are about to
          enter on the most perilous and dificuelt part of our Voyage, yet I See no one repineing;
          all appear ready to meet those dificuelties which await us with resolution and becomeing
          fortitude.</p>
               <p>We had a heavy dew this morning.    the Clouds near those mountains rise
          Suddonly and discharge their Contents partially on the neighbouring Plains; the Same
          Cloud discharge hail alone in one part, hail and rain in another and rain only in a
          third all within the Space of a fiew Miles; and on the Mountains to the South &amp; S.
          E. of us Sometimes Snow.    at present there is no Snow on those mountains;
          that which covered them a fiew days ago has all disappeared.    the Mountains
          to the N. W. and West of us are Still entirely Covered are white and glitter with the
          reflection of the Sun.</p>
               <p>I do not believe that the Clouds that pervale at this Season of the year reach the
          Summits of those lofty mountains; and if they do the probabillty is that they deposit
          Snow only for there has been no proceptable diminution of the Snow which they Contain
          Since we first Saw them. I have thought it probable that these mountains might have
          derived their appellation of 
          <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Shineing Mountains</name>
                  </hi>, from their glittering appearance when the Sun Shines in certain directions on the
          Snow which Cover them.</p>
               <p>Dureing the time of my being on the Plains and above the falls I as also all my party
          repeatedly heard a nois which proceeded from a Direction a little to the N. of West, as
          loud and resembling precisely the discharge of a piece of ordinance of 6 pounds at the
          distance of 5 or six miles.
          <ref target="n15062004" n="4"/>I was informed of it Several times by the men 
          <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">J. Fields</name>particularly before I paid any
          attention to it, thinking it was thunder most probably which they had mistaken.
             at length walking in the plains yesterday near the most extreem S. E. bend
          of the River above 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">the falls</name>I heard this
          
          <hi rend="italic">nois</hi>very distinctly, it was perfectly calm clear and not a Cloud
          to be Seen, I halted and listened attentively about two hour dureing which time I heard
          two other discharges, and took the direction of the Sound with my pocket Compass which
          was as nearly West from me as I could estimate from the Sound. I have no doubt but if I
          had leasure I could find from whence it issued. I have thought it probable that it might
          be caused by running water in Some of the caverns of those emence mountains, on the
          principal of the 
          <name type="place" key="Blowing Cave">blowing caverns</name>;
          <ref target="n15062005" n="5"/>but in Such case the Sounds would be periodical and
          regular, which is not the Case with this, being Sometimes heard once only and at other
          times Several discharges in quick Succession.    it is heard also at different
          times of the day and night. I am at a great loss to account for this Phenomenon. I well
          recollect hereing the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Minitarees</name>Say that those 
          <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky Mountains</name>make a great noise, but
          they could not tell me the Cause, neither Could they inform me of any remarkable
          substance or situation in these mountains which would autherise a conjecture of a
          probable cause of this noise—.    it is probable that the large river just
          above those 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">Great falls</name>which
          heads in the derection of the noise has taken it's name 
          <name type="place" key="Sun (Mah-pah-pah,-ah-zhah, Medicine) River">Medicine
          River</name>from this unaccountable rumbling Sound, which like all unacountable thing
          with the Indians of the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>is Called 
          <name type="place" key="Sun (Mah-pah-pah,-ah-zhah, Medicine) River">Medicine</name>.</p>
               <p>The 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Ricaras</name>inform us of the 
          <name type="place" key="Black Hills">black mountains</name>making a Simalar noise
          &amp;c. &amp;c. and maney other wonderfull tales of those 
          <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky mountains</name>and those 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">great falls</name>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="right">June 20th
            <ref target="n15062006" n="6"/>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>at our Camp below the enterance of 
          <name type="place" key="Belt (Portage) Creek">Portage River</name>observed Meridian
          altitude of 
          <seg n="u9737">☉</seg>s L. L. with Octant by the back observation    53° 10'
          0"</p>
               <p>Latitude deduced from the observation 47° 7' 10" 3/10</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-06-20.03" ref="">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Thursday 20th June 1805</hi>. Some cloudy &amp; cold for the Season.
             the wind continues high from the west off the mountains.    4 men
          Sent across the river to hunt.    a light Sprinkling of rain about noon
             we are now waiting the arival of 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name>.    late in the
          afternoon 2 of the hunters Came in and informed us that they had got 11 buffalow killed
          &amp; the most of them fat. the other 2 Stayed to butcher.    all hands in
          Camp turned out for the meat, &amp; brought about the half of what was fat   
          3 men Stayed all night to dress the remainder.    verry large gangs all around
          the place within Shot of the butchers &amp;C.    a light Sprinkling of rain.
             late in the evening 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name>and party returned to Camp
             they informed us that they traversed &amp; measured the River and falls, as
          they went up.    measured all the Small or little falls which were common
          &amp; of different hites.    the highest catteract or falls is 87 feet
          perpinticular.    the next highest 47 feet 8 Ich    the next or 3rd
          about 30 or upwards.    a nomber of Small ones &amp; a continued rapid the
          whole way for 17 miles to where we can take water again. those large falls all have a
          mist which rises about 200 yards from the Shoot.    about a mile above the
          falls of 47 feet, 8 Inches, the largest fountan or Spring
          <ref target="n15062007" n="7"/>falls in that we ever Saw before and it is the oppinion
          of 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name>that it is the largest Spring
          in america known.    this water boils up from under the rocks near the River
          &amp; falls immediately in to the river 8 feet &amp; keeps its colour for ½ a mile,
          which is verry clear and of a blueish cast&amp;c — two of 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clarks</name>party was attacted by a
          large white bear on an Island
          <ref target="n15062008" n="8"/>near where they had camped one night.    one
          of them 
          <name type="person" key="Willard, Alexander">A. Willard</name>like to have been caught.
             the other chased in the water after 
          <name type="person" key="Willard, Alexander">Willard</name>made his ascape towards camp.
          
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name>and 3 others went to their
          assistance.    the bear ratreated.    night came on    the
          bushes thick.    So they did not kill him, they Saw but little timber.
             the country up the 
          <name type="place" key="Sun (Mah-pah-pah,-ah-zhah, Medicine) River">medicine
          River</name>above 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">the falls</name>is level
          with low banks.    they Saw a chain of Mountains
          <ref target="n15062009" n="9"/>to the west Some of which perticular those to the N. W.
          and S. W. are covered with Snow, and appear to be verry high.    they turned
          back in order to look out the levelest way for the portage. 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name>lost a part of his notes
          which could not be found. 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name>Saw a rattle Snake out in the
          plains a long distance from timber or water.    they Saw verry large
          innumerable quantyties of buffalow while they were gone.    they killed 7
          buffalow &amp; Saved as much of the meat as possable. killed a beaver also,</p>
               <p>they Saw buffalow attempt to Swim the River above the falls. Some of which was Sucked
          over and Seen no more.    great numbers of those animels are lost in these
          falls which is the cause of our Seeing So many below for a long distance washed up on
          Shore. Some make the Shore above the falls half drowned.—</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-06-20.04" ref="">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Thursday 20th.</hi>   A cloudy morning: four hunters went
          out to kill some fat buffaloe. About 4 o'clock one of them came in for men to carry the
          meat to camp; as they had 14 down ready to butcher. We went out about a mile and an
          half, and brought in a load, leaving three men to dress the rest. 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain Clarke</name>and his party returned,
          having found a tolerable good road except where some draughts crossed it. They had left
          their blankets and provision at the place where they expect we will again embark.
          <ref target="n15062010" n="10"/>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-06-20.05" ref="">
            <sp who="jw">
               <speaker>Whitehouse</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Thursday 20th June 1805</hi>.    Some cloudy &amp; cold.
             the wind continues high from the west.    three or 4 men went
          across the River to hunt &amp;c.    we lay at Camp at the commencement of the
          carrying place, to wait the arival of 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name>&amp; party.    a
          light Squall of rain about noon.    in the afternoon 〈the〉 Some of the hunters
          came in had killed 11 buffalow the most of them verry fat.    all hands turned
          out after the meat, but could not fetch more than half of what was fat.    3
          men Stayed all night to butcher the remainder of the buffalow, which lay dead.
             Saw large gangs come about close to the men which was dressing the meat
          &amp;c—    a little rain.</p>
               <p>in the evening 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name>&amp; party returned.
             they informed us that they traversed the River going up &amp; measured 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">the falls</name>&amp; river
          found the first to be about 30 feet the highest &amp; middle 87 feet the upper one a 45
          feet all of which is perpinticular, a continued rapids between each other.
          <ref target="n15062011" n="11"/>   they found it to be 17 miles to the head
          to where we can take water again.    two men was attacted by a verry large
          White bear one of them 
          <name type="person" key="Willard, Alexander">A Willard</name>near being caught.
             
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name>went &amp; relieved them
          &amp; 3 men with him.    but night comming on &amp; the bushes thick it being
          on an Island they did not kill it.    they Saw 1 or 2 other white bear.
             they Saw also innumerable gangs of buffalow &amp; killed 8 of those
          animels, &amp; one beaver.    they Saved as much of the buffalow meat as
          possable.    〈one mile above〉 1 mile above the fall of 47 feet 8 Inches is the
          largest fountain or Spring, as they think is the largest in america known.   
          this water boils up from under the rocks near the river &amp; falls immediately into the
          river 8 feet &amp; keeps its coulour for ½ a mile which is clear &amp; of a blueish
          cast.    they inform us that their is many Shoots or little falls between the
          high ones.    the large catteract or falls
          <ref target="n15062012" n="12"/>is a large mist quite across the fall, for a long
          distance from them.    
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name>Saw rattle Snakes but Saw
          verry little timber.    they turned back this morning in order to look out the
          best &amp; Smoothest portage possable to take the canoes &amp; baggage &amp;. up to the 
          <name type="place" key="Sun (Mah-pah-pah,-ah-zhah, Medicine) River">medicine
          River</name>.    they informed us that the Country above the falls &amp; up
          the 
          <name type="place" key="Sun (Mah-pah-pah,-ah-zhah, Medicine) River">meddicine
          River</name>is level with low banks &amp; Smoth water.    they Saw a chain of
          mountains to the west, Some of which particular those to N. W. &amp; S. W. are covered
          with Snow, &amp; appear to be verry high.    
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name>lost a part of his notes
          which could not be found, as the wind blew high &amp; took them off.    they
          did not look out &amp; marke the road for the baggage &amp;c much more than half way
          down to Camp it being too late to go round the deep gulleys &amp;c.    
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name>Saw gangs of buffalow attempt
          to Swim the river abo. 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">the falls</name>.
             Some went over.</p>
               <p>Thursday June 20th    This morning we had Cloudy weather, and cold; and the
          wind continued high from the West, four of our Men were sent across the River to hunt,
          We now lay at Camp, at the commencement of the carrying place, waiting the arrival of 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain Clark</name>&amp; party.—   
          We had about noon some Squalls of wind, attended with Rain.—    In the
          afternoon some of our Hunters returned to us; and had killed 11 Buffalo, the most of
          them, they said were very fat, all our spare hands turned out, in Order to bring the
          Meat to our Camp.—    they returned, and had brought with them but above one
          half of it and that was very fat—    Three of the party that went after the
          meat, staid all night, to butcher the remainder of the buffalo, that the hunters had
          killed, the party that was sent for the meat mentioned that large Gangs of Buffalo came
          about close to the Men, who were employ'd dressing the Meat, &amp; that they appeared no
          ways shy of them.—    We had small Showers of rain this afternoon.—
             In the evening 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain Clarke</name>and his party returned to
          us, they informed us, that they had travers'd this small river, in going up; and had
          measured the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">falls—of the Mesouri</name>,
          of which there was three.—    the first falls being 30 feet high by
          measurement, the second or middle fall, being the highest 87 feet perpendicular, and the
          third fall 47 feet 8 Inches also perpendicular, and the Water running exceedingly Rapid,
          between each of these falls, and found the distance to be 17 Miles to the head fall,
          where we expect to proceed on again with our Crafts, &amp; take Water.—</p>
               <p>The party that was with 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain Clark</name>, mentioned, that two of
          their Men were attackted by a very large white or brown coloured bear, and that one of
          them had nearly been caught by that huge animal, &amp; that it certainly had been the
          case, had not 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain Clark</name>and three of the party
          releived him, but night coming on, the Bear made his escape among some very thick
          bushes, and got off from them, this happened on an Island—    They also
          mentioned of having Seen also two more very large 〈white〉 Bear of the same kind, and saw
          innumerable large Gangs of Buffalo in every direction, as far as their sight extended,
          they had killed 8 of them, and One beaver, they saved as much of the buffalo meat, as
          possible, they also mentioned that one Mile above the fall of 47 feet 8 Inches, is the
          largest fountain or spring, they had ever seen, and that they beleived it, to be the
          largest, in America that was known; this spring boils up from under the Rocks near the
          River, and falls immediately into it 8 feet 3 Inches, and keeps it colour for half a
          Mile in the River, which is Clear &amp; of a blueish colour, and mention'd that there
          was many Shoots or little falls of water, which lay between the large falls, and at
          where the Cataracts or large falls lay, that a large mists was quite across them and
          that it was the same a great distance below each of them.—    
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain Clark</name>mention'd that on his route
          he had seen a number of Rattle Snakes, and but little timber,—</p>
               <p>The party under 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain Clark</name>, had left 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">the falls</name>this
          morning, and had returned back, in order to look out for the best and smoothest Portage,
          for us to Convey the Crafts and baggage up to the head of 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">the falls</name>on the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Mesouri River</name>, they mentioned that the
          Country above the falls, and up the 
          <name type="place" key="Sun (Mah-pah-pah,-ah-zhah, Medicine) River">Medecine
          River</name>is level, with low banks, &amp; smooth Water.—    They saw a chain
          of mountains lying to the West, and some laying to the North West and South West; 〈both〉
          all of which chains of mountains appear'd to them to be covered with snow, and lay very
          high, 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain Clark</name>had lost part of the notes
          that he had taken which could not be found the Wind blowing hard, had taken them off.—
             they had not marked the road, above half the way down to our Camp; it being
          too late to go round the deep Gullys.—    The party mentioned of having seen
          Gangs of buffalo swimming the River above 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">the falls</name>, some of
          which from the Rapidity of the current, was washed down over them, We remained still at
          our encampment, preparing every thing necessary in Order to assend to the head of
          Portage.—</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n15062001" n="1">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>gives 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>narrative of his survey. It is not
        repeated here being a copy of the material from Voorhis No. 1.</note>
            <note xml:id="n15062002" n="2">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>repeats 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>survey as found in Voorhis No. 1
        with only slight variations; it is not included here.</note>
            <note xml:id="n15062003" n="3">Here 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>writes "Continues 10 pages back," a
        reference to the material written in the midst of the entry of June 17, 1805. The material
        is dated June 20 but is copied in fact from 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>entries of July 4 and 11. See
        further explanation at 
        <ref n="1805-06-17" type="related">June 17</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n15062004" n="4">This description largely follows that of 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>for 
        <ref n="1805-07-04" type="related">July 4, 1805</ref>. Apparently the captains never did
        find an explanation for the phenomenon, which is still heard today in the region. Biddle
        later suggested to 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>that the sound was that of an
        avalanche. A "piece of ordinance of 6 pounds" would be a cannon firing six-pound iron
        balls. 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>to 
        <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>, December 20, 1810, Jackson
        (LLC), 2:565; Wheeler, 1:337–38; Willard, 13.</note>
            <note xml:id="n15062005" n="5">The 
        <name type="place" key="Blowing Cave">Blowing Cave</name>, in 
        <name type="place" key="Bath County, Virg.">Bath County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Virginia">Virginia</name>, constantly emitted a strong current of
        air. 
        <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, 24; 
        <hi rend="italic">Virginia Guide</hi>, 512.</note>
            <note xml:id="n15062006" n="6">This observation appears with 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>
               <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">Great Falls</name>survey notes
        dated 
        <ref n="1805-06-17-19" type="related">June 17–19, 1805</ref>. It is placed by its own
        date.</note>
            <note xml:id="n15062007" n="7">
               <name type="place" key="Giant Springs">Giant Springs</name>, now located in a park
        northeast of the city of 
        <name type="place" key="Great Falls, Mont.">Great Falls</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Cascade County, Mont.">Cascade County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n15062008" n="8">The party's 
        <name type="place" key="White Bear Islands">White Bear Islands</name>, since nearly
        disappeared, a short distance north of 
        <name type="place" key="Sand Coulee Creek (Flattery Run)">Sand Coulee Creek</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Cascade County, Mont.">Cascade County</name>. It became the 
        <name type="place" key="Upper portage camp (Mont.)">upper portage camp</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n15062009" n="9">Probably the 
        <name type="place" key="Lewis (Snowy) Range">Lewis Range</name>and the main 
        <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rockies</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n15062010" n="10">At the 
        <name type="place" key="Upper portage camp (Mont.)">upper portage camp</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Cascade County, Mont.">Cascade County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>, on the 
        <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>about three-quarters of a mile
        north of 
        <name type="place" key="Sand Coulee Creek (Flattery Run)">Sand Coulee Creek.</name>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="n15062011" n="11">See 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>survey notes of 
        <ref n="1805-06-17-19" type="related">June 17–19, 1805</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n15062012" n="12">The 
        <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">Great Falls of the Missouri
        River</name>, in 
        <name type="place" key="Cascade County, Mont.">Cascade County</name>, now much reduced by 
        <name type="place" key="Ryan Dam">Ryan Dam</name>.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-06-17-19" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-06-21" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
