<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-04-20">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
April 20, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               
               
               
               
               
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml" n="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc" n="Clark, William">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 7</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">March 23–June 9, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1991</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">145-151</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo" n="Ordway, John">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf" n="Floyd, Charles">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">294-295</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg" n="Gass, Patrick">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">213</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Journal Entries</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-10-05</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1806-04-20">April 20, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-04-20.01" n="">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Sunday April 20th 1806.</hi>
                     <ref target="n32042001" n="1"/>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
some frost this morning. The <name type="native_nation" key="Tenino Indians">Enesher</name> an <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skillutes</name> are much better clad than they were last fall, there men have generally legings mockersons and large robes; many of them wear shirts of the same form with those of the <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshone</name>
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Chopunnish</name> &amp;c highly ornamented with porcupine quills.    the dress of their women differs very little from those of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Cascades (Great Rapids, Great Shute)">great rapids</name> and above.    their children frequently wear robes of the large grey squirrel skins, those of the men and women are principally deer skins, some wolf,<ref target="n32042002" n="2"/> elk, bighorn and buffaloe; the latter they procure from the nations who sometimes visit the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>.    indeed a considerable proportion of their wearing apparel is purchased from their neighbours to the N. W. in exchange for pounded fish copper and beads.    at present the principal village of the <name type="native_nation" key="Tenino Indians">Eneshur</name> is below <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Great Falls of the">the falls</name> on the N. side of the river.    one other village is above <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Great Falls of the">the falls</name> on the S. side and another a few miles above on the N. side.    the first consists of 19, the 2cd of 11, and the 3rd of 5 lodges.    their houses like those of the <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skillutes</name> have their floors on the surface of the ground, but are formed of sticks and covered with mats and straw.    they are large and contain usually several families each.<ref target="n32042003" n="3"/>    for fuel they use straw, small willows and the southern wood.<ref target="n32042004" n="4"/>    they use the silk grass in manufacturing their fishing nets and bags, the bear grass and cedar bark are employed in forming a variety of articles.    they are poor, dirty, proud, haughty, inhospitable, parsimonious and faithless in every rispect, nothing but our numbers I beleive prevents their attempting to murder us at this moment.—</p>
               <p>
This morning I was informed that the natives had pilfered six tomahawks and a knife from the party in the course of the last night. I spoke to the cheif on this subject.    he appeared angry with his people and addressed them but the property was not restored.    one horse which I had purchased and paid for yesterday and which could not be found when I ordered the horses into close confinement yesterday I was now informed had been gambled away by the rascal who had sold it to me and had been taken away by a man of another nation. I therefore took the goods back from this fellow. I purchased a gun from the cheif for which I gave him 2 Elkskins.    in the course of the day I obtained two other indifferent horses for which I gave an extravigant price. I found that I should get no more horses and therefore resolved to proceed tomorrow morning with those which I had and to convey the baggage in two small canoes that the horses could not carry.    for his purpose I had a load made up for seven horses, the eighth <name type="person" key="Bratton, William E.">Bratton</name> was compelled to ride as he was yet unable to walk. I barted my Elksins old irons<ref target="n32042005" n="5"/> and 2 canoes for beads.    one of the canoes for which they would give us but little I had cut up for fuel. These people have yet a large quantity of dryed fish on hand yet they will not let us have any but for an exorbitant price.    we purchased two dogs and some shappellel from them. I had the horses graized untill evening and then picquited and hubbled within the limited of our camp. I ordered the indians from our camp this evening and informed them that if I caught them attempting to perloin any article from us I would beat them severely.    they went off in reather a bad humour and I directed the party to examine their arms and be on their guard.    they stole two spoons from us in the course of the day. The <name type="native_nation" key="Klickitat Indians">Scaddals</name>, <name type="native_nation" key="Klickitat Indians">Squan-nan-os</name>, <name type="native_nation" key="Klickitat Indians">Shan-wah-pums</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Klickitat Indians">Shallattas</name>
                  <ref target="n32042006" n="6"/> reside to the N. W. of these people, depend on hunting deer and Elk and trade with these people for their pounded fish.
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-04-20.02" n="">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">April 20th 1806</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
This morning very Cold hills covered with Snow. I Showed the nativs what I had to give for their horses and attempted to purchase them.    they informed me that they would not Sell any horses to me, that their horses were at a long ways off and they would not trade them.    my offer was a blue rope, Callico Shirt, a handkerchef, 5 parcels of paint a Knife, a wampom moon<ref target="n32042007" n="7"/> 4 braces of ribin, a pice of Brass and about 6 braces of yellow beeds; and to that amount for what I had I also offered my large blue blanket for one, my Coat Sword &amp; Plume none of which Seem to entice those peple to give horses if they had any.    they Set in their huts which is of mats Supported on poles without fire.    at night when they wish a light they burn dry Straw &amp; Some fiew Small dry willows.    they Speak defferent from those below, have but little to eate. Some roots &amp; Dryed fish is to be found in their houses. I am half frozed at this inhospitable Village which is moved from its position above <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Great Falls of the">the falls</name> to one below and Contains 19 large houses, a village is also established on the other Side imedeately above <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Great Falls of the">the falls</name>.    all the natives who was established above <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Great Falls of the">the Falls</name> for Some distance has removed</p>
               <p>
Those people are much better dressed than they were at the time we went down the river. They have all new, Deer, Elk, Ibex Goat &amp; wolf Skin robes, their Children also the large squirel Skin robes, maney of them have Legins and mockersons, all of which they precure of the Indians at a distance in exchange for their pounded fish &amp; Beeds, they also purchase Silk grass, of which they make their nets &amp; Sales for takeing fish    they also purchase Bear grass and maney other things for their fish.    those people gave me roots and berries prepared in different ways for which I gave some Small articles in return.—Great numbers of Skiming knets on their houses. Those people are Pore and Kind durty &amp; indolt. They ware their hair loose flowing the men cut in the foward which the <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skilloots</name>
                  </hi> do not &amp;c. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
I could not precure a Single horse of those people, dureing this day at any price, they offered me 2 for 2 kittles of which we Could not spear. I used every artifice decent &amp; even false Statements to enduce those pore devils to Sell me horses.    in the evening two different men offered to Sell me three horses which they informed me was a little distance off and they would bring them imediately.    those two persons as I found went imediately off up the river to their tribe without any intention to find or Sell their horses.    a little before Sunset 3 men arived from Some distance above and informed me that they Came to See me.    at Sunset finding no probability of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt Lewis</name> arival, packed up the articles and took them into the lodge in which I lay last night. Great numbers of those people geathered around me to Smoke. I gave them 2 pipes and lay down in the back part of the house with <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Sgt. P.</name> &amp; the men with our arms in a Situation as to be ready in case of any alarm.    those pore people appear entirely harmless—    I purchased a dog and Some wood with a little pounded fish and Chappaless.    made a fire on the rocks and Cooked the dogs on which the men breckfast &amp; Dined.    wind hard all day cold from N W.
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-04-20.03" n="">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Sunday 20th April 1806</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
a very cold morning the western mountains Covered with Snow    I Shewed the <name type="native_nation" key="Tenino Indians">Eneshers</name> the articles I had to give for their horses.    they without hezitation informed me that they would not Sell me any for the articles I had, if I would give them Kittles they would let me have horses, and not without.    that their horses were at a long ways off in the planes and they would not Send for them &amp;c.    my offered was a blue robe, a Calleco Shirt, a Silk handkerchief, 5 parcels of paint, a knife, a Wampom moon, 8 yards of ribon, Several pieces of Brass, a mockerson awl and 6 braces of yellow beeds; and to that amount for each horse which is more than double what we gave either the <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Sohsohne</name> or first flat heads we met with on <name type="person" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">Clarks river</name>
                  <ref target="n32042008" n="8"/> I also offered my large blue blanket, my Coat Sword &amp; plume none of which Seamed to entice those people to Sell their horses.    not with standing every exertion not a Single horse Could be precured of those people in the Course of the day. Those people are much better Clad than they were last fall, their men have generally legins mockersons and large robes.    maney of them ware Shirts of the Same forom of those of the <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Chopunnish</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshone</name> highly ornimented with porcupine quills.    the dress of their winen differse verry little from those above the <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Cascades (Great Rapids, Great Shute)">great rapids</name>.    their Children have Small robes of the Squirel Skins.    those of the men &amp; women are principally deer, Some elk, wolf, Ibix &amp; buffalow which they precure from distance nations who purchase their Pounded fish in exchange for those robes &amp; Beeds. The principal village of the <name type="native_nation" key="Tenino Indians">Enesher</name> nation is imedeately below <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Great Falls of the">the falls</name> on the N. Side. one other village of the Same nation above <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Great Falls of the">the falls</name> on the opposit Side and one other a few miles above on the North Side.—    The Houses of those people like the <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skillutes</name> have the flores of their Summer dwelling on the Surface of the earth in Sted of those Sellers in which they resided when we passed them last fall.    those houses are Covered with mats and Straw are large and Contain Several families each. I counted 19 at this Village &amp; 11 on the opposit Side.    those people are pore durty haughty. they burn Straw and Small willows.    have but little to eate and deer with what they have.    they precure the Silk grass of which they make their nets, the bear grass for makeing their mats and Several other necessary of the Indians of the following nations who trade with them as also the <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skillutes</name> for their pounded fish. Viz. <name type="native_nation" key="Klickitat Indians">Skad-dats</name>, <name type="native_nation" key="Klickitat Indians">Squan-nun-os</name>, <name type="native_nation" key="Klickitat Indians">Shan-wap-poms</name>, <name type="native_nation" key="Klickitat Indians">Shall-lat-tos</name>, who reside to the north and Several bands who reside on the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> above.—    I precured a Sketch of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> and its branches of those people in which they made the river which <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Great Falls of the">falls into the Columbia</name> imediately above <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Great Falls of the">the falls</name> on the South Side to branch out into 3 branches one of which they make head in <name type="person" key="Mount Jefferson">Mt. Jefferson</name>, one in <name type="place" key="Mount Hood (Timm, Falls Mountain)">mount Hood</name> and the other in the S W. range of Mountains<ref target="n32042009" n="9"/> and does not water that extensive Country we have heretofore Calculated on.    a great portion of that extensive tract of Country to the S. and S. W. of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> and <name type="place"
                        key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Lewis's river</name> and between the Same and the <name type="place" key="Gulf of California">waters of Callifornia</name> must be watered by the <name type="place" key="Willamette (Multnomah) River">
                     <hi rend="italic">Multnomah</hi> river</name>.—    See <hi rend="italic">Sketch</hi> in the latter part of this book (No. 5).<ref target="n32042010" n="10"/> Those people are great jokies<ref target="n32042011" n="11"/> and deciptfull in trade.</p>
               <p>
at Sunset finding that <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt Lewis</name> would not arrive this evening as I expected, I packed up all the articles which I had exposed, at a Situation I had pitched on to Encamp, and at which place we had bought as maney fishing poles as made a fire to Cook a dog which I had purchased for the men to eate, and returned to the lodge which I had Slept in last night. great number gathered around me to Smoke, I gave them two pipes, and then lay my self down with the men to Sleep, haveing our merchendize under our heads and guns &amp;c in our arms, as we always have in Similar Situations</p>
               <p>
                  <figure rend="mhs">
                     <p>Confluence of <name type="place"
                              key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Snake</name> and <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>s and Environs, ca. April 18–20, 1806,<lb/>
Voorhis No. 3
<bibl>
                           <orgName>Missouri Historical Society</orgName>
                        </bibl>
                     </p>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-04-20.04" n="">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Sunday 20th of April 1806.    a clear cold morning. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name> went to tradeing for horses &amp;C. Several of our men went out to hunt their horses but could not find all of them    we expect the Indians loosed their Spanil<ref target="n32042012" n="12"/> and took them away expecting a reward to git them again. So we hired the Indians to hunt them.    found all except one who the man we bought him of Gambled him away with Some of an other nation &amp; they had taken him away.    all the Indians we have Seen play a game &amp; risque all the property they have at different games.    the game<ref target="n32042013" n="13"/> that these Savages play is by setting in a circle &amp; have a Small Smooth bone in their hands &amp; Sing crossing their hands to fix it in a hidden manner from the other Side who gass the hand that has it in then counts one    a Stick Stuck in the ground for tallies &amp; So on untill one Side or the other wins the propertey Stacked up.    this game is played with activity, and they appear merry &amp; peaceable. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name> took the property from the man that gambled away our horse.    we Sold old Robes Elk Skins &amp;C.    &amp;C. for white beeds.    these Savages have but little pounded Salmon in their village as they trade it to Several other nations &amp;C.    the Indians would not give us any thing worth mentioning for our canoes So we Split &amp; burnt one of them this evening.    we tyed up our horses &amp;C.    we bought 2 more dogs &amp; Some chappalell &amp;c


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-04-20.05" n="">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Sunday 20th.</hi>    This was a pleasant morning with some white frost. We got two more horses and lost one; remained here all day and had a great deal of trouble with our horses, as they are all studs, and break almost every rope we can raise. We had to tie them up at night, and one broke away notwithstanding all our care and attention. We have also much trouble with the Indians as they are disposed to steal whenever they have an opportunity. With all our care they stole 4 or 5 tomahawks.

</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n32042001" n="1">Following the date for this entry in Codex K it was apparently <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name> who wrote, "(see end of this book)." At the end of Codex K is the table of weather observations for April 1806, in which, under the remarks for April 20 is a long paragraph headed "<hi rend="italic">for the journal of this date</hi>" (in <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> hand) with a pointing hand. It consists of a description of the "<name type="native_nation" key="Tenino Indians">Enesher</name>" and "<name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skillutes</name>." It is the beginning paragraph of this entry.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32042002" n="2">Probably the gray wolf, <hi rend="italic">Canis lupus.</hi>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="n32042003" n="3">This may be the <name type="place" key="Sk!in village">Sk!in village</name> according to Spier (TDW), 19. The houses at this village were mat lodges as typically constructed by <name type="place" key="Columbia Plateau">Columbia Plateau</name> peoples. Ray (CRP), 137–40; Ray (CDP), 174–77.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32042004" n="4">Big, or common, sagebrush, <hi rend="italic">Artemisia tridentata</hi> Nutt. Hitchcock et al., 5:70; Cutright (LCPN), 403.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32042005" n="5">No doubt mostly broken pieces of iron equipment that the Indians could make into weapons or tools. This may explain how <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> branding iron came to be found in this vicinity years later; see <ref n="1805-10-05" type="related">October 5, 1805</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32042006" n="6">These four groups were apparently divisions of the <name type="native_nation" key="Klickitat Indians">Klickitat Indians</name>. In the <ref n="1805-1806.winter.part2" type="related">Estimate of Western Indians</ref>, they were incorrectly identified as being <name type="native_nation" key="Pisquow Indians">Pisquows</name> or <name type="native_nation" key="Kittita Indians">Kittitas</name>. The first tribe is discussed at <ref n="1806-04-18" type="related">April 18, 1806</ref>. Lewis and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> placed them on the <name type="place" key="Klickitat (Cataract) River">Klickitat River</name>, but some authorities have them on the <name type="place" key="Yakima (Tapteete) River">Yakima River</name>. Being hunting peoples, they may have shifted about as needed to find game. Spier (TDW), 15; Hodge, 2:521–22, 527, 585, 629. The term "<name type="native_nation" key="Klickitat Indians">Shan-wah-pums</name>" may be <name type="native_nation" key="Klickitat Indians">Shahaptian</name>
               <name type="native_nation" key="Klickitat Indians">
                  <hi rend="italic">pšwánwapam,</hi>
               </name> representing a Shahaptian group living in the upper <name type="place" key="Yakima (Tapteete) River">Yakima River</name> drainage.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32042007" n="7">Perhaps a crescent-shaped object decorated with beads.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32042008" n="8">The <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">Bitterroot River</name> in western <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>, where they met the <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Flatheads</name>, also called <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Salish</name>. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> maps 69, 70.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32042009" n="9">The river is the <name type="place" key="Deschutes (Clark's, Towanahiook's) River">Deschutes</name>. The branch heading at <name type="place" key="Mount Jefferson">Mt. Jefferson</name> might be either the <name type="place" key="Warm Springs River">Warm Springs</name> or the <name type="place" key="Metolius River">Metolius River</name>; that heading at <name type="place" key="Mount Hood (Timm, Falls Mountain)">Mt. Hood</name> would be the <name type="place" key="White River">White River</name>. The third branch may be <name type="place" key="Trout Creek">Trout Creek</name>, heading in the <name type="place" key="Blue (Southwest, Southeast) Mountains">Blue Mountains</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32042010" n="10">This notation apparently refers to the map near the back of Voorhis No. 3 (fig. 11); the reference to "No. 5" is not explainable. The map gives the date of its acquisition as April 18, two days before this entry.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32042011" n="11">Thwaites (LC), 4:309, has "jokers," but the word probably refers to their "jockeying" in trade.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32042012" n="12">
               <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> must mean spancel, that is, to hobble with rope.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32042013" n="13">
               <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> discusses the game on <ref n="1806-04-18" type="related">April 18</ref>; it is another version of the Indian hand game.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-04-19" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-04-21" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
