<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-01-19">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
January 19, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               
               
               
               
               
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml" n="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc" n="Clark, William">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 6</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">November 2, 1805–March 22, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1990</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">221-223</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo" n="Ordway, John">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf" n="Floyd, Charles">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">267</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg" n="Gass, Patrick">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">189</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jw" n="Whitehouse, Joseph">Joseph Whitehouse</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 11</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of Joseph Whitehouse, May 14, 1804–April 2, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1997</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">414</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Journal Entries</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-08-09</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1806-01-19">January 19, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-01-19.01" n="">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Monday</hi> [<hi rend="italic">NB: Sunday</hi>]
<hi rend="italic">January 9th 1806.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
This morning sent out two parties of hunters, consisting of <name type="person" key="Collins, John">Collins</name>
                  <ref target="n27011901" n="1"/> and <name type="person" key="Willard, Alexander">Willard</name> whom we sent down the bay towards <name type="place" key="Point Adams">point Adams</name>, and <name type="person" key="Labiche, François">Labuish</name> and <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name> whom we sent up <name type="place" key="Lewis and Clark (Fort, Netul) River">Fort River</name>;<ref target="n27011902" n="2"/> the fist by land and the latter by water.    we were visited today by two <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsop</name> men and a woman who brought for sale some Sea Otter skins of which we purchased one, giving in exchange the remainder of our blue beads consisting of 6 fathoms and about the same quantity of small white beads and a knife.    we also purchased a small quantity of train oil for a pair of Brass armbands and a hat for some fishinghooks.    these hats are of their own manufactory and are composed of Cedar bark and bear grass interwoven with the fingers and ornimented with varioius colours and figures, they are nearly waterproof, light, and I am convinced are much more durable than either chip<ref target="n27011903" n="3"/> or straw. These hats form a small article of traffic with the <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsops</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinnooks</name> who dispose of them to the whites.    the form of the hat is that which was in vogue in the Ued States and <name type="place" key="Britain">great Britain</name> in the years 1800 &amp; 1801 with a high crown reather larger at the top than where it joins the brim;<ref target="n27011904" n="4"/> the brim narrow or about 2 or 2½ inches.</p>
               <p>
Several families of these people usually reside together in the same room; they appear to be the father &amp; mother and their sons with their son's wives and children; their provision seems to be in common and the greatest harmoney appears to exist among them. The old man is not always rispected as the head of the family, that duty most commonly devolves on one of the young men. They have seldom more than one wife, yet the plurality of wives is not denyed them by their customs. These families when ascociated form nations or bands of nations each acknowledging the authority of it's own chieftain who does not appear to be heridatiry, nor his power to extend further than a mear repremand for any improper act of an individual; the creation of a chief depends upon the upright deportment of the individual &amp; his ability and disposition to render service to the community; and his authority or the deference paid him is in exact equilibrio with the popularity or voluntary esteem he has acquired among the individuals of his band or nation. Their laws like those of all uncivilized Indians consist of a set of customs which have grown out of their local situations.    not being able to speak their language we have not been able to inform ourselves of the existence of any peculiar customs among them.
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-01-19.02" n="">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Tuesday</hi> [Sunday]
<hi rend="italic">19th of January 1806</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
This morning Sent out two parties of hunters, one party towards <name type="place" key="Point Adams">Point adams</name> and the other part up <name type="place" key="Lewis and Clark (Fort, Netul) River">
                     <hi rend="italic">Ne tel</hi> River</name> by water.    we were visited to day by two <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsop</name> men and a woman who brought for Sale Some Sea otter Skins of which we purchased one gave in exchange the remainder of our blue beeds Consisting of 6 fathoms, and the Same quantity of Small white beids and a knife.    we also purchased a Small quantity of train oil for a par of Brass arm bands, and a hat for Som fishinghooks. these hats are of their own manufactory and are Composed of Cedar bark and bear grass interwoven with the fingers and ornimented with various Colours and figures, they are nearly water proof, light, and I am Convinced are much more dureable than either Chip or Straw,—  These hats forom a article of traffic with <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsops</name> an <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinnooks</name> who dispose of them to the whites, the form of the Hats is that which was in voge in the U States and <name type="place" key="Britain">Great Britain</name> in 1800 &amp; 1801 with a high Crown rather larger at the top than where it joins the brim, the brim narrow about 2 or 2½ inches.</p>
               <p>
Several families of those people usially reside together in the Same room; they appear to be the farther mother with their Sons and their Sons wives and children; their provisions appears to be in common and the greatest harmoney appears to exist among them.    the old man is not always respected as the head of the family that duty generally devolves on one of the young men. They have Sildom more than one wife, yet plurality of wives are not denyed them by their Customs.    those families when associated [form] bands of nations each acknowledgeing the authority of its own Chieftains, who does not appear to be heritatary, or has power to extend further than a mear repremand for any improper deportment of the individual his abiltity and disposition to render Service to the Comunity, and his authority and the defference paid him is in extent equilibrio with the popolarity or volintary esteem he has acquired among the individuals of his band, or nation. Their Laws like all uncivilized Indians Consist of a Set of customs which has grown out of their local Situations.    not being able to Speak their language we have not been able to inform ourselves of the existance of any peculiar Customs among them.
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-01-19.03" n="">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Sunday 19th    4 men<ref target="n27011905" n="5"/> went out a hunting.    moderate Showers of rain.    the men in the fort are employed dressing Elk Skins for Mockasons, &amp;C. Several of the natives visited us, and Sold us Several handsome Hats<ref target="n27011906" n="6"/> made of Some kind of Splits curiously worked &amp;C.—


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-01-19.04" n="">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Sunday 19th.</hi>    Four hunters<ref target="n27011907" n="7"/> went out this morning, which was fair with flying clouds; but in the evening it began to rain again. We had another visit 
from some of the natives.


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-01-19.05" n="">
            <sp who="jw">
               <speaker>Whitehouse</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Sunday Janry 19th    This morning we had moderate showers of rain, 4 Men<ref target="n27011908" n="8"/> of our party went out from the fort a hunting.    the Men in the fort were employed in dressing Elk skins, Several of the natives visited us, &amp; sold our Men several Hatts, which were made out of splits.    They were very handsome &amp; curiously worked



</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n27011901" n="1">Perhaps an error for <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name>; <name type="person" key="Collins, John">Collins</name> seems to have been with the saltmakers on the shore. See below, <ref n="lc.jrn.1806-01-25" type="related">January 25, 1806</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n27011902" n="2">
               <name type="place" key="Lewis and Clark (Fort, Netul) River">Lewis and Clark River</name>, <name type="place" key="Clatsop County, Oreg.">Clatsop County</name>, <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 82, 84.</note>
            <note xml:id="n27011903" n="3">Palm leaf, straw, or wood, split into thin pieces for making hats.</note>
            <note xml:id="n27011904" n="4">Not typical of the conical style of native hats, but like the one mentioned in <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> second entry of <ref n="lc.jrn.1805-11-21" type="related">November 21, 1805</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n27011905" n="5">Including <name type="person" key="Willard, Alexander">Willard</name>, <name type="person" key="Labiche, François">Labiche</name>, <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name>, and probably <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name>. See <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> entry for this 
day.</note>
            <note xml:id="n27011906" n="6">Besides the entry for this day, see <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> entries for <ref n="lc.jrn.1805-12-29" type="related">December 29, 1805</ref>, and <ref n="lc.jrn.1806-01-29" type="related">January 29, 1806</ref>, for descriptions of and notes on the native hats.</note>
            <note xml:id="n27011907" n="7">According to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, the hunters were <name type="person" key="Collins, John">Collins</name>, <name type="person" key="Willard, Alexander">Willard</name>, <name type="person" key="Labiche, François">Labiche</name>, and <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name>. "<name type="person" key="Collins, John">Collins</name>" may be an error for <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name>; see <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> entry.</note>
            <note xml:id="n27011908" n="8">According to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, the hunters were <name type="person" key="Collins, John">Collins</name>, <name type="person" key="Willard, Alexander">Willard</name>, <name type="person" key="Labiche, François">Labiche</name>, and <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name>. "<name type="person" key="Collins, John">Collins</name>" may be an error for <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name>; see <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> entry.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-01-18" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-01-20" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
