<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-10-31">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">October 31, 1805</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic
        Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            5</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">July 28–November 1, 1805</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1989</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">358-364</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">248</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">164</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jw">Joseph Whitehouse</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            11</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of Joseph Whitehouse, May 14, 1804–April 2,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1997</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">379</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journal Entries</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-07-09</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-04-12</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1805-10-31">October 31, 1805</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-10-31.01" ref="">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">October 31st Thursday 1805</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>a cloudey raney morning    I proceed down the river to view it more at
          leasure, I took 
          <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Jos. Fields</name>&amp; 
          <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Peter Crusat</name>and proceeded on down,
          Send 
          <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Crusat</name>back at 2 ms. to examine the
          rapid near the shore &amp; I proceeded on down about 10 miles to a very high rock
          <ref target="n24103101" n="1"/>in a bottom on the Stard. opsd. 2 Islands covered with
          timber on which I saw Inds. at a distance; found the river rocky for 6 miles, after
          which the Current became uniform—    at 1 mile I passed an old deserted
          village on a Pond on a high Situation of 8 Houses—    at 3 ½ miles one house
          the only remt. of an antient Villag
          <ref target="n24103102" n="2"/>   ½ a mile lower I saw 8 Vaults for the Dead
          which was nearly Square 8 feet Closely Covered with broad boads Curiously engraved, the
          bones in Some of those vaults wer 4 feet thick, in others the Dead was yet layed Side of
          each other nearly East &amp; west, raped up &amp; bound Securley in robes, great numbers
          of trinkets Brass Kittle, Sea Shells, Iron, Pan Hare &amp;c. &amp;c. was hung about the
          vaults and great many wooden gods, or Images of men Cut in wood, Set up round the
          vaults, Some of those So old and worn by time that they were nearly worn out of Shape,
          and Some of those vaults So old that they were roted entirely to the ground—
             not withstanding they wood is of Pine &amp; [
          <hi rend="italic">one word illegible</hi>] or Seder as also the wooden gods</p>
               <p>I can not learn certainly if those people worship those woden emiges, they have them
          in conspicuous parts of their houses    at 5 miles I passed 4 large houses
          <ref target="n24103103" n="3"/>on the Stard Side a little above the last rapid and
          opposit a large Island
          <ref target="n24103104" n="4"/>which is Situated near the Lard. Side—    The
          enhabitents of those houses had left them closely Shut up, they appeared to Contn. a
          great deel of property and Provisions Such as those people use, I did not disturb any
          thing about those houses, but proceed on down below the rapid which I found to be the
          last, a large village has at Some period been on the Stard. Side below this rapid
             The bottom is high Stoney and about 2 miles wide covered with grass, here
          C[overed?] is the head of a large Island in high water,
          <ref target="n24103105" n="5"/>at this time no water passes on the Stard. Side
             I walked thro this Island which I found to be verry rich, open &amp;
          covered with Strawberry vines,
          <ref target="n24103106" n="6"/>and has greatly the appearance of having at Some period
          been Cultivated, The natives has dug roots in Some parts of this Isld. which is about 3
          miles long &amp; 1 Wide, a Small Island covered with timber opposit the lower point no
          water runs on the Stard. Side. of it.    below and in the middle of the river
          is a large Island Covered with tall trees    opposit the 
          <name type="place" key="Hamilton (Strawberry) Island">Strawberry Island</name>on its
          Stard. Side a creek falls in which has no running water at present, it has the appearanc
          of throwing out emense torents—    I saw 5 Indians in a canoe below—
             
          <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Jo.</name>killed a Sand hill Crane &amp; we
          returned by the same rout to camp at the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Cascades (Great Rapids, Great Shute)">grand
          Shute</name>where I found Several Indians, I Smoked. Two canoes loaded with fish for the
          Trade below Came down &amp; unloaded the after noon fare</p>
               <p>
                  <table rows="5" cols="3">
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 30° E
                <ref target="n24103107" n="7"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">1</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">mile to a Lard Bend passing the grand Shute
                which is ¼ of a
                <lb/>mile and the Wate Confined within about 150 yards, passing
                <lb/>with Tremendious force, great number of rocks on the upper
                <lb/>pt. of this Shute, a low pine Mountain on the Stad. Side high
                <lb/>one on the Lard Side—</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 30° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">1</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">mile to a Lard. bend    passd.
                Several rocks in the river &amp; a
                <lb/>rapid at ¾ of a mile th water being Confined between large
                <lb/>rocks, maney of which is under water.    an old village of 8
                <lb/>houses on the Stard. Side on the hill opposit</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 45° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">2</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">miles to a high rock above the upper point of
                a large Isld. on
                <lb/>the Lard Side, passed maney rocks in different directions, a
                <lb/>house on the Stard. at 1 mile    just below is 8 Indian 
                <hi rend="italic">vaults</hi>
                           <lb/>in which is great number of dead raped up their trinkets, &amp;
                <lb/>wooden Gods are placed around the vaults, they lie East &amp; west</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 60° W
                <ref target="n24103108" n="8"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">2</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">miles to a large black rock in a Stard. bend
                at the Comence-
                <lb/>ment of a rapid opsd. a Lower point of an Island    passed a
                <lb/>rapid at ½ Ms. Ld not bad. Several large rocks in the river per-
                <lb/>miscusly, 4 large Ind. houses without inhabitants on the Stard.
                <lb/>Side at 1½ mile a Island on the Lard Side extensive high
                <lb/>Stoney bottoms on the Stard Side</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">South
                <ref target="n24103109" n="9"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">2</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">miles to a Creek under a Bluff in a Lard bend
                passed the rapid
                <lb/>¼ of a mile long—    the upper point of a large Island on the
                <lb/>Stard. Side no water running on the Stard. Side of it at present
                <lb/>this Island is high rich and open Covered with Strawbery vines
                <lb/>a narrow open bottom on the Lard. Side</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>Those Indians Cut off the hands of those they kill &amp; proserve the fingers.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-10-31.02" ref="">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">October 31st Thursday 1805</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>A Cloudy rainey disagreeable morning    I proceeded down the river to view
          with more attention [
          <hi rend="italic">NB: the rapids</hi>] we had to pass on the river below, the two men
          with me 
          <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Jo. Fields</name>&amp; 
          <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Peter Crusat</name>proceeded down to examine
          the rapids    the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Cascades (Great Rapids, Great Shute)">Great
          Shute</name>which commenced at the Island on which we encamped Continud with great
          rapidity and force thro a narrow chanel much compressd. and interspersed with large
          rocks for ½ a mile, at a mile lower is a verry Considerable rapid at which place the
          waves are remarkably high, and proceeded on in a old Indian parth 2½ miles by land thro
          a thick wood &amp; hill Side, to the river where the Indians make a portage, from this
          place I dispatched 
          <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Peter Crusat</name>(our principal waterman)
          back to follow the river and examine the practibility of the Canoes passing, as the
          rapids appeared to continue down below as far as I could See, I with 
          <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Jo. Fields</name>proceeded on, at ½ a mile below
          the end of the portage passed a house where there had been an old town for ages past as
          this house was old Decayed and a plac of flees I did not enter it, about ½ a mile below
          this house in a verry thick part of the woods is 8 vaults which appeared Closely Covered
          and highly deckerated with orniments. Those vaults are all nearly the Same Sise and form
          8 feet Square, 5 feet high, Slopes a little So as to convey off the rain made of Pine or
          Cedar boards Closely Connected &amp; Scurely Covered with wide boards, with a Dore left
          in The East Side which is partially Stoped with wide boards curiously engraved. In
          Several of those vaults the dead bodies wre raped up verry Securely in Skins tied around
          with cords of grass &amp; bark, laid on a mat, all east &amp; west and Some of those
          vaults had as maney as 4 bodies laying on he Side of each other.    the other
          Vaults Containing bones only, Some contained bones for the debth of 4 feet.   
          on the tops and on poles attached to those vaults hung Brass kittles &amp; frying pans
          pearced thro their bottoms, baskets, bowls of wood, Sea Shels, Skins, bits of Cloth,
          Hair, bags of Trinkets &amp; Small peices of bone &amp;c and independant of the [
          <hi rend="italic">NB: Hieroglyphics, figures of men &amp; animals</hi>] curious
          ingraveing and Paintings    on the boards which formed the vaults I observed
          Several wooden Images, cut in the figure of men and Set up on the 〈South〉 Sides of the
          vaults all round. Some of those So old and worn by time, that they were nearly out of
          Shape, I also observed the remains of Vaults rotted entirely into the ground and covered
          with moss. This must bee the burrying place for maney ages for the inhabitants of those
          rapids, the vaults are of the most lasting timber Pine &amp; Cedar—    I
          cannot Say certainly that those nativs worship those wooden idols as I have every reason
          to believe they do not; as they are Set up in the most conspicious parts of their
          houses, and treated more like orniments than objects of aderation.    at 2
          miles lower &amp; 5 below our Camp I passed a village of 4 large houses abandend by the
          nativs, with their dores bared up, I looked into those houses and observed as much
          property as is usial in the houses of those people which induced me to conclude that
          they wre at no great distance, either hunting or Colecting roots, to add to their winter
          Subsistance.    from a Short distance below the vaults the mountain which is
          but low on the Stard. Side leave the river, and a leavel Stoney open bottom Suckceeds on
          the Said Std. Side for a great Distance down, the mountains high and rugid on the Lard
          Side    this open bottom is about 2 miles    a Short distance below
          this village is a bad Stoney rapid and appears to be the last in view    I
          observed at this lower rapid the remains of a large and antient Village which I could
          plainly trace by the Sinks in which they had formed their houses, as also those in which
          they had buried their fish—    from this rapid to the lower end of the portage
          the river is Crouded with rocks of various Sizes between which the water passes with
          great velociety createing in many places large Waves, an Island which is Situated near
          the Lard. Side occupies about half the distance the lower point of which is at this
          rapid. immediately below this rapid the high water passes through a narrow Chanel
          through the Stard. Bottom forming an Island of 3 miles 〈wide〉 Long &amp; one wide, I
          walked through this Island which I found to be verry rich land, and had every appearance
          of haveing been at Some distant period Cultivated.    at this time it is
          Covered with grass intersperced with Strawberry vines.
          <ref target="n24103110" n="10"/>I observed Several places on this Island where the
          nativs had dug for roots and from its lower point I observed 5 Indians in a Canoe below
          the upper point of an Island near the middle of the river Covered with tall timber,
          which indued me to believe that a village was at no great distanc below, I could not See
          any rapids below 〈for〉 in the extent of my view which was for a long distance down the
          river, which from the last rapids widened and had everry appearance of being effected by
          the tide,—    [
          <hi rend="italic">NB: This was in fact the first tide water</hi>]    I
          deturmind to return to Camp 10 miles distant, a remarkable high detached rock Stands in
          a bottom on the Stard Side near the lower point of this Island on the Stard. Side about
          800 feet high and 400 paces around, we call the 
          <hi rend="italic">Beaten</hi>[
          <hi rend="italic">NB: Beacon</hi>] 
          <hi rend="italic">rock</hi>.    a Brook falls into the narrow Chanel which
          forms [
          <hi rend="italic">NB: what we call</hi>] the 
          <name type="place" key="Hamilton (Strawberry) Island">Strawberry Island</name>, which at
          this time has no running water, but has every appearance of dischargeing emence torrents
          &amp;c. &amp;c. 
          <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Jo. Fields</name>Shot a Sand hill Crane. I
          returned by the Same rout on an Indian parth passing up on the N W. Side of the river to
          our Camp at the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Cascades (Great Rapids, Great Shute)">Great
          Shute</name>.    found Several Indians from the village, I Smoked with them;
          Soon after my return two Canoes loaded with fish &amp; Bear grass for the trade below,
          came down from the village at the mouth of the 
          <name type="place" key="Klickitat (Cataract) River">Catterack River</name>, they
          unloaded and turned their Canoes up Side down on the beech, &amp; camped under a
          Shelveing rock below our Camp</p>
               <p>one of the men Shot a goose above this 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Cascades (Great Rapids, Great Shute)">Great
          Shute</name>, which was floating into the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Cascades (Great Rapids, Great Shute)">
          Shute</name>when an Indian observed it, plunged into the water &amp; Swam to the Goose
          and brought in on Shore, at the head of the Suck, [
          <hi rend="italic">NB: great danger, rapids bad, a descent close by him (150 feet off) of
          all 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia river</name>, current dashed among
          rocks if he had got in the Suck—lost</hi>]    as this Indian richly earned the
          goose I Suffered him to keep it which he about half picked and Spited it up with the
          guts in it to roste.</p>
               <p>This 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Cascades (Great Rapids, Great Shute)">Great
          Shute</name>or falls is about ½ a mile with the water of this great river Compressed
          within the Space of 150 paces in which there is great numbers of both large and Small
          rocks, water passing with great velocity forming &amp; boiling in a most horriable
          manner, with a fall of about 20 feet, below it widens to about 200 paces and current
          gentle for a Short distance.    a Short distance above is three Small rockey
          Islands, and at the head of those falls, three Small rockey Islands are Situated
          Crosswise the river, Several rocks above in the river &amp; 4 large rocks in the head of
          the Shute; those obstructions together with the high Stones which are continually
          brakeing loose from the mountain on the Stard Side and roleing down into the Shute aded
          to those which brake loose from those Islands above and lodge in the Shute, must be the
          Cause of the rivers daming up to Such a distance above, 〈and Show〉 where it Shows Such
          evidant marks of the Common current of the river being much lower than at the present
          day</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-10-31.03" ref="">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>Thursday 31st Oct. 1805. Cloudy.    we unloaded the canoes and went at
          halling them past the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Cascades (Great Rapids, Great Shute)">
          Shoote</name>   took one down at a time over verry high rocks.   
          this 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Cascades (Great Rapids, Great Shute)">
          Shoote</name>is full of rocks and roles verry high waves &amp;C.    the after
          part of the day pleasant.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-10-31.04" ref="">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Thursday 31st.</hi>   The morning was cloudy. We unloaded
          our canoes and took them past the rapids, some part of the way by water, and some over
          rocks 8 or 10 feet high. It was the most fatiguing business we have been engaged in for
          a long time, and we got but two over all day, the distance about a mile, and the fall of
          the water about 25 feet in that distance.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-10-31.05" ref="">
            <sp who="jw">
               <speaker>Whitehouse</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Thursday</hi>31st Oct. 1805.    Some cloudy.    we
          got in readiness to carry our baggage past the portage, which we expict will be about
          two miles.    about 9 oClock cleared off pleasant.    as the road
          was Slippery we concluded to take Some of the canoes down to day.    So we
          took down two canoes 1 at a time over high rocks on rollers, by main Strength and by
          being in the water which ran between Sd. Stone &amp; large rocks.    we had to
          hall them in that way past 2 of the worst rapids    then took them a half a
          mile below, where we intend loading which will make the portage in all only about one
          mile, but a verry bad one.    in the evening 2 Indian canoes came to our Camp
             5 Indians in them which were going down the River tradeing with fish
          &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Thursday October 31st    This morning was cool &amp; Cloudy.   
          Our party were employed in getting every thing fixed in order to carry the baggage
          &amp;ca. below the Portage, which we expect will be about 2 Miles.    About 9
          o'Clock A. M. the weather cleared off, and became pleasant.    The Road being
          slippey, Our officers concluded to have only part of our Canoes hawled down this day.
             We proceeded on with 2 of our Canoes on Rollers at a time; over high Rocks,
          by main strenghth hawling them all the way, which was about ½ Miles &amp; passed two of
          the worst Rapids, &amp; went about half a mile further below them, at which place we
          intend loading the Canoes again, making the whole of the Portage to be only about 1
          Mile—    and all this way bad Road.    In the Evening 2 indian
          Canoes came to our Camp.    They had 5 Indians in them, &amp; were going down
          the River in Order to trade away fish &amp;ca. which their Canoes were loaded with</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n24103101" n="1">
               <name type="place" key="Beacon Rock">Beacon Rock</name>is an eroded volcanic pipe or plug
        composed of Pliocene or Pleistocene olivine basalt. It is in 
        <name type="place" key="Skamania County, Wash.">Skamania County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>, just above 
        <name type="place" key="Skamania, Wash.">Skamania</name>in 
        <name type="place" key="Beacon Rock State Park">Beacon Rock State Park</name>. It was
        called 
        <name type="place" key="Beacon Rock">Castle Rock</name>for many years, but 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>name (given in the codex entry) was
        restored in 1916. 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>estimate of its height is
        remarkably correct. 
        <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>(BR); Appleman (LC), 189; 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>maps 79, 88.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24103102" n="2">This is the "old village" on 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>map 79, in 
        <name type="place" key="Skamania County, Wash.">Skamania County</name>between the Bridge
        of the Gods and 
        <name type="place" key="Bradford (Brant) Island">Bradford Island</name>. It is noted as
        having only one house. Investigators have named it 
        <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="place" key="Skamanyak village">sk!Ema'niak</name>
               </hi>or 
        <name type="place" key="Skamanyak village">Skamanyak</name>("obstructed"). Spier &amp;
        Sapir, 167; Beckham, 17–19, 28; Minor.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24103103" n="3">Investigators disagree on the relation of this village to
        the next site ("a large village has at Some period been"). Some view the two as a part of
        one complex, while others see them as separate entities. Beckham, 17–18, 31–34; Minor,
        Toepel, &amp; Beckham, 41–51; Dunnell &amp; Whitlam, 5–7; Dunnell; Phebus, 127–30. Only
        the first site is shown on 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>map 79; both are represented on figs. 28 and 29 in volume 5.
        They are in 
        <name type="place" key="Skamania County, Wash.">Skamania County</name>opposite present 
        <name type="place" key="Bradford (Brant) Island">Bradford</name>and 
        <name type="place" key="Hamilton (Strawberry) Island">Hamilton</name>islands.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24103104" n="4">Present 
        <name type="place" key="Bradford (Brant) Island">Bradford Island</name>, in 
        <name type="place" key="Hood River County, Oreg.">Hood River County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>, now crossed by 
        <name type="place" key="Bonneville Dam">Bonneville Dam</name>; "Brant I." on figs. 28 and
        29 in volume 5. 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>map 79.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24103105" n="5">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>"
        <name type="place" key="Hamilton (Strawberry) Island">Strawberry Island</name>" is now 
        <name type="place" key="Hamilton (Strawberry) Island">Hamilton Island</name>in 
        <name type="place" key="Skamania County, Wash.">Skamania County</name>. 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>map 79. Archaeological work on the island is discussed by
        Dunnell &amp; Campbell.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24103106" n="6">The woodland strawberry, 
        <hi rend="italic">Fragaria vesca</hi>L. var. 
        <hi rend="italic">crinita</hi>(Rydb.) C. L. Hitchc. Booth &amp; Wright, 112; Hitchcock et
        al., 3:108.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24103107" n="7">In the Codex H compendium of courses these courses are
        given under the date of 
        <ref n="1805-11-01" type="related">November 1, 1805</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24103108" n="8">In Codex H this distance is given as three miles.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24103109" n="9">In Codex H this course appears under the date of 
        <ref n="1805-11-02" type="related">November 2, 1805</ref>, with the distance given as
        one mile.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24103110" n="10">A vertical line through this passage from "from this
        rapid" to about this point was probably penned by 
        <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>, but not in his usual red
        ink.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-10-30" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-10-31-1" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
