<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-06-26">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">June 26, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic
        Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            8</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">June 10–September 26, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1987</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">52-55</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">327</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">244-245</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
         <geoDecl datum="WGS" xml:id="lc.geo.1806-06-26.01">
            <placeName/>
            <geo>45.4 -116.4667</geo>
            <note>Camped on Bald Mountain, Idaho County, ID.</note>
         </geoDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc/>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-11-04</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-04-12</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1806-06-26">June 26, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-06-26.01"
              ref="lc.geo.1806-06-26.01">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Thursday June 26th 1806.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>This morning we collected our horses and set out after an early breakfast or at 6 A.
          M.    we passed by the same rout we had travelled on the 17th inst. to our
          deposit on the top of the 
          <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Snow) Mountains">snowey mountain</name>to the N. E.
          of 
          <name type="place" key="Hungery Creek">hungary Creek</name>.
          <ref target="n36062601" n="1"/>   here we neceessarily halted about 2 hours
          to arrange our baggage and prepare our loads.    we cooked and made a haisty
          meal of boiled venison and mush of cows.    the snow has subsided near four
          feet since the 17th inst.    we now measured it accurately and found from a
          mark which we had made on a tree when we were last here on the 17th that it was then 10
          feet 10 inches which appeared to be about the common debth though it is deeper still in
          some places.    it is now generally about 7 feet.
          <ref target="n36062602" n="2"/>   on our way up this mountain about the
          border of the snowey region we killed 2 of the small black pheasant
          <ref target="n36062603" n="3"/>and a female of the large dommanicker or speckled
          pheasant,
          <ref target="n36062604" n="4"/>the former have 16 fathers in their tail and the latter
          20 while the common pheasant
          <ref target="n36062605" n="5"/>have only 18.    the indians informed us that
          neither of these speceis drumed; they appear to be very silent birds for I never heared
          either of them make a noise in any situation.
          <ref target="n36062606" n="6"/>   the indians haistened to be off and
          informed us that it was a considerable distance to the place which they wished to reach
          this evening where there was grass for our horses.    accordingly we set out
          with our guides who lead us over and along the steep sides of tremendious mountains
          entirely covered with snow except about the roots of the trees where the snow had
          sometimes melted and exposed a few square feet of the earth.    we ascended
          and decended severall lofty and steep hights but keeping on the dividing ridge between
          the 
          <name type="place" key="North Fork Clearwater (Chopunnish) River">Chopunnish</name>and 
          <name type="place" key="Lochsa (Upper Kooskooske) River">Kooskooske</name>rivers we
          passed no stream of water.
          <ref target="n36062607" n="7"/>   late in the evening much to the
          satisfaction of ourselves and the comfort of our horses we arrived at the desired spot
          and encamped on the steep side of a mountain convenient to a good spring.    [
          <hi rend="italic">NB: having passed a few miles our camp of 18 Sepr 1805</hi>]
          <ref target="n36062608" n="8"/>   here we found an abundance of fine grass
          for our horses. this situation was the side of an untimbered mountain with a fair
          southern aspect where the snows from appearance had been desolved about 10 days.
             the grass was young and tender of course and had much the appearance of the
          greenswoard.
          <ref target="n36062609" n="9"/>   there is a great abundance of a speceis of
          bear-grass
          <ref target="n36062610" n="10"/>which grows on every part of these mountains it's
          growth is luxouriant and continues green all winter but the horses will not eat it.
             soon after we had encamped we were overtaken by a 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Chopunnish</name>man who had pursued
          us with a view to accompany me to the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">falls of the
          Missouri</name>.    we were now informed that the two young men whom we met on
          the 21st and detained several days are going on a party of pleasure mearly to the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Oote-lash-shoots</name>or as they call
          them 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Sha-lees</name>
                  <ref target="n36062611" n="11"/>a band of the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Tush-she-pah</name>nation who reside
          on 
          <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">Clark's river</name>in the
          neighbourhood of 
          <name type="place" key="Travelers' Rest (Idaho)">traveller's rest</name>.   
          one of our guides lost 2 of his horses, which he returned in surch of; he found them and
          rejoined us a little before dark.—</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-06-26.02"
              ref="lc.geo.1806-06-26.01">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Thursday June 26th 1806</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>We collected our horses and Set out early and proceeded on Down 
          <name type="place" key="Hungery Creek">hungary Creek</name>a fiew miles and assended to
          the Summit of the mountain where we deposited our baggage on the 17th inst.   
          found every thing Safe and as we had left them.    the Snow which was 10 feet
          10 inches deep on the top of the mountain, had sunk to 7 feet tho' perfectly hard and
          firm.    we made Some fire Cooked dinner and dined, while our horses Stood on
          snow 7 feet deep at least.    after dinner we packed up and proceeded on.
             about the borders of the Snowey region we killed 2 Small black pheasents
          and a female of the large dommanicker or Speckled pheasent, the former have 16 feathers
          in the tail and the latter 20 while the common Pheasent have 18.    the
          indians informed us that neither of these Speces drumed; they appear to be very Silent
          birds for I never heard any of them make any noise.    the Indians hastened
          〈to the〉 us off and informed us that it was a considerable distance to the place they
          wished to reach this evening where there was grass for our horses. accordingly we Set
          out with our guides who led us over and along the Steep Sides of tremendious Mountains
          entirely covered with Snow except about the roots of the trees where the Snow was
          partially melted and exposed a Small Spot of earth.    we assended and
          decended Several Steep lofty hights but keeping on the dividing ridge of the 
          <name type="place" key="North Fork Clearwater (Chopunnish) River">Chopunnish</name>&amp;
          
          <name type="place" key="Lochsa (Upper Kooskooske) River">Kooskooske</name>river we
          passed no Stream of water.    late in the evening much to the Satisfaction of
          ourselves and the Comfort of the horses we arived at the desired Spot and Encamped on
          the Steep Side of a Mountain Convenient to a good Spring.    here we found an
          abundance of fine grass for our horses.    this Situation was the Side of an
          untimbered mountain with a fair Southern aspect where the Snow from appearance had been
          disolved about 10 days, the grass was young and tender of course and had much the
          appearance of the Green Swoard.    there is a great abundance of Species of
          bear grass which grows on every part of those Mountains, its growth is luxurient and
          continues green all winter but the horses will not eate it. Soon after we had encamped
          we were over taken by a 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Chopunnish</name>man who had pursued
          us with a view to accompany 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt Lewis</name>to the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">falls of Missouri</name>.
             we were now informed that the two young men we met on the 21st and detained
          Several days were going on a party of pleasure mearly to the 
          <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Oat-lash-shoots</name>
                  </hi>or as they call them 
          <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Sha-lees</name>
                  </hi>a band of the 
          <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Tush-she-pâh</name>
                  </hi>Nation who reside on 
          <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">Clarks river</name>in the
          neighbourhood of the Mouth of 
          <name type="place" key="Travelers' Rest (Idaho)">Travelers rest</name>.    one
          of our Guides lost 2 of his horses, he returned in Serch of them he found them &amp;
          rejoined us at Dark.    all of the Indians with us have two &amp; 3 horses
          each. I was taken yesterday with a violent pain in my head which has tormented me ever
          Since, most violently</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-06-26.03"
              ref="lc.geo.1806-06-26.01">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>Thursday 26th June 1806.    we Set out as usal and proceed. on to the top
          of mountains covred with Snow where we had left our baggage,
          <ref target="n36062612" n="12"/>and packed up and proceed. on    we find the
          Snow has Settled a little more than 2 feet Since we left this the other day.
             proceeded on thro. Snow deep.    in the evening we Came to the
          Side of a mountain where the Snow is melted away and a little young grass &amp;C. So we
          Camped.
          <ref target="n36062613" n="13"/>   Soon after we Camped another Indn. Came up
          who is going over the mountn. with us.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-06-26.04"
              ref="lc.geo.1806-06-26.01">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Thursday 26th.</hi>   We had a foggy morning; proceeded on
          early; and found the banks of snow much decreased: at noon we arrived at the place where
          we had left our baggage and stores. The snow here had sunk twenty inches. We took some
          dinner, but there was nothing for our horses to eat. We measured the depth of the snow
          here and found it ten feet ten inches. We proceeded over some very steep tops of the
          mountains and deep snow; but the snow was not so deep in the drafts between them; and
          fortunately, we got in the evening to the side of a hill where the snow was gone; and
          there was very good grass for our horses. So we encamped there all night. Some heavy
          showers of rain had fallen in the afternoon.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n36062601" n="1">The cache on 
        <name type="place" key="Willow Ridge">Willow Ridge</name>, in 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho County, Idaho">Idaho County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>; see 
        <ref n="1806-06-17" type="related">June 17, 1806</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36062602" n="2">Space, 36, judges the spring of 1806 to have been unusually
        late, since the snow is usually gone in the area by late June, except in isolated drifts
        and shaded spots.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36062603" n="3">Probably the blue grouse, 
        <hi rend="italic">Dendragapus obscurus</hi>[AOU, 297]; see 
        <ref n="1805-08-01" type="related">August 1, 1805</ref>, and 
        <ref n="1806-03-03" type="related">March 3, 1806</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36062604" n="4">Spruce grouse, 
        <hi rend="italic">Dendragapus canadensis</hi>[AOU, 298]; see 
        <ref n="1806-03-03" type="related">March 3, 1806</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36062605" n="5">Presumably the ruffed grouse, 
        <hi rend="italic">Bonasa umbellus</hi>[AOU, 300], "common" because 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>was familiar with it in the East.
        A red vertical line runs through this passage about the birds, perhaps 
        <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle's</name>doing.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36062606" n="6">Space, 36, confirms that these birds do not drum, though
        they make other noises during the mating season or in calling their young.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36062607" n="7">The 
        <name type="place" key="Lolo Trail">Lolo Trail</name>runs along the ridge or divide
        between the 
        <name type="place" key="North Fork Clearwater (Chopunnish) River">North Fork of the
        Clearwater (Chopunnish)</name>and the 
        <name type="place" key="Lochsa (Upper Kooskooske) River">Lochsa (Kooskooske)</name>,
        primarily in 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho County, Idaho">Idaho County</name>. 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>maps 69, 70.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36062608" n="8">This camp was on 
        <name type="place" key="Bald Mountain">Bald Mountain</name>, in 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho County, Idaho">Idaho County</name>. As 
        <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>notes, it was northeast of the
        camp of September 18, 1805, marked "Party Camped 18th" on 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>map 70. Space, 36; Peebles (LT), map; Peebles (RLC),
        26.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36062609" n="9">Greensward usually refers to a lush, green meadow rather
        than to a specific species. The grasses would be those noted at 
        <ref n="1806-06-19" type="related">June 19, 1806</ref>. A red vertical line runs through
        most of the remainder of the entry, again probably 
        <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle's</name>work.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36062610" n="10">Beargrass, 
        <hi rend="italic">Xerophyllum tenax</hi>(Pursh) Nutt., is indeed abundant here. When he
        says he sees "a speceis of bear-grass" he implies that he knows the eastern species, 
        <hi rend="italic">X. asphodeloides</hi>(L.) Nutt., and that this plant is different. He is
        correct. However, the eastern species is called turkey-beard, so 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>use of the name beargrass is
        curious. The wiry leaves are not edible, as he surmised, but as he noted on the type
        specimen label, they were used "by the natives to make baskets and other ornaments" (see
        also 
        <ref n="1806-01-17" type="related">January 17, 1806</ref>). Hitchcock et al., 1:812;
        Cutright (LCPN), 422.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36062611" n="11">
               <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Salish</name>(
        <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Flatheads</name>). The name "
        <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Tush-she-pah</name>" apparently
        represents the 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshone</name>term 
        <hi rend="italic">tatasiba,</hi>"the people with shaved heads," meaning the 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Flatheads</name>(see 
        <ref n="1805-09-04" type="related">September 4, 1805</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="n36062612" n="12">The cache on 
        <name type="place" key="Willow Ridge">Willow Ridge</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho County, Idaho">Idaho County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36062613" n="13">On 
        <name type="place" key="Bald Mountain">Bald Mountain</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho County, Idaho">Idaho County</name>.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-06-25" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-06-27" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
