<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-10-19">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">October 19, 1805</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic
        Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            5</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">July 28–November 1, 1805</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1989</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">301-307</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">241</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">158</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jw">Joseph Whitehouse</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            11</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of Joseph Whitehouse, May 14, 1804–April 2,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1997</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">360-361</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
         <geoDecl datum="WGS" xml:id="lc.geo.1805-10-19.01">
            <placeName/>
            <geo>45.9 -119.6167</geo>
            <note>Camped somewhere between Irrigon and Boardman, Morrow County, OR. Could potentially be Blalock Island.</note>
         </geoDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Journal Entries</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-07-06</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-04-12</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1805-10-19">October 19, 1805</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-10-19.01"
              ref="lc.geo.1805-10-19.01">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>October 19th 〈Thursday〉 Saturday, The Great Chief 2d Chief and a Chief of a band
          below Came and Smoked with us    we gave a Meadel a String of Wampom &amp;
          handkerchef to the Great Chief byname 
          <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="person" key="Yelleppit">Yel-lep-pet</name>
                  </hi>
                  <ref target="n23101901" n="1"/>   The 2d Chief we gave a String of wampom,
          his name is [
          <hi rend="italic">blank</hi>] The 3d who lives below a String of Wampom his name I did
          not learn. The chief requested us to Stay untill 12 we excused our Selves and Set out at
          9 oClock</p>
               <p>
                  <table rows="5" cols="3">
                     <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Course</hi>
                     </head>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">14</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">miles to a rock in a Lard. resembling that a
                hat
                <ref target="n23101902" n="2"/>just below a
                <lb/>rapid at the lower Point of an Island in the Midl: of the river
                <lb/>7 Lodges and opposit the head of one on the Stard. Side 5
                <lb/>Lodges    passed an Island at 8 miles 6 miles long close to
                <lb/>Lard Side    no water on Lard.    a Small one opsd. and
                at the
                <lb/>lower point    no water Lard.    passed an Isld. in
                middle at 8
                <lb/>miles on which 5 Indian Lodges, deserted    at the end of
                <lb/>this course a bad rockey 〈rapid〉 place plenty of water    rocks
                <lb/>in the river.—    passed a Stard. point at 4 miles   
                country a
                <lb/>little lower</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 80° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  7</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">miles to a Point of rocks on the Stard. bend
                   Passed the Is-
                <lb/>land on Std. Side    at 1 mile passed a verry bad rapid Above
                <lb/>the end of this Course 2 miles in length with Several Small
                <lb/>Islands in it &amp; Banks of Mussle Shels in the rapids.    here
                <lb/>the lower Countrey Commences—    Saw a high mountain
                <lb/>covered with snow 
                <hi rend="italic">West</hi>   this we Suppose to be 
                <name type="place" key="Mount Hood (Timm, Falls Mountain)">Mt. 〈Hood</name>〉
                <lb/>
                           <name type="place" key="Mount St. Helens">St Helens</name>
                           <ref target="n23101903" n="3"/>in dist.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 70° W.
                <ref target="n23101904" n="4"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">12</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Miles to a    passed 20 Lodge of
                Indians Scattered allong the
                <lb/>Stard. Side drying fish &amp; Prickley pare (to Burn in winter)
                <lb/>I went on Shore in a Small Canoe a head, landed at the first
                <lb/>5 Lodges, found the Indians much fritened, all got in to
                <lb/>their lodges and I went in found Some hanging down
                <lb/>their heads, Some Crying and others in great agitation, I
                <lb/>took all by the hand, and distributed a few Small articles
                <lb/>which I chanced to have in my Pockets and Smoked with
                <lb/>them which expelled their fears, Soon after the Canoes
                <lb/>landed &amp; we all Smoked and were friendly. I gave a String
                <lb/>of Wampom to the Principal man, we dined on dryed
                <lb/>Salmon &amp; Set out. I am confident that I could have toma-
                <lb/>hawked every Indian here. The Language is the Sam as
                <lb/>those above, those Lodges can turn out 〈250〉 350 men.
                <ref target="n23101905" n="5"/>I
                <lb/>shot a Crain
                <ref target="n23101906" n="6"/>&amp; 2 ducks and opposit to a Lodge on the Stard.
                <lb/>Side, one mile below a rapid.    a Single Mountn. bears S. W.
                <lb/>from the 
                <name type="place" key="Musselshell Rapids">Muscle Shell rapid</name>.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                           <hi rend="underline">  3</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">miles to a few 〈bushes〉 willow Trees on the
                Lard. Side below
                <lb/>the lower pt. of an Isd. Ld. opposit 24 Lodges of Indians In-
                <lb/>dians fishing.    here we came too and camped, 19 of them
                <lb/>on the Stard. Side &amp; 5 on an Island in the middle of the
                <lb/>river, about 100 Inds. come over    Some brought wood and
                <lb/>we gave Smoke to all which they were pleased at</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                           <hi rend="double underline">36</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <figure rend="mhs">
                     <p>
                        <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>near Mouth of 
              <name type="place" key="Umatilla (Youmalolam) River">Umatilla River</name>
                        <lb/>(not shown), 
              <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>and 
              <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>, ca. October 19, 1805,
              <lb/>Elkskin-bound Journal 
              <bibl>
                           <orgName>Missouri Historical Society</orgName>
                        </bibl>
                     </p>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>P. 
          <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Crusat</name>played on the Violin which
          pleasd and astonished those reches who are badly Clad, ¾ with robes not half large
          enough to cover them, they are homeley high Cheeks, and but fiew orniments. I Suped on
          the Crane which I killed 〈yesterday〉 to day.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-10-19.02"
              ref="lc.geo.1805-10-19.01">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">October 19th Saturday 1805</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>The great chief 
          <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="person" key="Yelleppit">Yel-lep-pet</name>
                  </hi>two other chiefs, and a Chief of Band below presented themselves to us verry early
          this morning.    we Smoked with them, enformed them as we had all others above
          as well as we Could by Signs
          <ref target="n23101907" n="7"/>of our friendly intentions towards our red children
          Perticular those who opened their ears to our Councils.    we gave a Medal, a
          Handkercheif &amp; a string of Wompom to 
          <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="person" key="Yelleppit">Yelleppit</name>
                  </hi>and a String of wompom to each of the others. 
          <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="person" key="Yelleppit">Yelleppit</name>
                  </hi>is a bold handsom Indian, with a dignified countenance about 35 years of age, about
          5 feet 8 inches high and well perpotiond.    he requested us to delay untill
          the Middle of the day, that his people might Come down and See us, we excused our Selves
          and promised to Stay with him one or 2 days on our return which appeared to Satisfy him;
          great numbers of Indians Came down in Canoes to view us before we Set out which was not
          untill 9 oClock A M.    we proceeded on passed a Island, close under the Lard
          Side about Six miles in length opposit to the lower point of which two Isds. are
          situated on one of which five Lodges 〈of Indians〉 vacent &amp; Saffolds drying fish
             at the upper point of this Island Swift water.    a Short
          distance below passed two Islands; one near the middle of the river on which is Seven
          lodges of Indians drying fish,
          <ref target="n23101908" n="8"/>at our approach they hid themselves in their Lodges and
          not one was to be seen untill we passed, they then Came out in greater numbers than is
          common in Lodges of their Size, it is probable that, the inhabitants of the 5 Lodges
          above had in a fright left their lodges and decended to this place to defend them Selves
          if attackted there being a bad rapid opposit the Island thro which we had to pass
          prevented our landing on this Island and passifying those people, about four miles below
          this fritened Island we arrived at the head of a verry bad rapid,
          <ref target="n23101909" n="9"/>we came too on the Lard Side to view the rapid before we
          would venter to run it, as the Chanel appeared to be close under the oppd. Shore, and it
          would be necessary to liten our canoe, I deturmined to walk down on the Lard Side, with
          the 2 Chiefs the interpreter &amp; his woman, and derected the Small canoe to prcede
          down on the Lard Side to the foot of the rapid which was about 2 miles in length
             I Sent on the Indian Chiefs &amp;c. down and I assended a high clift about
          200 feet above the water from the top of which is a leavel plain extending up the river
          and off for a great extent, at this place the Countrey becoms low on each Side of the
          river, and affords a pros[pect?] of the river and countrey below for great extent both
          to the right and left; from this place I descovered a high mountain of emence hight
          covered with Snow, this must be one of the mountains laid down by 
          <name type="place" key="Vancouver, George">Vancouver</name>, as Seen from the mouth of
          the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>, from the Course which it
          bears which is 
          <hi rend="italic">West</hi>I take it to be 
          <name type="place" key="Mount St. Helens">Mt. St. Helens</name>, destant 〈about 120〉 156
          miles    a range of mountains in the Derection crossing, a conacal mountain S.
          W. toped with Snow    This rapid I observed as I passed opposit to it to be
          verry bad interseped with high rock and Small rockey Islands, here I observed banks of
          Muscle Shells banked up in the river in Several places, I Delayed at the foot of the
          rapid about 2 hours for the Canoes which I could See met with much dificuelty in passing
          down the rapid on the oposit Side    maney places the men were obliged to get
          into the water and haul the canoes over Sholes—    while Setting on a rock
          wateing for 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt Lewis</name>I Shot a Crain which was
          flying over of the common kind. I observed a great number of Lodges on the opposit Side
          at Some distance below and Several Indians on the opposit bank passing up to where 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name>was with the Canoes,
          others I Saw on a knob nearly opposit to me at which place they delayed but a Short time
          before they returned to their Lodges as fast as they could run, I was fearfull that
          those people might not be informed of us, I deturmined to take the little Canoe which
          was with me and proceed with the three men in it to the Lodges, on my aproach not one
          person was to be Seen except three men off in the plains, and they Sheared off as I
          aproached near the Shore, I landed in front of five Lodges which was at no great
          distance from each other, Saw no person    the enteranc or Dores of the Lodges
          wer Shut with the Same materials of which they were built a mat, I approached one with a
          pipe in my hand entered a lodge which was the nearest to me found 32 persons men, women
          and a few children Setting permiscuesly in the Lodg, 〈Some〉 in the greatest agutation,
          Some crying and ringing there hands, others hanging their heads. I gave my hand to them
          all and made Signs of my friendly dispotion and offered the men my pipe to Smok and
          distributed a fiew Small articles which I had in my pockets,—this measure passified
          those distressed people verry much, I then Sent one man into each lodge and entered a
          Second myself the inhabitants of which I found more fritened than those of the first
          lodge    I destributed Sundrey Small articles amongst them, and Smoked with
          the men, I then entered the third 4h &amp; fifth Lodge which I found Somewhat passified,
          the three men 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewer</name>
                  <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Jo.</name>&amp; 
          <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">R. Fields</name>, haveing useed everey means in
          their power to convince them of our friendly disposition to them, I then 〈formd〉 Set my
          Self on a rock and made Signs to the men to come and Smoke with me not one Come out
          untill the Canoes arrived with 〈Some five Came out of each Lodge and Set by me and
          Smoked    
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt Lewis</name>at〉 the 2 Chiefs, one of
          whom spoke aloud, and as was their Custom to all we had passed the Indians came out
          &amp; Set by me and Smoked    They said we came from the clouds &amp;c &amp;c
          〈which the〉 and were not men &amp;c. &amp;c.    this time 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name>came down with the Canoes
          rear in which the Indians, as Soon as they Saw the Squar wife of the interperters 〈wife〉
          they pointed to her and informed those who continued yet in the Same position I first
          found them, they imediately all came out and appeared to assume new life,
          <ref target="n23101910" n="10"/>the sight of This Indian woman, wife to one of our
          interprs. confirmed those people of our friendly intentions, as no woman ever
          accompanies a war party of Indians in this quarter—    
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt Lewis</name>joined us and we Smoked
          with those people in the greatest friendship, dureing which time one of our Old Chiefs
          informed them who we were from whence we Came and where we were going giveing them a
          friendly account of us, those people do not Speak prosisely the Same language of those
          above but understand them, I Saw Several Horses and persons on hors back in the plains
          many of the men womin and children Came up from the Lodges below; all of them appeared
          pleased to See us, we traded some fiew articles for fish and berries, Dined, and
          proceeded on passed a Small rapid and 15 Lodges below the five, and Encamped below an
          Island Close under the Lard Side,
          <ref target="n23101911" n="11"/>nearly opposit to 24 Lodges on an Island near the
          middle of the river, and the Main Stard Shor    Soon after we landed which was
          at a fiew willow trees about 100 [
          <hi rend="italic">X: 5</hi>] Indians Came from the different Lodges, and a number of
          them brought wood which they gave us, we Smoked with all of them, and two of our Party 
          <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Peter Crusat</name>&amp; 
          <name type="person" key="Gibson, George">Gibson</name>played on the 
          <hi rend="italic">violin</hi>which delighted them greatly, we gave to the principal man
          a String of wompon treated them kindly for which they appeared greatfull, This Tribe [
          <hi rend="italic">NB: a branch of the nation called 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Yakima Indians">Pisch quit pas</name>
                  </hi>] can raise
          about 350 men    their Dress are Similar to those at the fork except their
          robes are Smaller and do not reach lower than the waste and ¾ of them have Scercely any
          robes at all, the women have only a Small pece of a robe which Covers their Sholders
          neck and reaching down behind to their wastes, with a tite piece of leather about the
          waste, the brests are large and hang down verry low illy Shaped, high Creeks flattened
          heads, &amp; have but fiew orniments, they are all employed in fishing and drying fish
          of which they have great quantites on their Scaffolds, their habits customs &amp;c. I
          could not lern. I killed a Duck that with the Crain afforded us a good Supper.
             the Indians continued all night at our fires</p>
               <p>This day we made 
          <hi rend="italic">36</hi>miles</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-10-19.03"
              ref="lc.geo.1805-10-19.01">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>Saturday 19th Oct. 1805.    a clear cold morning.    the natives
          brought us Some pounded Sammon.    about 7 oC A M we Set out   
          proceeded on    passd high clifts of rocks on each Side of the River.
             the natives are verry numrous.    our officers gave one
          <ref target="n23101912" n="12"/>a meddle and Some other small articles.   
          this morning passd. Several Small villages    the Savages all hid themselves
          in their flag loges untill we passed them.    the Indians are numerous along
          the River.    the villages near each other and great quantitys of Sammon
          drying.    we passed over Several rapids which are common in this River.
             we discovred a verry high round mountain a long distance down the River
          which appears to have Snow on the top of it.    we came 36 miles this day and
          Camped on the South Side    an Indian village on the opposite Shore
             a nomber of the natives came over the River in their Small canoes to see
          us.    when any of these Savages dye they bury them and all their property
          with them and picket in their grave yard.    even their canoes are put around
          them.—</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-10-19.04"
              ref="lc.geo.1805-10-19.01">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Saturday 19th.</hi>   The morning was clear and pleasant,
          with some white frost. A number of the natives came to our camp, and our Commanding
          Officers presented one of them with a medal and other small articles. At 8 o'clock we
          proceeded on; passed some islands and bad rapids, but no accident happened. We also
          passed a great many Indian camps. In the whole country around there are only level
          plains, except a few hills on some parts of the river. We went 36 miles and halted
          opposite a large Indian camp; and about thirty-six canoe loads of them came over to see
          us; some of whom remained all night; but we could not have much conversation with them
          as we did not understand their language.
          <ref target="n23101913" n="13"/>They are clothed much in the same manner with those at
          the forks above. The custom prevails among these Indians of burying all the property of
          the deceased, with the body. Amongst these savages when any of them die, his baskets,
          bags, clothing, horses and other property are all interred: even his canoe is split into
          pieces and set up round his grave.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-10-19.05"
              ref="lc.geo.1805-10-19.01">
            <sp who="jw">
               <speaker>Whitehouse</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>Saturday 19th Oct. 1805.    a clear cold morning.    we took an
          eairly breakfast.    the Natives came to See us in their canoes.   
          brought us Some fish which had been roasted and pounded up fine and made up in balls,
          which eat verry well.    about 7 oC. A m. we Set out and proceeded on down the
          R.    passed high clifts of rocks on each Side    passd. over
          Several rockey rapids.    our officers gave one of the Natives we left this
          morning a meddel.    we passed Several Islands on which was Indian fishing
          Camps.    the natives all hid themselves in their flag lodges when they Saw us
          comming.    the Indians are numerous    the camps near each other
          along the Shores    the River pleasant only at the rapid which are common
             we passd. over Several today but no exident hapened.    the
          Country around level plains except Some hills &amp; clifts along the Shores.
             we discovred a high hill or mountn a long distance down the River which
          appears to have Snow on it    we 〈came〉 went 36 miles this day and Campd
          opposite a large Indian Camp on the South Side.    a great nomber of the
          natives come over in their canos to see us.    when any of these natives die
          they deposite all their property with them.    we Saw one of their grave yards
          to day, even a canoe was Split in peaces and Set up around the yard Several other art.
          also.</p>
               <p>Saturday October 19th    This morning was clear &amp; cold, We took an
          early breakfast, the Natives still continuing to visit us, bringing with them some
          Salmon, which they had roasted &amp; pounded fine &amp; made up into Balls, which eat
          very well; About 7 oClock A. M. We proceeded on down the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>, We passed by Clifts of
          rocks, lying on each side of the River, &amp; also rockey rapids.    We passed
          by several Islands, on which were Indian fishing Camps.    The Natives all hid
          themselves (on these Islands on seeing us,) in their Flag lodges.    We now
          begin to find the Indians very numerous, and their Camps lay near each other along the
          Shores on both sides of the River, We found the day pleasant &amp; the Navigation of the
          River easy, excepting at the Rapids several of which we passed over this day, without
          any accident happening.—</p>
               <p>The Country as we passed along is level plains, and along some part of the Shores are
          some hills &amp; Clifts.    We discovered a high hill or mountain laying a
          long distance down the River which appears to have Snow on it.—    We came 36
          Miles this day, &amp; encamped opposite to a large Indian Camp, which lay on the South
          side of the River.    A number of the Natives came over to see us, &amp;
          behaved very friendly.—    These Indians have a custom among them, that when
          any of them die, they deposit all their property with them.—    We saw one of
          their grave Yards this day, &amp; even to a canoe, that belonged to the deceased person;
          was split up into pieces, and set up round the grave Yard</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n23101901" n="1">Evidently 
        <name type="person" key="Yelleppit">Yelleppit</name>was chief of the 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Walula Indians">Walula</name>(or 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Walula Indians">Walla Walla</name>) tribe, although it has
        been suggested that he was a 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Cayuse Indians">Cayuse</name>leader named 
        <name type="person" key="Ollicutt">Ollicutt</name>known to fur traders in the area a few
        years later. Ronda (LCAI), 167, 220–21; Ruby &amp; Brown (CIIT), 22–23; Ross, 137–38;
        Glover, 350. The term 
        <hi rend="italic">yelépt</hi>means "friend, blood brother" in 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>; 
        <hi rend="italic">yal
        <seg n="u616u769">ɨ́</seg>pt</hi>means "trading partner" in Shahaptian. Sometime in the
        1890s a 
        <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>peace medal, perhaps from the
        expedition, was discovered on an island (possibly 
        <name type="place" key="Goat Island">Goat Island</name>) at the mouth of the 
        <name type="place" key="Walla Walla (Waller Waller) River">Walla Walla River</name>; it
        may be the one given to 
        <name type="person" key="Yelleppit">Yelleppit</name>at this time or on the party's return
        trip in 1806. It is today a part of the 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>items of the Oregon Historical
        Society, Portland. Cutright (LCIPM), 164; Prucha (IPM), 16–24, 90–95, Strong (SACR),
        208.</note>
            <note xml:id="n23101902" n="2">
               <name type="place" key="Hat Rock">Hat Rock</name>retains its name from 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>and sits prominently in 
        <name type="place" key="Hat Rock State Park">Hat Rock State Park</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Umatilla County, Oreg.">Umatilla County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>. Several miles upstream the party passed
        today's 
        <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>-
        <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>border.</note>
            <note xml:id="n23101903" n="3">Probably not 
        <name type="place" key="Mount St. Helens">Mt. St. Helens</name>, which would not be
        visible from their location, but 
        <name type="place" key="Mount Adams">Mt. Adams</name>, east of the main 
        <name type="place" key="Cascade Range">Cascade Range</name>in 
        <name type="place" key="Yakima County, Wash.">Yakima County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>. Glover, 312 and n. 15.</note>
            <note xml:id="n23101904" n="4">Opposite this course in the Elkskin-bound Journal 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>sketched a map showing the journey
        from 
        <name type="place" key="Hat Rock">Hat Rock</name>to beyond the 
        <name type="place" key="Umatilla (Youmalolam) River">Umatilla River</name>(not shown) and
        the campsite of October 19, 1805.</note>
            <note xml:id="n23101905" n="5">These people were 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Umatilla Indians">Umatillas</name>, or perhaps 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Cayuse Indians">Cayuses</name>, living near present 
        <name type="place" key="Plymouth, Wash.">Plymouth</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Benton County, Wash.">Benton County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>, opposite the mouth of the 
        <name type="place" key="Umatilla (Youmalolam) River">Umatilla River</name>, which the
        captains did not notice on the outbound journey. Ronda (LCAI), 167–68, 285 n. 14; 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>map 75.</note>
            <note xml:id="n23101906" n="6">A crane "of the Common Kind" in Codex H; probably a
        sandhill crane. See above, 
        <ref n="1805-07-21" type="related">July 21</ref>and 
        <ref n="1805-07-29" type="related">29</ref>, 1805, for more description.</note>
            <note xml:id="n23101907" n="7">An indication, perhaps, that the sign language had
        penetrated this far from the 
        <name type="place" key="Great Plains">Great Plains</name>. Many 
        <name type="place" key="Columbia Plateau">Columbia Plateau</name>tribes made
        buffalo-hunting trips to the plains, where they could have picked up the signs.</note>
            <note xml:id="n23101908" n="8">The six-mile-long island may be later 
        <name type="place" key="Techumtas Island">Techumtas Island</name>, while that referred to
        as having five lodges may be later 
        <name type="place" key="Sheep Island">Sheep Island</name>. Osborne, 131, mentions the
        island with seven lodges. 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>map 75; Osborne, Bryan, &amp; Crabtree, 267–306; Ray (NVCB),
        150–51.</note>
            <note xml:id="n23101909" n="9">In the area of present 
        <name type="place" key="McNary Dam">McNary Dam</name>. "
        <name type="place" key="Musselshell Rapids">Muscle Shell rapid</name>" on 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>map 75.</note>
            <note xml:id="n23101910" n="10">At this point in Codex H (p. 41), in the right margin and
        at right angles to the text, 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>has written "See description." There
        is also a large "X" through this passage.</note>
            <note xml:id="n23101911" n="11">Apparently between 
        <name type="place" key="Irrigon, Oreg.">Irrigon</name>and 
        <name type="place" key="Boardman, Oreg.">Boardman</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Morrow County, Oreg.">Morrow County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>. 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>map 75. The island could be 
        <name type="place" key="Blalock Island">Blalock Island</name>, known as 
        <hi rend="italic">ama
        <hi rend="superscript">⊃</hi>ama'pa</hi>("island") by the 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Umatilla Indians">Umatillas</name>. Archaeological work
        performed on 
        <name type="place" key="Blalock Island">Blalock Island</name>in the late 1950s and 1960s
        has not yet been fully reported. There are several sites in this area of 
        <name type="place" key="Plymouth, Wash.">Plymouth</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>, which are likely candidates for the
        numerous lodges noted by 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>. Ray (NVCB), 151; Alexander; Galm et
        al.</note>
            <note xml:id="n23101912" n="12">
               <name type="person" key="Yelleppit">Yelleppit</name>, chief of the 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Walula Indians">Walula</name>, or 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Walula Indians">Walla Walla</name>, Indians.</note>
            <note xml:id="n23101913" n="13">Probably 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Umatilla Indians">Umatilla Indians</name>living in the
        vicinity of 
        <name type="place" key="Plymouth, Wash.">Plymouth</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Benton County, Wash.">Benton County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>, but possibly 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Cayuse Indians">Cayuses</name>.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-10-18" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-10-20" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
