<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-08-15">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
August 15, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               
               
               
               
               
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml" n="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc" n="Clark, William">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 8</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">June 10–September 26, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1987</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">300-303</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo" n="Ordway, John">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf" n="Floyd, Charles">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">350</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg" n="Gass, Patrick">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">267</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Journal Entries</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-12-13</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1806-08-15">August 15, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-08-15.01" n="">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>Thursday August 15th 1806 Continued <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name> Vilg<ref target="n39081501" n="1"/>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
after assembling the Chiefs and Smokeing one pipe, I informed them that I Still Spoke the Same words which we had Spoken to them when we first arived in their Country in the fall of 1804.    we then envited them to visit their great father the president of the U. States and to hear 〈their〉 his own Councils and receive his Gifts from his own hands as also See the population<ref target="n39081502" n="2"/> of a government which Can at their pleasure protect and Secur you from all your enimies, and chastize all those who will Shut their years to 〈their〉 his Councils.    we now offer to take you at the expense of our Government and Send you back to your Country again with a considerable present 〈of〉 in merchendize which you will recive of your great Father. I urged the necessity of their going on with us as it would be the means of hastening those Supples of Merchindize which would be Sent to their Country and exchanged as before mentioned for a moderate price in Pelteries and furs &amp;c.    the great Chief of the <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Menetaras</name> Spoke, he Said he wished to go down and See his great father very much, but that the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Scioux</name> were in the road and would most certainly kill him or any others who Should go down they were bad people and would not listen to any thing which was told them.    when 〈we〉 he Saw us last we told him that we had made peaace with all the nations below, Since that time the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Seioux</name> had killed 8 of their people and Stole a number of their horses.    he Said that he had opened his ears and followed our Councils, he had made peace with the <name type="native_nation" key="Cheyenne Indians">Chyennes</name> and <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">rocky mountains</name> indians, and repieted the same objecctions as mentioned.    that he went to war against none and was willing to receive all nations as friends.    he Said that the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Ricaras</name> had Stolen from his people a number of horses at different times and his people had killed 2 <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Ricaras</name>.    if the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sieoux</name> were at peace with them and Could be depended on he as also other Chiefs of the villages would be glad to go and See their great father, but as they were all afraid of the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sieoux</name> they Should not go down &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
The <name type="person" key="Black Cat (Posecopsahe)">Black Cat</name> 〈sent〉 Chief of the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name> Village on the North Side of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> Sent over and requested me to go over to his village which envertation I axceptd and crossed over to his village.    he had a parcel of Corn about 12 bushuls in a pile in his lodge.    he told me that his people had but little corn part of which they had given me.    after takeing a Smoke he informed me that as the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sieoux</name> were very troublesom and the road to his great father dangerous none of this village would go down with us. I told the Cheifs and wariers of the village who were there present that we were anxious that Some of the village Should go and See their great father and hear his good words &amp; recve his <hi rend="italic">bountifull gifts</hi> &amp;c. and told them to pitch on Some Man on which they could rely on and send him to See their Great father, they made the Same objections which the Chief had done before.    a young man offered to go down, and they all agreeed for him to go down    the charector of this young man I knew as a bad one and made an objection as to his age and Chareckter    at this time <name type="person" key="Gibson, George">Gibson</name> who was with me informed me that this young man had Stole his knife and had it then in his possession, this I informed the Chief and directed him to give up the knife he delivered the knife with a very faint apology for his haveing it in his possession. I then reproached those people for wishing to Send Such a man to See and hear the words of So great a man as their great father; they hung their heads and Said nothing for Some time when the Cheif Spoke and Said that they were afraid to Send any one for fear of their being killed by the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sieux</name>.    after Smoking a pipe and relateing Some passages I recrossed to our Camp—.<ref target="n39081503" n="3"/>    being informed by one of our enterpreters that the 2d Chief of the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name> Comonly Called the <name type="person" key="Little Crow (Ka-goh-ha-me)">little Crow</name>
                  <ref target="n39081504" n="4"/> intended to accompany us down, I took <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbono</name> and walked to the Village to See this Chief and talk with him on the Subject.    he told me he had deturmined to go down, but wished to have a council first with his people which would be in the after part of the day. I smoked a pipe with the <name type="person" key="Little Crow (Ka-goh-ha-me)">little Crow</name> and returned to the boat. <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name> one of our men expressed a desire to join Some trappers [<hi rend="italic">NB: the two <name type="place" key="Illinois">Illinois</name> Men we met, &amp; who now came down to us</hi>] who offered to become Shearers with and furnish traps &amp;c.    the offer a very advantagious one, to him, his Services Could be dispenced with from this down and as we were disposed to be of Service to any one of our party who had performed their duty as well as <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name> had done, we agreed to allow him the prvilage provided no one of the party would ask or expect a Similar permission to which they all agreeed that they wished <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name> every Suckcess and that as we did not wish any of them to Seperate untill we Should arive at <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> they would not apply or expect it &amp;c.<ref target="n39081505" n="5"/> The <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians, Awaxawi">Maharha</name> Chief brought us Some Corn, as did also the Chief of the little village of the <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Menetarras</name> on mules of which they have Several.    [<hi rend="italic">NB: bought from the <name type="native_nation" key="Crow Indians">Crow Inds.</name> who get or Steal them from the Spaniards</hi>]<ref target="n39081506" n="6"/>    The evening is Cool and windy.    great number of the nativs of the different villages Came to view us and exchange robes with our men for their Skins—    we gave <name type="place" key="Colter, John">Jo Colter</name> Some Small articles which we did not want and Some powder &amp; lead.    the party also gave him Several articles which will be usefull to him on his expedittion.— This evening <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbono</name> informed me that our back was scercely turned before a war party from the two <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">menetarry</name> villages followed on and attacked and killed the <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Snake Indians</name> whome we had Seen and in the engagement between them and the <name type="native_nation" key="Paiute Indians">Snake indians</name> they had lost two men one of which was the Son of the principal Chief of the little village of the <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">menitarras</name>.<ref target="n39081507" n="7"/>    that they had also went to war from the <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Menetarras</name> and killeld two <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Ricaras</name>.    he further informed me that a missunderstanding had taken place between the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name> &amp; <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">minetarras</name> and had verry nearly come to blows about a woman, the <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Mintarres</name> at length presented a pipe and a reconsilliation took place between them
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-08-15.02" n="">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Friday 15th August 1806.    a clear pleasant morning. Some of the party went at dressing themselves deer Skins &amp;C.    the natives brought us corn and beans &amp;C.    they brought us a breakfast of boild siniblins<ref target="n39081508" n="8"/> &amp; beans &amp;C.    the 2 village of <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>
                  <ref target="n39081509" n="9"/> gave us Considerable of corn and more than we would take away. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name> went over and tryed to perswade Some of the chief of that village to go down with us but they could not find any one willing to go with us.    the chiefs of the 1st village<ref target="n39081510" n="10"/> wished us to Stay
1 or 2 days longer with them    we gave the Swivvel to the <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Big Belleys or Grousevauntaus</name>.—


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-08-15.03" n="">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Friday 15th.</hi>    We had a fine clear pleasant morning, and continued here all day, to ascertain whether any of the chiefs would go down with us or not.— They had to hold councils among themselves, and we had to wait for their answers.<ref target="n39081511" n="11"/> The two hunters<ref target="n39081512" n="12"/> we left up the river came down, staid with us here, and got one of our party<ref target="n39081513" n="13"/> to join in partnership with them, and to return up the rivers <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> and <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Jaune</name> to hunt.


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n39081501" n="1">Codex N begins with a list, about a page and a half long, of items sent to <name type="place" key="Washington D.C.">Washington</name> from <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>; it has been placed in <ref n="lc.jrn.1806.postexpedition.part2" type="related">Postexpeditionary Miscellany</ref>. The first dated entry is for August 15, 1806, but as noted for August 14, there is in fact considerable doubt where the events of August 14 leave off and those of August 15 begin. This confusion is most unusual in the journals.</note>
            <note xml:id="n39081502" n="2">The sheer numbers of whites in the East often impressed Western Indian chiefs more than anything else on their travels to <name type="place" key="Washington D.C.">Washington</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n39081503" n="3">For reflections on these negotiations, see Ronda (LCAI), 245–48.</note>
            <note xml:id="n39081504" n="4">For <name type="person" key="Little Crow (Ka-goh-ha-me)">Little Crow, or Little Raven</name>, see <ref n="lc.jrn.1804-10-29" type="related">October 29, 1804</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n39081505" n="5">
               <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name> spent another four years in the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rockies</name> and on the upper <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>. In his wanderings he had various hairbreadth escapes from the <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name> and considerably increased white knowledge of the region, especially the area of the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone Plateau">Yellowstone Plateau</name> and <name type="place" key="Jackson Hole">Jackson Hole</name>. See <ref n="lc.jrn.v02.appendix.a" type="related">Appendix A</ref>. <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name> added some reflections of his own to his account of this incident, which he thought "shows how easily men may be weaned from the habits of civilized life to the ruder but scarcely less fascinating manners of the woods." Coues (HLC), 3:1182; Harris.</note>
            <note xml:id="n39081506" n="6">Whether the <name type="native_nation" key="Crow Indians">Crows</name> went as far as <name type="place" key="New Mexico">New Mexico</name> to steal mules from the Spanish settlements, or obtained them from other tribes closer to <name type="place" key="New Mexico">New Mexico</name>, is not clear. The former is by no means impossible.</note>
            <note xml:id="n39081507" n="7">
               <name type="person" key="Black Moccasin (Omp-se-ha-ra)">Black Moccasin</name> of the <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians, Awaxawi">Awatixa Hidatsa</name> village <name type="place" key="Metaharta (Metehartar) village">Metaharta</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n39081508" n="8">Simlins, which are summer squashes.</note>
            <note xml:id="n39081509" n="9">This would be <name type="place" key="Ruptáre (Rooptahee) village">Rooptahee, or Ruptáre, village</name>; see <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> entry of <ref n="lc.jrn.1804-10-27" type="related">October 27, 1804</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n39081510" n="10">
               <name type="person" key="Big White (Sheheke)">Big White</name>, or <name type="person" key="Big White (Sheheke)">Sheheke</name>, and <name type="person" key="Little Crow (Ka-goh-ha-me)">Little Crow</name> were the principal chiefs of <name type="place" key="Mitutanka (Matootonha) village">Mitutanka</name>, but
<name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> seems to have visited only with <name type="person" key="Little Crow (Ka-goh-ha-me)">Little Crow</name> on this day.</note>
            <note xml:id="n39081511" n="11">See <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> entries of <ref n="lc.jrn.1806-08-14" type="related">August 14</ref> and 15.</note>
            <note xml:id="n39081512" n="12">
               <name type="person" key="Dickson, Joseph">Dickson</name> and <name type="person" key="Hancock, Forrest">Hancrock</name>; see <ref n="lc.jrn.1806-08-12" type="related">August 12</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n39081513" n="13">
               <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name>. The next four years would give him fame as an explorer in his own right; see 
<name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> entry for the day.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-08-14" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-08-16" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
