<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1803-11-23">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">November 23, 1803</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2003</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic
        Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            2</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">August 30, 1803–August 24, 1804</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1986</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">105-110</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
         <geoDecl datum="WGS" xml:id="lc.geo.1803-11-23.01">
            <placeName>Cape Girardeau</placeName>
            <geo>37.338 -89.49</geo>
            <note>Cape Girardeau County, MO, just north of Cape Girardeau</note>
         </geoDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journal Entries</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2003-12-15</date>
            <date/>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>
            <name/>Initial creation Transcribed</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-04-12</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1803-11-23">November 23, 1803</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1803-11-23.01"
              ref="lc.geo.1803-11-23.01">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Novr. 23rd 1803</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">N. Pryor</name>, the man who was hunting
          yesterday has not yet arrived, had several guns fired again and the horn wlown [blown];
          waited untill half after 7 OC. and then set out without him    (1) about a
          mile from the commencement of this course a small creek puts in on the Lard. quatr. and
          abot ¾ of a mile another about the same size puts in on the same side.—
          <ref target="n02112301" n="1"/>(2) this creek puts in on the Stard. qutr. nearly
          oposite the mouth of the last on the Lard. qutr. on the commencement of this course—
             these creeks appear to be about the same size and may be recconed from 10
          to 15 miles long—    1¼ miles from the last creek a large creek puts in on
          Stad. qtr. oposite to the mouth of this creek a small 
          <hi rend="italic">Isld.</hi>called 
          <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="place" key="Rock Island">rock Island</name>.</hi>
                  <ref target="n02112302" n="2"/>   so called from the base of it being formed
          of a slate rock, there are some willows growing on it—    I know no names for
          these creeks— except the last which is called 
          <name type="place" key="Sexton Creek">East Lacrush</name>,
          <ref target="n02112303" n="3"/>this creek appeared to be about 40 yards wide at it's
          mouth and may recconed at 30 miles in length; passing by land from 
          <name type="place" key="Fort Massac (Ill.)">Massac</name>to 
          <name type="place" key="Cape Girardeau, Mo.">Cape 
          <hi rend="italic">Jeradeau</hi>
                  </name>
                  <ref target="n02112304" n="4"/>you cross the waters of this creek; the distance between
          these two places is about 35 miles through a low lagoon country    (3) about ¾
          of a mile from the commencement of this course, and just above a bold point which juts
          in, to the river, on the Lard. quarter, a large Creek puts in called 
          <name type="place" key="Cape La Croix (La'crush) Creek">Cape 
          <hi rend="italic">La'crush</hi>
                  </name>
                  <ref target="n02112305" n="5"/>from the rocky point just mentioned which has obtained
          that name—    this creek is about 25 yards wide at the mouth and may be
          recconed 30 m. long.    we have passed but three Islds. including 
          <name type="place" key="Rock Island">Rock Island</name>which was the first, a small one
          on the Lard. &amp; one 3½ miles from 
          <name type="place" key="Cape Girardeau, Mo.">Cape Jeradeau</name>which we left on the
          Stard.    this last is reather a sandbar than &amp; Island    some
          small parts of it are covered with 
          <hi rend="italic">willows</hi>&amp; small 
          <hi rend="italic">cottonwood.—</hi>   This sand-bar discribed was a
          continuation of an Island about ¾ of a mile long commencing just below 
          <name type="place" key="Cape Girardeau, Mo.">Cape Jeradeau</name>and which was hid from
          my view when I made the foregoing remark with respect to it—    (4) landed at
          the cape and called on the 
          <name type="person" key="Lorimier, Louis">Commandt.</name>
                  <ref target="n02112306" n="6"/>and delivered the letters of introduction which I had
          for him, from 
          <name type="person" key="Bissell, Daniel">Capt. Danl. Bisselle</name>,
          <ref target="n02112307" n="7"/>and a 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Mr. Drewyer</name>
                  <ref target="n02112308" n="8"/>a nephew of the 
          <name type="person" key="Lorimier, Louis">Commandt's</name>. sent the boat on with
          orders to come too for the night at Old 
          <name type="place" key="Cape Girardeau, Mo.">Cape Jeradeau</name>which is a point of
          land on the Lard. about 2 miles distant from the 
          <name type="person" key="Lorimier, Louis">Commandt's</name>. tho' this was the first
          place of his residence on his settleing himself in this country which he told me was
          about eight years since. On my arrival at the 
          <name type="person" key="Lorimier, Louis">Comds</name>. dwelling I was informed that he
          had gone out with his family to attend a Horse rase he himself being as I afterwards
          understood a party to the rase—    I persued him to the rase grown found him
          and delivered him my credentials, he treated me with much politeness in his way; the
          rase was just over before I reached the grown &amp; the 
          <name type="person" key="Lorimier, Louis">Comdt</name>. was busied for some time in
          settling the disputes which had arrisen in consequence of odds being given among the by
          betters; the 
          <name type="person" key="Lorimier, Louis">Comdts</name>. horse lost the main rase, but
          won by six inches the by betts, the odds generally given against him in the by betts was
          12 feet; the Comdt. lost four horses on the rase which had been valued at $200.—
             this seane reminded me very much of their small raises in 
          <name type="place" key="Kentucky">Kentucky</name>among the uncivilized backwoodsmen, nor
          did the subsequent disorder which took place in consequence of the descision of the
          judges of the rase at all lessen the resembleance; one fellow contrary to the descision
          of the judges swore he had won &amp; was carrying off not only his own horse but that
          also of his competitor; but the other being the stoutest of the two dismounted him and
          took both horses in turn; it is not extrawdinary that these people should be disorderly
             they are almost entirely emegrant from the fronteers of 
          <name type="place" key="Kentucky">Kentuckey</name>&amp; 
          <name type="place" key="Tennessee">Tennessee</name>, and are the most dessolute and
          abandoned even among these people; they are men of desperate fortunes, but little to
          loose either character or property—    they bett very high on these raises in
          proportion to their wealth; it is not uncommon for them to risk the half or even the
          whole of their personal property on a single wager; their property consists principally
          in Horses and black Cattle; the 
          <name type="person" key="Lorimier, Louis">Comdt</name>. seemed to bear his loss with
          much cheerfullness.    a son of his immediately made another rase for $600.
          these people have some specia
          <ref target="n02112309" n="9"/>among them, but their circulating medium is principally
          Horses, Cattle, Cotton &amp; lead—Horses from 50 to 200$. Cattle from 8 to 10$, Cotton
          &amp; lead are less fluctuating in their price, the former is estimated a $100 a Ton and
          the latter at $80 pr. Ton—    this settlement was commenced by the present 
          <name type="person" key="Lorimier, Louis">Comdt</name>. eight years since, with one
          other family, about 2 years after it began to form prety rapidly from the encouragement
          given these setlers by the Spanish government    it has now increased to the
          number 1,111 persons, they are allowed a bounty in lands proportioned to the number of
          their respective familys which are called head rights; this land is entered, surveyed
          and recorded by the clerk of the 
          <name type="person" key="Lorimier, Louis">Comdt</name>.
          <ref target="n02112310" n="10"/>which may or may not be confirmed by the Crown of 
          <name type="place" key="Spain">Spain</name>wich however is necessary to complete the
          title.—</p>
               <p>The 
          <name type="person" key="Lorimier, Louis">Comdt</name>. is Canadian by birth of French
          extraction; he was on[c]e a very considerable trader among the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Shawnee Indians">Shawness</name>&amp; 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Delaware Indians">Delewares</name>; About the year 1781
          a party under the command of 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, George Rogers">Genl. George Rogers Clark</name>of 
          <name type="place" key="Kentucky">Kentuckey</name>burnt the Store of this man—which
          stood at the mouth of a small creek a branch of the East branch of the 
          <name type="place" key="Miami River">Great Miami</name>of the 
          <name type="place" key="Ohio River">Ohio</name>which still beares the name of 
          <name type="person" key="Lorimier, Louis">Lorimier</name>, which has since become more
          remarkable as it forms one point in the boundary line between the N. Western tribes and
          the U.S. made with them at 
          <name type="place" key="Greenville, Ohio">Geenevile</name>by 
          <name type="person" key="Wayne, Anthony">Genl. Wayne</name>in the year 1795—
             the value of the property 
          <name type="place" key="Lorimier, Louis">Lorimier</name>lost on this occasion is
          estimated at 20 thousand dollars, this broke him as a mercht. bt he seems to have
          entirely recovered his losses, and is now a man of very considerable property; he is a
          man about 5 F 8 I high, dark skin hair and [e]yes; he is remarkable for having once had
          a remarkable suit of hair; he was very cheerfull &amp; I took occasion to mention this
          to him    he informed me that it was on[c]e so long that it touched the grond
          when he stood errect—nor was it much less remarkable for it's thickness; this I could
          readily believe from it's present appearance, he is about 60 years of age, and yet
          scarcely a grey hair in his head; which reaches now when cewed (the manner in which he
          dresses it) nearly as low as his knees, and it is proportionally thick; he appears yet
          quite active—    this uncommon cue falls dow his back to which it is kept
          close by means of a leather gerdle confined around his waist—    this man
          agreeably to the custom of many of the Canadian Traders has taken to himself a wife from
          among the aborigines of the country    
          <name type="person" key="Bougainville, Charlotte Pemanpieh">his wife</name>is a 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Shawnee Indians">Shawnee</name>woman,
          <ref target="n02112311" n="11"/>from her complexion is half blooded only.   
          she is a very desent woman and if we may judge from her present appearance has been very
          handsome when young, she dresses after the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Shawnee Indians">Shawnee</name>manner with a stroud
          leggings and mockinsons, differing however from them in her linin which seemed to be
          drawn beneath her girdle of her stroud, as also a short Jacket with long sleeves over
          her linin with long sleeves more in the stile of the French Canadian women; by this
          woman 
          <name type="person" key="Lorimier, Louis">Lorimier</name>has a large family of very
          handsome Children three of which have attained the age of puberty; the daughter is
          remarkably handsome &amp; dresses in a plain yet fashionable stile or such as is now
          Common in the Atlantic States among the respectable people of the middle class.
             she is an agreeable affible girl, &amp; much the most descent looking
          feemale I hae seen since I left the settlement in 
          <name type="place" key="Kentucky">Kentuckey</name>a little below 
          <name type="place" key="Louisville, Ky.">Louisville</name>.
          <ref target="n02112312" n="12"/>   The 
          <name type="person" key="Lorimier, Louis">Comdt.</name>pressed me to stay to supper
          which I did, the lady of the family presided, and with much circumspection performed the
          honours of the table: supper being over which was really a comfortable and desent onen I
          bid the family an afectionate adieeu—;    the 
          <name type="person" key="Lorimier, Louis">Comdt</name>. had a Couple of horses paraded,
          and one of his sons conducted me to Old 
          <name type="place" key="Cape Girardeau, Mo.">Cape Jeradeau</name>, the distance by the
          rout we went was 3 miles    here I found my boat and people   
          landed for the night.
          <ref target="n02112313" n="13"/>   found 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name>very unwell.</p>
               <p>The district of 
          <name type="person" key="Lorimier, Louis">Commandant Lorimiere</name>estends from the
          grand bend of the 
          <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name>to 
          <name type="place" key="Apple Creek (Mo.)">Apple River</name>
                  <ref target="n02112314" n="14"/>without limitation back    this settlement
          extends the distance of sixty miles W. from the river as far as the 
          <name type="place" key="Saint Francis (Tanslagrass) River">river St. Francis</name>.
          West from 
          <name type="place" key="Cape Girardeau, Mo.">Cape Jeredeau</name>about 16 miles is a
          large settlement of duch descendants who have emigrated from the 
          <name type="place" key="Atlantic Ocean">Atlantic</name>States;
          <ref target="n02112315" n="15"/>these people here preserve their uniform charracter, of
          〈sober,〉 temperate, laborious and honest people, they have erected two grist mills and a
          saw-mill—    The estimated distance by the french watermen to New
          <name type="place" key="Cape Girardeau, Mo.">Cape Jerd</name>: is 42 miles from the
          mouth of 
          <name type="place" key="Ohio">Ohio</name>.—    the old cape is 2 miles dist.
          bearing N. 10 E.</p>
               <p>
                  <table rows="8" cols="4">
                     <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Novr. 23d</hi>
                     </head>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Course</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Time</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">dist.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">References</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">h m</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">mils</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 30 W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">— 50</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">2 —</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Creek Lard. 1 mil. Creek Lard. ¾ (1)</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 3  W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">— 45</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">1 ¼</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Crk. Stad. oposite last 1 ¼ Crk. (2)</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 50 W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">2 30</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">2 ½</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">¾ large creek (3)</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 43 W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">3 15</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">5 ¼</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">New 
                <name type="place" key="Cape Girardeau, Mo.">Cape Jeradeau</name>(4)</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 10 E</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                           <hi rend="underline">1 15</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                           <hi rend="underline">2</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Old Cape Do.—    staid all night on
                Lard qutr.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">8 35</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">13 —</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n02112301" n="1">These creeks are difficult to identify; 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>is in the general area above 
        <name type="place" key="Commerce, Mo.">Commerce</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Scott County, Mo.">Scott County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Missouri">Missouri</name>, some 40 miles above the mouth of 
        <name type="place" key="Ohio River">the Ohio</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n02112302" n="2">Cumings show 
        <name type="place" key="Rock Island">Rock Island</name>directly across from 
        <name type="place" key="Cape La Croix (La'crush) Creek">Cape Le Croix</name>. Cumings, map
        3.</note>
            <note xml:id="n02112303" n="3">Apparently modern 
        <name type="place" key="Sexton Creek">Sexton Creek</name>, in 
        <name type="place" key="Alexander County, Ill.">Alexander County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Illinois">Illinois</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n02112304" n="4">
               <name type="place" key="Cape Girardeau, Mo.">Cape Girardeau</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Cape Girardeau County, Mo.">Cape Girardeau County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Missouri">Missouri</name>, may have received its name from a
        French ensign. The earliest settlement (
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>Old 
        <name type="place" key="Cape Girardeau, Mo.">Cape Girardeau</name>) was on the rock
        promontory above the present site of the city. 
        <name type="person" key="Lorimier, Louis">Louis Lorimier</name>may have settled there with
        a band of 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Shawnee Indians">Shawnee</name>and 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Delaware Indians">Delaware</name>Indians as early as 1786,
        but he was certainly established there by 1793. He developed a thriving trading post and
        encouraged Anglo-American emigration into the area. The town remained the local seat of
        government after the Lousiana Purchase but declined somewhat after the War of 1812. 
        <hi rend="italic">Missouri Guide,</hi>199–202; Houck, 2:167–92.</note>
            <note xml:id="n02112305" n="5">Cumings refers to 
        <name type="place" key="Cape La Croix (La'crush) Creek">Cape Le Croix</name>, also called 
        <name type="place" key="Cape La Croix (La'crush) Creek">La Bruche</name>. Cumings, 67.
        Present 
        <name type="place" key="Cape La Croix (La'crush) Creek">Cape La Croix Creek</name>divides 
        <name type="place" key="Scott County, Mo.">Scott</name>and 
        <name type="place" key="Cape Girardeau County, Mo.">Cape Girardeau</name>counties.</note>
            <note xml:id="n02112306" n="6">
               <name type="person" key="Lorimier, Louis">Louis Lorimier</name>was born near 
        <name type="place" key="Montreal">Montreal</name>. He and his father established
        "Laramie's Station" to trade with the Indians in 
        <name type="place" key="Ohio">Ohio</name>. As a Loyalist during the Revolutionary War, 
        <name type="person" key="Lorimier, Louis">Lorimier</name>led raiding parties of Indians
        into 
        <name type="place" key="Kentucky">Kentucky</name>; 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, George Rogers">George Rogers Clark</name>burned 
        <name type="person" key="Lorimier, Louis">Lorimier's</name>establishment as an enemy base
        in 1782. Within a few years he had moved to Spanish 
        <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name>and received a large land grant to
        establish a settlement for Indians, partly as a defense against possible American
        invasion. In spite of these indications of anti-American attitudes, he became an Indian
        agent for the United States after the Louisiana Purchase. As 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>notes, "Laramie's Store" was
        specifically named as a location point in the Greenville Treaty of 1795, and the name is
        still perpetuated by the modern 
        <name type="place" key="Lake Loramie (Ohio)">Lake Loramie</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Shelby County, Ohio">Shelby County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Ohio">Ohio</name>. Quaife (MLJO), 59 n. 1; Osgood (FN), 42 n. 4;
        Houck, 2:169–81; Nasatir (BLC), 2:771; Nasatir (SWV), 71–72 n. 27, 297–98 n. 22; 
        <hi rend="italic">Ohio Guide,</hi>558.</note>
            <note xml:id="n02112307" n="7">
               <name type="person" key="Bissell, Daniel">Daniel Bissell</name>joined the army in 1791; at
        this time he was in command at 
        <name type="place" key="Fort Massac (Ill.)">Fort Massac</name>. He became a brigadier
        general in the War of 1812. Heitman, 221.</note>
            <note xml:id="n02112308" n="8">Perhaps 
        <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">George Drouillard</name>, engaged by 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>at 
        <name type="place" key="Fort Massac (Ill.)">Fort Massac</name>on November 11, but the
        style of the reference suggests that it may be some relative of 
        <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">George's</name>. It appears that 
        <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">George Drouillard</name>may have been related
        to 
        <name type="person" key="Lorimier, Louis">Louis Lorimier</name>, especially since 
        <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">George</name>considered himself a resident of
        the 
        <name type="place" key="Cape Girardeau, Mo.">Cape Girardeau</name>district. 
        <name type="person" key="Droullard, Peter">Peter Droullard</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Droulliez, Jean Baptiste">Jean Baptiste Droulliez</name>were
        early 
        <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>settlers of the late eighteenth
        century. Allowing for the flexible spelling of the era, either might have been related to 
        <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">George</name>and possibly was the "
        <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Mr. Drewyer</name>" who wrote the letter.
        Skarsten (GDLC), 20–21; Huck, 2:150, 166.</note>
            <note xml:id="n02112309" n="9">Coins (specie) were usually in short supply on the frontier
        at this time.</note>
            <note xml:id="n02112310" n="10">The clerk was the 
        <name type="person" key="Cousin, Barthelemi">Barthelemi Cousin</name>. Houck,
        2:180–81.</note>
            <note xml:id="n02112311" n="11">
               <name type="person" key="Bougainville, Charlotte Pemanpieh">Charlotte Pemanpieh
        Bougainville</name>. Ibid., 2:170 and n. 9, 179 n. 21.</note>
            <note xml:id="n02112312" n="12">Among these children were 
        <name type="person" key="Lorimier, Louis, Jr.">Louis, Junior</name>, a trader like his
        father, 
        <name type="person" key="Lorimier, Auguste">Auguste Bougainville</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Lorimier, William">William</name>, who received appointments to 
        <name type="place" key="West Point, New York">West Point</name>, and 
        <name type="person" key="Lorimier, Agatha">Agatha</name>, perhaps the attractive daughter 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>noticed. Ibid., 1:231, 2:182, 190,
        381.</note>
            <note xml:id="n02112313" n="13">Near the promontory where the settlement was first
        located, north of the later town, in 
        <name type="place" key="Cape Girardeau County, Mo.">Cape Girardeau</name>County.</note>
            <note xml:id="n02112314" n="14">The District of 
        <name type="place" key="Cape Girardeau, Mo.">Cape Girardeau</name>extended from 
        <name type="place" key="Apple Creek (Mo.)">Apple Creek</name>to 
        <name type="place" key="Tywappity Bottom">Tywappity Bottom</name>. Ibid., 2:167.</note>
            <note xml:id="n02112315" n="15">These "duch" were German-Swiss and North Carolinians of
        German descent who settled along 
        <name type="place" key="White Water River">Whitewater River</name>. Ibid.,
        2:187–89.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1803-11-22" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1803-11-24" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
