<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-08-17">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">August 17, 1805</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic
        Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            5</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">July 28–November 1, 1805</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1989</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">109-117</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">204-206</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">126-127</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jw">Joseph Whitehouse</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            11</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of Joseph Whitehouse, May 14, 1804–April 2,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1997</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">272-275</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
         <geoDecl datum="WGS" xml:id="lc.geo.1805-08-17.01">
            <placeName/>
            <geo>44.9987 -112.8541</geo>
            <note>Established camp at "Camp Fortunate," Beaverhead River, Beaverhead County, MT.</note>
         </geoDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Journal Entries</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-06-07</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-04-12</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1805-08-17">August 17, 1805</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-08-17.01"
              ref="lc.geo.1805-08-17.01">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Saturday August 17th 1805.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>This morning I arrose very early and dispatched 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name>and the Indian down the
          river.    sent 
          <name type="person" key="Shields, John">Shields</name>to hunt. I made 
          <name type="person" key="McNeal, Hugh">McNeal</name>cook the remainder of our meat which
          afforded a slight breakfast for ourselves and the Cheif.    
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name>had been gone about 2 hours
          when an Indian who had straggled some little distance down the river returned and
          reported that the whitemen were coming, that he had seen them just below.   
          they all appeared transported with joy, &amp; the chef repeated his fraturnal hug. I
          felt quite as much gratifyed at this information as the Indians appeared to be. Shortly
          after 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name>arrived with the Interpreter 
          <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbono</name>, and 
          <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">the Indian woman</name>, who proved to be a sister
          of the Chif 
          <name type="person" key="Cameahwait">Cameahwait</name>.    the meeting of
          those people was really affecting, particularly between 
          <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sah cah-gar-we-ah</name>and an Indian woman,
          <ref target="n20081701" n="1"/>who had been taken prisoner at the same time with her,
          and who had afterwards escaped from the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Minnetares</name>and rejoined her
          nation. At noon the Canoes arrived, and we had the satisfaction once more to find
          ourselves all together, with a flattering prospect of being able to obtain as many
          horses shortly as would enable us to prosicute our voyage by land should that by water
          be deemed unadvisable.</p>
               <p>
                  <figure rend="map">
                     <p>From 
              <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Three Forks of the">Three Forks</name>to 
              <name type="place" key="Travelers' Rest (Idaho)">Travelers' Rest</name>,
              <lb/>July 25–September 11, 1805
              <bibl>
                           <title>(
                <hi rend="italic">Journals</hi>
                           </title>
                           <biblScope type="volume">5</biblScope>
                           <orgName>University of Nebraska Press,</orgName>
                           <note place="inline">used with permission.)</note>
                        </bibl>
                     </p>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>We now formed our camp
          <ref target="n20081702" n="2"/>just below the junction of the forks on the Lard. side
          in a level smooth bottom covered with a fine terf of green swoard.    here we
          unloaded our canoes and arranged our baggage on shore; formed a canopy of one of our
          large sails and planted some willow brush in the ground to form a shade for the Indians
          to set under while we spoke to them, which we thought it best to do this evening.
             acordingly about 4 P. M. we called them together and through the medium of 
          <name type="person" key="Labiche, François">Labuish</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbono</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sah-cah-gar-weah</name>, we communicated to them
          fully the objects which had brought us into this distant part of the country, in which
          we took care to make them a conspicuous object of our own good wishes and the care of
          our government.    we made them sensible of their dependance on the will of
          our government for every species of merchandize as well for their defence &amp; comfort;
          and apprized them of the strength of our government and it's friendly dispositions
          towards them. we also gave them as a reason why we wished to petrate the country as far
          as the ocean to the west of them was to examine and find out a more direct way to bring
          merchandize to them.    that as no trade could be carryed on with them before
          our return to our homes that it was mutually advantageous to them as well as to
          ourselves that they should render us such aids as they had it in their power to furnish
          in order to haisten our voyage and of course our return home.    that such
          were their horses to transport our baggage without which we could not subsist, and that
          a pilot to conduct us through the mountains was also necessary if we could not decend
          the river by water.    but that we did not ask either their horses or their
          services without giving a satisfactory compensation in return.    that at
          present we wished them to collect as many horses as were necessary to transport our
          baggage to their village on the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>where we would then trade with
          them at our leasure for such horses as they could spare us.—    They appeared
          well pleased with what had been said.    the chief thanked us for friendship
          towards himself and nation &amp; declared his wish to serve us in every rispect; that he
          was sorry to find that it must yet be some time before they could be furnished with
          firearms but said they could live as they had done heretofore untill we brought them as
          we had promised.    he said they had not horses enough with them at present to
          remove our baggage to their village over the mountain, but that he would return tomorrow
          and encourage his people to come over with their horses and that he would bring his own
          and assist us.    this was complying with all we wished at present.
             we next enquired who were chiefs among them. 
          <name type="person" key="Cameahwait">Cameahwait</name>pointed out two others whom he
          said were Chiefs    we gave him a medal of the small size with the likeness of
          
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Mr. Jefferson</name>the President of the U'
          States in releif on one side and clasp hands with a pipe and tomahawk on the other, to
          the other Chiefs we gave each a small medal which were struck in the Presidency of 
          <name type="person" key="Washington, George">George Washing [
          <hi rend="italic">NB: ton</hi>]</name>Esqr.    we also gave small medals of
          the last discription to two young men whom the 1st Chief informed us wer good young men
          and much rispected among them.    we gave the 1st Chief an uniform coat shit [
          <hi rend="italic">NB: irt</hi>] a pair of scarlet legings a carrot of tobacco and some
          small articles    to each of the others we gave a shi[r]t leging handkerchief
          a knife some tobacco and a few small articles    we also distributed a good
          quantity paint mockerson awls knives beads lookingglasses &amp;c among the other Indians
          and gave them a plentifull meal of lyed [
          <hi rend="italic">NB: hull taken off by being boiled in lye</hi>] corn which was the
          first they had ever eaten in their lives.    they were much pleased with it.
             every article about us appeared to excite astonishment in ther minds; the
          appearance of the men, their arms, the canoes, our manner of working them, the back man 
          <name type="person" key="York">york</name>and the segacity of 
          <name type="person" key="Seaman">my dog</name>were equally objects of admiration. I also
          shot my air-gun which was so perfectly incomprehensible that they immediately
          denominated it the great medicine.    the idea which the indians mean to
          convey by this appellation is something that eminates from or acts immediately by the
          influence or power of the great sperit; or that in which the power of god is manifest by
          it's incomprehensible power of action.    our hunters killed 4 deer and an
          Antelope this evening of which we also gave the Indians a good proportion.   
          the cerimony of our council and smoking the pipe was in conformity of the custom of this
          nation perfomed bearfoot.    on those occasions points of etiquet are quite as
          much attended to by the Indians as among scivilized nations. To keep indians in a good
          humour you must not fatiegue them with too much business at one time.   
          therefore after the council we gave them to eat and amused them a while by shewing them
          such articles as we thought would be entertaining to them, and then renewed our
          enquiries with rispect to the country.    the information we derived was only
          a repetition of that they had given me before and in which they appeared to be so candid
          that I could not avoid yealing confidence to what they had said. 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name>and myself now concerted
          measures for our future operations, and it was mutually agreed that he should set out
          tomorrow morning with eleven men furnished with axes and other necessary tools for
          making canoes, their arms accoutrements and as much of their baggage as they could
          carry. also to take the indians 
          <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Carbono</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">the indian woman</name>with him; that on his arrival
          at the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshone</name>camp he was to leave 
          <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbono</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">the Indian woman</name>to haisten the return of the
          Indians with their horses to this place, and to proceede himself with the eleven men
          down the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>in order to examine the river and
          if he found it navigable and could obtain timber to set about making canoes immediately.
          In the mean time I was to bring on the party and baggage to the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshone</name>Camp, calculating that
          by the time I should reach that place that he would have sufficiently informed himself
          with rispect to the state of the river &amp;c. as to determine us whether to prosicute
          our journey from thence by land or water.    in the former case we should want
          all the horses which we could perchase, the latter only to hire the Indians to transport
          our baggage to the place at which we made the canoes.    in order to inform me
          as early as possible of the state of the river he was to send back one of the men with
          the necessary information as soon as he should satisfy himself on this subject.
             this plan being settled we gave orders accordingly and the men prepared for
          an early march.    the nights are very cold and the sun excessively hot in the
          day.    we have no fuel here but a few dry willow brush.    and from
          the appearance of country I am confident we shall not find game here to subsist us many
          days.    these are additional reasons why I conceive it necessary to get under
          way as soon as possible.—    this morning 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name>had delayed untill 7 A. M.
          before he set out just about which time 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name>arrived with the Indian; he
          left the canoes to come on after him, and immediately set out and joined me as has been
          before mentioned.— The sperits of the men were now much elated as the prospect of geting
          horses.</p>
               <p>
                  <table rows="2" cols="3">
                     <head>Courses and distances traveled by 
              <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="italic">August 17th 1805.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S 30° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                           <hi rend="underline">4</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">to a high Knob or hill in the forks of 
                <name type="place" key="Beaverhead (Jefferson) River">Jefferson's River</name>,
                <ref target="n20081703" n="3"/>the
                <lb/>same being 10 M. by water.    the river making a considerable
                <lb/>bend to the Stard.    the forks of this river is the most distant
                <lb/>point to which the waters of the 
                <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>are navigable.   
                of
                <lb/>course we laid up our canoes at this place and commenced our
                <lb/>voyage by land.—</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                           <hi rend="right">Miles</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                           <hi rend="double underline">4</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-08-17.02"
              ref="lc.geo.1805-08-17.01">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">August 17th Satturday 1805</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>a fair Cold morning wind S. W. the Thermometer at 42 a. 0 at Sunrise, We Set out at 7
          oClock and proceeded on to the forks    I had not proceeded on one mile before
          I saw at a distance Several Indians on horsback Comeing towards me, The 
          <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Intertrepeter</name>&amp; 
          <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Squar</name>who were before me at Some distance
          danced for the joyful Sight, and She made signs to me that they were her nation, as I
          aproached nearer them descovered one of 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt Lewis</name>party With them dressed in
          their Dress; the met me with great Signs of joy, as the Canoes were proceeding on nearly
          opposit me I turned those people &amp; Joined 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt Lewis</name>who had Camped with 16 of
          those 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Snake</name>Indians at the forks 2
          miles in advance.    those Indians Sung all the way to their Camp where the
          others had provd. a cind of Shade of Willows Stuck up in a Circle    the Three
          Chiefs with 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name>met me with great
          cordialliaty embraced and took a Seat on a white robe, the Main Chief imedeately tied to
          my hair Six Small pieces of Shells resembling 
          <hi rend="italic">perl</hi>which is highly Valued by those people and is prcured from
          the nations resideing near the 
          <hi rend="italic">Sea Coast.</hi>   we then Smoked in their fassion without
          Shoes and without much cerimoney and form.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt Lewis</name>informed me he found those
          people on the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">
                     <hi rend="italic">Columbia</hi>River</name>about 40 miles from the forks at that place
          there was a large camp of them, he had purswaded those with him to Come and See that
          what he said was the truth, they had been under great apprehension all the way, for fear
          of their being deceived. The Great Chief of this nation proved to be the brother of the 
          <hi rend="italic">Woman</hi>with us and is a man of Influence Sence &amp; easey &amp;
          reserved manners, appears to possess a great deel of Cincerity. The 〈perog〉 Canoes
          arrived &amp; unloaded—    every thing appeared to asstonish those people.
             the appearance of the men, their arms, the Canoes, the Clothing 
          <name type="person" key="York">my black Servent</name>&amp; the Segassity of 
          <name type="person" key="Seaman">Capt Lewis's Dog</name>. we Spoke a fiew words to them
          in the evening respecting our rout intentions our want of horses &amp;c. &amp; gave them
          a fiew presents &amp; medals—    〈in the eving〉 we made a number of inquires
          of those people about the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>the Countrey game &amp;c.
          The account they gave us was verry unfavourable, that the River abounded in emence
          falls, one perticularly much higher than the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">falls of the
          Missouri</name>&amp; at the place the mountains Closed So Close that it was
          impracticable to pass, &amp; that the ridge Continued on each Side of perpendicular
          Clifts inpenetratable, and that no Deer Elk or any game was to be found in that
          Countrey, aded to that they informed us that there was no timber on the river
          Sufficiently large to make Small Canoes, This information (if true is alarming)
             I deturmined to go in advance and examine the Countrey, See if those
          dificueltes presented themselves in the gloomey picture in which they painted them, and
          if the river was practiable and I could find timber to build Canoes, those Ideas &amp;
          plan appeard to be agreeable to 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt Lewis's</name>Ideas on this point, and
          I selected 11 men,
          <ref target="n20081704" n="4"/>directed them to pack up their baggage Complete
          themselves with amunition, take each an ax and Such tools as will be Soutable to build
          Canoes, and be ready to Set out at 10 oClock tomorrow morning. Those people greatly
          pleased    our hunters killed three Deer &amp; an antilope which was eaten in
          a Short time the Indians being so harrassed &amp; compelleted to move about in those
          rugid mountains that they are half Starved liveing at this time on berries &amp; roots
          which they geather in the plains. Those people are not begerley but generous, only one
          has asked me for anything and he for powder.</p>
               <p>This nation Call themselves 
          <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Cho-shon-nê</name>
                  </hi>the Chief is name 
          <hi rend="italic">Too-et-te-con'l</hi>Black Gun is his war name 
          <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="person" key="Cameahwait">Ka-me-ah-wah</name>—</hi>   or Come &amp;
          Smoke.    this Chief gave me the following name and pipe 
          <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="person" key="Cameahwait">Ka-me-ah-wah</name>.</hi>[
          <hi rend="italic">NB: exchange names,</hi>
                  <ref target="n20081705" n="5"/>
                  <hi rend="italic">custom I was called by this name afd by the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Snake Inds</name>
                  </hi>]</p>
               <p>
                  <table rows="12" cols="3">
                     <head>Course and distance of the 
              <name type="place" key="Beaverhead (Jefferson) River">River Jefferson</name>Continud
              <ref target="n20081706" n="6"/>
                     </head>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                           <hi rend="right">Augt. 15th</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 25° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  6</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">miles by water (4 by land) to the Mo: of a
                Creek 10 yards
                <lb/>wide bold Current I call 
                <name type="place" key="Divide (Willard's) Creek">Willard's
                Creek</name>   Passed a point
                <lb/>of rocks on the Stard. Side at 2 miles, one on the Lard. at
                <lb/>5 miles    passed a bold running Stream at 4 miles on the
                <lb/>Lard Side &amp; an Isld.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 22° E</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  3</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">miles by water (1 mile by land) to a small
                bottom on the
                <lb/>Lard Side    passd. a high Clift on the Stard opposit is a
                <lb/>high sloping hill</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 20° W</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  6</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">miles by water (2 by land) to a Small branch
                on the Lard
                <lb/>Side passed no wood except Scrub. clover bottom</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                           <hi rend="right">
                              <hi rend="italic">16th August</hi>
                           </hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S 18° W</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  7</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">miles by water (3 by land) to a Lard bend
                under a low bluff,
                <lb/>the river bending to the Std. under Some high land verry
                <lb/>Crooked Shallow rapid &amp; Small    passed Several Island
                <lb/>4 of them opposit each other    
                <hi rend="italic">
                              <name type="place" key="Serviceberry Valley">Service Berry Vallie</name>
                           </hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S 12° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  4</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">miles by water (2 by land) to a high Clift on
                the Stard Side
                <lb/>pass several Small Isds. &amp; Bayoes</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 50° E.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  1 ½</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">m. by water (1 by land) to the mouth of a bold
                running
                <lb/>Stream on the Lard Side opposed a Considerable rapid
                <lb/>Clifts on both Sides below high Std. 〈
                <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colters</name>〉 above rapid
                <lb/>C. &amp;</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 45° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">     ½</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">mile to the lower point of an Isld. in the
                middle.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                           <hi rend="right">
                              <hi rend="italic">17th August</hi>
                           </hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 30° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                           <hi rend="underline">10</hi>
                           <lb/>
                           <hi rend="underline">    </hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">miles by water 4 by land to a high Point in
                the forks of the
                <lb/>river.    river bending to the Stard. Side.—    met
                Indians
                <lb/>&amp; Encamped to make a Portage</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                           <hi rend="right">Miles</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                           <hi rend="double underline">39</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-08-17.03"
              ref="lc.geo.1805-08-17.01">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Saturday 17th August 1805</hi>.    a clear cold morning.
             we have been cold this Several nights under 2 blankets or Robes, over us.
             a little white frost.    the air chilley &amp; cold.   
          we took an eairly breakfast and set out    proceeded on a Short distance
             heared Some Indians Singing on Shore on L. Side    directly came
          up Several of the Snake nation a horseback.    they told us that 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name>and party was at the forks
          waiting our arival. 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name>
                  <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">the Intrepter</name>&amp; 
          <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">wife</name>went with them to 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name>Camp.    the
          natives rode back forth the Shore to See us come up with the canoes.    we
          halled the Canoes over a great nomber of Shole places and arived at 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name>Camp abt. 10 oClock A. m.
          a little below the forks, their was 20 odd of the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Snake</name>nation Indians Camped here
          which came over the Mountains with 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name>.    they
          appeared verry friendly. 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name>informed us that he had
          been over the dividing ridge or mountain to the head waters of the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbian River</name>&amp; that it is only
          about 40 miles from this place.    they drank at the head Spring of the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missourie</name>&amp; went only about a mile and
          drank at the head Spring of the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbian River</name>which ran west.
             they Saw one Indian comming towards them on horse back a considerable
          distance from the band. 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name>wavered a blanket as a
          token of friendship.    he lay close on his horse &amp; Spyed 2 of the party
          makeing towards him who had been a hunting a little off the road.    the
          Indian turned his horse and ran him untill he got to his band &amp; told the news.
             the next they met was 3 Squaws digging roots.    2 of them ran
          off Some distance    the other being old Stood her ground. 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name>Set down and gave hir Some
          Small presents. She then called the other 2 which came up and piloted them to their Camp
          which was on a branch of the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">columbian River</name>   they were on
          their way over to this Side to hunt &amp;C.    they had Some Salmon
          <ref target="n20081707" n="7"/>which they caught in the main River    they
          tell us that their is no timber on the head waters for canoes.    they also
          tell us that their is no game, but we do not believe them.    they are poor. 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name>gave them what little
          presents he had with him and they came about 20 odd with their horses with him across
          the Mt.    2 chiefs among them.    when 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name>first came near them they
          appeared frightened untill he &amp; them with him lay down their arms &amp; made motions
          of friendship.    when they met the natives took them round the neck as a
          great token of friendship.    they were uneasy &amp; afraid that they were
          taken in when they came to the forks &amp; found that we were not their as they had
          motioned, but when they Saw us they were glad, and were verry friendly to lend us their
          horses to pack meat &amp;C.    we conclude to leave the canoes at this place,
          So we unloadd and formed a Camp
          <ref target="n20081708" n="8"/>a little below the forks on a Smooth prarie on L. S.
             no timber.    we have to cook with Small willow &amp;C.
             high hills on the point between the 2 Rivers, &amp; around this valley.
             a fiew Scattering pitch pine on them.    this valley Smooth &amp;
          pleasant    the natives horses appear good and in tollarable order, but they
          are verry poor    nothing to be Seen amongst them but thier horses &amp; 2 or
          3 guns, but no ammunition.    they are dressed tollarably well in antelope
          &amp; Mountain Rams Skins well dressed.    a fiew beeds hung in their ears
          with mussel Shells &amp;C    their hair Short the most of them.   
          we expect they git their horses from the Spanis and what other little art articles they
          have, but they have no knives tommahawks nor no weapons of war except their bow &amp;
          arrows.    it is only by their acct. 8 day travel to the South to the Spanish
          country.    our officers 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captains Lewis</name>&amp; 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>told the head chief
          <ref target="n20081709" n="9"/>of them that they wanted to by their horses to take our
          baggage over the Mountains.    the Chief Said they would let us have the use
          of their horses &amp; promised to assist us over as much as lay in their power. So they
          gave them out considerable of different kinds of marchandize.    gave the
          chief a meddel    made another chief &amp; gave him a meddle also.
             gave the head chief a uniform coat &amp; Shirt &amp; arm bands &amp;C
          &amp;C. 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name>Shot the airgun, which
          they thought a great meddicine &amp; Shewed them a nomber of Strange things to them.
             4 deer &amp; 2 antelopes killed by the hunters this day. 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name>tells us that the game is
          verry Scarse on the mountain    he was about 3 days with[out] meat.
             the natives gave 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name>ear bobs to put in ears
          and an ornament to Spread over his Shoulders, which was made of white wezels
          <ref target="n20081710" n="10"/>tails &amp; fastened on an otters Skin.   
          they fixed off all the men in the Same way who were returning with 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name>.    they take
          us round the neck and Sweze us in token of friendship as they have a practice in Stead
          of Shakeing hands</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-08-17.04"
              ref="lc.geo.1805-08-17.01">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Saturday 17th.</hi>   A fine morning. We proceeded on about
          2 miles, and discovered a number of the natives, of the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Snake</name>nation, coming along the
          bank on the South side. 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Lewis</name>had been as far as the
          waters of the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia river</name>and met them there.
          <ref target="n20081711" n="11"/>We continued on about two miles further to a place
          where the river forks, and there halted and encamped,
          <ref target="n20081712" n="12"/>after much fatigue and difficulty. The water is so
          shallow that we had to drag the canoes, one at a time, almost all the way. The distance
          across from this place to the waters of the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia river</name>is about 40 miles, and the
          road or way said to be good. There were about 20 of the natives came over with 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Lewis</name>and had the same number
          of horses. Here we unloaded the canoes, and had a talk with the Indians; and agreed with
          them that they should lend us some of their horses to carry our baggage to the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia river</name>.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-08-17.05"
              ref="lc.geo.1805-08-17.01">
            <sp who="jw">
               <speaker>Whitehouse</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Saturday 17th August 1805</hi>.    a clear cold morning.
             we lay last night with 2 blankets or Robes over us &amp; lay cold.
             Some frost this morning.    we took an eairly breakfast and Set
          out.    proceeded on a Short distance.    heared a nomber of Indians
          a Singing on L.    Side.    directly their came Several of the Snake
          nation
          <ref target="n20081713" n="13"/>Came to us &amp; told us that 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name>&amp; party was at the
          forks.    
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name>
                  <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">our Intrepter</name>&amp; 
          <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">wife</name>went with the natives rode their horses
          to the forks.    they kept rideing back &amp; forward to See us comeing up
          with the canoes.    we were obledged to hale the canoes a great part of the
          way untill we got to 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name>es Camp a little below the
          forks    their was 20 odd of the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Snake</name>nation Camped with 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name>.    they
          appeared harmeless &amp; friendly.    
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name>informed us that he had
          been over the mountain on the head waters of 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbian River</name>and that this band was
          Camped on Sd. waters and Creek or Small River on their way across to this place a
          hunting.    the first they Saw was one Spy they had Some distance a head on
          horse back.    
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name>Swung &amp; held up a
          blanket as a token of friendship, but as it hapened 2 of the men were a hunting one on
          each Side of him, which frightned him as he Suposed they wished to take prisoner
             turned about his horse &amp; rode verry Seedy out of his road &amp; made no
          halt untill he got to the band, &amp; told his people the news.    they met 3
          <ref target="n20081714" n="14"/>Squaws 〈2〉 on the Side of the mountain a digging roots
          2 of them ran off, the other being old Stood hir ground.    
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name>came or went up to hir
          &amp; gave hir Some Small presents, and Shewed everry mark of friendship.   
          She then called up the other 2 and they piloted 〈them〉 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name>&amp; party to the band,
          which received them with a great deal of fear at first.    appared frightened
          until they lay down their guns and made Some tokens &amp; motions of friendship.
             the natives then put their arms around their or our peoples necks &amp;
          appeared glad to See them and used them friendly.    they had Some Salmon
          which they had brought with them from the main river.    it is only about 40
          miles over the mount to the head waters of the other R.    the[y] drank at the
          head waters or Spring of the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missourie</name>and went only abt. a mile and
          drank out of the head Spring of the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbian</name>River which ran west.
             the natives tell us that their is no timber large enofe for canoes on the
          head waters &amp;c    
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name>got 2[0] odd of the band
          to come over with their horses, only 3 women with them.    we conclude to
          leave the canoes at this place and git horses of the natives to take our baggage over
          the mountains.    So we unloaded the canoes and formed a Camp on a Smooth
          prarie on L. Side.    the grass high, but no timber    we could git
          no timber to burn but Small dry willow Sticks about as big as a mans finger &amp;c.
             a high hill in the point or between the forks of the River.   
          high hills around this valley.    the hunters killed 3 deer &amp; 2 goats this
          day.    
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name>informes us that the game
          is verry Scarse on the mountain, &amp; that they were without any thing of account to
          eat for 2 or three days, but the natives tell us that their is pleanty of fish on the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">columbian River</name>Such as Salmon &amp;c.
             our officers told the natives that we wanted to git their horses to take
          our baggage over the Mountain &amp; wanted to buy Some from them also    So
          they Gave them considerable of marchandize divided it among them all.    they
          consented to let us have their horses &amp; assist us over the mo.    they
          tell us that it is only about 8 days travvel a South course to the Spanish country,
          <ref target="n20081715" n="15"/>but these Indians git but little trade amongst them
          &amp;c—</p>
               <p>Saturday August 17th    A Clear cold morning; the weather was so cold last
          night, that our party had to lay under 2 buffalo robes each in order to keep themselves
          warm, We took an early break fast and set out, we had proceeded on but a short distance
          when we were alarmed by several voices that were singing—    the Voices, came
          from the South side of the River.    We halted our Canoes, when a number of
          the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Snake</name>Nation of Indians came to
          us; these were the Persons who we had heard singing; They informed us by 
          <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">our Interpreter (the Indian Woman)</name>that 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Lewis</name>&amp; party was at the
          Forks of the River waiting for us.—    
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain Clark</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">our french Interpreter</name>&amp; 
          <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">his Indian Wife</name>, went off with these Indians—
             The 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Snake</name>Indians that came to us,
          rode very fine horses, 〈which〉 and they let 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain Clark</name>&amp; the 
          <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Interpreter</name>&amp; 
          <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">wife</name>ride 2 of them to the forks of the River.
             We proceeded on, the Indians riding their horses back &amp; forward to see
          us coming on, with our Canoes.    We were obliged to hawl our Canoes a great
          part of the way over shallow places, till we arrived at the place, where 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Lewis</name>was encamped, which lay
          a small distance below the forks of this River.    We found between 20 &amp;
          30 of the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Snake</name>Nation of Indians encamped
          with him.—</p>
               <p>The Indians appeared to be very harmless &amp; inoffensive, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Lewis</name>informed us, that he had
          crossed the Mountains that lay a head of us &amp; had gone on to the head Waters of 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>, and that he had found
          Some of this band of Indians, encamped on the head waters of said River, &amp; a part of
          them at a Creek or small River, on their way across the Mountains to this place; on a
          hunting party.—    he likewise mentioned, that the first Indian of this party
          that they had seen, was one of their spies, that was some distance a head of the party
          on horseback, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Lewis</name>swung a blanket as a
          token of friendship to this Indian, but two of [his, 
          <hi rend="italic">erased</hi>] 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Lewis's</name>party who were hunting
          happen'd to be on each side of 〈him〉 that Indian which frightened 〈the Indian〉 him,
          &amp; he supposing that 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Lewis</name>&amp; party wanted to
          take him prisoner, he turned about his horse, and rode very speedily out of his Road,
          &amp; made no halt, untill he got to his band, to who he told the news &amp; of what
          people he had seen; that afterwards they had met with 3 of their Squaws on the side of
          the mountain who were digging Roots, 2 of these squaws ran off, &amp; the other being
          old &amp; feeble stood her ground.    
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Lewis</name>went up to this Squaw,
          and made her some small presents, and showed her every mark of friendship.   
          This Squaw then called to the other two, who came to her, and those 3 Squaws piloted 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Lewis</name>&amp; his party to their
          band; who received them with a great deal of fear at first, &amp; appeared to be much
          frightened, untill 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Lewis</name>&amp; his party laid
          down their guns, &amp; made some motions of friendship, the Indians then hung their Arms
          (Bows &amp; Arrows) round their own &amp; our Mens necks &amp; appeared very glad to see
          them, &amp; used them very friendly.    These Indians, had some Salmon with
          them which they had brought from the main 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>.    they
          mentioned to us that it is only 40 Miles across the mountains to the head waters of 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>.    The party
          that was with 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Lewis</name>mentioned that they had
          drank at the head water or Source of the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Mesouri River</name>, which was a large spring.—
             They also inform'd us that about one Mile from that large spring, that they
          had also drank water out of another spring, which was the head Waters of 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>, The 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Snake</name>Indians informed us by our
          
          <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Interpreter</name>, that there was no
          timber on the other side of the Mountains, large enough to make Canoes, near to the head
          of 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>—    
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Lewis</name>had persuaded 20 odd 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Snake</name>Indians of that band to
          come over with their horses with him.—    Our officers concluded to leave our
          Canoes at this place, &amp; to get horses from those Indians to transport our baggage
          across the mountains, to 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>.—    We unloaded
          our Canoes at that place, &amp; formid a Camp in a smooth Priari, lying on the So—
             side of the River; where the Grass was very high.    We found no
          timber here, &amp; was forced to make use of small dry willows to cook our Meat with.—
             In the fork of this River, on a point, lay a high hill, and hills all round
          where we 〈are〉 were encamped at, which is in a Valley.    Our hunters killed 3
          deer &amp; 2 Goats this day, which they brought to our Camp.    
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Lewis</name>informed us that Game is
          very scarce to be found on the mountains, &amp; that they were without any thing of any
          account to eat for 3 days, The indians inform'd us, that there is plenty of fish to be
          caught in the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>, such as Salmon, &amp;ca.
             Our Officers informed the Indians that they wanted to get their horses, to
          carry our baggage over the Mountains, and that they would purchase some of them also,
          &amp; that they would give them some Merchandise for them, The Indians consented to the
          officers proposals, The officers gave the Indians some Merchandise for part of their
          horses, &amp; they agreed to assist us across the mountains.    They informed
          us that it is only 8 days travel, from that place to where the Spaniards have a
          settlement, which they told us lays a South course from this place but that they have
          very little trade with them</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n20081701" n="1">Rees says her name was 
        <name type="person" key="Pop-pank">Pop-pank, "Jumping Fish,"</name>from the manner in
        which she jumped through the water of a stream in escaping from the 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name>. Rees, 4, 9.</note>
            <note xml:id="n20081702" n="2">"
        <name type="place" key="Camp Fortunate (Mont.)">Camp Fortunate</name>," in 
        <name type="place" key="Beaverhead County, Mont.">Beaverhead County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>, lies just below the forks of 
        <name type="place" key="Beaverhead (Jefferson) River">the Beaverhead</name>, where a part
        of the party would remain until 
        <ref n="1805-08-24" type="related">August 24</ref>. The site is now under 
        <name type="place" key="Clark Canyon Dam and Reservoir">Clark Canyon Reservoir</name>. 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>map 66.</note>
            <note xml:id="n20081703" n="3">Now an island surrounded by 
        <name type="place" key="Clark Canyon Dam and Reservoir">Clark Canyon Reservoir</name>. 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>map 66.</note>
            <note xml:id="n20081704" n="4">Including Sergeants 
        <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Pryor</name>, Privates 
        <name type="person" key="Collins, John">Collins</name>, 
        <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name>, 
        <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Cruzatte</name>, 
        <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name>, 
        <name type="person" key="Windsor, Richard">Windsor</name>, and four others unidentified. 
        <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name>accompanied 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>as far as the 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshone</name>village. Appleman (LC),
        372 n. 111.</note>
            <note xml:id="n20081705" n="5">Such exchange of names, creating a ceremonial kinship
        between the persons concerned, was a custom of several Western tribes. However, Rees, 7,
        believes the name given 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>was not the chief's name but was
        Kim-ah-pawn, which he also interprets as "come and smoke," which he derived from 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>smoking with the 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshones</name>on 
        <ref n="1805-08-20" type="related">August 20, 1805</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n20081706" n="6">Here in Codex G, p. 67, 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>has inserted accumulated courses for
        August 15, 16, and 17, 1805.</note>
            <note xml:id="n20081707" n="7">Salmon, 
        <hi rend="italic">Oncorhynchus</hi>sp., of an unknown type.</note>
            <note xml:id="n20081708" n="8">Called 
        <name type="place" key="Camp Fortunate (Mont.)">Camp Fortunate</name>by the party, it was
        located just below the forks of the 
        <name type="place" key="Beaverhead (Jefferson) River">Beaverhead River</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Beaverhead County, Mont.">Beaverhead County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>. The site is now under 
        <name type="place" key="Clark Canyon Dam and Reservoir">Clark Canyon Reservoir</name>. The
        group would remain here until 
        <ref n="1805-08-24" type="related">August 24</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n20081709" n="9">
               <name type="person" key="Cameahwait">Cameahwait</name>, the brother of 
        <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n20081710" n="10">Long-tailed weasel, 
        <hi rend="italic">Mustela frenata</hi>. 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>received such a tippet from 
        <name type="person" key="Cameahwait">Cameahwait</name>; it is 
        <ref n="1805-08-20" type="related">shown</ref>in vol. 5, p. xii.</note>
            <note xml:id="n20081711" n="11">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>party had crossed the 
        <name type="place" key="Continental Divide">Continental Divide</name>and met the 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshones</name>on the 
        <name type="place" key="Lemhi (East Fork Lewis's) River">Lemhi River</name>in 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n20081712" n="12">The junction of 
        <name type="place" key="Horse Prairie Creek (West Fork Jefferson River)">Horse Prairie
        Creek</name>and 
        <name type="place" key="Red Rock (East Fork Jefferson) River">Red Rock River</name>to form
        
        <name type="place" key="Beaverhead (Jefferson) River">Beaverhead River</name>. Here, in 
        <name type="place" key="Beaverhead County, Mont.">Beaverhead County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>, they formed 
        <name type="place" key="Camp Fortunate (Mont.)">Camp Fortunate</name>just below the forks
        on a site now under 
        <name type="place" key="Clark Canyon Dam and Reservoir">Clark Canyon
        Reservoir</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n20081713" n="13">The 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians, Lemhi">Lemhi Shoshones</name>, 
        <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea's</name>people. See 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>entries of August 11–17 for his
        meeting with them and his efforts to get them to meet the main party at the forks (see
        note 12).</note>
            <note xml:id="n20081714" n="14">The number "3" is written over "2."</note>
            <note xml:id="n20081715" n="15">The "Spanish country" would be 
        <name type="place" key="New Mexico">New Mexico</name>, but eight days seems an optimistic
        estimate.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-08-16" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-08-18" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
