<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-05-17">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">May 17, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic
        Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            7</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">March 23–June 9, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1991</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">266-268</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">312</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">229</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Journal Entries</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-10-14</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-04-12</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1806-05-17">May 17, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-05-17.01" ref="">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Saturday May 17th 1806.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>It rained the greater part of the last night and this morning untill 8 OCk.
             the water passed through flimzy covering and wet our bed most perfectly in
          shot we lay in the water all the latter part of the night.    unfortunately my
          chronometer which for greater security I have woarn in my fob for ten days past, got wet
          last night; it seemed a little extraordinary that every part of my breechies which were
          under my head, should have escaped the moisture except the fob where the time peice was.
          I opened it and founded it nearly filled with water which I carefully drained out
          exposed it to the air and wiped the works as well as I could with dry feathers after
          which I touched them with a little bears oil.    several parts of the iron and
          steel works were rusted a little which I wiped with all the care in my power. I set her
          to going and from her apparent motion hope she has sustained no material injury.—
             at 9 A. M. 
          <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Sergt. Pryor</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Collins, John">Collins</name>returned, 
          <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Sergt. Pryor</name>brought the Skin and
          flesh of a black bear which he had killed; 
          <name type="person" key="Collins, John">Collins</name>had also killed a very large
          variegated bear but his horse having absconded last evening was unable to bring it.
             they had secured this meat perfectly from the wolves or birds and as it was
          at a considerable distance we did not think proper to send for it today.   
          neither of these bear were in good order.    as the bear are reather ferocious
          and we are obliged to depend on them pincipally for our subsistence we thought it most
          advisable to direct at least two hunters to go together, and they accordingly peared
          themselves out for this purpose.    we also apportioned the horses to the
          several hunters in order that they should be equally rode and thereby prevent any horse
          being materially injured by being too constantly hunted.    we appointed the
          men not hunters to take charge of certain horses in the absence of the hunters and
          directed the hunters to set out in different directions early in the morning and not
          return untill they had killed some game.    it rained moderately the greater
          part of the day and snowed as usual on the plain. 
          <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Sergt. Pryor</name>informed me that it
          was shoe deep this morning when he came down.    it is somewhat astonishing
          that the grass and a variety of 〈herbatious〉 plants which are now from a foot to 18
          inches high on these plains sustain no injury from the snow or frost; many of those
          plants are in blume and 〈many of them〉 appear to be of a tender susceptable texture.
             we have been visited by no indians today, and occurrence which has not
          taken place before since we left the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">Narrows of
          the Columbia</name>.—    I am pleased at finding the river rise so rapidly, it
          now doubt is attributeable to the meting snows of the mountains; that icy barier which
          seperates me from my friends and Country, from all which makes life esteemable.—
             patience, patience—</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-05-17.02" ref="">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Saturday 17th May 1806</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>rained moderately all the last night and this morning untill we are wet. The little
          river on which we are encamped rise Sepriseingly fast.    at 9 A. M. 
          <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Sergt. Pryor</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Collins, John">Collins</name>returned with the flesh and Skin
          of a Black bear on 
          <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Sgt. Pryors</name>horse. 
          <name type="person" key="Collins, John">Collins's</name>horse haveing run off from him
          yesterday.    they informed us that they had each killed a Bear neither of
          which were fat.    the one which they left in the woods was of the white
          Species and very large    we did not think it necessary in the cours of this
          day to Send for the flesh of the bear left in the woods.    the rains of the
          last night unfortunately wet the Crenomuter in the fob of 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. L.</name>breaches. which has never
          before been wet Since we Set out on this expedition.    her works were
          cautiously wiped and made dry by 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. L.</name>and I think She will recive
          no injury from this misfortune &amp;c.    we arranged the hunters and horses
          to each hunter and directed them to turn out in the morning early and continue out
          untill they Killed Something.    others arranged so as to take care of the
          hunters horses in their absence.    rained moderately all day.    at
          the Same time Snowed on the mountains which is in to the S. E. of us.    no
          Indians visit us to day which is a Singular circumstance as we have not been one day
          without Indians Since we left the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">long narrows
          of the Columbia</name>.    the fiew worm days which we have had has melted the
          Snows in the Mountains and the river has rose considerably.    that icy barier
          which Seperates me from my friends and Country, from all which makes life estimable, is
          yet white with the Snow which is maney feet deep. I frequently Consult the nativs on the
          subject of passing this tremendious barier which now present themselves to our view for
          great extent, they all appear to agree as to the time those Mountains may be passed
          which is about the Middle of 
          <hi rend="italic">June.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Sergt. pryor</name>informs me that the
          Snow on the high plains from the river was Shoe deep this morning when he Came down.
             it is somewhat estonishing that the grass and a variety of Plants Sustain
          no injurey from the Snow or frost; Maney of those plants are in blume and appear to be
          of tender susceptable texture. At the distance of 18 Miles from the river and on the
          Eastern border of the high Plain the 
          <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky Mountain</name>Commences and presents us
          with 
          <hi rend="italic">Winter</hi>   here we have Summer, Spring and Winter in the
          Short Space of twenty or thirty miles—.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-05-17.03" ref="">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>Saturday 17th of May 1806.    rained the greater part of last night and
          continues this morning.    about 10 oClock A. M. 
          <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Sergt. pryor</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Collins, John">Collins</name>returned    had killed
          one black bear and one white bear, and brought in one of them.    in the
          evening our officers directed that 10 or 12 hunters turn out a hunting tommorrow.
             asigned them horses    Some three &amp; others 4 to hunt on in
          turn.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-05-17.04" ref="">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Thursday</hi>[Saturday] 
          <hi rend="italic">17th.</hi>   We had a cloudy wet morning and some light rain
          all day. Our other two hunters
          <ref target="n35051701" n="1"/>came in, and had killed two large bears. They said it
          snowed on the hills, when it rained at our camp in the valley.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n35051701" n="1">
               <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Pryor</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Collins, John">Collins</name>.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-05-16" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-05-18" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
