<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.1805-11-30">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">November 30, 1805</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic
        Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            6</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">November 2, 1805–March 22, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1990</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">95-99</biblScope>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">257</biblScope>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">179</biblScope>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            11</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of Joseph Whitehouse, May 14, 1804–April 2,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1997</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">400</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
         <geoDecl datum="WGS">
            <placeName/>
            <geo>45.95 -123.8333</geo>
            <note>Lewis camped on the left side of what appears to be the Little South Fork Lewis and Clark River, Clatsop County, OR. Clark and the others are still at the 11-27 camp. Remained at their respective camps until 12-07.</note>
            <note>Approximate location</note>
         </geoDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc/>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-07-29</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-04-12</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date>November 30, 1805</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.1805-11-30.01">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">November 30th 1805.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>cloudy morning    set out before sun rise and continued our rout up the
          bey—</p>
               <p>
                  <table rows="7" cols="3">
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 60 E.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">1 ½</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">to a point.    land not very high
                and open    woods a little back
                <lb/>from the bay</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 80 E.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">3</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">m. to the center of a bend passing a point at
                1 m. land the
                <lb/>〈same as in last course〉 from the commenct. of this course</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 35 W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">2 ½</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">m across the bay to a point of marshey ground
                which for
                <lb/>three miles in width borders this coast—</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 60 W</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">2</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">m. to a point of marshey ground—</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 50 W</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">   ¾</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">m. to a marshey point at arm of the bay.
                   from this point a
                <lb/>point of highland bore S. 25 E. 3 miles distant—</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 80 W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">2 ½</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">to a marshey point passing the arm of the bey
                ¼ of a mile
                <lb/>wide—
                <ref target="n26113001" n="1"/>   the country to the S. E. appears to
                be low for a
                <lb/>great distance and is marshey and untimbered for three miles
                <lb/>back, from this point, the eastern point or commencement of
                <lb/>the bay bore N. 15 E. 3 miles.—</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 60 W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">3
                <ref target="n26113002" n="2"/>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">miles passing an inlet
                <ref target="n26113003" n="3"/>of 100 yds. wide at 4 m. to a point of
                <lb/>marshey ground, here an inlet
                <ref target="n26113004" n="4"/>of from 40 to 60 yds. in width
                <lb/>comes in just opposite to the upper point of a shore which we
                <lb/>have heretofore thought and island but which I am now con-
                <lb/>vinced is the main land.    we asscended this stream about 2 m.
                <lb/>it's course being S. 15 E.    we halted near a small cops of tim-
                <lb/>bered land to which we walked and dined 〈after which〉</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>Sent out three men to examin the country to the S. &amp; W.    they
          returned after about 2 hours and informed me that the wood was so thick and obstructed
          by marrasses &amp; lakes that they were unable to proceed to the ocean which could not
          be at any considerable distance from the apparent sound of the waves breaking on the
          Coast.    we now returned and asscended the inlet which we had last passd
          <ref target="n26113005" n="5"/>   no fresh appearance of Elk or deer in our
          rout so far.    asscend the inlet as we intended about 1 m. found it became
          much smaller and that it did not keep it's direction to the high land which boar S. 10
          W. but inclined West.    therefore returned to the large arm of the bay which
          we passed this morning.
          <ref target="n26113006" n="6"/>   here we expect to meet with the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clât-sop</name>Indians, who have
          tantilized us with there being much game in their neighbourhood.    this
          information in fact was the cause of my present resurch, for where there is most game is
          for us the most eliguble winter station.—    continued our rout up the large
          arm of the bay about 6 miles and encamped on the Stard. side on the highland. the water
          was quite sweet.    therefore concluded that it must be supplyed from a large
          crick.    at our camp it is 120 yds. wide, tho' it gets narrower above. 〈about
          2 miles〉    it rained but little on us today tho' it was cloudy generally.—
             Wind from N. E.—    saw a great abundance of fowls, brant, large
          geese, white brant sandhill Cranes, common blue crains,
          <ref target="n26113007" n="7"/>cormarants, haulks, ravens, crows, gulls and a great
          variety of ducks, the canvas back, duckinmallard,
          <ref target="n26113008" n="8"/>black and white diver,
          <ref target="n26113009" n="9"/>brown duck— &amp;c &amp;c—</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.1805-11-30.02">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">November 30th Saturday 1805</hi>
                     <ref target="n26113010" n="10"/>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>Some rain and hail with intervales of fair weather for 1 and 2 hours dureing the
          night and untill 9 oClock this morning at which time it Cleared up fair and the Sun
          Shown, I Send 5 men in a Canoe in the Deep bend above the Peninsulear to hunt fowles,
          &amp; 2 men in the thick woods to hunt Elk    had all our wet articles dried
          &amp; the men all employed dressing their Skins, I observe but few birds in this
          Countrey of the Small kinds— great numbers of wild fowl, The large Buzzard with white
          under their wings Grey &amp; Bald eagle large red tailed hawk, ravins, Crows, &amp; a
          small brown bird which is found about logs &amp;c.    but fiew small hawks or
          other smaller birds to be seen at this time    Snakes, Lizzards, Snales bugs
          worms Spiders, flies &amp; insects of different kinds are to be Seen in plenty at this
          time.    The Squar, gave me a piece of Bread to day made of Some flower She
          had Cearfully kept for her child, and had unfortunately got wet— The hunters killed only
          3 hawks, saw 3 Elk but Could not git a Shot at them, The fowlers, killed 3 black ducks,
          <ref target="n26113011" n="11"/>with white Sharp bills, a brown Spot in their forward,
          Some white under the tail, which Short, and a fiew of the tips of the wing feathers
          white, Their toes are long Seperated and flaped, no Craw, keep in emence large flocks in
          the Shallow waters &amp; feed on Grass &amp;c.—    Several men Complaining of
          being unwell to day—    a Broock comes in to the bend above the 1st point
          above, and a river falls in the next nitch above this river is Small,—    I
          observe rose bushes Pine, a kind of ash
          <ref target="n26113012" n="12"/>a Species of Beech
          <ref target="n26113013" n="13"/>and a Species of Maple, in addition to the pine Lorrel
          <ref target="n26113014" n="14"/>and under groth Common to the woods in this Lower
          Countrey    the hills are not high &amp; Slope to the river</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.1805-11-30.03">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Saturday 30th of November 1805</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>Some rain and hail with intervales of fair weather for the Space of one or two hours
          at a time dureing the night untill 9 oClock this morning, at which time it Cleared away
          and the Sun Shewn for [
          <hi rend="italic">blank</hi>] hours, Several men out hunting    I Send 5 men
          in the bend above to hunt fowl &amp;c. in a Canoe, employ all the others in drying our
          wet articles by the fire— Several men Complain of a looseness and gripeing
          <ref target="n26113015" n="15"/>which I contribute to the diet, pounded fish mixed with
          Salt water, I derect that in future that the party mix the pounded fish with fresh
          water—    
          <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">The Squar</name>gave me a piece of bread made of
          flour which She had reserved for 
          <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Jean Baptiste">her child</name>and carefully Kept
          untill this time, which has unfortunately got wet, and a little Sour—    this
          bread I eate with great Satisfaction, it being the only mouthfull I had tasted for
          Several months past.    my hunters killed 
          <hi rend="italic">three</hi>Hawks, which we found fat and delicious, they Saw 3 Elk but
          Could not get a Shot at them. The fowlers killed 3 black Ducks with Sharp White beeks
          keep in large flocks &amp; feed on Grass, they have no Craw and their 〈feet〉 toes are
          Seperate, Comon in the U. States</p>
               <p>The 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinnooks</name>
                  <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Cathlamet Indians">Cath lâh mâh</name>
                  </hi>&amp; others in this neighbourhood bury their dead in their Canoes.
          <ref target="n26113016" n="16"/>   for this purpose 4 pieces of Split timber
          are Set erect on end, and sunk a fiew feet in the ground, each brace having their flat
          Sides opposit to each other and Sufficiently far assunder to admit the width of the
          Canoe in which the dead are to be deposited; through each of those perpindicular posts,
          at the hight of 6 feet a mortice is Cut, through which two bars of wood are incerted; on
          those Cross bars a Small Canoe is placed, in which the body is laid after beaing
          Carefully roled in a robe of Some dressed Skins; a paddle is also deposited with them; a
          larger Canoe is now reversed, overlaying and imbracing the Small one, and resting with
          its gunnals on the Cross bars; one or more large mats of flags or rushes are then rold.
          around the Canoe and the whole Securely lashed with a long Cord usially made of the bark
          of the arbar vita or white Cedar.    on the Cross bars which Support the
          Canoes is frequently hung or laid various articles of Clothing Culinary utensils &amp;c.
             we cannot understand them Sufficiently to make any enquiries relitive to
          their religious opinions, from their depositing Various articles with their dead, beleve
          in a State of future ixistance.</p>
               <p>I walked on the point and observed rose bushes different Species of pine, [
          <hi rend="italic">NB: Copy for 
          <name type="person" key="Barton, Benjamin Smith">Dr Barton</name>
                  </hi>]
          <ref target="n26113017" n="17"/>a Spcies of ash, alder, a Species of wild Crab Loral
          and Several Species of under groth Common to this lower part of the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia river</name>—    The hills on
          this Coast rise high and are thickly covered with lofty pine maney of which are 10 &amp;
          12 feet through and more than 200 feet high.    hills have a Steep assent.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.1805-11-30.04">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>Saturday 30th Nov. 1805. Some of the party killed three ducks.    the after
          part of the day clear.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.1805-11-30.05">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Saturday 30th.</hi>   This was a fair day; and some hunters
          went round the cape and killed two or three ducks. This is all the supply of fresh
          provisions, that we have had since we have been at this camp. We live almost altogether
          on pounded salmon. The whole of the day was fair, pleasant and warm for the season.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.1805-11-30.06">
            <sp who="jw">
               <speaker>Whitehouse</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>Saturday Novemr 30th    We had several hard showers of rain, &amp; some
          hail fell during last night, and this morning after day light it cleared off.
             We put a Canoe into the River in order to try &amp; kill some Geese &amp;
          Ducks, which we saw plenty of, in a bay a small distance above where we are encamped.
             We put out our baggage &amp;ca to dry, as they appear'd to be in danger of
          spoiling by the wetness of the weather.    Our Hunters went out but did not
          kill any thing but 3 Ducks.    They mentioned of having seen several Elk, but
          that they were so shy, that they could not get within Rifle Shot of them.—</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n26113001" n="1">Present 
        <name type="place" key="Youngs (Kilhow-a-nah-kle) River">Youngs River</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Clatsop County, Oreg.">Clatsop County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>, nameless on 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>maps 82, 92; 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>"
        <name type="place" key="Youngs (Kilhow-a-nah-kle) River">Kilhowanahkle</name>." The term
        is 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookan</name>
               <hi rend="italic">giławanax̣ł.</hi>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="n26113002" n="2">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>has crossed out the following at
        this point: "5 me to a marshey point at 1½ m."</note>
            <note xml:id="n26113003" n="3">
               <name type="place" key="Lewis and Clark (Fort, Netul) River">Lewis and Clark River</name>,
        the captains' "
        <name type="place" key="Lewis and Clark (Fort, Netul) River">Netul</name>," in 
        <name type="place" key="Clatsop County, Oreg.">Clatsop County</name>, nameless on 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>maps 82, 92. It is 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookan</name>
               <hi rend="italic">ní
        <seg n="utu787">t̓</seg>ul.</hi>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="n26113004" n="4">Evidently the present 
        <name type="place" key="Skipanon River">Skipanon River</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Clatsop County, Oreg.">Clatsop County</name>; "
        <name type="place" key="Skipanon River">Skip â nor win C</name>" on 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>maps 82, 84. The name is again 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookan</name>
               <hi rend="italic">sqipanawnx.</hi>The point mistaken as an island is 
        <name type="place" key="Point Adams">Point Adams</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n26113005" n="5">Apparently 
        <name type="place" key="Lewis and Clark (Fort, Netul) River">Lewis and Clark
        River</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n26113006" n="6">
               <name type="place" key="Youngs (Kilhow-a-nah-kle) River">Young River</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n26113007" n="7">Probably the great blue heron, 
        <hi rend="italic">Ardea herodias</hi>[AOU, 194], also called a blue crane in 
        <ref n="1804-02-29" type="related">weather remarks</ref>for February 13, 1804. See also 
        <ref n="1806-03-06" type="related">March 6, 1806</ref>. Burroughs, 183–84.</note>
            <note xml:id="n26113008" n="8">Mallard, 
        <hi rend="italic">Anas platyrhynchos</hi>[AOU, 132].</note>
            <note xml:id="n26113009" n="9">Perhaps the bufflehead, 
        <hi rend="italic">Bucephala albeola</hi>[AOU, 153], already known to science. See below, 
        <ref n="1806-03-09" type="related">March 9, 1806</ref>. Ibid., 187–88. Holmgren
        considers it the western grebe, 
        <hi rend="italic">Aechmophorus occidentalis</hi>[AOU, 1], on the basis of the word "diver"
        being an old term for loons and grebes. Personal communication. See mention of other
        divers on 
        <ref n="1806-03-10" type="related">March 10, 1806</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n26113010" n="10">The purpose of the asterisk at the end of this line is not
        known.</note>
            <note xml:id="n26113011" n="11">The American coot, 
        <hi rend="italic">Fulica americana</hi>[AOU, 221], and a known species; it is not a duck.
        See below, 
        <ref n="1805-03-10" type="related">March 10, 1805</ref>. Burroughs, 224–25.</note>
            <note xml:id="n26113012" n="12">Possibly Oregon ash, then unknown to science. But see 
        <ref n="1806-02-10" type="related">February 10, 1806</ref>, about the confusion of ash
        and maple when seeing these deciduous trees without leaves. Little (CIH), 127-W; Cutright
        LCPN), 409.</note>
            <note xml:id="n26113013" n="13">
               <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>is again confusing the eastern beech
        with the red alder; he calls it alder in the second entry.</note>
            <note xml:id="n26113014" n="14">Again perhaps the California rhododendron, as on 
        <ref n="1805-11-06" type="related">November 6, 1805</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n26113015" n="15">Here indicating a pinching and spasmodic pain in the
        bowels, along with the "looseness" of diarrhea.</note>
            <note xml:id="n26113016" n="16">In addition to the more common use of burial canoes as
        described here by 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, the 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookan</name>peoples around the mouth
        of the 
        <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>also sometimes placed the
        dead in boxes. A combination of these methods was employed by the 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Tillamook Indians">Tillamook Indians</name>of the northern
        
        <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>coast (see 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>entry for 
        <ref n="1806-01-08" type="related">January 8, 1806</ref>). The use of burial canoes was
        a common mortuary practice among native peoples of the Northwest Coast. Ray (LCEN), 74–77;
        Hajda, 139.</note>
            <note xml:id="n26113017" n="17">The red vertical line drawn through this paragraph may be 
        <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle's</name>further reminder not to use this
        passage in his 
        <hi rend="italic">History.</hi>
            </note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-11-29" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-11-30-1" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
