<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-04-10">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">April 10, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic
        Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            7</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">March 23–June 9, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1991</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">101-104</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">289-290</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">208-209</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
         <geoDecl datum="WGS" xml:id="lc.geo.1806-04-10.01">
            <placeName/>
            <geo>45.6333 -121.9667</geo>
            <note>Camped east of North Bonneville, Skamania County, WA. Remained at this camp until
          04-12.</note>
         </geoDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc/>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-10-01</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-04-12</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1806-04-10">April 10, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-04-10.01"
              ref="lc.geo.1806-04-10.01">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Thursday April 10th 1806.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>We set out early and droped down the channel to the lower end of 
          <name type="place" key="Bradford (Brant) Island">brant Island</name>from whence we drew
          them up the rapid by a cord about a quarter of a mile which we soon performed; 
          <name type="person" key="Collins, John">Collins</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Gibson, George">Gibson</name>not having yet come over we
          directed 
          <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Sergt. Pryor</name>to remain with the
          cord on the Island untill 
          <name type="person" key="Gibson, George">Gibson</name>arrived and assist him with his
          crew in geting his canoe up the rapid, when they were to join us on the oposite side at
          a small village of six houses of the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Clahclellar Indians">Clah-clah'lahs</name>where we
          halted for breakfast.
          <ref target="n31041001" n="1"/>   in passing the river which is here about
          400 yds. wide the rapidity of the currant was such that it boar us down a considerable
          distance notwithstanding we employed five oars.    on entering one of these
          lodges, the natives offered us a sheepskin for sail,
          <ref target="n31041002" n="2"/>than which nothing could have been more acceptable
          except the animal itself.    the skin of the head of the sheep with the horns
          remaining was cased in such manner as to fit the head of a man by whom it was woarn and
          highly prized as an ornament.    we obtained this cap in exchange for a knife,
          and were compelled to give two Elkskins in exchange for the skin.    this
          appeared to be the skin of a sheep not fully grown; the horns were about four inches
          long, celindric, smooth, black, erect and pointed; they rise from the middle of the
          forehead a little above the eyes.    they offered us a second skin of a full
          grown sheep which was quite as large as that of a common deer.    they
          discovered our anxity to purchase and in order to extort a great plrice declared that
          they prized it too much to dispose of it.    in expectation of finding some
          others of a similar kind for sale among the natives of this neighbourhood I would not
          offer him a greater price than had been given for the other which he refused.
             these people informed us that these sheep were found in great abundance on
          the hights and among the clifts of the adjacent mountains.    and that they
          had lately killed these two from a herd of 36, at no great distance from their village.
             we could obtain no provision from those people except four white salmon
          trout.    at ten oclock 
          <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Sergt. Pryor</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Gibson, George">Gibson</name>joined us with 
          <name type="person" key="Collins, John">Collins</name>who had killed 3 deer.
             these were all of the blacktailed fallow kind.    we set out and
          continued our rout up the N. side of the river with great difficulty in consequence of
          the rapidity of the current and the large rocks which form this shore; the South side of
          the river is impassable.    as we had but one sufficient toerope and were
          obliged to employ the cord in geting on our canoes the greater part of the way we could
          only take them one at a time which retarded our progress very much.    by
          evening we arrived at the portage on the North side where we landed and conveyed our
          bagage to the top of the hill about 200 paces distant where we formed a camp.
          <ref target="n31041003" n="3"/>   we had the canoes drawn on shore and
          secured.    the small canoe got loose from the hunters and went a drift with a
          tin vessel and tommahawk in her; the Indians caught her at the last village and brought
          her up to us this evening for which service we gave them a couple of knives; the canoe
          overset and lost the articles which were in her.—    Saw the white pine at
          this place.
          <ref target="n31041004" n="4"/>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-04-10.02"
              ref="lc.geo.1806-04-10.01">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Thursday April 10th 1806</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Collins, John">Collins</name>went out in the bottom to hunt
          agreeable to the order of last evening, and 
          <name type="person" key="Gibson, George">gibson</name>s Crew was derected to delay for 
          <name type="person" key="Collins, John">Collins</name>dureing which time they were
          derected to Collect rozin from the pines in the bottom near our Camp    at 6 A
          M. we Set out and proceeded to the lower point of the Island from whence we were
          Compelled to draw our Canoes up a rapid for about ¼ mile which we Soon performed. 
          <name type="person" key="Collins, John">Collins</name>&amp; 
          <name type="person" key="Gibson, George">gibson</name>haveing not yet Come over we
          derected 
          <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Serjt. Pryor</name>to delay on the
          Island untill 
          <name type="person" key="Gibson, George">Gibson</name>Came over &amp; assist him with
          the large toe roap which we also left and to join us at a village of four houses of the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Clahclellar Indians">Clah-lah-lar</name>Tribe which is
          opposit to this Island on North Side at which place we intened to brackfast.
             in crossing the River which at this place is not more than 400 yards wide
          we fell down a great distance owing to the rapidity of the Current. I entered one of the
          houses of those people and was Scercely Seated before they offered me a Sheep Skin for
          Sale    nothing could be more acceptable except the Animal itself   
          in examoning this Skin I found it was a young one, the Skin of the head was Cased So as
          to fit the head of a man and was esteemed as a great orniment and highly prised by them.
             we precured this Cased head for a knife and, the Skin we were obliged to
          give two Raw Elk Skins for. Soon after they offered a large one for Sall.   
          after finding us anxious to purchase they declined silling this Skin.    those
          people informed us that they killed those Animals among the rocks in the mountains under
          which they live; and that great numbers of those animals inhabit those mountains &amp;
          that the lamb was killed out of a gange of 36 at a Short distance from their village.
          The wool of the full grown Sheep, or that on the Skin which we Saw was much Corser than
          that of the one which we purchased, the Skin was about the Size of that of a Common
          dear. The Skin we obtained appeared to be the Skin of a Sheep not fully grown, the wool
          fine, the Horns were abought 4 inches long, Celindric, Smooth, black, a little bending
          backwards and pointed; they rise from the Middle of the foeheard, and a little above the
          eyes, and appeared to possess all the marks of the Common Sheep as already discribed. We
          could precure no provisions from those people except four white Salmon trout.
             at 10 oClock 
          <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Sergt. Pryor</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Gibson, George">Gibson</name>joined us with 
          <name type="person" key="Collins, John">Collins</name>who had killed 3 deer.
             these were all of the blacktailed fallow kind. We Set out and Continued up
          on the N. Side of the river with great dificuelty in Consequence of the Rapidity of the
          Current and the large rocks which forms this Shore; the South Side of the river is
          impassable.</p>
               <p>As we had but one Sufficent toe roap and were obliged to employ the Cord in getting
          on our Canoes the greater part of the way we could only take them one at a time which
          retarded our progress very much.    by evening we arived at the portage on the
          N. Side where we landed and Conveyed our baggage to the top of the hill about 200 paces
          distant where we found [formd?] a Camp.    we had the Canoes drawn on Shore
          and Secured.    the Small Canoe got loose from the hunters and went adrift
          with a tin cup &amp; a tomahawk in her; the Indians Caught her at the last Village and
          brought her up to us this evening for which we gave them two knives; the Canoe overset
          and lost the articles which were in her.—.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-04-10.03"
              ref="lc.geo.1806-04-10.01">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>Thursday 10th of April 1806.    rained hard the grater part of last night.
             a cloudy &amp; Showery morning.    2 men
          <ref target="n31041005" n="5"/>Sent out to hunt pitch who belonged to a Small canoe.
             we took up the large canoes one at a time up the rapids with the towing
          line.    the Small one also who was left to help up with the other small one.
             we then crossed over the River to the N. Side and halted at a village where
          we took breakfast.    the men who were hunting pitch came up with their canoe
             one of them by the name of 
          <name type="person" key="Collins, John">Collins</name>had killed three Deer and brought
          them to us. 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name>purchased a white mountain
          Sheep
          <ref target="n31041006" n="6"/>Skin for which he gave 2 Elk hides    we
          bought a fiew Salmon trout
          <ref target="n31041007" n="7"/>   then we proceed. on    Soon came
          to bad rapids where we had to tow one canoe up at a time. 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name>&amp; the 
          <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph and Reubin">2 Fields</name>went on a head with
          their Smal canoe.    their chord broke &amp; their canoe went back down the
          rapids and taken up by the Indians below, who returnd. it to us.    our
          officers gave them two knives for the kindness.    one of the men lamed one of
          his feet towing over the Stons    with Some fatigue we got all the canoes to
          the lower end of the portage of the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Cascades (Great Rapids, Great Shute)">big
          Shoote</name>and unloaded in the large eddy below on N. Side and carried all the baggage
          on the top of the hill, and Camped
          <ref target="n31041008" n="8"/>   a number of the natives visited us
             Some distance below this place I Saw a large grave yard little below an
          ancient village.
          <ref target="n31041009" n="9"/>   this is a different manner from any I have
          Seen of burrying the dead in tombs about 8 feet Square made of wood plank and tite
          flowers [floors?] made of plank layn in them and the corps are layn out on the flower
          Roped up in Some kind of a Robe, and all thier property is deposited with them Such as
          copper tea kittles baskets cockle Shells    canoes are layn by the Side of Sd.
          tombs also. Several Images cut in wood one put up at the ends of Said tombs &amp;C
             one of the Indians Stole an axe from us    another told one of
          our men and he followed him and took it from him and told him that he was bad and he
          replied that he was &amp;C—</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-04-10.04"
              ref="lc.geo.1806-04-10.01">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Thursday 10th.</hi>   A party of men went out to collect
          pitch to repair one of our canoes, which was split; and the rest went round the point of
          the island, and took the canoes over the rapid, one at a time, with the assistance of a
          line. When we got over the rapids we crossed to another village of the natives of the
          north side,
          <ref target="n31041010" n="10"/>where I saw the skin of a wild sheep, which had fine
          beautiful wool on it. Here we took breakfast and waited the arrival of the other canoe,
          which in about an hour came up; and the men
          <ref target="n31041011" n="11"/>when out for pitch killed three deer. We proceeded on,
          and the water was so rapid that we had to tow the canoes up by the line almost all the
          way to the landing at the lower end of the portage, a distance of about six miles. In
          passing a bad place the tow-line of the small canoe, which the hunters had on ahead,
          broke; but fortunately there was nothing in her, as the three hunters were on shore
          dragging her up, and had taken out all the loading.
          <ref target="n31041012" n="12"/>As she passed by us 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name>got some of the natives to
          bring her to shore. In the evening, we got to the end of the portage, which is about two
          miles. We took our baggage to the top of the hill and remained with it all night; during
          which, some showers of rain fell.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n31041001" n="1">In 
        <name type="place" key="Skamania County, Wash.">Skamania County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>, in or near present 
        <name type="place" key="North Bonneville, Wash.">North Bonneville</name>. 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>map 79. This village of six houses (four according to 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>) was visited by the Corps on 
        <ref n="1805-10-31" type="related">October 31, 1805</ref>; see the entry for that day.
        See also Minor, Toepel, &amp; Beckham (Rev).</note>
            <note xml:id="n31041002" n="2">The mountain goat, 
        <hi rend="italic">Oreamnos americanus.</hi>This was the only specimen they obtained,
        although 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>thought he saw one at a distance
        earlier (see 
        <ref n="1805-08-24" type="related">August 24, 1805</ref>). Apparently the earliest
        descriptions and naming of the animal, by George Ord and M. H. D. deBlainville, were based
        on 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>description and specimen.
        Burroughs, 168–71; Cutright (LCPN), 263, 387, 444.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31041003" n="3">In 
        <name type="place" key="Skamania County, Wash.">Skamania County</name>; the site is not
        marked on 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>maps 78 or 79, nor on other maps of the area; it may be at the
        same place as the camp of November 1, 1805, in the vicinity east of 
        <name type="place" key="North Bonneville, Wash.">North Bonneville</name>. This is the area
        that was once the 
        <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Cascades (Great Rapids, Great Shute)">Cascades of
        the Columbia</name>, now inundated by 
        <name type="place" key="Bonneville Dam">Bonneville Dam</name>. The constriction of the 
        <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>formed by the rapids created an
        extremely favorable location for native fishing; it also required travelers to portage in
        order to pass up or down the river. The 
        <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Cascades (Great Rapids, Great Shute)">
        Cascades</name>area was a major focus of native settlement in the late prehistoric and
        early historic periods. Archaeological research in 
        <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Cascades (Great Rapids, Great Shute)">the
        Cascades</name>area has most recently been revised by Minor, Toepel, &amp; Beckham
        (Rev).</note>
            <note xml:id="n31041004" n="4">This is the first mention of the occurrence of the western
        white pine since leaving the 
        <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>. The lack of white pine was
        specifically noted by 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>on 
        <ref n="1806-03-30" type="related">March 30, 1806</ref>, as the party passed the mouth
        of the 
        <name type="place" key="Willamette (Multnomah) River">Willamette River</name>. Since white
        pine tends to be found at higher elevations, it is interesting that 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>observed it at this low elevation
        along the 
        <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>. Little (CIH), 62-W;
        Franklin &amp; Dyrness, 310–11.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31041005" n="5">Apparently 
        <name type="person" key="Collins, John">Collins</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Gibson, George">Gibson</name>, according to 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>and to 
        <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>in this entry.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31041006" n="6">The mountain goat, 
        <hi rend="italic">Oreamnos americanus</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31041007" n="7">Salmon trout was the party's name for the steelhead
        trout.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31041008" n="8">In the area east of 
        <name type="place" key="North Bonneville, Wash.">North Bonneville</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Skamania County, Wash.">Skamania County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>; see the captains' entries for this
        day.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31041009" n="9">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>places this description under his
        entry of 
        <ref n="1806-04-11" type="related">April 11</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31041010" n="10">Another 
        <name type="place" key="Clahclellar village">"Clahclellah" (Watlala) village</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Skamania County, Wash.">Skamania County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>, at or near 
        <name type="place" key="North Bonneville, Wash.">North Bonneville</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31041011" n="11">Including 
        <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Pryor</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Gibson, George">Gibson</name>, who had waited for 
        <name type="person" key="Collins, John">Collins</name>, who was hunting; they were
        collecting pitch to repair cracks in the canoes while they waited.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31041012" n="12">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>says the canoe had "a tin vessel
        and tomahawk in her."</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-04-09" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-04-11" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
