<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1804-02-20">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
February 20, 1804</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2003</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               
               
               
               
               
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 2</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">August 30, 1803–August 24, 1804</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1986</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">174-176</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Journal Entries</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-01-05</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1804-02-20">February 20, 1804</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1804-02-20.01" n="">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Detatchment Orders</hi>
                     <lb/>
                     <name type="place" key="Camp Dubois (Camp Wood, River Dubois) (Ill.)">Camp River Dubois</name>, Febr. 20th 1804<ref target="n03022001" n="1"/>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
The Commanding officer directs that during the absence of himself and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name> from <name type="place" key="Camp Dubois (Camp Wood, River Dubois) (Ill.)">Camp</name>, that the party shall consider themselves under the immediate command of <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Sergt. Ordway</name>, who will be held accountable for the good poliece and order of the <name type="place" key="Camp Dubois (Camp Wood, River Dubois) (Ill.)">camp</name> during that period, and will also see the susequent parts of this order carried into effect—</p>
               <p>
The sawyers will continue their work untill they have cut the necessary quantity of plank, the quantity wanting will be determined by <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Pryor</name>; during the days they labour they shall recieve each an extra gill of whiskey pr. day, and be exempt from guard duty; when the work is accomplished, they will join the party and do duty in common with the other men.—</p>
               <p>
The Blacksmiths<ref target="n03022002" n="2"/> will also continue their work untill they have completed the [articles?] contained in the memorandam with which I have furnished them, and during the time they are at work will recieve each an extra gill of whiskey pr. day and be exempt from guard duty; when the work is completed they will return to <name type="place" key="Camp Dubois (Camp Wood, River Dubois) (Ill.)">camp</name> and do duty in common with the detatcment.—</p>
               <p>
The four men who are engaged in making sugar will continue in that employment untill further orders, and will recieve each a half a gill of extra whiskey pr. day and be exempt from guard duty.—</p>
               <p>
The practicing party will in futer discharge only one round each per. day, which will be done under the direction of <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Sergt. Ordway</name>, all at the same target and at the distance of fifty yards off hand. The prize of a gill of extra whiskey will be received by the person who makes the best show at each time of practice.—</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Floyd, Charles">Floyd</name> will take charge of our quartes and store and be exempt from guard duty untill our return, the commanding Officer hopes that this proof of his confidence will be justifyed by the rigid performance of the orders given him on that subject.—</p>
               <p>
No man shal absent himself from <name type="place" key="Camp Dubois (Camp Wood, River Dubois) (Ill.)">camp</name> without the knowledge and permission of <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Sergt. Ordway</name>, other than those who have obtained permission from me to be absent on hunting excurtions, and those will not extend their absence to a term by which they may avoid a tour of guard duty, on their return they will report themselves to <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Sergt. Ordway</name> and recieve his instructions—</p>
               <p>
No whiskey shall in future be delivered from the Contractor's store except for the legal ration, and as appropriated by this order, unless otherwise directed by <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name> or myself—</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="right">
                     <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name> Capt.<lb/>
1st U. S. Regt. Infty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Sergt. Ordway</name> will have the men peraded this evening and read the inclosed orders to them—<ref target="n03022003" n="3"/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="right">
                     <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">M. Lewis</name>
                  </hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n03022001" n="1">The first of the Detachment Orders (see <ref n="v02.appendix.c" type="related">Appendix C</ref>). <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Sergeant Ordway</name> was left in charge because no other sergeants had yet been appointed, and <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, who had been serving in the regular army, already held the rank and was an experienced soldier.</note>
            <note xml:id="n03022002" n="2">
               <name type="person" key="Shields, John">John Shields</name> and <name type="person" key="Willard, Alexander">Alexander Willard</name> were the expedition's blacksmiths, <name type="person" key="Shields, John">Shields</name> being particularly versatile. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> to Henry Dearborn, January 15, 1807, Jackson (LLC), 1:367, 372 n. 26; Russell (FTT), 39, 41, 358–61.</note>
            <note xml:id="n03022003" n="3">These lines were placed on the back of the sheet after it was folded. The orders are endorsed "To <name type="person" key="Floyd, Charles">Floyd</name>" in <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> hand and "1804 <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Merryweather Lewis</name>" in an unknown hand.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1804-02-09" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1804-02-29" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
