<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-05-10">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">May 10, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic
        Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            7</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">March 23–June 9, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1991</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">237-241</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">308</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">224-225</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
         <geoDecl datum="WGS" xml:id="lc.geo.1806-05-10.01">
            <placeName/>
            <geo>46.2167 -116.0167</geo>
            <note>Camped on Lawyer Creek, Lewis County, ID. Southwest of Kamiah and near Broken Arm's village. Remained at this camp until 05-13.</note>
         </geoDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journal Entries</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-10-12</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-04-12</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1806-05-10">May 10, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-05-10.01"
              ref="lc.geo.1806-05-10.01">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Saturday May 10th 1806.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>This morning the snow continued falling ½ after 6 A. M. when it ceased, the air keen
          and cold, the snow 8 inches deep on the plain; we collected our horses and after taking
          a scant breakfast of roots we set out for the village of 
          <name type="person" key="Broken Arm">Tunnachemootoolt</name>; our rout lay through an
          open plain course S. 35 E. and distance 16 ms.    the road was slippery and
          the snow clogged to the horses feet, and caused them to trip frequently.   
          the mud at the sources of the little ravines was deep black
          <ref target="n34051001" n="1"/>and well supplyed with quawmash. 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name>turned off to the left of the
          road in order to hunt and did not join us this evening.    at 4 in the
          afternoon we decended the hills to 
          <name type="place" key="Lawyer (Commearp) Creek">Commearp Creek</name>and arrived at the
          Village of 
          <name type="person" key="Broken Arm">Tunnachemootoolt</name>,
          <ref target="n34051002" n="2"/>the cheeif at whos lodge we had left a flag last fall.
             this flag was now displayed on a staff placed at no great distance from the
          lodge. underneath the flag the Cheif met my friend 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. C.</name>who was in front and conducted
          him about 80 yds. to a place on the bank of the creek where he requested we should
          encamp; I came up in a few minutes and we collected the Cheifs and men of consideration
          smoked with them and stated our situation with rispect to provision.    the
          Cheif spoke to his people and they produced us about 2 bushels of the Quawmas roots
          dryed, four cakes of the bread of 
          <hi rend="italic">cows</hi>and a dryed salmon trout.
          <ref target="n34051003" n="3"/>We thanked them for this store of provision but informed
          them that our men not being accustomed to live on roots alone we feared it would make
          them sick, to obviate which we proposed exchangeing a good horse in reather low order
          for a young horse in tolerable order with a view to kill.    the hospitality
          of the cheif revolted at the aydea of an exchange, he told us that his young men had a
          great abundance of young horses and if we wished to eat them we should by furnished with
          as many as we wanted.    accordingly they soon produced us two fat young
          horses one of which we killed, the other we informed them we would pospone killing
          untill we had consumed the one already killed. This is a much greater act of hospitality
          than we have witnessed from any nation or tribe since we have passed the 
          <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky mountains</name>.    in short
          be it spoken to their immortal honor it is the only act which deserves the appellation
          of hospitallity which we have witnessed in this quarter.
          <ref target="n34051004" n="4"/>   we informed these people that we were
          hungry and fatiegued at this moment, that when we had eaten and refreshed ourselves we
          would inform them who we were, from whence we had come and the objects of our resurches.
             a principal Cheif by name 
          <name type="person" key="Hohots Ilppilp">Ho-hâst,-ill-pilp</name>
                  <ref target="n34051005" n="5"/>arrived with a party of fifty men mounted on eligant
          horses.    he had come on a visit to us from his village which is situated
          about six miles distant near the river.    we invited this man into our circle
          and smoked with him, his retinue continued on horseback at a little distance.
             after we had eaten a few roots we spoke to them as we had promised; and
          gave 
          <name type="person" key="Broken Arm">Tinnachemootoolt</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Hohots Ilppilp">Hohâstillpilp</name>each a medal; the former
          one of the small size with the likeness of Mr. 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>and the latter one of the
          sewing medals struck in the presidency of 
          <name type="person" key="Washington, George">Washington</name>,
          <ref target="n34051006" n="6"/>we explained to them the desighn and the importance of
          medals in the estimation of the whites as well as the red men who had been taught their
          value. The Cheif had a large conic lodge of leather
          <ref target="n34051007" n="7"/>erected for our reception and a parsel of wood collected
          and laid at the door after which he invited 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. C.</name>and myself to make that lodge
          our home while we remained with him.    we had a fire lighted in this lodge
          and retired to it accompanyed by the Cheifs and as many of the considerate men as could
          croud in a circcle within it.    here after we had taken a repast on some
          horsebeef we resumed our council with the indians which together with smoking the pipe
          occupyed the ballance of the evening. I was surprised to find on decending the hills of 
          <name type="place" key="Lawyer (Commearp) Creek">Commearp Cr.</name>to find that there
          had been no snow in the bottoms of that stream.    it seems that the snow
          melted in falling and decended here in rain while it snowed on the plains.   
          the hills are about six hundred feet high about one fourth of which distance the snow
          had decended and still lay on the sides of the hills.    as these people had
          been liberal with is with rispect to provision I directed the men not to croud their
          lodge surch of food in the manner hunger has compelled them to do at most lodges we have
          passed, and which the 
          <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">Twisted hair</name>had informed me
          was disgreeable to the natives.    but their previous want of hospitality had
          induced us to consult their enclinations but little and suffer our men to obtain
          provision from them on the best terms they could. The village of the broken arm as I
          have heretofore termed it consists of one house only which is 150 feet in length built
          in the usual form of sticks matts and dry grass.    it contains twenty four
          fires and about double that number of families.    from appearances I presume
          they could raise 100 fighting men.    the noise of their women pounding roots
          reminds me of a nail factory. The indians seem well pleased, and I am confident that
          they are not more so than our men who have their somachs once more well filled with
          horsebeef and mush of the bread of cows.—    the house of coventry is also
          seen here.—
          <ref target="n34051008" n="8"/>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-05-10.02"
              ref="lc.geo.1806-05-10.01">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Saturday 10th of May 1806</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>This morning the Snow continued falling untill ½ past 6 A M when it Seased.
             the air keen and Cold the Snow 8 inches deep on the plain.    we
          Collected our horses and after takeing a Scanty brackfast of roots, we Set out for the
          Village of the Chief with a flag, and proceeded on through an open plain.   
          the road was Slipry and the Snow Cloged and caused the horses to trip very frequently.
             the mud at heads of the Streams which we passed was deep and well Supplied
          with the 
          <hi rend="italic">Car mash.</hi>
                  <ref target="n34051009" n="9"/>
                  <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name>turned off the road to hunt
          near the river to our lef and did not join us today.    at 4 P M we arrived at
          the Village of 
          <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="person" key="Broken Arm">Tin nach-e-moo-toolt</name>
                  </hi>
                  <ref target="n34051010" n="10"/>the Chief whome We had left a flag.    this
          flag was hoisted on a pole    unde the flag the Chief met me and Conducted me
          to a Spot near a Small run about 80 paces from his Lodges here he requested me to halt
          which I did. Soon after 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Cap Lewis</name>who was in the rear Came up
          and we Smoked with and told this Chief our Situation in respect to provisions.
             they brought foward about 2 bushels of quawmash 4 Cakes of bread made of
          roots and a dried fish.    we informed the Chief that our Party was not
          accustomed to eate roots without flesh &amp; proposed to exchange Some of our oald
          horses for young ones to eate.    they Said that they would not exchange
          horses, but would furnish us with Such as we wished, and produced 2 one of which we
          killed and informd. them that we did not wish to kill the other at this time.
             we gave Medals to the 
          <name type="person" key="Broken Arm">broken arm</name>or 
          <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="person" key="Broken Arm">Tin-nach-e-moo tolt</name>
                  </hi>and 
          <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="person" key="Hohots Ilppilp">Hoh-hâst-ill-pitp</name>
                  </hi>
                  <ref target="n34051011" n="11"/>two principal Chiefs of the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Chopunnish</name>Natn. and was
          informed that there was one other Great Chief (in all 4) who had but one eye.
             he would be here tomorrow.    a large Lodge of Leather was
          pitched and 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name>and my Self was envited
          into it.    we entered and the Chief and principal men came into the lodge and
          formed a Circle    a parcel of wood was Collected and laid at the dore and a
          fire made in this Conic lodge before we entered it.    the Chief requested
          that we might make the Lodge our homes while we remained with him.    here
          after we had taken a repast on roots &amp; horse beef we resumed our Council with the
          indians which together with Smokeing took up the ballance of the evening. I was
          Supprised to find decending the hill to 
          <name type="place" key="Lawyer (Commearp) Creek">
                     <hi rend="italic">Commearp</hi>Creek</name>to find that there had been no snow in the
          bottoms of that Stream.    it seams that the Snow melted in falling and
          decended here in rain while it snowed in the plain.    the hills are about
          Eight hundred feet high about ¼ of which distance the Snow had decended and Still lay on
          the Sides of the hill.    as those people had been liberal I directed the men
          not to croud their Lodge in serch of food the manner hunger has Compelled them to do, at
          most lodges we have passed, and which the 
          <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">Twisted Hair</name>
                  </hi>had informed us was disagreeble to the nativs.    but their previous want
          of hospitality had enduced us to consult their enclinations but little and Suffer our
          men to obtain provisions from them on the best terms they could.</p>
               <p>The Village of the 
          <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="person" key="Broken Arm">broken Arm</name>
                  </hi>consists of one house or Lodge only which is 150 feet in length built in the usial
          form of Sticks, Mats and dry grass.    it contains 24 fires and about double
          that number of families.    from appearance I prosume they could raise 100
          fighting men.    the noise of their women pounding the cows roots remind me of
          a nail factory. The Indians appear well pleased, and I am Confident that they are not
          more so than our men who have their Stomach once more well filled with horse beef and
          the bread of cows. Those people has Shewn much greater acts of hospitallity than we have
          witnessed from any nation or tribe Since we have passed the 
          <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">rocky Mountains</name>.    in Short
          be it Spoken to their immortal honor it is the only act which diserves the appelation of
          hospitallity which we have witnessed in this quarter.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-05-10.03"
              ref="lc.geo.1806-05-10.01">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>Saturday 10th of May 1806.    the wind fell and the rain turned to Snow
          Some time last night and the Snow fell 6 Inches deep &amp; continues chilly &amp; cold
          this morning, &amp; we had not any thing to eat.    got up our horses &amp;
          Set out &amp; proced. on over a high Smooth plain no timber. The Snow melts a little but
          the air cold.    wrode about 20 miles    descended a Steep hill down
          in a valley and bottom in which a creek runs through, and Camped
          <ref target="n34051012" n="12"/>near a village of the head chiefs of abt. 15 lodges.
             they had their flag hoisted and appeared glad to See us.    gave
          us Some commass roots which had been Swetted last fall. Some Shapealell and a little dry
          fish, but have but little    the natives have great numbers of horses
             gave us two to kill.    we killed one to eat. Some of the women
          pitched a leather lodge
          <ref target="n34051013" n="13"/>and brought wood &amp; made a fire in it and chiefs
          invited our officers to Stay in it, and talked together    our officers told
          them our business &amp;C.    in the evening we played the fiddle and danced a
          while    a number of Indians came from other villages to See us   
          the Snow is gone in this bottom but lyes on the high plains &amp; hills   
          considerable of cottonwood and wild or choke cherry along this creek &amp; Scattering
          pine on the edges of the hills, &amp;C.    we are now as near the Mountains as
          we can git untill Such times as the Snow is nearly gone of[f] the mountains as we are
          too eairly to cross.    one of the party purchased a dog this eveng. but the
          most of their dogs are too poor to eat</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-05-10.04"
              ref="lc.geo.1806-05-10.01">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Saturday 10th.</hi>   At dark last night the weather became
          cloudy and it rained about an hour, when the rain turned to snow, and it continued
          snowing all night. In the morning the weather became clear. Where we are lying in the
          plains the snow is about five inches deep; and amidst snow and frost we have nothing
          whatever to eat. Without breakfast we started to go to a village of the natives, who
          live on a branch of the river, about a south course from this place. We travelled
          through the snow about 12 miles, and then went down a long steep descent to the branch
          where the village is situated. When we were about half way down the hill there was not a
          particle of snow nor the least appearance of it. It was about 3 o'clock when we arrived
          at the village,
          <ref target="n34051014" n="14"/>and the Commanding Officers held a conversation with
          the natives, who informed them that they had not more provisions and roots, than they
          wanted for themselves. They, however, divided their stock with us; and told us what they
          had given was all they could spare; but drove up some horses and told us to shoot one,
          which we did. They then offered another, but that was reserved for another time, and we
          dressed the one we had killed; and in our situation find it very good eating. We
          remained here all night. One of the hunters who had gone on before the party did not
          join us yet.
          <ref target="n34051015" n="15"/>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n34051001" n="1">Snow meltwater or spring discharge of groundwater from
        snowmelt when mixed with the rich volcanic soil of the area would form a black sandy or
        silty mud.</note>
            <note xml:id="n34051002" n="2">In 
        <name type="place" key="Lewis County, Idaho">Lewis County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>, on 
        <name type="place" key="Lawyer (Commearp) Creek">Lawyer (Commearp) Creek</name>, southwest
        of present 
        <name type="place" key="Kamiah, Idaho">Kamiah</name>; not shown on 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>map 71. "
        <name type="place" key="Lawyer (Commearp) Creek">Commearp</name>" is 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
               <hi rend="italic">qémyex̣p,</hi>the designation for 
        <name type="place" key="Lawyer (Commearp) Creek">Lawyer Creek</name>. They remained here
        until May 13. Space, 27; Peebles (RLC), 20; Peebles (LT), map. If the party traveled along
        the historic 
        <name type="place" key="Nez Perce Trail">Nez Perce trail</name>in this area, they followed
        
        <name type="place" key="Suzie Creek">Suzie Creek</name>to its junction with 
        <name type="place" key="Lawyer (Commearp) Creek">Lawyer Creek</name>about five miles above
        its mouth. Peebles places the party approximately one mile farther east, but he is
        uncertain about this portion of the route. Peebles (LT), map. From the journal description
        of 
        <ref n="1806-05-13" type="related">May 13, 1806</ref>, the campsite and village was
        located about three and one-half miles up 
        <name type="place" key="Lawyer (Commearp) Creek">Lawyer Creek</name>. There were a number
        of historic 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>villages along this
        portion of 
        <name type="place" key="Lawyer (Commearp) Creek">Lawyer Creek</name>. Several of these
        have been confirmed as archaeological sites but none have yet been excavated or dated.
        Shawley, 40; Stapp, Bryan, &amp; Rigg, 43, 67–68.</note>
            <note xml:id="n34051003" n="3">Steelhead trout, 
        <hi rend="italic">Oncorhynchus mykiss</hi>(formerly 
        <hi rend="italic">Salmo gairdneri</hi>). Kendall. See 
        <ref n="1806-03-14" type="related">March 14, 1806</ref>, for 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>full description.</note>
            <note xml:id="n34051004" n="4">
               <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>has a comment, perhaps given by 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>in their conversations in 1810, that
        those who had had no contact with whites were much more hospitable than those who had,
        such as the coastal Indians. 
        <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>Notes [ca. April 1810], Jackson
        (LLC), 2:543–44.</note>
            <note xml:id="n34051005" n="5">Somewhat more correctly, 
        <name type="person" key="Hohots Ilppilp">Hohots Ilppilp</name>. His name referred to a
        red, or bleeding, grizzly bear, his spiritual animal helper or guardian. From this, or
        from his many battle scars, later whites called him "The Bloody Chief." The 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>word is 
        <hi rend="italic">
                  <seg n="uxu803">x̣</seg>á
        <seg n="uxu803">x̣</seg>a·c 'ilpílp,</hi>"red grizzly." He was still alive in the early
        1840s, when he claimed to be the oldest chief of the 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perces</name>, and spoke to whites
        of having met 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>. He was friendly to the missionaries
        and his grandson, 
        <name type="person" key="Ellis">Ellis</name>, having received an education in English, was
        designated "head chief" by U.S. authorities. 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>legend asserts that the
        sister of 
        <name type="person" key="Red Grizzly Bear">Red Grizzly Bear</name>bore a son by 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark</name>. This man, who had light
        hair, was proud of his ancestry and would proclaim "Me 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>!" He was photographed at least once,
        in his old age. He was with the famous 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>flight in 1877, and
        with this group was deported to 
        <name type="place" key="Indian Territory">Indian Territory</name>, where he died. His
        descendents were known by the name 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>. Reportedly a black child was also
        born after the expedition's passing, but did not live to maturity. Wheeler, 2:267; Josephy
        (NP), 11, 14, 165, 228, 231, 238; Space, 29; [Toole]; Ronda (LCAI), 233.</note>
            <note xml:id="n34051006" n="6">A medal showing a man sowing grain, one of a series of
        three depicting the white man's way of life, to show Indians the attractions of
        "civilization." They were discontinued because most Indians preferred a likeness of the
        "Great Father"—the president. See also 
        <ref n="1804-10-29" type="related">October 29, 1804</ref>. Prucha (IPM), 89–90.</note>
            <note xml:id="n34051007" n="7">A tipi, showing the assimilation of some elements of plains
        culture.</note>
            <note xml:id="n34051008" n="8">Again the lodge for menstruating women. This sentence may
        have been crowded in at the end of the entry later.</note>
            <note xml:id="n34051009" n="9">Or quamash, which is camas.</note>
            <note xml:id="n34051010" n="10">His name may have been added to a blank space.</note>
            <note xml:id="n34051011" n="11">The two names may have been added to blank spaces.</note>
            <note xml:id="n34051012" n="12">On 
        <name type="place" key="Lawyer (Commearp) Creek">Lawyer Creek</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Lewis County, Idaho">Lewis County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>, southwest of 
        <name type="place" key="Kamiah, Idaho">Kamiah</name>and near 
        <name type="person" key="Broken Arm">Broken Arm's</name>village; the party remained here
        until May 13.</note>
            <note xml:id="n34051013" n="13">A tipi, showing the influence of Plains Indian
        culture.</note>
            <note xml:id="n34051014" n="14">In 
        <name type="place" key="Lewis County, Idaho">Lewis County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>, southwest of 
        <name type="place" key="Kamiah, Idaho">Kamiah</name>, on 
        <name type="place" key="Lawyer (Commearp) Creek">Lawyer Creek</name>, which they called 
        <name type="place" key="Lawyer (Commearp) Creek">Commearp Creek</name>, from its 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>name. They remained
        here until May 13.</note>
            <note xml:id="n34051015" n="15">Apparently 
        <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name>, who came in the next
        day.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-05-09" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-05-11" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
