<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-04-07">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">April 7, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic
        Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            7</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">March 23–June 9, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1991</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">90-93</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">287-288</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">207</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journal Entries</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-10-01</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-04-12</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1806-04-07">April 7, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-04-07.01" ref="">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Monday April 7th 1806.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>This morning early the flesh of the remaining Elk was brought in and 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name>with the 
          <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph and Reubin">Feildses</name>departed agreeable to
          the order of the last evening.    we employed the party in drying the meat
          today which we completed by the evening, and we had it secured in dryed Elkskins and put
          on board in readiness for an early departure.    we were visited today by
          several parties of indians from a village about 8 miles above us of the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Sahhalah</name>nation. I detected one
          of them in steeling a peice of lead and sent him from camp. I hope we have now a
          sufficient stock of dryed meat to serve us as far the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Chopunnish</name>provided we can
          obtain a few dogs horses and roots by the way.    in the neignbourhood of the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Chopunnish</name>we can procure a few
          deer and perhaps a bear or two for the mountains.    last evening 
          <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">Reubin Fields</name>killed a bird of the quail
          kind it is reather larger than the quail, or partridge as they are called in 
          <name type="place" key="Virginia">Virginia</name>.    [
          <hi rend="italic">NB: Copy for 
          <name type="person" key="Barton, Benjamin Smith">Dr Barton</name>
                  </hi>]
          <ref target="n31040701" n="1"/>   it's form is precisely that of our
          partridge tho' it's plumage differs in every part.    the upper part of the
          head, sides and back of the neck, including the croop and about ⅓ of the under part of
          the body is of a bright dove coloured blue, underneath the under beak, as high as the
          lower edge of the eyes, and back as far as the hinder part of the eyes and thence coming
          down to a point in front of the neck about two thirds of it's length downwards, is of a
          fine dark brick red.    between this brick red and the dove colour there runs
          a narrow stripe of pure white.    the ears are covered with some coarse stiff
          dark brown feathers.    just at the base of the under chap there is narrow
          transverse stripe of white.    from the crown of the head two long round
          feathers extend backwards nearly in the direction of the beak and are of a black colour.
             the longest of these feathers is two inches and an half, it overlays and
          conceals the other which is somewhat shorter and seems to be raped in the plumage of
          that in front which folding backwards colapses behind and has a round appearance.
             the tail is composed of twelve dark brown feathers of nearly equal length.
             the large feathers of the wings are of a dark brown and are reather short
          in proportion to the body of the bird in that rispect very similar to our common
          partridge.    the covert of the wings and back are of a dove colour with a
          slight admixture of redish brown.    a wide stripe which extends from side to
          side of the body and occupyes the lower region of the breast is beautifully variagated
          with the brick red white and black which pedominate in the order they are mentioned and
          the colours mark the feathers transversely.    the legs are covered with
          feathers as low as the knee; these feathers are of a dark brown tiped with the dark
          brick red as are also those between and about the joining of the legs with the body.
             they have four toes on each foot of which three are in front and that in
          the center the longest, those one each side nearly of a length; that behing is also of
          good length and are all armed with long and strong nails.    the legs and feet
          are white and imbrecated with proportionably large broad scales.    the upper
          beak is short, wide at it's base, black, convex, curved downwards and reather obtusely
          pointed.    it exceeds the under chap considerably which is of a white colour,
          also convex underneath and obtusely pointed.    the nostrils are remarkably
          small placed far back and low down on the sides of the beak.    they are
          covered by a thin protuberant elastic, black leatherlike substance.    the
          eyes are of a uniform piercing black colour.    this is a most beautifull
          bird. I preserved the skin of this bird retaining the wings feet and head which I hope
          will give a just idea of the bird.    it's loud note is single and consists of
          a loud squall, intirely different from the whistling of our quales or partridge.
             it has a cherping note when allarmed something like ours.—   
          today there was a second of these birds killed by 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt C.</name>which precisely resembled that
          just discribed I believe these to be the male bird the female, if so, I have not yet
          seen.—    the day has been fair and weather extreemly pleasant.   
          we made our men exercise themselves in shooting today and regulate their guns found
          several of them that had their sights moved by accedent, and others that wanted some
          little alterations all which were compleately rectifyed in the course of the day.
             in the evening all the indians departed for their village.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-04-07.02" ref="">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Monday April 7th 1806</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>This morning 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name>&amp; the 
          <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph and Reubin">two Fields</name>Set out agreeably to
          their orders of last evening, the remainder of the party employed in drying the flesh of
          the five Elk killed by 
          <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name>yesterday.    which
          was completed and we had it Secured in dried Shaved Elk Skins and put on board in
          readiness for our early departure.    we were visited by Several parties of
          Indians from a Village about 12 miles above us of the 
          <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Sahhalah</name>
                  </hi>nation.    one of them was detected in Stealing a piece of Lead. I Sent
          him off imedeately. I hope now we have a Sufficient Stock of dryed meat to Serve us as
          far as the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Chopunnish</name>provided we can
          obtain a fiew dogs, horses and roots by the way.    in the neighbourhood of
          the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Chopunnish</name>under the 
          <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky Mountains</name>we can precure a fiew
          deer, and perhaps a Bear or two for the Mountains.</p>
               <p>The day has been fair and weather exceedingly pleasent.    we made our men
          exersise themselves in Shooting and regulateing their guns, found Several of them that
          had their Sights moved by accident, and others that wanted Some little alterations all
          which were compleated rectified in the Course of the day except my Small rifle, which I
          found wanted Cutting out.
          <ref target="n31040702" n="2"/>   about 4 oClock P M all the Indians left us,
          and returned to their Village.    they had brought with them Wappato, &amp;
          pashequa roots Chapellel cakes,
          <ref target="n31040703" n="3"/>and a Species of Raspberry for Sale, none of which they
          disposed of as they asked Such enormous prices for those articles that we were not able
          to purchase any. 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name>returned down the river in
          the evening &amp; informed us that the nativs had Sceared all the Elk from the river
          above. 
          <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph and Reubin">Joseph &amp; reuben Fields</name>had
          proceeded on further up the river in the canoe, he expected to the village.</p>
               <p>I provaled on an old indian to mark the 
          <name type="place" key="Willamette (Multnomah) River">Multnomah R</name>down on the Sand
          which hid and perfectly Corisponded with the Sketch given me by sundary others, with the
          addition of a circular mountain which passes this river at the falls and connects with
          the mountains of the Seacoast.    he also lais down the 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>a mos passing a high Conical
          Mountain near it's mouth on the lower Side and heads in Mount 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>which he lais down by
          raiseing the Sand as a very high mountain and Covered with eternal Snow.   
          the high mountain which this Indian lais down near the enterance of 
          <name type="place" key="Clackamas (Clarkamos) River">Clark a mos river</name>, we have
          not Seen as the hills in it's direction from this vally is high and obscures the Sight
          of it from us. 
          <name type="place" key="Mount Jefferson">Mt Jefferson</name>we Can plainly See from the
          enterance of 
          <name type="place" key="Willamette (Multnomah) River">Multnomah</name>from which place
          it bears S. E.    this is a noble Mountain and I think equally as high or
          Something higher than 
          <name type="place" key="Mount St. Helens">Mt. St. Heleans</name>
                  <ref target="n31040704" n="4"/>but its distance being much greater than that of the
          latter, So great a portion of it does not appear above the range of mountains which lie
          between both those Stupendious Mountains and the Mouth of 
          <name type="place" key="Willamette (Multnomah) River">Multnomah</name>.   
          like 
          <name type="place" key="Mount St. Helens">Mt. St. Heleans</name>its figure is a regular
          Cone and is covered with eturnial Snow.    that the 
          <name type="place" key="Clackamas (Clarkamos) Indians">Clarkamos nation</name>as also
          those at the 
          <name type="place" key="Willamette Falls">falls of the Multnomah</name>live principally
          on fish of which those Streams abound and also on roots which they precure on it's
          borders, they also Sometimes Come down to the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>in Serch of Wappato.   
          they build their houses in the Same form with those of the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbian</name>Vally of wide Split boads and
          Covered with bark of the White Cedar which is the entire length of the one Side of the
          roof and jut over at the eve about 18 inches.    at the distance of about 18
          inches transvers Spinters of dried pine is inserted through the Ceder bark inorder to
          keep it Smooth and prevent it's edge from Colapsing by the heat of the Sun; in this
          manner the nativs make a very Secure light and lasting roof of this bark.   
          which we have observed in every Vilege in this Vally as well as those above.
             this Indian also informed me the 
          <name type="place" key="Willamette (Multnomah) River">multnomah</name>above the falls
          was Crouded with rapids and thickly inhabited by indians of the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Kalapuya Indians">Cal-lah-po-é-wah</name>Nation.
             he informed he had himself been a long way up that river &amp;c.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-04-07.03" ref="">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>Monday 7th of April 1806.    a fair morning    
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name>&amp; the 
          <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph and Reubin">2 Fields</name>were sent on a head to
          ascend the River &amp; hunt untill our arival    all hands set at jurking
          &amp; drying the Elk meat.    a number of Savages came down the River in their
          canoes    brought a fiew dogs a little Chapellel
          <ref target="n31040705" n="5"/>&amp; roots for trade, but asked a large price for them
          So we purchased only one dog.    we got the meat all dry towards evening and
          packed it up &amp;C    the Musquetoes trouble us a little &amp;c—   
          
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name>returned with the Savages and
          killed 2 ducks this evening &amp;c—</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-04-07.04" ref="">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Monday 7th.</hi>   This was a plesant day, but cloudy. Three
          hunters
          <ref target="n31040706" n="6"/>went on ahead again and the rest of the party remained
          drying meat to subsit on while we passed the 
          <name type="place" key="Great Columbian Plain">Columbia plains</name>, as there is no
          game in that part of the country, according to the accounts given by the natives, who
          are daily coming down; and say that those remaining in the plains are in a starving
          condition, and will continue so until the salmon begin to run, which is very soon
          expected. We continued here all day; and one of our hunters killed a beautiful small
          bird of the quail kind.
          <ref target="n31040707" n="7"/>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n31040701" n="1">Following the interlineation, 
        <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>drew a vertical line through
        several lines, all in red ink.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31040702" n="2">Apparently the rifling of 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>small-bore, 
        <name type="place" key="Kentucky">Kentucky</name>-style hunting rifle had worn down and
        needed re-boring. Most of 
        <name type="person" key="Shields, John">John Shield's</name>tools had been cached at the 
        <name type="place" key="Marias River">Marias River</name>, but he managed the job to 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>satisfaction. See 
        <ref n="1806-04-08" type="related">April 8, 1806</ref>. Russel (GEF), 99–100; Russell
        (FTT), 361.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31040703" n="3">Sometimes the men begin it with "sh." It is from the
        Chinookan 
        <hi rend="italic">a-sáblal,</hi>"bread," and is cous, 
        <hi rend="italic">Lomatium cous</hi>(Wats.) Coult. &amp; Rose. Hitchcock et al., 3:548–49.
        See 
        <ref n="1805-11-01" type="related">November 1, 1805</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31040704" n="4">
               <name type="place" key="Mount St. Helens">Mt. St. Helens</name>reaches a height of 9,677
        feet; 
        <name type="place" key="Mount Jefferson">Mt. Jefferson</name>is 10,495 feet.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31040705" n="5">Usually spelled by the captains with "s" instead of "c" at
        the beginning; it is cous, 
        <hi rend="italic">Lomatium cous</hi>(Wats.) Coult. &amp; Rose. The Chinookan word is 
        <hi rend="italic">a-sáblal,</hi>"bread."</note>
            <note xml:id="n31040706" n="6">
               <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name>and the 
        <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph and Reubin">Field brothers</name>again.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31040707" n="7">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>says on this date that this
        happened "last evening," and that 
        <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">Reubin Field</name>was the hunter. The bird is the
        mountain quail, 
        <hi rend="italic">Oreortyx pictus,</hi>a new species. See 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>entry for 
        <ref n="1806-04-06" type="related">April 6</ref>and 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>for April 7.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-04-06" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-04-08" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
