<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-04-27">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">April 27, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic
        Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            7</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">March 23–June 9, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1991</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">173-177</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">298</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">216-217</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
         <geoDecl datum="WGS" xml:id="lc.geo.1806-04-27.01">
            <placeName/>
            <geo>46.0336 -118.6835</geo>
            <note>Camped at a Walula village in Benton County, WA, below and opposite the mouth of the Walla Walla River, south of Yellepit. Remained at this camp until 04-29.</note>
         </geoDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc/>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-10-07</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-04-12</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1806-04-27">April 27, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-04-27.01"
              ref="lc.geo.1806-04-27.01">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Sunday April 27th 1806.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>This morning we were detained untill 9 A. M. in consequence of the absence of one of 
          <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbono's</name>horses.   
          the horse at length being recovered we set out and [
          <hi rend="italic">NB: passed above our camp a small river called 
          <name type="place" key="Umatilla (Youmalolam) River">Youmalolam riv</name>.</hi>
                  <ref target="n32042701" n="1"/>&amp; 
          <hi rend="italic">to</hi>] at the distance of fifteen miles passed through a country
          similar to that of yesterday; the hills at the extremity of this distance again approach
          the river and are rocky abrupt and 300 feet high.    we ascended the hill and
          marched through a high plain for 9 miles when we again returned to the river,
          <ref target="n32042702" n="2"/>I now thought it best to halt as the horses and men were
          much fatiegued altho had not reached the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Walula Indians">Wallah wollah</name>village as we had
          been led to beleive by our guide who informed us that the village was at the place we
          should next return to the river, and the consideration of our having but little
          provision had been our inducement to make the march we had made this morning.
             we collected some of the dry stalks of weeds and the stems of a shrub which
          resembles the southern wood; made a small fire and boiled a small quantity of our jerked
          meat on which we dined; while here the principal Cheif of the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Walula Indians">Wallahwallahs</name>joined us with six
          men of his nation.    this Cheif by name 
          <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="person" key="Yelleppit">Yel-lept'</name>
                  </hi>had visited us on the morning of the 19 of October at our encampment a little below
          this place; we gave him at that time a small medal, and promised him a larger one on our
          return.
          <ref target="n32042703" n="3"/>   he appeared much gratifyed at seeng us
          return, invited us to remain at his village three or four days and assured us that we
          should be furnished with a plenty of such food as they had themselves; and some horses
          to assist us on our journey.    after our scanty repast we continued our march
          accompanyed by 
          <name type="person" key="Yelleppit">Yellept</name>and his party to the village which we
          found at the distance of six miles situated on the N. side of the river at the lower
          side of the low country about 12 ms. below the entrance of 
          <name type="place" key="Lewis (Cahwahnakiooks) River">Lewis's river</name>.
          <ref target="n32042704" n="4"/>This Cheif is a man of much influence not only in his
          own nation but also among the neighbouring tribes and nations.—    This
          Village consists of 15 large mat lodges.    at present they seem to subsist
          principally on a speceis of mullet which weigh from one to three lbs. and roots of
          various discriptions which these plains furnish them in great abundance.   
          they also take a few salmon trout of the white kind.—    
          <name type="person" key="Yelleppit">Yellept</name>haranged his village in our favour
          intreated them to furnish us with fuel and provision and set the example himself by
          bringing us an armfull of wood and a platter of 3 roasted mullets.
          <ref target="n32042705" n="5"/>   the others soon followed his example with
          rispect to fuel and we soon found ourselves in possession of an ample stock.
             they birn the stems of the shrubs in the plains there being no timber in
          their neighbourhood of any discription.    we purchased four dogs of these
          people on which the party suped heartily having been on short allowance for near two
          days.    the indians retired when we requested them this evening and behaved
          themselves in every rispect extreemly well. the indians informed us that there was a
          good road which passed from the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">columbia</name>opposite to this village to the
          entrance of the 
          <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Kooskooske</name>on
          the S. side of 
          <name type="place" key="Lewis (Cahwahnakiooks) River">Lewis's river</name>;
          <ref target="n32042706" n="6"/>they also informed us, that there were a plenty of deer
          and Antelopes on the road, with good water and grass.    we knew that a road
          in that direction if the country would permit would shorten our rout at least 80 miles.
             the indians also informed us that the country was level and the road good,
          under these circumstances we did not hesitate in pursuing the rout recommended by our
          guide whos information was corroberated by 
          <name type="person" key="Yelleppit">Yellept</name>&amp; others.    we
          concluded to pass our horses over early in the morning.—</p>
               <p>
                  <figure rend="mhs">
                     <p>Confluence of 
              <name type="place"
                              key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">
              Snake</name>and 
              <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>Rivers and Environs by 
              <name type="person" key="Yelleppit">Yelleppit</name>, ca. April 27,
              <lb/>1806, Astronomy Notebook 
              <bibl>
                           <orgName>Missouri Historical Society</orgName>
                        </bibl>
                     </p>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-04-27.02"
              ref="lc.geo.1806-04-27.01">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Sunday April 27th 1806.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>This morning we were detained untill 9 A M in consequence of the absence of one of 
          <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Shabono's</name>horses.   
          the horse being at length recovered we Set out and to the distance of 15 miles passed
          through a Country Similar to that of yesterday.    (passed 
          <name type="place" key="Musselshell Rapids">Muscle Shell rapid</name>)
          <ref target="n32042707" n="7"/>and at the experation of this distance again approached
          the river, and are rocky abrupt and 300 feet high.    we assended the hill and
          marched through a high plain 10 miles where we again returned to the river.   
          we halted altho we had not reached the 
          <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Walula Indians">Wal-lah-lal-lah</name>
                  </hi>village as we had been led to believe by our guide who informed us that the village
          was that the place we Should next return to the river, and the considiration of our
          haveing but little provisions had been our inducement to make the march we had made this
          morning.    we collected Some of the dry stalks of weeds and the Stems of
          Shrubs or weeds which resemble the Southern wood; made a Small fire and boiled a Small
          quantity of our 〈boiled〉 jurked meat on which we dined; while here we were met by the
          principal Chief of the 
          <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Walula Indians">Wal lah wal lah</name>
                  </hi>Nation and Several of his nation.    this chief by name 
          <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="person" key="Yelleppit">Yel lep-pet</name>
                  </hi>had visited us on the morning of the 19th of Octr. at our encampment imedeately
          opposit to us; we gave him at that time a Small medal, and promised him a large one on
          our return.    he appeared much gratified at Seeing us return.    he
          envited us to remain at his village 3 or 4 days and assured us that we Should be
          furnished with a plenty of Such food as they had themselves, and Some horses to assist
          us on our journey.    after our Scanty repast we Continued our March
          accompanied by 
          <name type="person" key="Yelleppit">Yelleppit</name>and his party to the Village which
          we found at the distance of Six miles, Situated on the North Side of the river.
             about 16 miles below the enterance of 
          <name type="place" key="Lewis (Cahwahnakiooks) River">Lewis's river</name>. This Chief
          is a man of much influence not only in his own nation but also among the neignbouring
          tribes and nations.—    the village Consists of 15 large mat Lodges.
             at present they Seam to Subsist principally on a Species of Mullet which
          weighs from one to 3 pds. and roots of various discriptions which those plains furnish
          them in great abundance. They also 〈furnish〉 take a fiew Salmon trout of the white kind.
             
          <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="person" key="Yelleppit">Yelleppet</name>
                  </hi>haranged his village in our favor intreated them to furnish us with fuel &amp;
          provisions and Set the example himself by bringing us an armfull of wood, and a platter
          with 3 rosted mullets.    Soon followed his example with respect to fuel and
          we Soon found ourselves in possession of an ample Stock, they burn the Stems of the
          Shrubs in the plains, there being no timber in this neighbourhood of any discription.
             we purchased 4 dogs of those people on which the party Suped hartily
          haveing been on Short allowance for near 2 days.    the Indians retired when
          we requested them this evening and behaved themselves in every respect very well.
             the Indians informed us that there was a good road Which passed from the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>opposit to this Village to the
          enterance of 
          <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Kooskooske</name>on
          the S. Side of 
          <name type="place" key="Lewis (Cahwahnakiooks) River">Lewis's river</name>, they also
          informed us, there were a plenty of Deer and Antilopes on the road with good water and
          grass.    we knew that a road in that direction if the Country would permit it
          would Shorten the rout at least 80 miles.    the Indians also inform us that
          the County was leavel and the road good, under those circumstances we did not hesitate
          in pursueing the rout recommended by our guide and Corroberated by 
          <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="person" key="Yelleppit">Yetleppit</name>
                  </hi>and others.    we Concluded to pass our horses over early in the
          morning.—    made 31 miles to day—</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-04-27.03"
              ref="lc.geo.1806-04-27.01">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>Sunday 27th of April 1806.    a little rain fell the latter part of last
          night.    we Set out as usal and proceed. on    Soon passd. a Small
          village of 3 lodges then assended a high plain where we Saw an extensive country around
          us &amp; not a tree to be Seen    came about 20 miles before we halted &amp;
          delayed a Short time    eat a little dry meat &amp; let our horses feed a
          Short time and proceed on about 5 miles further and arived at a large village of the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Walula Indians">wal-a-wal tribe</name>, at the
          commencement of a low barron Smooth country where we Camped
          <ref target="n32042708" n="8"/>   bought a fat dog to each mess.   
          these natives are numerous    their is another village on the opposite Side of
          the river &amp; a great number of horses.    we get different kinds of roots
          and fresh Salmon trout &amp; Suckers &amp;C.    all these Savages are glad to
          See us and appear verry friendly.—</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-04-27.04"
              ref="lc.geo.1806-04-27.01">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Sunday 27th.</hi>   The morning was cloudy with some light
          showers of rain; and about 9 o'clock we proceeded on through the plains, accompanied by
          a great many of the natives. Some light showers of rain fell at intervals during the
          day; and after halting about 2 hours we continued our journey to sunset, when we came to
          a large village of mat-lodges, belonging to a band of the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Walula Indians">Wal-la-wal-las</name>, who have encamped
          here on the north side of the river. Here we remained all night, and the natives were
          good enough to supply us with some faggots of brush, they had gathered in the plains
          from the sage bushes,
          <ref target="n32042709" n="9"/>which grow in great abundance on some part of these
          plains and are very large.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n32042701" n="1">Unnoticed on the outbound journey, it is the 
        <name type="place" key="Umatilla (Youmalolam) River">Umatilla River</name>, in 
        <name type="place" key="Umatilla County, Oreg.">Umatilla County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>; "
        <name type="place" key="Umatilla (Youmalolam) River">You ma lol am R</name>" on 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>map 75. It is a 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>term, 
        <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="place" key="Umatilla (Youmalolam) River">y</name>
                  <seg n="u243">ó</seg>:
        <name type="place" key="Umatilla (Youmalolam) River">matalam</name>,</hi>for the 
        <name type="place" key="Umatilla (Youmalolam) River">Umatilla River</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32042702" n="2">The route, through southeastern 
        <name type="place" key="Benton County, Wash.">Benton County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>, does not appear on 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>map 75.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32042703" n="3">
               <name type="person" key="Yelleppit">Yelleppit</name>(
        <hi rend="italic">yelépt,</hi>"friend, blood brother" in 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>, and 
        <hi rend="italic">yal
        <seg n="u616u769">ɨ́</seg>pt,</hi>"trading partner" in Shahaptian) is discussed at 
        <ref n="1805-10-19" type="related">October 19, 1805</ref>. His medal may be the one that
        is among the 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>items at the Oregon Historical
        Society (see 
        <ref n="1805-10-19" type="related">October 19, 1805</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="n32042704" n="4">This village was in 
        <name type="place" key="Benton County, Wash.">Benton County</name>, opposite and below the
        mouth of the 
        <name type="native_place" key="Walla Walla (Waller Waller) River">Walla Walla
        River</name>, probably south of present 
        <name type="place" key="Yellepit Way Station">Yellepit way station</name>, at a site
        perhaps now under 
        <name type="place" key="Lake Walula">Lake Wallula</name>. The Indian site was recorded by
        Drucker, but has not been investigated. Drucker's placement of the village, above high
        water line, may provide opportunity for future excavation. Drucker (ARMR); Osborne; Shiner
        (MR). 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>map 75 indicates that the camp for April 27 was across the
        river in 
        <name type="place" key="Walla Walla County, Wash.">Walla Walla County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>, just above the mouth of the 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Walula Indians">Walla Walla</name>. The journals, however,
        make it clear that this day's camp was at the village, and that the party crossed the 
        <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>on 
        <ref n="1806-04-29" type="related">April 29</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32042705" n="5">Mullets are suckers, 
        <hi rend="italic">Catostomus</hi>sp.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32042706" n="6">The trail that they would take in a few days through
        southeastern 
        <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>, across 
        <name type="place" key="Walla Walla County, Wash.">Walla Walla</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Columbia County, Wash.">Columbia</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Garfield County, Wash.">Garfield</name>, and 
        <name type="place" key="Asotin County, Wash.">Asotin</name>counties, to the mouth of the 
        <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Clearwater
        (Kooskooske)</name>at 
        <name type="place" key="Lewiston, Idaho">Lewiston</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>. The "S. side" apparently refers to the
        starboard, or east, side of the 
        <name type="place"
                     key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Snake (Lewis's)
        River</name>, where the 
        <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Clearwater</name>comes
        in. It may have been about this time that 
        <name type="person" key="Yelleppit">Yelleppit</name>gave 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>information for a map of the
        country that appears in the captain's Astronomy Notebook (fig. 14). See 
        <ref n="v02.appendix.c" type="related">Appendix C</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32042707" n="7">In the vicinity of present 
        <name type="place" key="McNary Dam">McNary Dam</name>, between 
        <name type="place" key="Umatilla County, Oreg.">Umatilla County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>, and 
        <name type="place" key="Benton County, Wash.">Benton County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>. 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>map 75.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32042708" n="8">A 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Walula Indians">Walula</name>(
        <name type="native_nation" key="Walula Indians">Walla Walla</name>) village in 
        <name type="place" key="Benton County, Wash.">Benton County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>, below and opposite the mouth of the
        
        <name type="place" key="Walla Walla (Waller Waller) River">Walla Walla River</name>, south
        of 
        <name type="place" key="Yellepit Way Station">Yellepit way station</name>and perhaps now
        under 
        <name type="place" key="Lake Walula">Lake Walula</name>. The party remained with them
        until April 29, at their insistence.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32042709" n="9">Big sagebrush.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-04-26" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-04-28" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
