<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-05-01">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">May 1, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic
        Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            7</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">March 23–June 9, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1991</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">195-198</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">301-302</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">218-219</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
         <geoDecl datum="WGS" xml:id="lc.geo.1806-05-01.01">
            <placeName/>
            <geo>46.2667 -118.15</geo>
            <note>Camped near Waitsburg, eastern Walla Walla County, WA.</note>
         </geoDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc/>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-10-08</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-04-12</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1806-05-01">May 1, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-05-01.01"
              ref="lc.geo.1806-05-01.01">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Thursday May 1st 1806.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>We collected our horses tolerably early this morning took and set out a little after
          7 A. M.    we pursued the indian road which led us up the creek about nine
          miles, here the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Chopunnish</name>man wo was in front
          with me informed that an old unbeaten tract which he pointed out to the left was our
          nearest rout.    〈I〉 we halted the party and directed them to unload and let
          their horses graize untill our guide came up who was at some distance behind. I wished
          to obtain good information of this newly recommended tract before I could consent to
          leave the present road which seemed to lead us in the proper direction was level and
          furnished with wood and water.    when the guide arrived he seemed much
          displeased with the other, he assured us that the rout up the creek was the nearest, and
          much the best, that if we took the other we would be obliged to remain here untill
          tomorrow morning, and then travel a whole day before we could reach water, and that
          there was no wood; the other agreed that this was the case.    we therefore
          did not hesitate to pursue the rout recommended by the guide.
          <ref target="n32050101" n="1"/>   the creek, it's bottom lands, and the
          appearance of the plains were much as those of esterday only with this difference that
          the latter were not so sandy.    we had sent out four hunters this morning two
          on foot and 2 on horseback they joined us while we halted here. 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name>had killed a beaver.
             at 1 P. M. we resumed our march, leaving the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Chopunnish</name>man and his family;
          he had determined to remain at that place untill the next morning and then pursue the
          rout he had recommended to us.    he requested a small quantity of powder and
          lead which we gave him.    we traveled 17 miles this evening, making a total
          of 26 Ms. and encamped.
          <ref target="n32050102" n="2"/>   the first 3 miles of our afternoons march
          was through a similar country with that of the forenoon; the creek bottoms then became
          higher and widened to the extent of from 2 to 3 Ms.    the hills on the N.
          side were low but those on the opposite side retained their hight.    we saw a
          number of deer of which 
          <name type="person" key="Labiche, François">Labuish</name>killed one.    the
          timber on the creek becomes more abundant and it's extensive bottoms affords a pleasent
          looking country.    the guide informs us that we shall now find a plenty of
          wood water and game quite to the 
          <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Kooskooske</name>. we
          saw a great number of the Curloss, some Crains, ducks, prarie larks
          <ref target="n32050103" n="3"/>and several speceis of sparrows common to the praries. I
          see very little difference between the apparent face of the country here and that of the
          plains of the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>only that these are not enlivened
          by the vast herds of buffaloe Elk &amp;c which ornament the other.    the
          courses and distances of this day are N. 45 E. 9 M. and N. 75 E. 17 M. along the
          Northern side of this creek to our encampment.    some time after we had
          encamped three young men arrived from the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Walula Indians">Wallahwollah</name>village bringing with
          them a steel trap belonging to one of our party which had been neglegently left behind;
          this is an act of integrity rarely witnessed among indians.    during our stay
          with them they several times found the knives of the men which had been carelessly
          lossed by them and returned them. I think we can justly affirm to the honor of these
          people that they are the most hospitable, honest, and sincere people that we have met
          with in our voyage.—</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-05-01.02"
              ref="lc.geo.1806-05-01.01">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Thursday May 1st 1806.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>This morning we collected our horses and made an early Start, haveing preveously Sent
          a hed 4 hunters with derections to proceed up the Creek and kill every Species of game
          which they might meet with.    the Small portion of rain which fell last night
          Caused the road to be much furmer and better than yesterday.    the morning
          Cloudy and Cool.    we proceeded up the Creek on the N. E. Side through a
          Countrey of less sand and Some rich bottoms on the Creek which is partially Supplyed
          with Small Cotton trees, willow, red willow, choke Cherry, white thorn, birch, elder,
          <ref target="n32050104" n="4"/>[
          <hi rend="italic">blank</hi>] rose &amp; honey suckle. Great portion of these bottoms
          has been latterly burnt which has entirely distroyed the timbered growth. at the
          distance of 
          <hi rend="italic">nine</hi>miles we over took our hunters, they had killed one bever
          only    at this place the road forked, one leaveing the Creek and the Corse of
          it is nearly North.    the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Chopunnish</name>who had accompanied
          us with his family informed us that this was our best way.    that it was a
          long distance without water.    and advised us to Camp on the Creek at this
          place and in the morning to Set out early. This information perplexed us a little, in as
          much as the idea of going a days march without water thro an open sandy plain and on a
          Course 50° our [out?] of our derection.    we deturmined to unlode and wate
          for our Guide, or the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Chopunnish</name>man who had
          accompanied us from the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">long
          Narrows</name>, who was in the rear with 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name>our interpreter.   
          on his arrival we enquired of him which was the best and most direct roade for us to
          take.    he informed us that the road pointed out by his cumerade was through
          a open hilly and Sandy Countrey to the river 
          <name type="place"
                        key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Lewis's
          River</name>, and was a long ways around, and that we Could not git to any water to day.
             the other roade up the creek was a more derect Course, plenty of water wood
          and only one hill in the whole distance and the road which he had always recommended to
          us. Some words took place between those two men    the latter appeared in
          great pation Mounted his horse and Set out up the Creek. we Sent a man after him and
          brought him back informed him that we believed what he Said and Should imedeately after
          dinner proceed on the road up the Creek with him.    we gave the former man
          Some powder and ball which had been promised him, and after an early dinner Set out up
          the Creek with our guide leaveing the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Chopunnish</name>man and his family
          encamped at the forks of the road where they intended to Stay untill the morning and
          proceed on the rout he had recommended to us. we traviled 17 miles this evening makeing
          a total of 26 mls. and encamped.    the first 3 miles of our afternoons march
          was through a Simaler Country of that of the fore noon; the Creek bottoms then became
          higher and wider; to the extent of from 2 to 3 miles.    we Saw Several Deer
          of which 
          <name type="person" key="Labiche, François">Labiech</name>killed one.    the
          timber on the Creek became more abundant and less burnt, and its extensive bottoms
          afford a pleasent looking Country.    we Saw a Great number of Curloos, Some
          Crains, Ducks, prarie cocks, and Several Species of Sparrows common to the praries. I
          See Very little difference between the apparant face of the Country here and that of the
          plains of the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>.    only that those
          are not enlivened by the vast herds of Buffalow, Elk &amp;c. which animated those of the
          
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>. The Courses &amp; distances of
          this day are N. 45° E. 9 mls. &amp; N. 75° E. 17 Miles allong the North Side of this
          Creek to our encampment. Sometime after we had encamped three young men arrived from the
          
          <name type="native_nation" key="Walula Indians">Wallah wallah</name>Village bringing
          with them a Steel trap belonging to one of our party which had been negligently left
          behind; this is an act of integrity rearly witnessed among Indians.    dureing
          our Stay with them they Several times found the knives of the men which had been
          Carefully lossed by them and returned them. I think we can justly affirm to the honor of
          those people that they are the most hospitable, honist and Sencere people that we have
          met with on our Voyage.—</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-05-01.03"
              ref="lc.geo.1806-05-01.01">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Thursday 1st day</hi>of 
          <hi rend="italic">May 1806</hi>.    four hunters Set out eairly to go on a
          hunting.    we Set out as usal &amp; proceeded on up this river over high
          plains and river bottom which is partly covred with cotton &amp; other timber.
             the beaver are pleanty.    one of the hunters
          <ref target="n32050105" n="5"/>killd. one.    no other game to be Seen
             about noon we halted to dine. Several of the Savages who accompy. us leave
          us here and take a cross road to the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia river</name>.    we proceed.
          on up the branch
          <ref target="n32050106" n="6"/>over Smooth handsom plains and bottoms. Saw a timbred
          country a long distance to the S. E. &amp; Mount of Snow. Saw Several deer run out of
          the groves of timber along the branch.    about Sunset one of the hunters
          <ref target="n32050107" n="7"/>killed a deer. So we Camped
          <ref target="n32050108" n="8"/>by the branch having made 26 miles this day   
          Soon after we Camped two young men of the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Walula Indians">wal-awal tribe</name>came up to our Camp
          &amp; brought us our Steel trap which was forgot at their village.    this is
          an Instance which we had not any right to expect from Savages.    we gave them
          one a knife the other a Sun glass, &amp;.C. and a little vension    the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Walula Indians">wal-a-wal trib</name>e of 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Flat heads</name>have proved
          themselves the honnestest Savages we have met with for they had great chance to Steel
          had they been disposed, but instead of that they helped us as much as lay in their power
          and believe that we will return and trade with them, as we have told them   
          they disired us to bring them guns and ammunition, copper kittles.    knives
          beeds Scarlet buttens, and allmost any kind of marchandize as other Savages,
          &amp;C.—</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-05-01.04"
              ref="lc.geo.1806-05-01.01">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Thursday 1st May,</hi>1806.    Some rain fell during the
          night, and the morning continues cloudy. We set out early and travelled up the branch,
          which is a fine stream about twenty yards wide, with some cottonwood, birch and willows
          on its banks. One of four hunters, who went forward very early this morning, returned at
          noon with a beaver he had killed; other game is scarce. We then halted to dine, where
          the road forks, one going up the branch an east course, and the other north towards the
          large river.
          <ref target="n32050109" n="9"/>Here our Indians differed in opinion with respect to the
          best road to be taken. The man with the family and gang of horses said he would go
          across to the Great river to-morrow; but we followed the opinion of the young man our
          guide, and proceeded on up the creek. We travelled about twenty-five miles, and encamped
          without any of the natives, except our guide, who generally keeps with the hunters, one
          of whom
          <ref target="n32050110" n="10"/>killed a deer this evening. The higher we go up the
          creek the cotton-wood
          <ref target="n32050111" n="11"/>is more large and plenty; and the plains beautiful.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n32050101" n="1">The route goes up 
        <name type="place" key="Touchet River">Touchet River</name>, in 
        <name type="place" key="Walla Walla County, Wash.">Walla Walla County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>; this portion of it does not appear
        on any 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>maps.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32050102" n="2">Apparently in the vicinity of 
        <name type="place" key="Waitsburg, Wash.">Waitsburg</name>, in eastern 
        <name type="place" key="Walla Walla County, Wash.">Walla Walla County</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32050103" n="3">
               <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>calls it a prairie cock in his entry.
        
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>bird could be either the western
        meadowlark or the horned lark (see 
        <ref n="1806-04-30-1" type="related">weather remarks</ref>for April 15, 1806), while 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>is perhaps the sage grouse, 
        <hi rend="italic">Centrocercus urophasianus</hi>[AOU, 309]. Most likely it is the same
        bird in both entries and one of these three. Holmgren, 29, 31.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32050104" n="4">Blue elderberry, 
        <hi rend="italic">Sambucus cerulea</hi>Raf. Hitchcock et al., 4:462.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32050105" n="5">
               <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name>, reports 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32050106" n="6">Up the 
        <name type="place" key="Touchet River">Touchet River</name>, in 
        <name type="place" key="Walla Walla County, Wash.">Walla Walla County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32050107" n="7">
               <name type="person" key="Labiche, François">Labiche</name>, says 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32050108" n="8">In the vicinity of 
        <name type="place" key="Waitsburg, Wash.">Waitsburg</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Walla Walla County, Wash.">Walla Walla County</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32050109" n="9">The branch is 
        <name type="place" key="Touchet River">Touchet River</name>; the large river is the 
        <name type="place"
                     key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">
        Snake</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32050110" n="10">
               <name type="person" key="Labiche, François">Labiche</name>, according to the
        captains.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32050111" n="11">Black cottonwood.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-04-30-1" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-05-02" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
