<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-06-28">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">June 28, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic
        Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            8</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">June 10–September 26, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1987</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">59-61</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">327-328</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">245</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
         <geoDecl datum="WGS" xml:id="lc.geo.1806-06-28.01">
            <placeName/>
            <geo>46.5667 -114.7167</geo>
            <note>Camped near Powell Junction on the present Forest Road 500, Idaho County, ID. Also
          near Papoose Saddle and north of Powell Ranger Station.</note>
         </geoDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc/>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-11-04</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-04-12</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1806-06-28">June 28, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-06-28.01"
              ref="lc.geo.1806-06-28.01">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Saturday June 28th 1806.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>This morning we collected our horses and set out as usual after an early breakfast.
             several of our horses had straggled to a considersble distance in surch of
          food but we were fortunate enough to find them in good time they look extreemly gant
          this morning, however the indians informed us that at noon we would arrive at a place
          where there was good food for them.    we continued our rout along the
          dividing ridge passing one very deep hollow and at the distance of six miles passed our
          encampment of the 〈16〉 [
          <hi rend="italic">NB: 15th</hi>]
          <ref target="n36062801" n="1"/>of September last, one and a half miles further we
          passed the road which leads by the fishery falling in on the wright immediately on the
          dividing ridge.
          <ref target="n36062802" n="2"/>   about eleven O'clock we arrived at an
          untimbered side of a mountain with a Southern aspect just above the fishery   
          here we found an abundance of grass for our horses as the Indians had informed us.
             as our horses were very hungary and much fatiegued and from information no
          other place where we could obtain grass for them within the reach of this evening's
          travel we determined to remain at this place all night having come 13 miles only.
          <ref target="n36062803" n="3"/>   the water was distant from our encampment
          we therefore melted snow and used the water principally.    the whole of the
          rout of this day was over deep snows.    we find the traveling on the snow not
          worse than without it, as the easy passage it gives us over rocks and fallen timber
          fully compensate for the inconvenience of sliping, certain it is that we travel
          considerably faster on the snow than without it.    the snow sinks from 2 to 3
          inches with a hors, is coarse and firm and seems to be formed of the larger and more
          dense particles of the snow; the surface of the snow is reather harder in the morning
          than after the sun shines on it a few hours, but it is not in that situation so dense as
          to prevent the horse from obtaining good foothold.    we killed a small black
          pheasant; this bird is generally found in the snowey region of the mountains and feeds
          on the leaves of the pine and fir.
          <ref target="n36062804" n="4"/>   there is a speceis of small whortleburry
          <ref target="n36062805" n="5"/>common to the hights of the mountains, and a speceis of
          grass with a broad succulent leaf which looks not unlike a flag;
          <ref target="n36062806" n="6"/>of the latter the horses are very fond, but as yet it is
          generally under the snow or mearly making it's appearance as it confined to the upper
          parts of the highest mountains.—</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-06-28.02"
              ref="lc.geo.1806-06-28.01">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Saturday June 28th 1806</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>This morning we Colected our horses and Set out as usial after an early brackfast.
             we continued our rout along the dividig ridge over knobs &amp; through deep
          hollows    passed our encampmt of the 14 Sept. last near the forks of the road
          leaving the one on which we had Came one leading to the fishery to our right imediately
          on the dividing ridge.    at 12 oClock we arrived at an untimberd side of a
          mountain with a southern aspect just above the fishery    here we found an
          abundance of grass for our horses as the guids had informed us.    as our
          horses were hungary and much fatiegued and from information no other place where we
          could obtain grass for them within the reach of this evening's travel we deturmined to
          remain at this place all night haveing come 13 m. only.    the water was
          distant from our Encampment we therefore melted Snow and used the water.   
          the whole of the rout of this day was over deep Snow.    we find the
          travelling on the Snow not worse than without it, as easy passage it givs us over rocks
          and fallen timber fully compensates for the inconvenience of sliping, certain it is that
          we travel considerably faster on the snow than without it.    the Snow Sinks
          from 2 to 3 inches with a horse, is course and firm and seems to be formed of the larger
          particles    the surface of the snow sees to be rather harder in the morning
          than after the Sun Shines on it a fiew hours, but it is not in that situation so dense
          as to prevent the horses from obtaining good foothold. I killed a Small black pheasant;
          this bird is generally found in the Snowey region of the mountains and feeds on the
          leaves of the pine &amp; fir.    there is a Species of Small huckleberry
          common to the hights of the mountains, and a Species of grass with a broad succulent
          leaf which looks not unlike a flag; of the latter the horses are very fond, but as yet
          it is generally under the Snow, or mearly makeing it's appearance as it confined to the
          upper part of the highest mountains.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-06-28.03"
              ref="lc.geo.1806-06-28.01">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>〈Saturday 28th June 1806.    a fair cool morning.    we Set out
          as usal and proceeded on    [
          <hi rend="italic">four words illegible</hi>] the vallies on to the ridge [thick?]
             2 hunters went on a head to hunt.    we descended a mountn. down
          on a fork of 
          <name type="place" key="Lolo (Collins's) Creek (Idaho)">Collinses Creek</name>, found
          the meat of a deer which one of the hunters had killed.    we crossed the
          creek and ascended    a high Steep mountn.    came in [our old] road
             had a bad Shower of hail and [Some?] Thunder〉</p>
               <p>Saturday 28th June 1806.    a clear cool morning    we Set out as
          usal and proceeded on verry well    the Snow continues as yesterday.
             our guides took us on a ridge different from that we went last fall, but a
          better way.
          <ref target="n36062807" n="7"/>   about one oClock we halted on the top of a 
          <name type="place" key="Bald Mountain">bald mountain</name>on the South Side of which
          our horses git tollarable feed. So we delay this afternoon to let our horses refresh
          themselves &amp;C    in the evening we had Thunder &amp; hail.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-06-28.04"
              ref="lc.geo.1806-06-28.01">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Saturday 28th.</hi>   The morning was pleasant, we set out
          early, and passed the place where we had encamped on the 15th Sept. last when the snow
          fell on us. After passing this place about a mile, we took a left-hand path,
          <ref target="n36062808" n="8"/>and travelled along high ridges till noon, when we came
          to a good place of grass; where we halted and remained all the afternoon to let our
          horses feed, as they had but little grass last night. Some hunters went out, as we saw
          some elk signs here, and our meat is exhausted. We still have a good stock of roots,
          which we pound and make thick soup of, that eats very well. In the evening our hunters
          came in but had not killed any thing. On the south side of this ridge there is summer
          with grass and other herbage in aboundance; and on the north side, winter with snow six
          or eight feet deep.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n36062801" n="1">Again, a substitution and a revision in an apparent blank
        space. 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>gives the date of the previous camp
        as 
        <ref n="1805-09-14" type="related">September 14</ref>. 
        <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>has it right; they were passing
        the camp of 
        <ref n="1805-09-15" type="related">September 15</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36062802" n="2">They deviated here from their westbound route, which went
        down into the valley of the 
        <name type="place" key="Lochsa (Upper Kooskooske) River">Lochsa River</name>in 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho County, Idaho">Idaho County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>. Now they continued eastward on the 
        <name type="place" key="Lolo Trail">Lolo Trail</name>, as it is known today, along the
        ridge. This portion of the eastbound route does not appear on 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>map 70. Space, 38; Peebles (LT), map.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36062803" n="3">The camp was near 
        <name type="place" key="Powell Junction">Powell Junction</name>on the present 
        <name type="place" key="Forest Service Road 500">Forest Road 500</name>in 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho County, Idaho">Idaho County</name>, also near 
        <name type="place" key="Papoose Saddle">Papoose Saddle</name>and a few miles north of 
        <name type="place" key="Powell Ranger Station">Powell Ranger Station</name>and the camp of
        
        <ref n="1805-09-14" type="related">September 14, 1805</ref>, on 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>map 70. Space, 38; Peebles (LT), map.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36062804" n="4">The middle portion of this sentence is crossed through with
        a red vertical line, perhaps done by 
        <name type="place" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36062805" n="5">Grouseberry, whortleberry, 
        <hi rend="italic">Vaccinium scoparium</hi>Leiberg, is a common subalpine, low shrub that
        produces very small, but delicious, red berries. Hitchcock et al., 4:35.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36062806" n="6">Smooth woodrush, 
        <hi rend="italic">Luzula hitchcockii</hi>Hamet-Ahti, is not a grass but a member of the
        woodrush family. It occurs only at high elevations and is particularly abundant where snow
        accumulations regularly provide moister conditions.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36062807" n="7">Instead of going down to the valley of the 
        <name type="place" key="Lochsa (Upper Kooskooske) River">Lochsa River</name>as on the
        westbound route, the party continued eastward on the 
        <name type="place" key="Lolo Trail">Lolo Trail</name>along the ridge.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36062808" n="8">They followed the 
        <name type="place" key="Lolo Trail">Lolo Trail</name>along the ridge in 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho County, Idaho">Idaho County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>, instead of retracing their westward route,
        which would have taken them down into the valley of the 
        <name type="place" key="Lochsa (Upper Kooskooske) River">Lochsa River</name>.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-06-27" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-06-29" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
