<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.1805-11-10">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">November 10, 1805</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic
        Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            6</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">November 2, 1805–March 22, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1990</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">38-40</biblScope>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">252</biblScope>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">169</biblScope>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            11</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of Joseph Whitehouse, May 14, 1804–April 2,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1997</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">391-392</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
         <geoDecl datum="WGS">
            <placeName/>
            <geo>46.2333 -123.8667</geo>
            <note>Camped on the eastern side of Point Ellice, Pacific County, WA. East of the Astoria Bridge and near Meglar. Remained here until 11-15 but for a slight move on 11-12.</note>
         </geoDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc/>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-07-20</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-04-12</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date>November 10, 1805</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.1805-11-10.01">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">November 10th Sunday 1805</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>rained verry hard the greater part of the last night &amp; Continus this morning, the
          wind has layed and the Swells are fallen.    we loaded our Canoes and
          proceeded on, passed a Deep Bay on the Stard. Side I Call [
          <hi rend="italic">blank</hi>]</p>
               <p>
                  <table rows="2" cols="3">
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                           <hi rend="underline">  8</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">miles to point on the Stard. Side   
                passed a deep Bay and
                <lb/>6 points on the Stard. Side    rained hard Saw enoumurable
                <lb/>quantites of Sea guls and Ducks</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">10</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>The wind rose from the N W. and the Swells became So high, we were Compelled to
          return about 2 miles to a place where we Could unld. our Canoes, which was in a Small
          Bay on Driftwood, on which we had also to make our fires to dry our Selves as well as we
          could the Shore being either a Clift of Purpendicular rocks or Steep assents to the
          hight of 4 or 500 feet, we continued on this drift wood untill about 3 oClock when the
          evening appearing favourable we loaded &amp; Set out in hopes to turn the Point below
          and get into a better harber, but finding the 
          <hi rend="italic">waves &amp; Swells</hi>continue to rage with great fury below, we got
          a Safe place for our Stores &amp; a much beter one for the Canoes to lie and formed a
          Campment
          <ref target="n25111001" n="1"/>on Drift logs in the Same little Bay under a high hill
          at the enterence of a Small drean which we found verry convt. on account of its water,
          as that of the river is Brackish—    The logs on which we lie is all on flote
          every high tide—    The rain Continud all day—    we are all wet,
          also our beding and many other articles.    we are all employed untill late
          drying our bedding.    nothing to eate but Pounded fish</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.1805-11-10.02">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">November 10th Sunday 1805</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>Rained verry hard the greater part of last night and continues this morning.
             the wind has luled and the waves are not high; we loaded our canoes and
          proceeded on    passed Several Small and deep nitch on the Stard. Side, we
          proceeded on about 10 miles    Saw great numbers of Sea Guls, the wind rose
          from the N. W. and the waves became So high that we were compelled to return about 2
          miles to a place we Could unload our Canoes, which we did in a Small nitch at the mouth
          of a Small run on a pile of drift logs where we Continued untill low water, when the
          river appeared calm we loaded and Set out; but was obliged to return finding the waves
          too high for our Canoes to ride, we again unloaded the Canoes, and Stoed the loading on
          a rock above the tide water, and formed a camp on the Drift Logs which appeared to be
          the only Situation we could find to lie, the hills being either a perpendicular Clift,
          or Steep assent, riseing to about 500 feet—    our Canoes we Secured as well
          as we could—    we are all wet the rain haveing continued all day, our beding
          and maney other articles, employ our Selves drying our blankets—    nothing to
          eate but dried fish pounded which we brought from the falls.    we made 10
          miles today—</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.1805-11-10.03">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>Sunday 10th Nov. 1805.    considerable of rain fell last night.
             a rainy morning.    the waves not So high as yesterdy
             we loaded the canoes and Set out and went on    passed high
          clifts of rocks, and fine Springs.    we Saw porpises
          <ref target="n25111002" n="2"/>in the River. Saw a number of Sea otter, Sea gulls,
          <ref target="n25111003" n="3"/>ducks &amp;C.    continued raining hard
             abt. noon the wind rose So high that obledged us to turn back from a point
          of rocks and roe about 2 miles back into a cove before we could git a place to unload
          the canoes.    we got in to the harbour and unloaded the canoes and Stayed
          untill towards evening.    then loaded again thinking to find a Safer harbour.
             we went on a Short distance to a Spring run where we Camped.
          <ref target="n25111004" n="4"/>   the wind contind. So high that we could not
          proceed.    the hills and pine timber make close to the River on each Side.
             we had Scarsely room for to camp.—</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.1805-11-10.04">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Sunday 10th.</hi>   We had a rainy morning, but the wind was
          not so high as it had been yesterday; and we set out from 
          <name type="place" key="Grays Point (Cape Swells)">Cape Swell</name>, coasted along 8
          miles, passed some high cliffs of sandy rocks, and then came to a point; where we found
          the swells so high, the wind having risen, that we could not proceed; so we had to
          return back about a mile to get a safe harbour. Here we dined on some pounded salmon,
          that we had procured from the Indians; and unloaded our canoes. After we had been here
          about 2 hours, it became more calm, and we loaded the canoes again, but could not get
          round the point, the swells were still so high; we therefore put too at a branch of
          fresh water, under high cliffs of rocks and unloaded again. Here we scarcely had room to
          lie between the rocks and water; but we made shift to do it among some drift wood that
          had been beat up by the tide. It rained hard all night, and was very disagreeable. While
          on our way down today, we saw some porpoises, sea otter and a great many sea gulls. The
          water is become very salt.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.1805-11-10.05">
            <sp who="jw">
               <speaker>Whitehouse</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>Sunday Novemr. 10th    We had rain the greater part of last night &amp; a
          wet rainey morning, but the Waves did not run so high as they did Yesterday.
             We loaded our Canoes &amp; set out.    We proceeded on, and
          passed high hills with pine trees growing on them, some high Clifts of rocks &amp;
          several fine Springs of fresh water.    We saw in the River a number of
          Porpoises, &amp; Sea Otters, Sea Gulls &amp; Ducks in the greatest abundance.
             We continued on our way, it raining hard on us, 'till about noon; when it
          ceased.    The Waves then ran so high that we had to turn back and went up the
          River about 2 Miles, before we could find a harbour to unload the Canoes.   
          We at last found a convenient place, at which we unloaded our Canoes.    We
          halted at that place, where we staid till towards evening, when we loaded our Canoes
          again, and proceedd on up the River in hopes to find a safer harbour, than the one that
          we had left.    We went a small distance from the place we left, &amp; came to
          a large Spring run; lying on the South side, in a bend of the River, where we stopped
          &amp; Encamped.    we again unloaded the Canoes, &amp; had scarcely room to
          lay down, the hills making in so close to the River.    We went about 7 Miles
          this day, our course being nearly West.—</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n25111001" n="1">They remained at this campsite until November 15 except for
        a short move on November 12; it was on the eastern side of 
        <name type="place" key="Point Ellice (Point Distress)">Point Ellice</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Pacific County, Wash.">Pacific County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>, east of the 
        <name type="place" key="Astoria Bridge">Astoria Bridge</name>and near the town of 
        <name type="place" key="Meglar, Wash.">Meglar</name>. Appleman (LC), 360: 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>maps 82, 89.</note>
            <note xml:id="n25111002" n="2">The harbor, or common, porpoise, 
        <hi rend="italic">Phocoena phocoena</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n25111003" n="3">The gulls could be any of a number of species of 
        <hi rend="italic">Larus</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n25111004" n="4">On the eastern side of 
        <name type="place" key="Point Ellice (Point Distress)">Point Ellice</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Pacific County, Wash.">Pacific County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>, near the town of 
        <name type="place" key="Meglar, Wash.">Meglar</name>, where they stayed until November 15
        except for a short move on November 12.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-11-09" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-11-11" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
