<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-03-04">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
March 4, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               
               
               
               
               
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml" n="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc" n="Clark, William">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 6</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">November 2, 1805–March 22, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1990</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">378-381</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo" n="Ordway, John">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf" n="Floyd, Charles">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">275</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jw" n="Whitehouse, Joseph">Joseph Whitehouse</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 11</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of Joseph Whitehouse, May 14, 1804–April 2, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1997</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">425</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Journal Entries</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-08-30</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1806-03-04">March 4, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-03-04.01" n="">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Tuesday March 4th 1806.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
Not any occurrence today worthy of notice.    we live sumptuously on our wappetoe and Sturgeon.    the Anchovey is so delicate that they soon become tainted unless pickled or smoked.    the natives run a small stick through their gills and hang them in the smoke of their lodges, or kindle a small fire under them for the purpose of drying them.    they need no previous preperation of guting &amp;c and will cure in 24 hours.    the natives do not appear to be very scrupelous about eating them when a little feated.—<ref target="n28030401" n="1"/>    the fresh sturgeon they keep for many days by immersing it in water.    they coock their sturgeon by means of vapor or steam.    the process is as follows.    a brisk fire is kindled on which a parcel of stones are lad.    when the fire birns down and the stones are sufficiently heated, the stones are so arranged as to form a tolerable level surface, the sturgeon which had been previously cut into large fletches is now laid on the hot stones; a parsel of small boughs of bushes is next laid on and a second course of the sturgeon thus repating alternate layers of sturgeon and boughs untill the whole is put on which they design to cook.    it is next covered closely with matts and water is poared in such manner as to run in among the hot stones and the vapor arrising being confined by the mats, cooks the fish.    the whole process is performed in an hour, and the sturgeon thus cooked is much better than either boiled or roasted.</p>
               <p>
The turtle dove<ref target="n28030402" n="2"/> and robbin are the same of our country and are found as well in the plain as open country.    the Columbian robbin<ref target="n28030403" n="3"/> heretofore discribed seems to be the inhabitant of the woody country exclusively.    The Magpy<ref target="n28030404" n="4"/> is most commonly found in the open country and are the same with those formerly discribed on the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>.    the large woodpecker or log cock, the lark woodpecker<ref target="n28030405" n="5"/> and the small white woodpecker with a read head<ref target="n28030406" n="6"/> are the same with those of the Atlantic states and are found exclusively in the timbered country. The blue crested Corvus and the small white breasted do<ref target="n28030407" n="7"/> have been previously discribed and are the natives of a piney country invariably, being found as well on the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">rocky mountain</name>s as on this coast.—    the lark<ref target="n28030408" n="8"/> is found in the plains only and are the same with those before mentioned on the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, and not very unlike what is called in <name type="place" key="Virginia">Virginia</name> the <hi rend="italic">old field lark.</hi>— The large blueish brown or sandhill Crain are found in the valley of the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky mountains</name> in Summer and Autumn where they raise their young, and in the winter and begining of spring on this river below tidewater and on this coast. they are the same as those common to the Southern and Western States where they are most generally known by the name of the Sandhill crain. The vulture<ref target="n28030409" n="9"/> has also been discribed.    there are two species of the fly-catch, a small redish brown species<ref target="n28030410" n="10"/> with a short tail, round body, short neck and short pointed beak.    they have some fine black specks intermixed with the uniform redish brown.    this the same with that which remains all winter in <name type="place" key="Virginia">Virginia</name> where it is sometimes called the wren.    the second species<ref target="n28030411" n="11"/> has lately returned and dose not remain here all winter. it's colours are a yellowish brown on the back head neck wings and tail the breast and belley of a yellowish white; the tail is in proportion as the wren but it is a size smaller than that bird.    it's beak is streight pointed convex reather lage at the base and the chaps of equal length.    the first species is the smallest, in short it is the smalest bird that I have ever seen in America except the humming bird.    both these species are found in the woody country only or at least I have never seen them elsewhere.
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-03-04.02" n="">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Tuesday March 4th 1806</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
Not any accurrance to day worthy of notice.    we live Sumptiously on our wappatoe and Sturgeon.    the Anchovey is so delicate that they Soon become tainted unless pickled or Smoked.    the nativs run a Small Stick through their gills and hang them in the Smoke of their Lodges, or Kindle Small fires under them for the purpose of drying them.    they need no previous preperation of gutting &amp;c. and will Cure in 24 hours. the nativs do not appear to be very Scrupilous about eating them a little feated.</p>
               <p>
the fresh sturgeon they Keep maney days by immersing it in water. they Cook their Sturgeon by means of vapor or Steam.    the process is as follows.    a brisk fire is kindled on which a parcel of Stones are Sufficiently heated, the Stones are So arranged as to form a tolerable leavel Surface, the Sturgeon which had been previously cut into large flaetches is now laid on the hot Stones; a parcel of Small boughs of bushes is next laid on, and a Second course of the Sturgeon thus repeating alternate layers of Sturgeon &amp; boughs untill the whole is put on which they design to Cook.    it is next covered closely with mats and water is poared in Such manner as to run in among the hot Stones, and the vapor arriseing being confind by the mats, cooks the fish.    the whole process is performd in an hour and the Sturgeon thus Cooked is much better than either boiled or roasted.    in their usial way of boiting of other fish in baskets with hot Stones is not so good.</p>
               <p>
The <hi rend="italic">turtle doves</hi> and robin are the Same of those of our countrey and are found as well as the plains as open countrey.    the Columbia robin heretofore discribed Seams to be the inhabitent of the woody Country exclusively.    the magpye is most commonly found in the open Country and are the Same with those formerly discribed on the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>.</p>
               <p>
The <hi rend="italic">large wood pecker</hi> or log cock the <hi rend="italic">lark woodpecker</hi> and the common wood pecker with a red head as the Same with those of the Atlantic States, and are found exclusively in the timbered Country. The Blue crested <hi rend="italic">Corvus</hi> and the Small white brested <hi rend="italic">corvus</hi> are the nativs of a piney country invariably, being found as well on the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky Mountains</name> as on this coast—. The <hi rend="italic">lark</hi> is found in the plains only and are the Same with those on the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> and the <name type="place" key="Illinois">Illinois</name> and not unlike what is Called in <name type="place" key="Virginia">Virginia</name> the <hi rend="italic">old field Lark.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
The large bluish brown or <hi rend="italic">Sandhill Crain</hi> are found in the Vally's of the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky Mountain</name> in Summer and autumn when they raise their young and in the winter and beginning of Spring on this river below tide water and on this coast.    they are the same as those Common to the Southern and Western States where they are most generally known by the name of the Sand hill Crain. The <hi rend="italic">Vulture</hi> has already been discribed.</p>
               <p>
There are two Species of fly Catch, a Small redish brown with a Short tail, round body, Short neck, and Short pointed beak, and the Same as that with us sometimes called the Wren.    the 2d Species does not remain all winter they have just returned and are of a Yellowish brown Colour.

</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-03-04.03" n="">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Tuesday 4th March 1806.    rained hard all last night and continues all this day.

</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-03-04.04" n="">
            <sp who="jw">
               <speaker>Whitehouse</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Tuesday March 4th    It rained hard all last night, &amp; continued the same during the whole of this day.    Nothing material happened at the fort worth mentioning.—</p>
               <p>
Tuesday March 4th<ref target="n28030412" n="12"/>    It rained very hard all last night &amp; continued so during this day, &amp; nothing material happened during this day.—


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n28030401" n="1">Perhaps "fetid." A dark "x" covers the first part of this paragraph.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28030402" n="2">The mourning dove, <hi rend="italic">Zenaida macroura</hi> [AOU, 316]. A faint red vertical line goes through the first few lines of this paragraph, perhaps Biddle's doing.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28030403" n="3">The previously described varied thrush; see above, <ref n="1806-01-31" type="related">January 31, 1806</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28030404" n="4">The black-billed magpie, <hi rend="italic">Pica pica</hi> [AOU, 475].</note>
            <note xml:id="n28030405" n="5">Respectively, the pileated woodpecker, <hi rend="italic">Dryocopus pileatus</hi> [AOU, 405], and the northern, or common, flicker, <hi rend="italic">Colaptes auratus</hi> [AOU, 412], both new species. Logcock was a folk name for the pileated woodpecker, while lark woodpecker was used for flickers. Burroughs, 241–42; Holmgren, 32, 34.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28030406" n="6">The red-breasted sapsucker, <hi rend="italic">Sphyrapicus ruber</hi> [AOU, 403]. Burroughs, 241; Holmgren, 34.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28030407" n="7">Steller's jay and the gray jay. See above, <ref n="1805-12-18" type="related">December 18, 1805</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28030408" n="8">The western meadowlark, <hi rend="italic">Sturnella neglecta</hi> [AOU, 501.1]. The "old field lark" is the eastern meadowlark, <hi rend="italic">S. magna</hi> [AOU, 501].</note>
            <note xml:id="n28030409" n="9">The California condor, described on <ref n="1806-02-16" type="related">February 16</ref> and <ref n="1806-02-17" type="related">17</ref>, 1806.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28030410" n="10">The winter wren.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28030411" n="11">Perhaps Hammond's flycatcher, <hi rend="italic">Empidonax hammondii</hi> [AOU, 468]. Holmgren, 30. See also Coues (HLC), 3:876 n. 78.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28030412" n="12">In slightly different wording, <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse's</name> copyist repeated an entry.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-03-03" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-03-05" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
