<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-01-09">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">January 9, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic
        Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            6</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">November 2, 1805–March 22, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1990</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">186-192</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">265</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages"/>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jw">Joseph Whitehouse</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            11</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of Joseph Whitehouse, May 14, 1804–April 2,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1997</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">411</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
         <geoDecl datum="WGS" xml:id="lc.geo.1806-01-09.01">
            <placeName/>
            <geo>45.9833 -123.9167</geo>
            <note>Clark and his party return to the Fort Clatsop camp, Clatsop County, OR. Remained here until 03-23-1806.</note>
         </geoDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc/>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-08-06</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-04-12</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1806-01-09">January 9, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-01-09.01"
              ref="lc.geo.1806-01-09.01">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Friday</hi>[
              <hi rend="italic">NB: Thursday</hi>] 
              <hi rend="italic">January 9th 1806.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>Our men are now very much engaged in dressing Elk and Deer skins for mockersons and
          cloathing.    the deer are extreemly scarce in this neighbourhood, some are to
          be found near the praries and open grounds along the coast.    this evening we
          heard seven guns in quick succession after each other, they appeared to be on the Creek
          to the South of us and several miles distant; I expect that the hunters 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Collins, John">Collins</name>have fallen in with a gang of Elk.
             some marrow bones and a little fresh meat would be exceptable; I have been
          living for two days past on poor dryed Elk, or 
          <hi rend="italic">jurk</hi>as the hunters term it.</p>
               <p>The 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsops</name>
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinnooks</name>&amp;c. bury their dead
          in their canoes.    for this purpose four pieces of split timber are set erect
          on end, and sunk a few feet in the grown, each brace having their flat sides opposite to
          each other and sufficiently far assunder to admit the width of the canoes in which the
          dead are to be deposited; through each of these perpendicular posts, at the hight of six
          feet a mortice is cut, through which two bars of wood are incerted; on these cross bars
          a small canoe is placed in which the body is laid after being carefully roled in a robe
          of some dressed skins; a paddle is also deposited with them; a larger canoe is now
          reversed, overlaying and imbracing the small one, and resting with it's gunwals on the
          cross bars; one or more large mats of rushes or flags are then roled around the canoes
          and the whole securely lashed with a long cord, usually made of the bark of the 
          <hi rend="italic">Arbor vita</hi>or white cedar.    on the cross bars which
          support the canoes is frequently hung or laid various articles of cloathing culinary
          eutensels &amp;c.    I cannot understand them sufficiently to make any
          enquiries relitive to their religious opinions, but presume from their depositing
          various articles with their dead, that they believe in a state of future existence.</p>
               <p>The persons who usually visit the entrance of this river for the purpose or traffic
          or hunting I believe are either English or Americans; the Indians inform us that they
          speak the same language with ourselves, and give us proofs of their varacity by
          repeating many words of English, as musquit, powder, shot, nife, file, damned rascal,
          sun of a bitch &amp;c.    whether these traders are from 
          <name type="place" key="Nootka Sound">Nootka sound</name>, from some other late
          establishment on this coast, or immediately from the U' States or 
          <name type="place" key="England">Great Britain</name>, I am at a loss to determine, nor
          can the Indians inform us.    the Indians whom I have asked in what direction
          the traders go when they depart from hence, or arrive here, always point to the S. W.
          from which it is presumeable that Nootka cannot be their destination; and as from Indian
          information a majority of these traders annually visit them about the beginning of April
          and remain with them six or seven Months, they cannot come immediately from 
          <name type="place" key="England">Great Britain</name>or the U' States, the distance
          being too great for them to go and return in the ballance of the year.    from
          this circumstance I am sometimes induced to believe that there is some other
          establishment on the coast of America south West of this place of which little is but
          yet known to the world, or it may be perhaps on some Island in the pacific ocean between
          the Continents of Asia and America to the South West of us.
          <ref target="n27010901" n="1"/>This traffic on the part of the whites consists in
          vending, guns, (principally old british or American musquits) powder, balls and Shot,
          Copper and brass kettles, brass teakettles and coffee pots, blankets from two to three
          point,
          <ref target="n27010902" n="2"/>scarlet and blue Cloth (coarse), plates and strips of
          sheet copper and brass, large brass wire, knives, beads and tobacco with fishinghooks
          buttons and some other small articles; also a considerable quantity of Sailor's cloaths,
          as hats coasts, trowsers and shirts.    for these they receive in return from
          the natives, dressed and undressed Elkskins, skins of the sea Otter, common Otter,
          beaver, common fox,
          <ref target="n27010903" n="3"/>spuck,
          <ref target="n27010904" n="4"/>and tiger cat;
          <ref target="n27010905" n="5"/>also dryed and pounded sammon in baskets, and a kind of
          buisquit, which the natives make of roots called by them shappelell.
          <ref target="n27010906" n="6"/>   The natives are extravegantly fond of the
          most common cheap blue and white beads, of moderate size, or such that from 50 to 70
          will weigh one penneyweight.
          <ref target="n27010907" n="7"/>   the blue is usually pefered to the white;
          these beads constitute the principal circulating medium with all the indian tribes on
          the river; for these beads they will dispose any article they possess.—    the
          beads are strung on strans of a fathom in length and in that manner sold by the bredth
          or yard.—</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-01-09.02"
              ref="lc.geo.1806-01-09.01">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>January 9th Thursday 180[5?]</date>
               </ab>
               <p>a fine morning wind N E    Set out at day lighte every man Some meat of the
          whale and a little oile    proceded on the track    we Came out to a
          house at a branch where we halted ½ an hour to rest this house is at at place an old
          village has formerly been, on the Coast at the Comencment [
          <hi rend="italic">blank</hi>] 27 foot wide 35 feet long Sunk in the ground 5 feet 2
          Dores &amp; 2 fire places dores 29 Ins. high &amp; 14¼ wide handsom Steps to decend down
          a post in the middle Coverede with boards Split thin an 2 feet wide, old grave in Canoes
          of 3 feet 8 Inches wide &amp; 5 feet long neetly made high at bow    proceded
          on to the top of the hill Passing 3 bad points rockey &amp;.    from the 
          <name type="place" key="Tillamook Head (Clark's Point of View)">Point Clarks Point of
          view</name>
                  <name type="place" key="Cape Disappointment">Cape Disapt.</name>bears S. 12° E passing a
          Great point at 15 miles one at 40 miles rocks out to the 1st large point from the Creek
          4 points, between the 1st large Point and 2d a point of many large rocks, Day Clouded
          up, I can See a point Bearing N 5° East a long way just in Sight.    from 
          <name type="place" key="Tillamook Head (Clark's Point of View)">Clarks 〈lookout〉 View
          Point</name>to 
          <name type="place" key="Cape Disappointment">Cape Disapointment</name>is N 20° W.
             To 
          <name type="place" key="Point Adams">point 
          <hi rend="italic">adams</hi>
                  </name>&amp; the open Slope point is North and a Sharp
          point, met a party of 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinnooks</name>going to get whale
          blubber to eate &amp; oile each of which they eate together, we also over took Several
          parties of the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clot Sops</name>loaded with imence
          laods of the blubber and 
          <hi rend="italic">oile</hi>   maney of those loads I with difficuelty raised,
          Estonishing what custom will [do?]    at 2 oClock we arrived at the Camp of
          our Salt makers verry much fatigued, more So than I ever was before, the Indians all
          proceeded on, I concluded to Stay all night,
          <ref target="n27010908" n="8"/>as the party was much fatigued, and Send out 2 men which
          I had left here to hunt Ducks up the little river, 
          <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Jo. Fields</name>had killed an Elk and brought
          in a quarter on which we Dined    he also had killed &amp; brought in a 
          <hi rend="italic">Deer.</hi>The Indians with the oile &amp; bluber tole me they had to
          purchase of the 
          <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Tillamook Indians">Ca-le nixx</name>
                  </hi>
                  <ref target="n27010909" n="9"/>and would Come to the 
          <hi rend="italic">fort</hi>&amp; Sell to us in 3 Days time, this I incouraged, as I
          expect to purchase at the fort as cheep as at the village at which I was, day proved
          fine.    rained the greater part of the night    I went into an
          Indian Lodge they were pore Durty and the house full of flees.    he offered
          me roots which they geather on the Sea Cost a kind of rush, of which they offered me to
          eate,</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-01-09.03"
              ref="lc.geo.1806-01-09.01">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Thursday 9th of January 1805</hi>[1806]</date>
               </ab>
               <p>a fine morning wind from the N. E.    last night about 10 oClock while
          Smokeing with the nativ's I was alarmed by a loud Srile voice from the Cabins on the
          opposite Side, the Indians all run immediately across to the village, my guide who
          Continued with me made Signs that Some one's throat was Cut, by enquiry I found that one
          man 
          <name type="person" key="McNeal, Hugh">mcNeal</name>was absent, I imediately Sent off 
          <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Sergt. N. Pryor</name>&amp; 4 men in
          quest of 
          <name type="person" key="McNeal, Hugh">McNeal</name>who' they met comeing across the
          Creak in great hast, and informed me that the people were alarmed on the opposit Side at
          Something but what he could not tell, a man had verry friendly envited him to go and
          eate in his lodge, that the Indian had locked armes with him and went to a lodge in
          which a woman gave him Some blubber, that the man envited him to another lodge to get
          Something better, and the woman [
          <hi rend="italic">NB: knowing his design</hi>] held him [
          <hi rend="italic">NB: 
          <name type="person" key="McNeal, Hugh">McNeal</name>
                  </hi>] by the blanket which he had
          around him    [
          <hi rend="italic">NB: He not knowing her object freed himself &amp; was going off, when
          this woman a 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinnook</name>an old friend of 
          <name type="person" key="McNeal, Hugh">McNeals</name>
                  </hi>] 〈and〉 another ran out and
          hollow'd and his pretended friend disapeared—    I emediately ordered every
          man to hold themselves in a State of rediness and Sent 
          <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Sergt. Pryor</name>&amp; 4 men to know
          the cause of the alarm which was found to be a premeditated plan of the pretended friend
          of 
          <name type="person" key="McNeal, Hugh">McNeal</name>to assanate for his Blanket and what
          fiew articles he had about him, which was found out by a 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chin nook</name>woman who allarmed the
          men of the village who were with me in time to prevent the horred act.    this
          man was of another band at Some distance and ran off as Soon as he was discovered.
             we have now to look back and Shudder at the dreadfull road on which we have
          to return of 45 miles S E of 
          <name type="place" key="Point Adams">Point adams</name>&amp; 35 miles from 
          <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort 
          <hi rend="italic">Clatsop.</hi>
                  </name>   I had the blubber &amp; oil divided
          among' the party and Set out about Sunrise and returned by the Same rout we had went
          out, met Several parties of men &amp; womin of the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinnook</name>and 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsops</name>nations, on their way to
          trade with the 
          <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Tillamook Indians">Kil a mox</name>
                  </hi>for blubber and oil; on the Steep decent of the Mountain I overtook five men and
          Six womin with emence loads of the Oil and blubber of the Whale, those Indians had
          passed by Some rout by which we missed them as we went out yesterday; one of the women
          in the act of getting down a Steep part of the mountain her load by Some means had
          Sliped off her back, and She was holding the load by a Strap which was fastened to the
          mat bag in which it was in, in one hand and holding a bush by the other, as I was in
          front of my party, I endeavored to relieve this woman by takeing her load untill She
          Could get to a better place a little below, &amp; to my estonishment found the load as
          much as I Could lift and must exceed 100 wt.    the husband of this woman who
          was below Soon came to her releif, those people proceeded on with us to the Salt works,
          at which place we arrived late in the evening, found them without meat, and 3 of the
          Party 
          <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">J. Field</name>
                  <name type="person" key="Gibson, George">Gibson</name>&amp; 
          <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name>out hunting.    as I
          was excessively fatigued and my party appeared verry much so, I deturmined to Stay
          untill the morning and rest our Selves a little. The 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsops</name>proceeded on with their
          lodes—    The 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsops</name>, 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chin nooks</name>
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Tillamook Indians">Kil á mox</name>&amp;c. are verry
          loquacious and inquisitive; they possess good memories and have repeeted to us the names
          capasities of the Vessels &amp;c of many traders and others who have visited the mouth
          of this river; they are generally low in Statue, proportionably Small, reather lighter
          complected and much more illy formed than the Indians of the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>and those of our fronteers; they
          are generally Chearfull but never gay.    with us their Conversation generally
          turns upon the subject of trade, Smokeing, eating or their womin; about the latter, they
          Speak without reserve in their presence, of their every part, and of the most farmiliar
          Connection.    they do not hold the virtue of their womin in high estimation,
          and will even prostitute their wives and daughters for a fishing hook or a Stran of
          beeds.    in Common with other Savage nations they make their womin perform
          ever Species of domestic drugery; but in almost every Species of this drugery the men
          also participate. their woman are compelled to gather roots, and assist them in takeing
          fish; which articles form much the greater prat of their Subsistance; notwithstanding
          the Survile manner in which they treat their womin they pay much more respect to their
          judgement and opinion in maney respects than most indian nations; their womin are
          permited to Speak freely before them, and Sometime appear to command with a tone of
          authority; they generally consult them in their traffic and act conformably to their
          opinions.</p>
               <p>I think it may be established as a general maxim that those nations treat their old
          people and women with most defference and respect where they Subsist principally on Such
          articles that these can participate with the men in obtaining them; and that, that part
          of the Community are treated with least attention, when the act of precureing
          subsistance devolves intirely on the men in the vigor of life. It appears to me that
          nature has been much more deficient in her filial ties than in any others of the Strong
          effections of the humane heart, and therefore think our old men equally with our woman
          indebted to Sivilization for their ease and Comfort. I am told among the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux's</name>, 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Assiniboine Indians">Assinniboins</name>and others on
          the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>who Subsist by hunting it is a
          Custom when a person of either Sex becoms So old and infirm that they are unable to
          travel on foot, from Camp to Camp as they rove in serch of Subsistance, for the Children
          or near relations of Such person to leave them with Compunction or remorse; on those
          occasions they usially place within their reach a Small piece of meat and a platter of
          water, telling the poor old Superannuated retch for their Consolation, that he or She
          had lived long enough, and that it was time they Should die and go to their relations
          who Can afford to take Care of them, much better than they Could. I am informed that the
          
          <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Me ne tar es</name>
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians, Awaxawi">Ar war har mays</name>and 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Ricares</name>when attended by their
          old people on their hunting expedition prosued the Same Custom; but in justice to those
          people I must observe that it appeared to me at their villages, that they provided
          tolerably well for their aged persons, and Several of their 
          <hi rend="italic">feasts</hi>appear to have principally for their object a contribution
          for their aged and infirm persons. In one of the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>villages I Saw an old man
          to whome I gave a knife and enquired his age, he Said he had Seen more than 100 winters,
          and that he Should Soon go down the river to their old village—    he
          requested I would give him Something to prevent the pain in his back    his
          grand Son a Young man rebuked the old man and Said it was not worth while, that it was
          time for the old man to die.    the old man occupied one Side of the fire and
          was furnished with plenty of Covouring and food, and every attention appeared to be paid
          him &amp;c. 
          <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Jo. Field</name>in my absence had killed an Elk
          and a Deer, brought in the Deer and half of the Elk on a part of which we Suped, Some
          rain a little after dark. I visited a house near the Salt boilers found it inhabited by
          2 families, they were pore dirty and their house Sworming with flees.—</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-01-09.04"
              ref="lc.geo.1806-01-09.01">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>Thursday 9th Jany. 1806.    rained the greater part of last night but
          cleared off pleasant this morning, and continues warm</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-01-09.05"
              ref="lc.geo.1806-01-09.01">
            <sp who="jw">
               <speaker>Whitehouse</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>Thursday Janry 9th    It rained the greater part of last night, &amp; the
          two hunters that went out Yesterday did not return.    the Weather cleared off
          this morning &amp; became warm &amp; pleasant.    the Men in the fort were
          employed mending their Clothes, airing the baggage, making moccasins dressing Skins
          &amp;ca.—</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n27010901" n="1">In 1788 the British sea captain 
        <name type="person" key="Meares, John">John Meares</name>established a trading base on 
        <name type="place" key="Nootka Sound">Nootka Sound</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Vancouver Island">Vancouver Island</name>. A few years later
        American traders were using 
        <name type="place" key="Clayoquot Sound">Clayoquot Sound</name>on the same island as a
        base. Neither of these was a permanent settlement. The conjecture about a Pacific island
        was also correct, for most of these traders were operating out of the 
        <name type="place" key="Hawaii">Hawaiian Islands</name>. Thwaites (LC), 3:327 n. 1; Gibson
        (BMNC); Gough; Ruby &amp; Brown (CITC), 40–90.</note>
            <note xml:id="n27010902" n="2">Referring to a system for measuring trade blankets by size
        and weight. See above, 
        <ref n="1805-08-20" type="related">August 20, 1805</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n27010903" n="3">Probably the red fox, 
        <hi rend="italic">Vulpes vulpes.</hi>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="n27010904" n="4">See below, 
        <ref n="1806-02-23" type="related">February 23, 1806</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n27010905" n="5">The men's term for the Oregon bobcat. Burroughs,
        92–93.</note>
            <note xml:id="n27010906" n="6">Cous, 
        <hi rend="italic">Lomatium cous</hi>(Wats.) Coult. &amp; Rose. Hitchcock et al., 3
        :548–49. See above, 
        <ref n="1805-11-01" type="related">November 1, 1805</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n27010907" n="7">A troy weight of twenty-four grains, one-twentieth of a
        troy ounce.</note>
            <note xml:id="n27010908" n="8">At the 
        <name type="place" key="Saltmaking Camp (Oreg.)">salt works</name>camp at 
        <name type="place" key="Seaside, Oreg.">Seaside</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Clatsop County, Oreg.">Clatsop County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>. 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>map 84; fig. 13.</note>
            <note xml:id="n27010909" n="9">Presumably the 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Tillamook Indians">Tillamooks</name>.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-01-08" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-01-10" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
