<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-10-21">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
October 21, 1805</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               
               
               
               
               
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml" n="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc" n="Clark, William">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 5</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">July 28–November 1, 1805</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1989</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">314-320</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo" n="Ordway, John">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf" n="Floyd, Charles">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">242</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg" n="Gass, Patrick">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">159</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jw" n="Whitehouse, Joseph">Joseph Whitehouse</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 11</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of Joseph Whitehouse, May 14, 1804–April 2, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1997</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">362-364</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
         <geoDecl datum="WGS" xml:id="lc.geo.1805-10-21.01">
            <placeName/>
            <geo>45.7 -120.6833</geo>
            <note>Camped near the present John Day Dam, Klickitat County, WA.</note>
         </geoDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Journal Entries</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-07-07</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1805-10-21">October 21, 1805</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-10-21.01" n="lc.geo.1805-10-21.01">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">October 21st 1805 〈Thursday〉</hi> Monday</date>
               </ab>
               <p>
a verry Cold morning    we Set out early    wind from the S W.    we Could not Cook brakfast before we embarked as usial for the want of wood or Something to burn.—</p>
               <p>
                  <table rows="6" cols="3">
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">South</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  3</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">miles to a Lard Bend</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S 55° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">17</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">miles to a Lard Bend below a bad rapid high ruged rock<lb/>
Passed a Small Island at 2½ miles one at 4 miles, in th middle of<lb/>
the river, at Smome Swift water    an Indn Camp of 8 Lodges<lb/>
on the Std. Side opsd. th Lower point where we Brackfast,<lb/>
and bought Some fine fish &amp; Pounded rotes.    people well<lb/>
disposed    passed a rapid at 10 miles. Rocks out in the water<lb/>
passed a Stard. point &amp; a Strd. point    at 15 [miles] passed 5<lb/>
Lodges of Indians, &amp; 2 Lodges Some distance above on Std.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 45° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  4</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">miles to a Stard. bend    passd. the lower pt. of the Isd. at 1<lb/>
mile and 2 Lodges of fishers below on the Stard Side, the<lb/>
rocks on th Lard. appear as if Sliped from the Clifts under<lb/>
which they are    passed emence rocks in differt. parts of the<lb/>
river which were large and too noumerous to notice. Fowl of<lb/>
all kinds more plentiful than above    passed a verry bad rapid<lb/>
at 2 miles, this rapid is Crouded with Islands of bad rocks di-<lb/>
ficuelt &amp; crooked passage    2 Lodges of Indians below on Std.<lb/>
Side. I saw Some fiew Small Pine on the tops of the high hills<lb/>
and bushes in the hollers</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 60° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  5</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">miles to the Stard. Bend.    passed maney ruged black rocks in<lb/>
diffierent parts of the river, and a bad rapid at 2 miles &amp; river<lb/>
narrow    Several Canoes loaded with Indians (<hi rend="italic">
                              <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Pierce noses</name>
                           </hi>)<lb/>
came to See us—    〈To〉 at the expiration of this course a river<lb/>
falls in on the Lard. 40 yds. wide Islands of rocks in every di-<lb/>
rection in the river &amp; rapids</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 52° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                           <hi rend="underline">13</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">miles to upr. point of a rocky Island 80 feet high    a rapid<lb/>
above    passed the little river rapid thro narrow channels be-<lb/>
tween the rocks    4 Lodges of Indians on the Stard. Side op-<lb/>
posit, a round toped mountain imediately in front and is the<lb/>
one we have been going towards &amp; which bore S. W. from the<lb/>
2d course below the Forks—    passed the lower point of an<lb/>
Island on the Stard. at 2 miles    landed at 5 Lodges of <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Pierced<lb/>
noses</name> Indians at 4 miles where we encamped and purchased<lb/>
a little wood to boil our Dogs &amp; fish, those Indians are the<lb/>
〈inhabitents〉 relations of the falls below, fortunately for us the<lb/>
night was worm.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                           <hi rend="double underline">42</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="right">22d Octr. Course Continued<ref target="n24102101" n="1"/>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>
fine water for 7 miles    passed a rapid of rocks nearly across above which at 6 miles    passed 6 Lodges Std., at 9 miles    passed a Bad rapid, &amp; Lodges of Indians on Std. Side    20 piles [<hi rend="italic">one word illegible</hi>] of fish on an Island drying, Several Indians in Canoes fishing in  Canos &amp; gigs &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <figure rend="mhs">
                     <p>
                        <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name> near Mouth of <name type="place" key="Deschutes (Clark's, Towanahiook's) River">Deschutes River</name>, <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>
                        <lb/>
and <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>, ca. October 21, 1805, Elkskin-bound Journal
<bibl>
                           <orgName>Missouri Historical Society</orgName>
                        </bibl>
                     </p>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Collins, John">Collins</name> made Some excellent beer of the <hi rend="italic">Pasheco quar mash</hi> bread of roots which was verry good    obliged to purchase wood at a high rate.<ref target="n24102102" n="2"/>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-10-21.02" n="lc.geo.1805-10-21.01">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">October 21st Monday 1805</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
A verry cool morning wind from the S. W.    we Set out verry early and proceeded on, last night we could not Collect more dry willows the only fuel, than was barely Suffient to cook Supper, and not a Sufficency to cook brackfast this morning, passd. a Small Island at 5½ miles a large one 8 miles in the middle of the river, Some rapid water at the head and Eight Lodges of nativs opposit its Lower point on the Stard. Side, we came too at those lodges, bought some wood and brackfast. Those people recived us with great kindness, and examined us with much attention, their employments custom Dress and appearance Similar to those above; Speak the same language,<ref target="n24102103" n="3"/> here we Saw two Scarlet and a blue cloth blanket, also a Salors Jacket    the Dress of the men of this tribe only a Short robe of Deer or Goat Skins, and that of the womn is a Short piece of Dressd Skin which fall from the neck So as to Cover the front of the body as low as the waste, a Short robe, which is of one Deer or antilope Skin, and a flap, around their waste and Drawn tite between their legs as before described, their orniments are but fiew, and worn as those above.</p>
               <p>
we got from those people a fiew pounded rotes [<hi rend="italic">NB: roots</hi>] fish and <hi rend="italic">Acorns</hi> of the white oake, those Acorns they make use of as food [<hi rend="italic">NB: raw &amp; roasted</hi>], and inform us they precure them of the nativs who live near the falls below which place they all discribe by the term <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="place" key="Mount Hood (Timm, Falls Mountain)">Timm</name>
                  </hi>—<ref target="n24102104" n="4"/>    at 2 miles lower passed a rapid, large rocks Stringing into the river of large Size,<ref target="n24102105" n="5"/> opposit to this rapid on the Stard. Shore is Situated <hi rend="italic">two</hi> Lodges of the nativs drying fish    here we halted a fiew minits to examine the rapid before we entered it which was our constant Custom, and at all that was verry dangerous put out all who could not Swim to walk around, after passing this rapid we proceeded on passed anoothe rapid at 5 miles lower down, above this rapid on 〈the Stard. Side〉 <hi rend="italic">five</hi> Lodges of Indians fishing &amp;c.<ref target="n24102106" n="6"/>    above this rapid maney large rocks on each Side at Some distance from Shore, one mile passed an Island Close to the Stard. Side, below which is <hi rend="italic">two</hi> Lodge of nativs, a little below is a bad rapid which is bad crouded with hugh rocks Scattered in every Direction which renders the pasage verry Difficuelt    a little above this rapid on the Lard. Side emence piles of rocks appears as if Sliped from the Clifts under which they lay passed great number of rocks in every direction Scattered in the river    5 Lodges a little below on the Stard. Side, and one lodge on an Island near the Stard. Shore opposit to which is a verry bad rapid, thro which we found much dificuelty in passing, the river is Crouded with rocks in every direction, after Passing this dificult rapid to the mouth of a Small river on the Larboard Side 40 yards wide descharges but little water at this time, and appears to take its Sourse in the Open plains to the S. E.<ref target="n24102107" n="7"/>    from this place I proceved Some fiew Small pines on the tops of the high hills and bushes in the hollars.    imediately above &amp; below this little river comences a rapid which is crouded with large rocks in every direction, the pasage both crooked and dificuelt, we halted at a Lodge to examine those noumerous islands of rock which apd. to extend maney miles below,—. great numbs. of Indians came in canoes to View us at this place, after passing this rapid which we accomplished without loss; 〈we passed〉 winding through between the hugh rocks for about 2 miles—.    (from this rapid the Conocil mountain is <hi rend="italic">S. W.</hi> which the Indians inform me is not far to the left of the great falls; this I call the <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="place" key="Mount Hood (Timm, Falls Mountain)">Timm</name>
                  </hi> or <name type="place" key="Mount Hood (Timm, Falls Mountain)">falls mountain</name> it is high and the top is covered with Snow)<ref target="n24102108" n="8"/>    imediately below the last rapids there is four Lodges of Indians on the Stard. Side, proceeded on about two miles lower and landed and encamped near <hi rend="italic">five</hi> Lodges of nativs, drying fish    those are the relations of those at the <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Great Falls of the">Great falls</name>,</hi> they are pore and have but little wood which they bring up the river from the falls as they Say, we purchasd a little wood to cook our Dog meat and fish; those people did not recive us at first with the same cordiality of those above, they appeare to be the Same nation Speak the Same language with a little curruption of maney words    Dress and fish in the Same way,<ref target="n24102109" n="9"/> all of whome have <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">pierced noses</name>
                  </hi> and the men when Dressed ware a long taper'd piece of Shell or beed put through the nose—<ref target="n24102110" n="10"/>    this part of the river is furnished with fine Springs which either rise high up the Sides of the hills or 〈out〉 on the bottom near the river and run into the river.    the hills are high and rugid a fiew scattering trees to be Seen on them either Small pine or Scrubey white oke.</p>
               <p>
The probable reason of the Indians residing on the Stard. Side of this as well as the waters of <name type="place" key="Lewis (Cahwahnakiooks) River">Lewis's</name>
                  <ref target="n24102111" n="11"/>
                  <name type="place" key="Lewis (Cahwahnakiooks) River">River</name> is their fear of the <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Paiute Indians">Snake</name> Indians</hi> who reside, as they nativs Say on a great river to the South,<ref target="n24102112" n="12"/> and are at war with those tribes, 〈our to〉 one of the Old Chiefs who accompanies us pointed out a place on the lard. Side where they had a great battle, not maney years ago, in which maney were killed on both Sides—, one of our party <name type="person" key="Collins, John">J. Collins</name> presented us with Some verry good <hi rend="italic">beer</hi> made of the <hi rend="italic">Pa-shi-co-quar-mash</hi> bread, which bread is the remains of what was laid in as [<hi rend="italic">X: a part of our</hi>] Stores of Provisions, at the first <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">flat heads</name> or <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Cho-pun-nish</name> Nation at the head of the <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Kosskoske</name>
                  </hi> river which by being frequently wet molded &amp; Sowered &amp;c.    we made 33 miles to day.<ref target="n24102113" n="13"/>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-10-21.03" n="lc.geo.1805-10-21.01">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Monday 21st Oct. 1805.    a clear cold morning.    we Set out eairly and proceeded on as usal    we then halted at an Indian village where we bought a little wood and cooked breakfast.    bought Some pounded Sammon from the natives, and Some white root cakes which is verry good.    we Saw among them a number of fisher and rackoon Skins.<ref target="n24102114" n="14"/> Some otter Skins<ref target="n24102115" n="15"/> also.    these Savages gave us any thing we asked them for, by our giving them any Small article as we pleased, as if they were in fear of us.    we proceeded on    passed River hills and cliffs of rocks on each side.    passed over a number of bad rockey rapids where the River is nearly filled with high dark couloured rocks    the water divided in narrow deep channels, bad whorl pools.    passed several Islands and fishing camps. Saw a great quantity of pounded Sammon Stacked up on the Shores.    we Saw a fiew Scattering pine on the hills.    we came about 32 miles this day and Camped at some Indian lodges close under high clifts of rocks on the Stard Side    a handsome Spring 
flowed out of the clifts.    these Savages have a fiew Elk and Deer Skins dressed with the hair on which they wear for covering.    they have also a fiew blue cloth blankets &amp;C—


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-10-21.04" n="lc.geo.1805-10-21.01">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Monday 21st.</hi>    We continued our voyage at an early hour, and had a fine morning. At 10, we came to the lodges of some of the natives,<ref target="n24102116" n="16"/> and halted with them about 2 hours. Here we got some bread, made of a small white root,<ref target="n24102117" n="17"/> which grows in this part of the country. We saw among them some small robes made of the skins of grey squirrels,<ref target="n24102118" n="18"/> some racoon skins, and 
acorns,<ref target="n24102119" n="19"/> which are signs of a timbered country not far distant. Having proceeded on again, we passed several more lodges of Indians; and through two very rocky rapid parts of the river with great difficulty. We went 32 miles and encamped at some Indian lodges, where we procured wood from the natives to cook with.

</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-10-21.05" n="lc.geo.1805-10-21.01">
            <sp who="jw">
               <speaker>Whitehouse</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Monday 21st Oct</hi>. <hi rend="italic">1805</hi>.<ref target="n24102120" n="20"/>    a clear cold morning.    we Set out eairly and proceeded on as usal, untill about 8 oClock at which time we halted at an Indian Camp where we bought Some wood and cooked breakfast.    bought Some pounded fish from the Natives and Some roots bread which was made up in cakes in form of ginger bread and eat verry well.    Saw a nomber of Rackoon Skins also otter and fisher Skins &amp;c.    they gave us any thing we asked for by our giving any Small article we pleased.    we proceeded on    passed clifts of rocks and River hills on each Side    passed over Several verry bad rockey rapids, where the River was nearly filled with high rocks of a dark coulour, and the water divided in narrow deep channels, where we ran through verry fast    high waves and whorl pools below.    passd. Several Islands and fishing Camps where the natives had a large quantity of pounded fish the best of their Sammon pounded up and put up in Small Stacks along the Shore for winter, &amp; cover them with Straw and pile the Stone around them.    the Solid clifts continue on each Side.    Saw a little Scattering pine timber on the hills on each Side of the River.    Some places the rocks are high and Steep.    we went about 32 miles and Camped at Some Indian Camps on the Stard. Side.    a handsom Spring run from a clift of rocks near our Camp.    we bought Some wood from the Natives to cook with    these natives appeer to be mostly covd. in deer and Elk Some rabit &amp; Squerrel Skins.    they have Some blew Cloth blankets &amp;.    we passed a Small River<ref target="n24102121" n="21"/> which came in on the Lard. Side</p>
               <p>
Monday October 21st    A clear cold morning.    We set out early, and proceeded on as usual, untill about 8 oClock A. M. when we halted at an Indian Camp, lying on the River side, &amp; bought some wood, with which we cooked breakfast, We also purchased from those Indians some pounded fish, and root bread, made up in the form of ginger bread, which eat very well.    We also saw among these Indians, Raccoon, Otter, fisher &amp; a number of other kinds of small Skins, These Indians behaved very kind to us, they gave us any article that we asked for which they had among them, by our giving them any small article ever so trifling we pleased; &amp; seemed very well pleased with us.    We proceeded on down the River, &amp; passed Clifts of rocks, &amp; hills, which lay near the river on both sides of it.    We also passed over several very bad rockey rapids, where the River was nearly filled with Rocks, which were high &amp; of a dark Colour, &amp; the Water divided into narrow Channels.    We ran with our Canoes through those Channels very fast, the Waves at that place run high, &amp; whirl pools lay below the Rocks, which made it extreamly dangerous for us to pass.—    We continued on, and passed several Islands &amp; fishing Camps, where the natives had large Quantities of pounded fish.    The Natives dry &amp; pound the best of their fish which they put up in small stacks, along the River Shores for winter, &amp; cover them over with Straw and pile Stones up high round them.—    The Solid clifts of rocks continue along each side of the River.    We saw some scattering pine trees growing on the hills on both sides of the River, &amp; the Rocks are steep &amp; high—    We passed a small River which lay on the South side of the River which we called <name type="place"
                        key="John Day (Lepage's) River (Sherman-Gilliam counties, Oreg.)">Baptiste River</name> &amp;    We came about 32 Miles this day &amp; encamped near some Indian Camps, which were Inhabited by a number of Indians; lying on the North side of the River.    We found near to our Camp, a handsome spring of water which ran from under some Clifts of rocks.    We purchased from those Indians some wood to Cook with.    These Natives were chiefly 〈covered〉 Cloathed with deer &amp; Elk skins, which they dress into leather.    They had also some Rabbit, &amp; squirrel skins among them.—    We also saw with them blue Cloth &amp; blankets, Our Course continues nearly West.



</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n24102101" n="1">Here in the Elkskin-bound Journal <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> gives the first course of the next day. There is also the number "33" by the total of "42" representing the actual miles traveled that day, that is, four instead of thirteen on the last course.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24102102" n="2">Above this sentence in the Elkskin-bound Journal is a sketch map showing the camp of October 21, 1805, and the return camp of <ref n="1806-04-21" type="related">April 21, 1806</ref> (misidentified as April 23). The entrances of the <name type="place"
                     key="John Day (Lepage's) River (Sherman-Gilliam counties, Oreg.)">John Day</name> and <name type="place" key="Deschutes (Clark's, Towanahiook's) River">Deschutes</name> rivers are also shown, but the streams are not named.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24102103" n="3">Referred to as "Met-cow-wes" on <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 77 and in entries on the return journey on <ref n="1806-04-24" type="related">April 24, 1806</ref>, they may have been the Methows, although these spoke a <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Salishan</name> language, not the Shahaptian of the people upstream. They lived in <name type="place" key="Klickitat County, Wash.">Klickitat County</name>, <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>, between the present towns of <name type="place" key="Roosevelt, Wash.">Roosevelt</name> and <name type="place" key="Blalock, Wash.">Blalock</name>. Hodge, 1:850. The Shahaptian term <hi rend="italic">m<seg n="u616u769">ɨ́</seg>t<seg n="uxu803">x̣</seg>aw</hi> designates a <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Salish</name>-speaking group closely associated with the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> and <name type="place" key="Okanogan River">Okanogan</name> rivers.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24102104" n="4">The Chiookan term <hi rend="italic">t<seg n="umu769">ḿ</seg>m</hi> is an onomatopoeic particle, derived from the Chinook jargon, meaning "(river) falls."</note>
            <note xml:id="n24102105" n="5">The rocks are more resistant parts of the middle Miocene Grande Ronde Basalt and the <name type="place" key="Frenchman Springs Member">Frenchman Springs Member</name> of the Wanapum Basalt, both part of the Columbia River Basalt Group.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24102106" n="6">These two groups of lodges are located near the mouth of present <name type="place" key="Rock Creek (Klickitat County, Wash.)">Rock Creek</name>, shown entering from the north in the upper right hand corner of <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 77. This was the location of a <name type="native_nation" key="Umatilla Indians">Umatilla</name> village named <hi rend="italic">k<hi rend="superscript">
                     <seg n="u8835">⊃</seg>
                  </hi>ami'<seg n="uluslash">l\</seg>p<hi rend="superscript">u</hi>
               </hi> ("opening through the canyon where light penetrates"). The location marked the downriver boundary of the <name type="native_nation" key="Umatilla Indians">Umatilla Indians</name> where over one hundred persons lived. It was a popular area because wood was plentiful. Archaeological work has been extensive on the opposite (<name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>) shore in this area. Ray (NVCB), 151; Dumond &amp; Minor.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24102107" n="7">The <name type="place"
                     key="John Day (Lepage's) River (Sherman-Gilliam counties, Oreg.)">John Day River</name>, marking the boundary between <name type="place" key="Gilliam County, Oreg.">Gilliam</name> and <name type="place" key="Sherman County, Oreg.">Sherman</name> counties, <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>. It is "<name type="place"
                     key="John Day (Lepage's) River (Sherman-Gilliam counties, Oreg.)">River de Page</name>" on fig. 20 in volume 5 and "<name type="place"
                     key="John Day (Lepage's) River (Sherman-Gilliam counties, Oreg.)">River La Page</name>" on <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 77, after expedition member <name type="person" key="Lepage, Jean Baptiste">Jean Baptiste Lepage</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24102108" n="8">
               <name type="place" key="Mount Hood (Timm, Falls Mountain)">Mt. Hood</name>; see above, <ref n="1805-10-18" type="related">October 18, 1805</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24102109" n="9">"<name type="native_nation" key="Tenino Indians">Wah-how pum</name>" on <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 77. A small Shahaptian-language group living near the mouth of <name type="place" key="Rock Creek (Klickitat County, Wash.)">Rock Creek</name>, in <name type="place" key="Klickitat County, Wash.">Klickitat County</name>. Hodge, 2:890.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24102110" n="10">The shell belongs to a marine mollusk of the genus <hi rend="italic">Dentalium,</hi> resembling a miniature elephant tusk, much used by tribes as far east as the <name type="place" key="Great Plains">Great Plains</name> for decoration. Cutright (LCPN), 229.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24102111" n="11">The phrase "waters of Lewis's" appears to have been substituted for some erased words.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24102112" n="12">Perhaps the <name type="place" key="Deschutes (Clark's, Towanahiook's) River">Deschutes River</name> or <name type="place"
                     key="John Day (Lepage's) River (Sherman-Gilliam counties, Oreg.)">John Day River</name>; these "Snakes" are probably <name type="native_nation" key="Northern Paiute Indians">Northern Paiutes</name>. Ray &amp; Lurie, 361–65; Murdock.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24102113" n="13">Camp was in <name type="place" key="Klickitat County, Wash.">Klickitat County</name>, in the vicinity of the present <name type="place" key="John Day Dam">John Day Dam</name>. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 77.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24102114" n="14">Fisher, <hi rend="italic">Martes pennanti,</hi> and raccoon, <hi rend="italic">Procyon lotor</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24102115" n="15">Perhaps the river otter, but notice confusion about the sea otter and harbor seal in the 
next entry.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24102116" n="16">Perhaps <name type="native_nation" key="Methow Indians">Methow Indians</name>, living in <name type="place" key="Klickitat County, Wash.">Klickitat County</name>, <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>, between <name type="place" key="Roosevelt, Wash.">Roosevelt</name> 
and <name type="place" key="Blalock, Wash.">Blalock</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24102117" n="17">Probably camas.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24102118" n="18">Perhaps western gray squirrel, <hi rend="italic">Sciurus griseus.</hi>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="n24102119" n="19">
               <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> reports that they were acorns of the Oregon white oak, <hi rend="italic">Quercus garryana</hi> Dougl. ex. Hook.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24102120" n="20">Above the date is the word "this."</note>
            <note xml:id="n24102121" n="21">
               <name type="place"
                     key="John Day (Lepage's) River (Sherman-Gilliam counties, Oreg.)">John Day River</name>, marking the boundaries of <name type="place" key="Gilliam County, Oreg.">Gilliam</name> and <name type="place" key="Sherman County, Oreg.">Sherman</name> counties, <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>. It 
was named "<name type="place"
                     key="John Day (Lepage's) River (Sherman-Gilliam counties, Oreg.)">River La Page</name>" by the party for member <name type="person" key="Lepage, Jean Baptiste">Jean Baptiste Lepage</name>. This last sentence appears to be squeezed in between entries.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-10-20" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-10-22" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
