<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.1805-11-21">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">November 21, 1805</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic
        Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            6</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">November 2, 1805–March 22, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1990</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">73-78</biblScope>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">255-256</biblScope>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">176</biblScope>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            11</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of Joseph Whitehouse, May 14, 1804–April 2,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1997</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">396-397</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc/>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-07-27</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-04-12</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date>November 21, 1805</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.1805-11-21.01">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">November 21st Thursday 1805</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>a Cloudy morning    most of the Indians left us, The nation on the opposit
          Side is Small &amp; Called 
          <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clap-sott</name>,</hi>
                  <ref target="n25112101" n="1"/>Their great chief name 
          <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="person" key="Stil-la-sha">Stil-la-sha</name>
                  </hi>—The nation liveing to the North is Called 
          <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Chehalis Indians">Chieltz</name>.</hi>
                  <ref target="n25112102" n="2"/>   The chief is name 
          <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="person" key="Ma-laugh">Malaugh</name>
                  </hi>   not large nation and wore 〈their〉 his beards as informed by the Inds.
             In my absence the hunters Kild. 7 Deer, 4 brants &amp; a Crane.</p>
               <p>Great numbers of the dark brant passing Southerley, the white yet Stationary, no gees
          &amp; Swan to be Seen. The wind blew hard from the S. E. which with the addition of the
          flood tide raised emence Swells &amp; waves which almost entered our Encampment
             morng. dark &amp; Disagreeable, a Supriseing Climent. We have not had One
          cold day Since we passed below the last falls or 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Cascades (Great Rapids, Great Shute)">great
          Shute</name>&amp; Some time before    the Climent is temperate, and the only
          change we have experienced is from fair weather to rainey windey weather—    I
          made a chief &amp; gave a medel    this man is name 
          <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="person" key="Tow-wall">Tow-wâll</name>
                  </hi>and appears to have Some influence with the nation and tells me he lives at the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Cascades (Great Rapids, Great Shute)">great
          Shute</name>—
          <ref target="n25112103" n="3"/>   we gave 
          <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">the Squar</name>a Coate of Blue Cloth for the belt
          of Blue Beeds we gave for the Sea otter Skins purchased of an Indian.    at 12
          oClock it began to rain, and continued moderately all day, Some wind from the S. E.,
          waves too high for us to proceed on our homeward bound journey. Latitude of this place
          is 
          <hi rend="italic">46° 19' 11 1/10"</hi>North    Several Indians and Squars
          came this evening I beleave for the purpose of gratifying the passions of our men, Those
          people appear to View 〈horedom〉 Sensuality as a necessary evile, and do not appear to
          abhore this as Crime in the unmarried females. The young women Sport openly with our
          men, and appear to receive the approbation of their friends &amp; relations for So doing
             maney of the women are handsom. They are all low both men and women, I saw
          the name of 
          <name type="person" key="Bowmon, J.">J. Bowmon</name>marked or picked on a young Squars
          left arm. The women of this nation Pick their legs in different figures as an orniment.
             the[y] were their hair loose, Some trinkets in their ears, none in the nose
          as those above, their Dress is as follows, i,e the men, were a roabe of either the skins
          of [
          <hi rend="italic">blank</hi>] a Small fured animal, &amp; which is most common, or the
          Skins of the Sea orter, Loon, Swan, Beaver,
          <ref target="n25112104" n="4"/>Deer, Elk, or blanketes either red, blu, or white, which
          roabes cover the sholders arms &amp; body, all other parts are nakd.</p>
               <p>The women were a Short peticoat of the iner bark of the white Ceder or 
          <hi rend="italic">Arber Vita,</hi>which hang down loose in Strings nearly as low as the
          knee, with a Short Robe which fall half way down the Thigh.    no other part
          is Covered. The orniments are beeds, Blue principally, large Brass wire around their
          rists Som rings, and maney men have Salors Clothes, many have good fusees &amp; Ball
          &amp; Powder—    The women ware a String of Something curious tied tight above
          the anckle, all have large Swelled legs &amp; thighs    The men Small legs
          &amp; thighs and Generally badly made—
          <ref target="n25112105" n="5"/>They live on Elk Deer fowls, but principally fish and
          roots of 3 Kinds, Lickorish, 
          <hi rend="italic">Wapto</hi>&amp;c. The women have more privaleges than is Common
          amongst Indians—    Pocks &amp; Venerial [
          <hi rend="italic">X: venereous</hi>] is Common amongst them
          <ref target="n25112106" n="6"/>   I Saw one man &amp; one woman who appeared
          to be all in Scabs, &amp; Several men with the venereal, their other Disorders and the
          remides for them I could not lern    we divided Some ribin between the men of
          our party to bestow on their favourite Lasses, this plan to Save the knives &amp; more
          valuable articles.</p>
               <p>Those people gave me Sturgion Salmon &amp; wapto roots, &amp; we bought roots, 〈high
          bush Cranberies,〉 Some mats &amp;c. &amp;c. for which we were obliged to give emence
          prices—    we also purchased a kind of Cranberry
          <ref target="n25112107" n="7"/>which the Indians Say the geather in the low lands, off
          of Small either vines or bushes just abov the ground—    we also purchased
          hats made of Grass &amp;c.
          <ref target="n25112108" n="8"/>of those Indians, Some very handsom mats made of flags—
          <ref target="n25112109" n="9"/>   Some fiew curious baskets made of a Strong
          weed &amp; willow or [
          <hi rend="italic">blank</hi>] Splits—
          <ref target="n25112110" n="10"/>, also a Sweet Soft black root,
          <ref target="n25112111" n="11"/>about th Sise &amp; Shape of a Carrot, this root they
          Value verry highly—    The 
          <hi rend="italic">Wapto</hi>root is Scerce, and highly valued by those people, this root
          they roste in hot ashes like a potato and the outer Skin peals off, tho this is a
          trouble they Seldom perform.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.1805-11-21.02">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Thursday November 21st 1805</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>a cloudy morning    most of the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinnooks</name>leave our Camp and
          return home, great numbers of the dark brant passing to the South, the white Brant have
          not yet commenced their flight. The wind blew hard from the S. E. which with the
          addition of the flood tide raised verry high waves which broke with great violence
          against the Shore throwing water into our Camp—    the fore part of this day
          Cloudy    at 12 oClock it began to rain and Continued all day moderately,
          Several Indians Visit us to day of different nations or Bands Some of the 
          <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Chehalis Indians">Chiltz</name>
                  </hi>Nation who reside on the Sea Coast near 
          <name type="place" key="Point Lewis">Point Lewis</name>, Several of the 
          <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clotsops</name>
                  </hi>who reside on the opposit Side of the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>imediately opposit to us, and a
          Chief from the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Cascades (Great Rapids, Great Shute)">Grand
          rapid</name>to whome we gave a Medal.</p>
               <p>An old woman &amp; wife to a Cheif of the 
          <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinnooks</name>
                  </hi>
                  <ref target="n25112112" n="12"/>came and made a Camp near ours    She brought
          with her 6 young Squars [
          <hi rend="italic">NB: her daughters &amp; nieces</hi>] I believe for the purpose of
          gratifying the passions of the men of our party and receving for those indulgiences Such
          Small as She (the old woman) thought proper to accept of, Those people appear to view
          Sensuality as a Necessary evel, and do not appear to abhor it as a Crime in the
          unmarried State—    The young females are fond of the attention of our men and
          appear to meet the sincere approbation of their friends and connections, for thus
          obtaining their favours; the womin of the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinnook</name>Nation have handsom
          faces low and badly made with large legs &amp; thighs which are generally Swelled from a
          Stopage of the circulation in the feet (which are Small) by maney Strands of Beeds or
          curious Strings which are drawn tight around the leg above the anckle, their leges are
          also picked with different figures, I Saw on the left arm of a Squar the following
          letters 
          <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="person" key="Bowmon, J.">J. Bowmon</name>,</hi>all those are Considered by
          the natives of this quarter as handsom deckerations, and a woman without those
          deckorations is Considered as among the lower Class    they ware their hair
          lose hanging over their back and Sholders maney have blue beeds 〈in〉 threaded &amp; hung
          from different parts of their 
          <hi rend="italic">ears</hi>and about their neck and around their wrists, their dress
          other wise is prosisely like that of the Nation of 
          <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Wahkiakum Indians">Wa ci a cum</name>
                  </hi>as already discribed.    a Short roab, and 
          <hi rend="italic">tissue</hi>or kind of peticoat of the bark of Cedar which fall down in
          Strings as low as the knee behind and not So low before    maney of the men
          have blankets of red blue or Spotted Cloth or the common three &amp; 2½ point blankets,
          <ref target="n25112113" n="13"/>and Salors old clothes which they appear to prise
          highly, they also have robes of 
          <hi rend="italic">Sea Otter,</hi>Beaver, Elk, Deer, fox and Cat
          <ref target="n25112114" n="14"/>common to this countrey, which I have never Seen in the
          U States. They also precure a roabe from the nativs above, which is made of the Skins of
          a Small animal
          <ref target="n25112115" n="15"/>about the Size of a Cat, which is light and dureable
          and highly prized by those people—    the greater numbers of the men of the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinnoks</name>have Guns and powder and
          Ball—    The Men are low homely and badly made, Small Crooked legs 〈and Small
          thighs〉 large feet, and all of both Sects have flattened heads—    The food of
          this nation is principally fish &amp; roots    the fish they precure from the
          river by the means of nets and gigs, and the Salmon which run up the Small branches
          together with what they collect drifted up on the Shores of the Sea coast near to where
          they live—</p>
               <p>The roots which they use are Several different kinds, the 
          <hi rend="italic">Wappato</hi>which they precure from the nativs above, a black root
          which they call 
          <hi rend="italic">Shaw-na tâh que</hi>
                  <ref target="n25112116" n="16"/>&amp; the wild licquorish is the most Common, they also
          kill a fiew Elk Deer &amp; fowl—    maney of the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinnooks</name>appear to have
          venerious and pustelus disorders.    one woman whome I saw at the beech
          appeared all over in Scabs and ulsers &amp;c.</p>
               <p>we gave to the men each a pece of ribin    We purchased Cramberies Mats
          verry netely made of flags and rushes, Some roots, Salmon and I purchased a hat made of
          Splits &amp; Strong grass, which is made in the fashion which was common in the U States
          two years ago also Small baskets to hold Water made of Split and Straw, for those
          articles we gave high prices—.
          <ref target="n25112117" n="17"/>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.1805-11-21.03">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>Thursday 21st Nov. 1805.    a cloudy and a little rain    The
          Latitude of 
          <name type="place" key="Baker (Haley's) Bay">Hailys bay</name>or at our Incampment at
          the point above is 46° 19' 11 7/10" Min North.    the Natives value their Sea
          otter Skins verry high.    our officers being anxious to purchase a robe made
          of two of those animels, they offered great prices in cloaths trinkets &amp;C. but they
          would not take any thing except blue beeds.    at length they purchasd the
          Robe for a beeded belt which 
          <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">our Intrepters Squaw</name>had    these
          animels are Scarse &amp; hard to kill.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.1805-11-21.04">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Thursday 21st.</hi>   A cloudy morning. About 8 o'clock, all
          the natives left us. The wind blew so violent to day, and the waves ran so high, that we
          could not set out on our return, which it is our intention to do as soon as the weather
          and water will permit. The season being so far advanced, we wish to establish our winter
          quarters as soon as possible. One of the natives here had a robe of sea-otter skins, of
          the finest fur I ever saw; which the Commanding Officers wanted very much, and offered
          two blankets for it, which the owner refused, and said he would not take five. He wanted
          beads of a blue colour, of which we had none, but some that were on a belt belonging to
          our 
          <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">interpreter's squaw</name>; so they gave him the
          belt for the skins. In the evening more of the natives came to our camp, and the night
          was very wet and disagreeable.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.1805-11-21.05">
            <sp who="jw">
               <speaker>Whitehouse</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>Thursday Novemr 23d
          <ref target="n25112118" n="18"/>   A Cloudy morning, and a light sprinkling
          of rain fell.    The Indians all left our Camp.    Two of our
          hunters left the Camp to go out ahunting.    The Swell in the River ran so
          high that it detain'd us, at our Camp from going up the River again, to look out for
          Winter Quarters, which our officers intended as soon as the Weather would permit, and
          the Season of the Year advancing made it absolutely necessary that it should be the
          case.—    The Season of the Year, is generally cold at this place, but at the
          present time it was very pleasant.    We are now convinced that the wide part
          of the River, or bay we entered into a few days past; is a bay only, and is called 
          <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="place" key="Baker (Haley's) Bay">Haleys bay</name>
                  </hi>   the Latitude is as follows of the point above the said Bay, &amp; Bay;
          both these lying in the same Latitude which is 46° 19' 7S North.    The
          Indians here, set a high value on the Sea Otter skins.    Our officers were
          very anxious to purchase 〈an〉 a Robe made out of the Skins of two of these animals.
             They offered the Indians a great price in Cloths &amp; trinkets for it; but
          they refused their offer, &amp; would take nothing but beads for them.    They
          at last offered to let them have it for 5 New blankets, which our Officers would not
          give them.    They at last purchas'd it from them for a Belt which had a
          number of beads on it, which our officers procured from 
          <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">the Indian woman our Interpreter</name>, which we
          got at the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>Nation, as Interpreter to
          the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Snake</name>nation; who is still with
          us.    I mention this in Order to show the high value that they set on these
          Skins, which were very beautiful.—</p>
               <p>I also mention this circumstance, in order, to show the very high value, they also
          set on Beads.    The Sea Otter is plenty, between this and the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Great Falls of the">great falls of the Columbia
          River</name>; but are very difficult to be got.    They are rarely to be
          caught in traps, &amp; when shot they sink immediately, which makes the procuring of
          them so difficult.    The evening was rainey &amp; a number of Indians both
          Male &amp; female came to our Camp this evening.—</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n25112101" n="1">The 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsops</name>, for whom the party's
        winter quarters on the coast were named, occupied the south bank of the 
        <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>from 
        <name type="place" key="Point Adams">Point Adams</name>at the river's mouth and upstream
        as far as 
        <name type="place" key="Tongue Point (Point William)">Tongue Point</name>, and south along
        the 
        <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>coast to 
        <name type="place" key="Tillamook Head (Clark's Point of View)">Tillamook Head</name>, all
        in 
        <name type="place" key="Clatsop County, Oreg.">Clatsop County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>. 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>map 82; Hodge, 1:305; Berreman, 15; Taylor (CkI); Hajda,
        102–4. Their name derives from 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookan</name>
               <hi rend="italic">łac'ǝp</hi>or 
        <hi rend="italic">łak'ílak</hi>(two dialectical variants), "those who have pounded
        salmon," whie one of their main villages on 
        <name type="place" key="Point Adams">Point Adams</name>was called 
        <hi rend="italic">łiak'ílaki(x),</hi>"where there is pounded salmon." Silverstein. The 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsops</name>and the 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinooks</name>across the river spoke
        dialects which were practically identical and which together comprise the Lower Chinook
        language. These languages were distinct from the related but mutually unintelligible Upper
        Chinook language spoken by 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookan</name>peoples upriver. Although
        they possessed many skills which the newcomers admired, many aspects of their culture
        aroused negative reactions in Anglo-Americans and British. The ambivalence of the captains
        was far from unique. The chief's name as given here does not appear again. The name is not
        recorded on the undated list placed with entries of 
        <ref n="1806-01-01" type="related">January 1, 1806</ref>. Perhaps it was an error in
        communication.</note>
            <note xml:id="n25112102" n="2">The 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Chehalis Indians">Chehalis</name>, or more precisely the
        Lower 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Chehalis Indians">Chehalis</name>, were a 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Salish</name>-speaking people living in 
        <name type="place" key="Grays Harbor County, Wash.">Grays Harbor</name>and 
        <name type="place" key="Pacific County, Wash.">Pacific</name>counties on the southern 
        <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>coast. Their term is apparently 
        <hi rend="italic">c̓x̣i'ls,</hi>from 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookan</name>
               <hi rend="italic">giłac̓x̣i'ls,</hi>"Lower 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Chehalis Indians">Chehalis</name>
               <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Salish</name>people." Their 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Salish</name>name is 
        <hi rend="italic">ʦũ'ǝx̣il'ǝs,</hi>"sand," for a large and important village at 
        <name type="place" key="Westport, Wash.">Westport</name>on 
        <name type="place" key="Grays Harbor">Grays Harbor</name>. Lower 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Chehalis Indians">Chehalis</name>territory centered around
        
        <name type="place" key="Grays Harbor">Grays Harbor</name>and extended southward to 
        <name type="place" key="Willapa Bay">Willapa Bay</name>, where the north shore was claimed
        by both the Lower 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Chehalis Indians">Chehalis</name>and the 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinooks</name>proper. Hodge, 1:241;
        Spier, 29–31; Ray (LCEN), 36; Swanton, 415–16; Taylor (CsI); Hajda, 96; Silverstein. "
        <name type="person" key="Ma-laugh">Ma-laugh</name>" may be the same as "
        <name type="person" key="Mar-lock-ke">Mar-lock-ke</name>" in an undated entry at 
        <ref n="1806-01-01" type="related">January 1, 1806</ref>. His name is not identifiable
        linguistically.</note>
            <note xml:id="n25112103" n="3">A vertical line runs through these words in the
        Elkskin-bound Journal, beginning with "I made a chief." Also in a passage below, from
        "otter skins" to "homeward bound journey." 
        <name type="person" key="Tow-wall">Tow-wâll</name>(
        <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="person" key="Tow-wall">Túwal</name>
               </hi>) is unknown.</note>
            <note xml:id="n25112104" n="4">American beaver, 
        <hi rend="italic">Castor canadensis.</hi>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="n25112105" n="5">One word is added interlinearly near here in the
        Elkskin-bound Journal but is difficult to read. It appears in the same hand and ink as
        "venereous" below and may be "Perstetus" for "prostitutes."</note>
            <note xml:id="n25112106" n="6">The pox, or syphilis, and venereal disease.</note>
            <note xml:id="n25112107" n="7">Wild cranberry, 
        <hi rend="italic">Vaccinium oxycoccos</hi>L., much used by the natives of the lower 
        <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>. The cranberry was plentiful in
        the Lower 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinook</name>territory and was an item
        of trade. Hitchcock et al., 4:34–35; Gunther (EWW), 45; Ray (LCEN), 122; Swan (NC),
        89.</note>
            <note xml:id="n25112108" n="8">These hats were made of cedar bark and beargrass; see
        illustrations of the conical style in figs. 10, 11, 21, 22. 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>brief notes here about the
        ethnobotany of the Lower 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinooks</name>are treated more
        expansively by 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>during the winter at 
        <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name>. Cutright (LCPN),
        264–69.</note>
            <note xml:id="n25112109" n="9">Flags are again the common cat-tail, and woven mats of the
        plant were widely used by coastal Indians. Gunther (EWW), 21.</note>
            <note xml:id="n25112110" n="10">Here 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>does not clearly distinguish between
        baskets for cooking, woven watertight of cedar bark and beargrass, and other baskets, less
        closely woven of the same materials or of rushes, grasses, and sedges. Split willow stems
        or willow bark, as well as split spruce roots, were often used with rushes for making
        baskets. Gunther (EWW), 17, 26–27; Ruby &amp; Brown (CITC), 15; Cutright (LCPN), 267–68.
        See also Swan (ICF), as a source for the material culture of Northwest Coast
        Indians.</note>
            <note xml:id="n25112111" n="11">Edible thistle, 
        <hi rend="italic">Cirsium edule</hi>Nutt., a species new to science. See below, 
        <ref n="1806-01-21" type="related">January 21, 1806</ref>, for 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>description. Hitchcock et al.,
        5:137–38; Ray (LCEN), 120; Cutright (LCPN), 264, 274, 406.</note>
            <note xml:id="n25112112" n="12">Evidently the wife of 
        <name type="person" key="Delashelwilt">Delashelwilt</name>. See below, 
        <ref n="1806-03-15" type="related">March 15, 1806</ref>. Ruby &amp; Brown (CITC),
        106.</note>
            <note xml:id="n25112113" n="13">A 2½ point blanket would be 5 feet 4 inches by 4 feet 3
        inches; see 
        <ref n="1805-08-20" type="related">August 20, 1805</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n25112114" n="14">Probably the Oregon bobcat, 
        <hi rend="italic">Lynx rufus fasciatus,</hi>a subspecies then unknown to science. See
        below, 
        <ref n="1806-02-18" type="related">February 18</ref>and 
        <ref n="1806-02-21" type="related">21</ref>, 1806. Burroughs, 92–93; Cutright (LCPN),
        273, 387, 442; Hall, 2:1053.</note>
            <note xml:id="n25112115" n="15">The mountain beaver, 
        <hi rend="italic">Aplodontia rufa,</hi>
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>"sewelel." A rodent, not a beaver,
        it was then unknown to science. See below, 
        <ref n="1806-02-26" type="related">February 26, 1806</ref>. Cutright (LCPN), 263, 271,
        387, 439; Hall, 1:334–36.</note>
            <note xml:id="n25112116" n="16">The term may be Lower 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookan</name>
               <hi rend="italic">[i|a]
        <seg n="u353">š</seg>anáta(n)qi,</hi>"thistle" for the edible thistle above. Gibbs (AVC),
        19.</note>
            <note xml:id="n25112117" n="17">It is apparent that strong weed (of first entry), strong
        grass, and straw all refer to beargrass which was used to weave both watertight hats as
        well as baskets. Swan (NC), 162–63; Gunther (EWW), 23. There is a vertical line through
        the botany passage, perhaps done by 
        <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>but not in his red ink. The hat
        mentioned here is not the typical, conical style of hat worn by the natives (see below, 
        <ref n="1805-12-29" type="related">December 29, 1805</ref>, and 
        <ref n="1806-01-29" type="related">January 29</ref>, 
        <ref n="1805-01-30" type="related">30</ref>, 1806). It is probably one like that
        pictured in Gunther (ILNC), 185. The popular hat of the United States was simimilar to a
        top hat, but with a lower crown and a wider brim. See 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>entry, 
        <ref n="1806-01-19" type="related">January 19, 1806</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n25112118" n="18">Again a misdate, this time for November 21.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-11-20" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-11-22" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
