<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.1805-08-04">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">August 4, 1805</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic
        Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            5</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">July 28–November 1, 1805</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1989</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">40-44</biblScope>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">195-196</biblScope>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">121</biblScope>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            11</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of Joseph Whitehouse, May 14, 1804–April 2,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1997</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">254-255</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
         <geoDecl datum="WGS">
            <placeName/>
            <geo>45.4427 -112.5054</geo>
            <note>Camped near the Madison-Beaverhead County line, above the mouth of the Nez Perce Creek</note>
         </geoDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc/>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-06-01</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-04-12</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date>August 4, 1805</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.1805-08-04.01">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">August 4th 1805.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>Set out very early this morning and steered S. E. by E. about 4 Miles when we passed
          a bould runing creek about 12 yards wide the water could and remarkably clear, we then
          changed our course to S. E. passing obliquely across a valley which boar nearly E
          leaving the valley which we had pursued for the 2 precedeing days.    at the
          distance of 3 miles we passed a handsome little river which passes through this valley;
          it is about 30 yards wide affords a considerable quantity of water and I believe it may
          be navigated some miles.    I then changed my rout to S. W. passed a high
          plain which lyes between the vallies and returned to the S. valley, in passing which I
          fell in with a river about 45 yards wide which I waideg and then continued my rout down
          to it's junction with the river just mentioned, and from thence to the entrance of the
          creek which falls in about 2 miles below; still continuing my rout down this stream
          about three miles further and about 2 M. below our encampment of the last evening
             this river forms a junction with a river 50 yards wide which comes from the
          N. W. and falling into the S. valley runs parrallel with the 
          <name type="place" key="Madison River (Middle Fork)">middle fork</name>about 12 miles.
             this is a bould rappid &amp; clear stream it's bed so broken and obstructed
          by gravel bars and Islands that it appeared to me impossible to navigate it with safety.
             the 
          <name type="place" key="Madison River (Middle Fork)">middle fork</name>is gentle and
          possesses about ⅔ds as much water as this rappid stream, it's cours so far as I can
          observe it is about S. W. and it appears to be navigable; its water is much warmer than
          that of the rappid fork and somewhat turbid, from which I concluded that it had it's
          source at a greater distance in the mountains and passed through an opener country than
          the other.
          <ref target="n18080401" n="1"/>   under this impression I wrote a note to 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name>recommending his taking the 
          <name type="place" key="Madison River (Middle Fork)">middle fork</name>provided he
          should arrive at this place before my return which I expect will be the day after
          tomorrow.    the note I left on a pole at the forks of the river and having
          refreshed ourselves and eat heartily of some venison we killed this morning I continued
          my rout up the Stard. side of the N. W. fork, determining to pursue it untill 12 OC. the
          next day and then pass over to the 
          <name type="place" key="Madison River (Middle Fork)">middle fork</name>and return to
          their junction or untill I met 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name>.    we encamped
          this evening near the point where the river leaves the valley and enters the mountains,
          having traveled about 20 miles.—
          <ref target="n18080402" n="2"/>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.1805-08-04.02">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Sunday August 4th 1805.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>Set out very early this morning and Steered S. E. by E. 4 M. when we pased a bold
          runing Creek 12 yds. wide, the water of which was clear and very cold.    it
          appears to be formed by four dranes from the snowey mountains to our left.   
          after passing this creek we changed our direction to S. E. passing obliquely across a
          valley which boar E leaving the valley we had pursued for the two peceeding days.
             at the distance of 3 Ms. we passed a handsome little river which meanders
          through this valley; it is about 30 yds wide, affords a considerable quantity of water
          and appears as if it might be navigated some miles.    the currant is not
          rapid nor the water very clear; the banks are low and the bed formed of stone and
          gravel.
          <ref target="n18080403" n="3"/>   I now changed my rout to S. W.   
          passed a high plain which lies betwen the valleies and returned to the South valley, in
          passing which I fell in with a river about 45 yds. wide gravley bottom gentle currant
          waist deep and water of a whitish blue tinge.    this stream we waded and
          continued our rout down it to the entrance of the river just mentioned about ¾ of a
          mile.    still continuing down we passed the entrance of the creek about 2
          miles lower down; and at the distance of three miles further arrived at it's junction
          with a river 50 yds. wide which Comes from the S. W. and falling into the South valley
          runs parallel with the 
          <name type="place" key="Madison River (Middle Fork)">middle fork</name>about 12 miles
          before it forms a junction. I now found that our encampment of the last evening was
          about 1½ miles above the entrance of this large river on Stard.    this is a
          bold rappid and Clear Stream, it's bed so much broken and obstructed by gravley bars and
          it's waters so much subdivided by Islands that it appears to me utterly impossible to
          navigate it with safety. the 
          <name type="place" key="Madison River (Middle Fork)">middle fork</name>is gentle and
          possesses about ⅔rds as much water as this stream.    it's course so far as I
          can observe it is about S. W., and from the opening of the valley I beleive it still
          bears more to the West above    it may be safely navigated.    it's
          water is much warmer then the rapid fork and it's water more turbid; from which I
          conjecture that it has it's sources at a greater distance in the mountains and passes
          through an opener country than the other.    under this impression I wrote a
          note to 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt Clark</name>, recommending his taking the 
          <name type="place" key="Madison River (Middle Fork)">middle fork</name>povided he should
          arrive at this place before my return, which I expect will be the day after tomorrow.
             this note I left on a pole at 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Three Forks of the">the forks</name>of the
          river, and having refreshed ourselves and eat heartily of some venison which we killed
          this morning we continued our rout up the rapid fork on the Stard side, resolving to
          pursue this stream untill noon tomorrow and then pass over to the 
          <name type="place" key="Madison River (Middle Fork)">middle fork</name>and come down it
          to their junction or untill I meet 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt Clark</name>. I have seen no recent Indian
          sign [
          <hi rend="italic">NB: Qu</hi>] in the course of my rout as yet. 
          <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbono</name>complains much of his
          leg, and is the cause of considerable detention to us.    we encamped on the
          river bank near the place at which it leaves the valley and enters the mountain having
          traveled about 23 miles.    we saw some Antelopes deer Crains, gees, and ducks
          of the two species common to this country.    the summer duck has ceased to
          appear, nor do I beleive it is an inhabitant of this part of the country. the timber
          &amp;c is as heretofore tho' there is more in this valley on the rapid fork than we have
          seen in the same extent on the river since we entered this valley.    the
          Indians appear on some parts of the river to have distroyed a great proporiton of the
          little timber which there is by seting fire to the bottoms. This morning 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name>set out at sunrise, and sent
          two hunters ahead to kill some meat.    at 8 A. M. he arrived at my camp of
          the 2ed inst. where he breakfasted; here he found a note which I had left for him at
          that place informing him of the occurences of my rout &amp;c. the river continued to be
          crouded with Islands, rapid and shoaly.    these shoals or riffles succeeded
          each other every 3 or four hundred yards; at those places they are obliged to drag the
          canoes over the stone there not being water enough to float them, and betwen the riffles
          the current is so strong that they are compelled to have cecourse to the cord; and being
          unable to walk on the shore for the brush wade in the river along the shore and hawl
          them by the cord; his has increased the pain and labour extreemly; their feet soon get
          tender and soar by wading and walking over the stones.    these are also so
          slipry that they frequently get severe falls.    being constantly wet soon
          makes them feble also.    their hunters killed 2 deer today and some gees and
          ducks wer killed by those who navigated the canoes.    they saw deer antelopes
          Crains beaver Otter &amp;c. 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark's</name>ancle became so painfull to
          him that he was unable to walk.—    This evening they encamped on the Stard.
          side in a bottom of cottonwood timber all much fatiegued.
          <ref target="n18080404" n="4"/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <table rows="4" cols="3">
                     <head>Courses and distances traveled by 
              <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name>and party.
              <lb/>
                        <hi rend="italic">August 4th 1805.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 45° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  5</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">on a direct course to a Lard. bend passing 4
                bends on the
                <lb/>Lard. side and several bayous on either side.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 20° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  4</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">With the river to a bluff on the Lard. side,
                passing 3 bends on
                <lb/>the Stard. and two small Islands and 2 Bayous on Stard. side.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 60° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                           <hi rend="underline">  6</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">with the river to an island, passing six
                circular bends on the
                <lb/>Stard. and several small bayous.    encamped on stard. side in
                <lb/>a bottom covered with cottonwood.—</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                           <hi rend="right">Miles</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                           <hi rend="double underline">15</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.1805-08-04.03">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">August 4th Sunday 1805</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>a fine morning cool    proceeded on verry early and Brackfast at the Camp 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt Lewis</name>left yesterday morning, at
          this Camp he left a note informing that he discovered no fresh Sign of Indians &amp;c.
          The river continued to be crouded with Islands Sholey rapid &amp; clear, I could not
          walk on Shore to day as my ankle was Sore from a tumer on that part.    the
          method we are compelled to take to get on is fatigueing &amp; laborious in the extreen,
          haul the Canoes over the rapids, which Suckceed each other every two or three hundred
          yards and between the water rapid oblige to towe &amp; walke on Stones the whole day
          except when we have poleing men wet all day Sore feet &amp;c. &amp;c   
          Murcury at Sun rise 49 a. 0,</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.1805-08-04.04">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Sunday 4th August 1805</hi>.    a clear morning.
             we Set out at Sunrise    one hunter Sent on a head to kill some
          fresh meat for the party.    proceeded on    about 8 oC. A M. we
          found a note which 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name>had left &amp; his camp
          yesterday morning, letting us know that if he found no Indians or fresh Sign by this
          evening he would return a fiew miles back &amp; hunt till we come up.    we
          Saw a flock of goats in the high plain under the Mountains, on the top of which is a
          little Snow &amp; considerable of pine timber.    the Mountains are makeing
          near the River on each Side    only a valley along the River which is
          pleasant, but the Soil indifferent.    we proceeded on    came up
          with our hunter who killed 2 deer    the rapids continue.    we have
          hard halling over them with the chord, and where the Shore will not admit we have to
          waid in the water. Some of the Mountains near the River has been burned by the natives
          Some time ago.    the pine timber killed.    the cotten timber in
          Some of the R. bottoms killd. &amp; dry also.    not So much timber along the
          River as below.    we proceeded on    killed a goose &amp; a duck
             they are pleanty on the River.    we Came 15 miles this day and
          Camped
          <ref target="n18080405" n="5"/>on S. Side at a bottom covd. with dry trees red willows
          <ref target="n18080406" n="6"/>&amp; rose bush which are verry thick.   
          beaver ponds &amp; Sign pleanty,—&amp;.C.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.1805-08-04.05">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Sunday 4th.</hi>   At sunrise we continued our march, in a
          fine morning; went about 6 miles when we came to a fork of the river;
          <ref target="n18080407" n="7"/>crossed the south branch and from a high knob discovered
          that the river had forked below us, as we could see the timber on the north branch about
          6 or 7 miles from the south and west branches. We therefore crossed to the north branch,
          and finding it not navigable for our canoes, went down to the confluence and left a note
          for 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clarke</name>directing him to take the
          left hand branch. We then went up the north branch about 10 miles and encamped on
          it.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.1805-08-04.06">
            <sp who="jw">
               <speaker>Whitehouse</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Sunday 4th August 1805</hi>.    a clear morning.
             we Set out at Sunrise.    a hunter Sent on a head to kill Some
          fresh meat for us to eat.    proceeded on    abt. 8 oC. A. m. we
          Came to 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name>camp of the 2 ult.
          <ref target="n18080408" n="8"/>   he left a note letting us know he left this
          place yesterday morning, and ment to go on untill this evening, &amp; if they found no
          fresh Sign of Indian, they would return back a fiew miles &amp; hunt untill we came up.
             we Saw Several 〈buffalow &amp;〉 Elk in a plain on L. Side.   
          proceeded on    our hunters killed 2 deer.    the rapids bad as
          usal.    we are obledged to use the towing lines where ever the Shore will
          admit.    Some of the Mountains near the River on L. S. has been burned by the
          natives Some time ago.    The timber killed.    not So much timber
          on the River as below.    proceeded on    killed a goose and a duck.
             they are pleanty on the River.    we Came 15 miles this day and
          Camped at a bottoms covered with dry timber and wild rose bush which is verry thick on
          S. Side.    the beaver ponds and Sign pleanty &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Sunday August 4th    This morning we had clear cool weather; we set out at
          sun rise, having sent one of our hunters to go on, a head of us, in order to procure
          some fresh meat for our party.    we proceeded on, and about 8 o'Clock A. M.
          we came to where 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Lewis</name>had encamped the 2nd
          instant.    he left a note, wherein he informed us, that he had left this
          place Yesterday morning, and that he meant to go on untill this evening, &amp; if he or
          his party found no fresh sign of Indians, that they would return back a few Miles and
          hunt, untill we came up.    We saw several Elk, in a plain on the South side
          of the River, We proceeded on, the Rapids being bad as usual, and we are obliged to make
          use of the Tow Ropes, wherever the Shore will admit, some of the Mountains on the South
          side of the River has had the Grass burned off from them, &amp; the Timber killed on
          them.—    The timber is not so plenty here, as it is some distance below.
             We proceeded on and saw plenty of Ducks &amp; Geese in the River.
             Our hunter that went out this morning killed 2 deer, which we took on
          board.    We encamped in the Evening at a bottom covered with dry timber, and
          wild rose bushes in great plenty on the South side of the River, where we saw ponds made
          by the beaver in great abundance.—</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n18080401" n="1">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>route is shown by the dotted
        line on 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>map 65. He had arrived at the "Forks of 
        <name type="place" key="Beaverhead (Jefferson) River">the Jefferson</name>." 
        <name type="place" key="Ruby (Philanthropy) River">Ruby River</name>(
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>
               <name type="place" key="Ruby (Philanthropy) River">Philanthropy River</name>) comes in
        from the east to join 
        <name type="place" key="Beaverhead (Jefferson) River">the Beaverhead</name>(which they
        called 
        <name type="place" key="Beaverhead (Jefferson) River">the Jefferson</name>), forming the 
        <name type="place" key="Beaverhead (Jefferson) River">Jefferson River</name>. A few miles
        downstream the 
        <name type="place" key="Big Hole (Sensable, Wisdom) River">Big Hole River</name>(their 
        <name type="place" key="Big Hole (Sensable, Wisdom) River">Wisdom River</name>) joins 
        <name type="place" key="Beaverhead (Jefferson) River">the Jefferson</name>from the west.
        Between the two junctions is the present town of 
        <name type="place" key="Twin Bridges, Mont.">Twin Bridges</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Madison County, Mont.">Madison County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n18080402" n="2">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>route up the 
        <name type="place" key="Big Hole (Sensable, Wisdom) River">Big Hole (Wisdom)
        River</name>is not marked on 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>map 66. He camped near the 
        <name type="place" key="Madison County, Mont.">Madison</name>-
        <name type="place" key="Beaverhead County, Mont.">Beaverhead</name>county line on the 
        <name type="place" key="Big Hole (Sensable, Wisdom) River">Big Hole River</name>, above
        the mouth of present 
        <name type="place" key="Nez Perce Creek (Beaverhead County, Mont.)">Nez Perce
        Creek</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n18080403" n="3">The 
        <name type="place" key="Ruby (Philanthropy) River">Ruby River</name>has a steep gradient
        and has its source in the mountains. Additionally, it is joined by numerous short
        tributaries that carry rocks down to it during their peak runoff stage. Consequently, like
        most streams in this area, the stream bed is composed principally of rounded stones of
        various sizes.</note>
            <note xml:id="n18080404" n="4">
               <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>camp was in the vicinity of present
        
        <name type="place" key="Silver Star, Mont.">Silver Star</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Madison County, Mont.">Madison County</name>. 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>map 65.</note>
            <note xml:id="n18080405" n="5">In the vicinity of 
        <name type="place" key="Silver Star, Mont.">Silver Star</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Madison County, Mont.">Madison County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n18080406" n="6">Red osier dogwood, 
        <hi rend="italic">Cornus sericea</hi>L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n18080407" n="7">The forks of 
        <name type="place" key="Beaverhead (Jefferson) River">the Jefferson</name>, where 
        <name type="place" key="Ruby (Philanthropy) River">Ruby River</name>(the party's 
        <name type="place" key="Ruby (Philanthropy) River">Philanthropy River</name>) comes from
        the east to join 
        <name type="place" key="Beaverhead (Jefferson) River">the Beaverhead</name>and form 
        <name type="place" key="Beaverhead (Jefferson) River">the Jefferson</name>. They had
        passed the 
        <name type="place" key="Big Hole (Sensable, Wisdom) River">Big Hole (Wisdom) River</name>,
        
        <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass's</name>"north branch," the previous day
        without knowing it.</note>
            <note xml:id="n18080408" n="8">It should be "inst." rather than "ult."</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-08-03" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-08-05" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
