<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.preface.v09">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">Volume 9 Preface</title>
            <title type="sub"/>
            <author>Gary E. Moulton</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               
               
               
               
               
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">John Ordway</name> and <name type="person" key="Floyd, Charles">Charles Floyd</name>
               </title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">vii</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Journal Editorial</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-03-19</date>
            <date/>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>
            <name/>Initial creation Transcribed</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="main">Volume 9 Preface</head>
         <head type="sub"/>
         <div type="preface">
            <p>

This volume and the two to follow rely largely on the editorial work of previous
books in this edition. Therefore, the editorial notes and supporting material in
these three books owe a debt to former consultants and friends of the project. Here
again we extend our great appreciation to the unselfish work of these generous
people.</p>
            <p>
Nevertheless, we have several persons to thank specifically for help with this volume. The journal of <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Sergeant John Ordway</name> is located at the American Philosophical
Society, <name type="place" key="Philadelphia, Pa.">Philadelphia</name>, where the project received the able assistance of Beth <name type="person" key="Cann, E.">Carr</name>oll-Horrocks, Martin L. Levitt, Martha Harrison, Roy E. Goodman, and Edward C. Carter II. At the State Historical Society of Wisconsin, Madison, we were aided with the journal of <name type="person" key="Floyd, Charles">Sergeant Charles Floyd</name> by Josephine L. Harper and Harry Miller. Closer
to home, help came from John R. Wunder, Linda J. Ratcliffe, and Sharon Bays of
the Center for Great Plains Studies, University of Nebraska–Lincoln, and Thomas
W. Dunlay and Doris VanSchooten of the project.</p>
            <p>
Scholars again provided advice in their respective disciplines. BOTANY: A. T. Harrison, Westminster College, Salt Lake City, and Robert B. Kaul, University of Nebraska–Lincoln. ETHNOLOGY: John Ludwickson, Nebraska State Historical Society, Lincoln. LINGUISTICS: American Indian linguistic data in the notes were collected
by Raymond J. DeMallie, Indiana University, and were provided by himself and by
the following persons: <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshone</name>
               </hi>. Wick R. Miller, University of Utah, and Christopher
Loether, Idaho State University. TOOLS: Michael E. Dotson, Brookston, Indiana.</p>
            <p>
The project received financial support from Samuel H. Douglas III (Whittier,
California), Nelson S. Weller (Piedmont, California), the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Trail
Heritage Foundation, and the National Endowment for the Humanities, an independent federal agency.</p>
            <p>
We extend our sincerest appreciation to all these individuals but must ourselves
carry blame for any deficiencies in the present work.
</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
