<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-08-24">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">August 24, 1805</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic
        Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            5</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">July 28–November 1, 1805</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1989</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">158-164</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">209-210</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">132</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jw">Joseph Whitehouse</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            11</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of Joseph Whitehouse, May 14, 1804–April 2,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1997</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">283-284</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
         <geoDecl datum="WGS" xml:id="lc.geo.1805-08-24.01">
            <placeName/>
            <geo>44.3667 -114.2667</geo>
            <note>Clark camped in a different location again from the rest of the group. Camped near Shoup, Lemhi County, ID.</note>
         </geoDecl>
         <geoDecl datum="WGS" xml:id="lc.geo.1805-08-24.02">
            <placeName/>
            <geo>44.7667 -113.1333</geo>
            <note>The group was at Shoshone Cove, Beaverhead County, MT.</note>
         </geoDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journal Entries</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-06-08</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-04-12</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1805-08-24">August 24, 1805</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-08-24.01"
              ref="lc.geo.1805-08-24.02">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Saturday August 24th 1805.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>As the Indians who were on their way down the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>had a number of spare hoses with
          them I thought it probable that I could obtain some of them and therefore desired the
          Cheif to speak to them and inform me whether they would trade.    they gave no
          positive answer but requested to see the goods which I was willing to give in exchange.
          I now produced some battle axes which I had made at 
          <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name>with which they were
          much pleased.    knives also seemed a great demand among them. I soon
          purchased three horses and a mule.    for each horse I gave an ax a knife
          handkercheif and a little paint; &amp; for the mule the addition of a knife a shirt
          handkercheif and a pair of legings; at this price which was quite double that given for
          the horses, the fellow who sold him made a merit of having bestoed me one of his mules.
          I consider this mule a great acquisition. These Indians soon told me that they had no
          more horses for sale and I directed the party to prepare to set out. I had now nine
          horses and a mule, and two which I had hired made twelve these I had loaded and the
          Indian women took the ballance of the baggage. I had given the Interpreter some articles
          with which to purchase a horse for the woman which he had obtained.    at
          twelve Oclock we set out and passed the river below the forks, directing our rout
          towards the cove along the track formerly mentioned.
          <ref target="n21082401" n="1"/>   most of the horses were heavily laden, and
          it appears to me that it will require at least 25 horses to convey our baggage along
          such roads as I expect we shall be obliged to pass in the mountains. I had now the
          inexpressible satisfaction to find myself once more under way with all my baggage and
          party.    an Indian had the politeness to offer me one of his horses to ride
          which I accepted with cheerfullness as it enabled me to attend better to the march of
          the party. I had reached the lower part of the cove when an Indian rode up and informed
          me that one of my men was very sick and unable to come on. I directed the party to halt
          at a small run which falls into the creek on Lard. at the lower part of the Cove and
          rode back about 2 Miles where I found 
          <name type="person" key="Weiser, Peter">Wiser</name>very ill with a fit of the cholic. I
          sent 
          <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Sergt. Ordway</name>who had remained with him for
          some water and gave him a doze of the essence of Peppermint and laudinum
          <ref target="n21082402" n="2"/>which in the course of half an hour so far recovered him
          that he was enabled to ride my horse and I proceeded on foot and rejoined the party.
             the sun was yet an hour high but the Indians who had for some time
          impatiently waited my return at length unloaded and turned out their horses and my party
          had followed there example.    as it was so late and the Indians had prepared
          their camp for the night I thought it best to acquiess and determined also to remain.
          <ref target="n21082403" n="3"/>   we had traveled only about six miles.
             after we encamped we had a slight shower of rain. 
          <name type="person" key="Goodrich, Silas">Goodrich</name>who is our principal fisherman
          caught several fine trout. 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name>came to us late in the
          evening and had not killed anything. I gave the Indians who were absolutely engaged in
          transporting the baggage, a little corn as they had nothing to eat. I told 
          <name type="person" key="Cameahwait">Cameahwait</name>that my stock of provision was too
          small to indulge all his people with provision and recommended it to him to advise such
          as were not assisting us with our baggage to go on to their camp to morrow and wait our
          arrival; which he did accordingly. 
          <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="person" key="Cameahwait">Cameahwait</name>
                  </hi>literally translated is 
          <hi rend="italic">one who never walks.</hi>   he told me that his nation had
          also given him another name by which he was signalized as a warrior which was 
          <name type="person" key="Cameahwait">Too-et'-te-con'-e</name>or 
          <hi rend="italic">black gun.</hi>   these people have many names in the course
          of their lives, particularly if they become distinguished characters.    for
          it seems that every important event by which they happen to distinguish themselves
          intitles them to claim another name which is generally scelected by themselves and
          confirmed by the nation.    those distinguishing acts are the killing and
          scalping an enemy, the killing a white bear, leading a party to war who happen to be
          successfull either in destroying their enemies or robing them of their horses, or
          individually stealing the horses of an enemy.    these are considered acts of
          equal heroism among them, and that of killing an enemy without scalping him is
          considered of no importance; in fact the whole honour seems to be founded in the act of
          scalping, for if a man happens to slay a dozen of his enemies in action and others get
          the scalps or first lay their hand on the dead person the honor is lost to him who
          killed them and devolves on those who scalp or first touch them.
          <ref target="n21082404" n="4"/>Among the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshones</name>, as well as all the
          Indians of America, bravery is esteemed the primary virtue; nor can any one become
          eminent among them who has not at some period of his life given proofs of his possessing
          this virtue.    with them there can be no preferment without some warelike
          achievement, and so completely interwoven is this principle with the earliest Elements
          of thought that it will in my opinion prove a serious obstruction to the restoration of
          a general peace among the nations of the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>.    while at 
          <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name>I was one day
          addressing some cheifs of the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Minetares</name>wo visited us and
          pointing out to them the advantages of a state of peace with their neighbours over that
          of war in which they were engaged.    the Chiefs who had already geathered
          their havest of larals, and having forceably felt in many instances some of those
          inconveniences attending a state of war which I pointed out, readily agreed with me in
          opinion.    a young fellow under the full impression of the Idea I have just
          suggested asked me if they were in a state of peace with all their neighbours what the
          nation would do for Cheifs?, and added that the cheifs were now oald and must shortly
          die and that the nation could not exist without cheifs.    taking as granted
          that there could be no other mode devised for making Cheifs but that which custom had
          established through the medium of warlike acievements.</p>
               <p>The few guns which the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshones</name>have are reserved for
          war almost exclusively and the bow and arrows are used in hunting. I have seen a few
          skins among these people which have almost every appearance of the common sheep.
             they inform me that they finde this animal
          <ref target="n21082405" n="5"/>on the high mountains to the West and S. W. of them.
             it is about the size of the common sheep, the wool is reather shorter and
          more intermixed with long hairs particularly on the upper part of the neck.   
          these skins have been so much woarn that I could not form a just Idea of the animal or
          it's colour.    the Indians however inform me that it is white and that it's
          horns are lunated comprest twisted and bent backward as those of the common sheep.
             the texture of the skin appears to be that of the sheep. I am now perfectly
          convinced that the sheep as well as the Bighorn exist in these mountains. [
          <hi rend="italic">WC?: 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. C</name>Saw one at a distance to
          day—</hi>]</p>
               <p>The usual caparison of the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshone</name>horse is a halter and
          sadle.    the 1st consists either of a round plated or twisted cord of six or
          seven strands of buffaloe's hair, or a throng of raw hide made pliant by pounding and
          rubing.    these cords of bufaloe's hair are about the size of a man's finger
          and remarkably strong.    this is the kind of halter which is prefered by
          them.    the halter of whatever it may be composed is always of great length
          and is never taken from the neck of the horse which they commonly use at any time.
             it is first attatched at one end about the neck of the horse with a knot
          that will not slip, it is then brought down to his under jaw and being passed through
          the mouth imbaces the under jaw and tonge in a simple noose formed by crossing the rope
          inderneath the jaw of the horse.    this when mounted he draws up on the near
          side of the horse's neck and holds in the left hand, suffering it to trail at a great
          distance behind him sometimes the halter is attatched so far from the end that while the
          shorter end serves him to govern his horse, the other trails on the grond as before
          mentioned.    they put their horses to their full speed with those cords
          trailing on the ground.    when they turn out the horse to graze the noose is
          mearly loosed from his mouth.    the saddle is made of wood and covered with
          raw hide which holds the parts very firmly together.    it is made like the
          pack saddles in uce among the French and Spaniards.    it consists of two flat
          thin boards which fit the sides of the horses back, and are held frirm by two peices
          which are united to them behind and before on the outer side and which rise to a
          considerable hight terminating sometimes in flat horizontal points extending outwards,
          and alwas in an accute angle or short bend underneath the upper part of these peices.
             a peice of buffaloe's skin with the hair on, is usually put underneath the
          saddle; and very seldom any covering on the saddle [
          <hi rend="italic">NB: but when they ride they throw on a piece of Skin</hi>].
             stirrups when used are made of wood and covered with leather.   
          these are generally used by the elderly men and women; the young men scarcely ever use
          anything more than a small pad of dressed leather stuffed with hair, which is confined
          with a leather thong passing arond the body of the horse in the manner of a girth.
             they frequently paint their favorite horses, and cut their ears in various
          shapes.    they also decorate their mains and tails, which they never draw or
          trim, with the feathers of birds, and sometimes suspend at the breast of the horse the
          finest ornaments they possess.    the Spanish bridle is prefered by them when
          they can obtain them, but they never dispence with the cord about the neck of the horse,
          which serves them to take him with more ease when he is runing at large. They are
          excellent horsemen and extreemly expert in casting the cord about the neck of a horse. [
          <hi rend="italic">NB: Make a noose &amp; catch him running &amp;c</hi>] the horses that
          have been habituated to be taken with the cord in this way, however wild they may appear
          at first, surrender the moment they feel the cord about their necks.—    There
          are no horses in this quarter which can with propriety be termed wild.   
          there are some few which have been left by the indians at large for so great a length of
          time that they have become shye, but they all shew marks of having been in possession of
          man.    such is that one which 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name>saw just below the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Three Forks of the">three forks of the
          Missouri</name>, and one other which I saw on the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>below the entrance of the 
          <name type="place" key="Musselshell (Mah-tush,-ah-zhah, Shell) River">Mussle shell
          river</name>.—    
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name>set out very early this
          morning on his return, he traveled down the creek to it's entrance by the same Indian
          track he had ascended it; at the river he marked his name on a pine tree, then ascended
          to the bottom above the second creek, and brekfasted on burries, which occupyed them
          about one hour.    he now retraced his former track and joined the party where
          he had left them at 4 P. M.    on his way 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. C.</name>fell from a rock and injured one
          of his legs very much.    the party during his absence had killed a few
          pheasants and caught a few small fish on which together with haws and Serviceburies they
          had subsisted.    they had also killed one cock of the Mountains 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name>now wrote me a discription of
          the river and country, and stated our prospects by this rout as they have been
          heretofore mentioned [
          <hi rend="italic">WC?: related the information of his guide &amp; recomeds to me to
          purchase horses &amp;c</hi>] and dispatched 
          <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name>on horseback with orders to loose no
          time reaching me.    he set out late with the party continued his rout about
          two miles and encamped.
          <ref target="n21082406" n="6"/>
                  <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt Clark</name>had seen some trees which
          would make small canoes but all of them some distance below the Indian Caps which he
          passed at the entrance of 
          <name type="place" key="Fish Creek (Idaho County, Idaho)">fish Creek</name>. [
          <hi rend="italic">WC?: he had learned from his guid that he had been on a river to the
          N. where he Saw people from the other Side the mountain and there was a road, he route
          he shewed in the Sand which gave me hope of finding a route across the m. in that
          direction</hi>]</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-08-24.02"
              ref="lc.geo.1805-08-24.01">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">August 24th Satturday 1805</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>Set out verry early this morning on my return passed down the 
          <name type="place" key="Indian (Berry) Creek (Idaho)">[
          <hi rend="italic">EC: Berry</hi>] Creek</name>at the mouth marked my name on a pine
          Tree, proceed on to the bottom above the Creek &amp; Brackfast on buries &amp; delayed 1
          hour, then proceed on up the river by the Same rout we decended to the place I left my
          party where we arrived at 4 oClock, (I Sliped &amp; bruised my leg verry much on a rock)
             the party had killed Several phesents and Cought a fiew Small fish on which
          they had Subsisted in my absence. also a heath hen, near the Size of a Small turkey.</p>
               <p>I wrote a letter to 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt Lewis</name>informing him of the
          prospects before us and information recved of my guide which I thought favourable
          &amp;c. &amp; Stating two plans 〈for〉 one of which for us to pursue &amp;c. and
          despatched one man &amp; horse and directed the party to get ready to march back, every
          man appeared disheartened from the prospects of the river, and nothing to eate, I Set
          out late and Camped 2 miles above, nothing to eate but Choke Cherries &amp; red haws
          <ref target="n21082407" n="7"/>which act indifferent ways So as to make us Sick, dew
          verry heavy, my beding wet    in passing around a rock the horses were obliged
          to go deep into the water.</p>
               <p>The plan I stated to 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt Lewis</name>if he agrees with me we
          shall adopt is to procure as many horses (one for each man) if possible and to hire my
          present guide who I sent on to him to interegate thro' the Intprtr. and proceed on by
          land to Some navagable part of the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">
                     <hi rend="italic">Columbia</hi>River</name>, or to the 
          <hi rend="italic">Ocean,</hi>depending on what provisions we can procure by the gun aded
          to the Small Stock we have on hand depending on our horses as the last resort.</p>
               <p>a second plan to divide the party one part to attempt this deficuet river with what
          provisions we had, and the remaindr to pass by Land on hose back Depending on our gun
          &amp;c for Provisions &amp;c. and come together occasionally on the river.</p>
               <p>〈a third to [send?] one party to attempt to pass the mountain by horses, &amp; the
          other to return to the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>Collect provisions &amp; go up 
          <name type="place" key="Sun (Mah-pah-pah,-ah-zhah, Medicine) River">Medison rivr</name>〉
          the 1s of which I would be most pleased with &amp;c.
          <ref target="n21082408" n="8"/>
               </p>
               <p>I saw Several trees which would make Small Canoes and by putting 2 together would
          make a Siseable one, all below the last Indian Camp Several miles</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-08-24.03"
              ref="lc.geo.1805-08-24.02">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Saturday 24th August 1805</hi>.    a clear cool morning.
             we find that the band of the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Snake nation</name>who came here
          yesterday are going down on the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missourie</name>after the buffaloe and offers
          Some of their horses for Sale So we delay this morning in order to purchase Some from
          them.    we got three or 4 more horses &amp; hired two and loaded all our
          horses 12 in nomber.    then the Squaws took on their horses the remainder of
          our baggage    we had abt. 20 horses loaded with baggage and Set out about 12
          oClock on our journey to cross the dividing mountains.    we went about 3
          miles up the valley.    one of the men 
          <name type="person" key="Weiser, Peter">P. Wiser</name>was taken of a Sudden with the
          collick and ditained us So that we got only about 5 miles this afternoon and Camped at
          the creek on the edge of a large Smooth plain.
          <ref target="n21082409" n="9"/>   we had a Small Shower of rain   
          one of the men caught Several large Trout    one of the hunters came to camp
             had killd. nothing.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-08-24.04"
              ref="lc.geo.1805-08-24.02">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Saturday 24th.</hi>   We had a pleasant morning and some of
          the men went out to hunt. The river at this place is so confined by the mountains that
          it is not more than 20 yards wide, and very rapid. The mountains on the sides are not
          less than 1000 feet high and very steep. There are a few pines growing on them. We
          caught some small fish to day, and our hunters killed 5 prairie fowls. These were all we
          had to subsist on. At 1 o'clock 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain Clarke</name>and his party returned,
          after having been down the river about 12 miles.
          <ref target="n21082410" n="10"/>They found it was not possible to go down either by
          land or water, without much risk and trouble. The water is so rapid and the bed of the
          river so rocky, that going by water appeared impracticable; and the mountains so
          amazingly high, steep and rocky, that it seemed impossible to go along the river by
          land. Our guide speaks of a way to sea, by going up the south fork of this river,
          <ref target="n21082411" n="11"/>getting on to the mountains that way, and then turning
          to the south west again. 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain Clarke</name>therefore wrote a letter
          to 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Lewis</name>, and dispatched a man
          on horseback to meet him; and we all turned back up the river again, poor and
          uncomfortable enough, as we had nothing to eat, and there is no game. We proceeded up
          about 3 miles, and supperless went to rest for the night.
          <ref target="n21082412" n="12"/>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-08-24.05"
              ref="lc.geo.1805-08-24.02">
            <sp who="jw">
               <speaker>Whitehouse</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Saturday 24th August 1805</hi>.    a clear cool morning.
             we find that the band of the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Snake</name>nation who came here
          yesterday is going down on the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missourie</name>after the buffaloe, and offers
          Some of their horses for Sale.    So we Detain this morning in order to
          purchase Some of them.    we got 3 or 4 more horses and hired 2 and loaded all
          our horses which was abt. 12 in nomber    then the Squaws took the remainder
          of our baggage and we then Set out about 12 oC. on our way to cross the divideing ridge.
             proceeded on abt. 3 miles    one of the men
          <ref target="n21082413" n="13"/>was taken Sick with the collick, and detained us So
          that we came only about 6 miles and Camped on the creek.
          <ref target="n21082414" n="14"/>   one of the hunters came to us had killed
          nothing    we gave the Indians Some corn, as they had nothing to eat.</p>
               <p>Saturday August 24th    This morning we had Clear, cold weather, The 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Snake</name>band of Indians, that came
          to our Camp Yesterday, informed our Officer, that they intend going down the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Mesouri River</name>, to hunt buffalo, and offer
          some of their horses for sale.    
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Lewis</name>delayed for a while, in
          Order to try &amp; purchase some of their horses from them.    he succeeded in
          his expectation &amp; purchased 4 〈more〉 horses, &amp; hired from those Indians 2 more,
          which is intended to be packed with our baggage.—    We packed all our horses,
          being 12 in number, &amp; what baggage remain'd, the Indian Squaws carried for us—
             We set out about 12 o'Clock A. M. on our way, to cross the dividing ridge
          of mountains, &amp; proceeded on about 3 Miles.    One of our party was here
          taking very Ill of the Cholic, which detained us some Considerable time, we proceeded on
          our way, and went only 3 Miles further, and encamped at a Creek, having only came 6
          Miles this day.    One of our hunters came to us here, he having met with
          nothing to kill.—    We gave the Indians some Corn, to eat, they having no
          Provisions with them.—</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n21082401" n="1">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>party crossed 
        <name type="place" key="Beaverhead (Jefferson) River">the Beaverhead</name>and went up 
        <name type="place" key="Horse Prairie Creek (West Fork Jefferson River)">Horse Prairie
        Creek</name>into 
        <name type="place" key="Shoshone Cove">Shoshone Cove</name>. His route appears as a dotted
        line on 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>maps 66–67 and his campsites are marked.</note>
            <note xml:id="n21082402" n="2">The essential oil of peppermint was used as a digestive
        stimulant and as a carminative, that is, to expel gas from the alimentary canal. Laudanum
        is a tincture of opium.</note>
            <note xml:id="n21082403" n="3">The campsite, marked by a faint symbol on 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>map 67, is a few miles east of 
        <name type="place" key="Grant, Mont.">Grant</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Beaverhead County, Mont.">Beaverhead County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n21082404" n="4">Among the plains tribes, to be first to touch an enemy was
        considered the bravest of war deeds. Whites called this practice "counting coup," from the
        French word for "blow" or "strike." The 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshones</name>, being strongly
        influenced by plains culture, had adopted the custom. Hodge, 1:354.</note>
            <note xml:id="n21082405" n="5">The first notice in the journals of the mountain goat, 
        <hi rend="italic">Oreamnos americanus,</hi>then unknown to science. 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>were never to see one alive and at
        close range. Cutright (LCPN), 192. It was probably 
        <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>who drew a red vertical line
        through this passage.</note>
            <note xml:id="n21082406" n="6">Not marked on 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>map 67, the site would be approximately two miles up the 
        <name type="place"
                     key="Salmon (Lewis's, Main Fork Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">
        Salmon</name>(northeast) from the place 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>left the eight men on his route
        downstream, in 
        <name type="place" key="Lemhi County, Idaho">Lemhi County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>, a few miles southwest of present 
        <name type="place" key="North Fork Salmon River (Fish Creek)">North Fork</name>and the
        mouth of the 
        <name type="place" key="North Fork Salmon River (Fish Creek)">North Fork Salmon
        River</name>. On 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>map 67, at the mouth of present 
        <name type="place" key="Indian (Berry) Creek (Idaho)">Indian (Berry) Creek</name>, 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>has written, "Pin[e] marked W. C.,"
        indicating where he marked his name or initials.</note>
            <note xml:id="n21082407" n="7">Columbia hawthorn, 
        <hi rend="italic">Crataegus columbiana</hi>How., is the only species of native,
        red-fruited hawthorn west of the 
        <name type="place" key="Continental Divide">Continental Divide</name>. Hitchcock et al.,
        3:101; Booth &amp; Wright, 111.</note>
            <note xml:id="n21082408" n="8">Having returned from the unsatisfactory reconnaissance of
        the 
        <name type="place"
                     key="Salmon (Lewis's, Main Fork Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">
        Salmon River</name>, 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>here thought out on paper the
        possible methods of crossing the mountains. The first and favored proposal, for hiring 
        <name type="person" key="Old Toby">Old Toby</name>as a guide and crossing the 
        <name type="place" key="Lolo Trail">Lolo Trail</name>on horseback, was the one the
        captains adopted. The second involved sending part of the party down the 
        <name type="place"
                     key="Salmon (Lewis's, Main Fork Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">
        Salmon</name>by canoe while the remainder traveled by horseback and attempted to stay in
        touch with the river party; 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>had already gained enough knowledge
        of the difficulties of the country to rule this course out. The third appears to be a
        considerably modified version of the first, prompted by the concern over the scanty
        sources of food in the mountains. One party would have gone down the 
        <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">Bitterroot
        River</name>toward the 
        <name type="place" key="Lolo Trail">Lolo Trail</name>while the other would have returned
        down the 
        <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>to the buffalo range near the 
        <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Great Falls of the">Great Falls</name>to "collect
        provisions"—probably by jerking meat—and then gone up the 
        <name type="place" key="Sun (Mah-pah-pah,-ah-zhah, Medicine) River">Sun (Medicine)
        River</name>to seek a way to rejoin the others. They had not known of the 
        <name type="place" key="Sun (Mah-pah-pah,-ah-zhah, Medicine) River">Sun River</name>route,
        which 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>would follow on the return trip in
        1806, until they discussed the geography of the region with the 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshones</name>. Having set this last
        plan down on paper, 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>obviously found it unacceptable,
        probably because of the cost in time and the wide separation of the two parties, and
        crossed it out. The suggestions do indicate 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>soundness of judgment and
        understanding of the problems the Corps of Discovery faced.</note>
            <note xml:id="n21082409" n="9">The party crossed the 
        <name type="place" key="Beaverhead (Jefferson) River">Beaverhead River</name>and went up 
        <name type="place" key="Horse Prairie Creek (West Fork Jefferson River)">Horse Prairie
        Creek</name>along 
        <name type="place" key="Shoshone Cove">Shoshone Cove</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Beaverhead County, Mont.">Beaverhead County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n21082410" n="10">On August 23 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>reached a point perhaps three miles
        above 
        <name type="place" key="Shoup, Idaho">Shoup</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Lemhi County, Idaho">Lemhi County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>. See the captains' descriptions for that
        date.</note>
            <note xml:id="n21082411" n="11">This could refer to the 
        <name type="place"
                     key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Snake
        River</name>, into which the 
        <name type="place"
                     key="Salmon (Lewis's, Main Fork Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">
        Salmon</name>flows. However, 
        <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name>may mean the 
        <name type="place" key="North Fork Salmon River (Fish Creek)">North Fork Salmon
        River</name>, up which the party did indeed travel to reach the 
        <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">Bitterroot</name>valley in 
        <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>, and then travel southwest on the 
        <name type="place" key="Lolo Trail">Lolo Trail</name>to the 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>country on the 
        <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Clearwater
        River</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n21082412" n="12">About two or three miles up the 
        <name type="place"
                     key="Salmon (Lewis's, Main Fork Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">
        Salmon</name>(northeast) from the spot where 
        <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name>had remained with the enlisted men, in 
        <name type="place" key="Lemhi County, Idaho">Lemhi County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>, a few miles southwest of 
        <name type="place" key="North Fork Salmon River (Fish Creek)">North Fork</name>and the
        mouth of the 
        <name type="place" key="North Fork Salmon River (Fish Creek)">North Fork Salmon
        River</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n21082413" n="13">
               <name type="person" key="Weiser, Peter">Peter Weiser</name>, according to 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n21082414" n="14">The party crossed 
        <name type="place" key="Beaverhead (Jefferson) River">Beaverhead River</name>and followed 
        <name type="place" key="Horse Prairie Creek (West Fork Jefferson River)">Horse Prairie
        Creek</name>upstream along 
        <name type="place" key="Shoshone Cove">Shoshone Cove</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Beaverhead County, Mont.">Beaverhead County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-08-23" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-08-25" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
