<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-06-01">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">June 1, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic
        Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            7</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">March 23–June 9, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1991</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">322-325</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">318</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">234-235</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc/>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-10-26</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-04-12</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1806-06-01">June 1, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-06-01.01" ref="">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Sunday June 1st 1806.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>Yesterday evening 
          <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbono</name>an 
          <name type="person" key="Lepage, Jean Baptiste">LaPage</name>returned, having made a
          broken voyage.    they ascended the river on this side nearly opposite to a
          village eight miles above us,
          <ref target="n35060101" n="1"/>here their led horse which had on him their merchandize,
          feell into the river from the side of a steep clift and swam over; they saw an indian on
          the opposite side whom they prevailed on to drive their horse back again to them; in
          swiming the river the horse lost a dressed Elkskin of 
          <name type="person" key="Lepage, Jean Baptiste">LaPages</name>and several small
          articles, &amp; their paint was destroyed by the water.    here they remained
          and dryed their articles the evening of the 30th Ult.    the indians at the
          village learning their errand and not having a canoe, made an attempt esterday morning
          to pass the river to them on a raft with a parsel of roots and bread in order to trade
          with them; the indian raft struck a rock, upset and lost thir cargo; the river having
          fallen heir to both merchandize and roots, our traders returned with empty bags. This
          morning 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name>accompanyed by 
          <name type="place" key="Hohots Ilppilp">Hohâst-illpilp</name>set out in surch of two
          tomahawks of ours which we have understood were in the possession of certain indians
          residing at a distance in the plains on the South side of the 
          <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Kooskoske</name>; the
          one is a tomahawk which 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. C.</name>
                  <ref target="n35060102" n="2"/>left at our camp on 
          <name type="place" key="Big Canyon (Mosquito) Creek">Musquetoe Creek</name>
                  <ref target="n35060103" n="3"/>and the other was stolen from us while we lay at the
          forks of this and the 
          <name type="place" key="North Fork Clearwater (Chopunnish) River">
          Chopunnish</name>rivers last fall. 
          <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Willard, Alexander">Willard</name>set out this morning on a
          hunting excurtion towards the 
          <name type="place" key="Packer Meadows (Quawmash Glades)">quamash grounds</name>beyond 
          <name type="place" key="Lolo (Collins's) Creek (Idaho)">Collins's Creek</name>.
             we begin to feel some anxiety with rispect to 
          <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Sergt. Ordway</name>and party who were sent to 
          <name type="place"
                        key="Salmon (Lewis's, Main Fork Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">
          Lewis's river</name>for salmon; we have received no inteligence of them since they set
          out.    we desired 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name>to make some enquiry after
          the 
          <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">Twisted hair</name>;</hi>the old
          man has not been as good as his word with rispect to encamping near us, and we fear we
          shall be at a loss to procure from T
          <name type="place" key="Travelers' Rest (Idaho)">raveller's rest</name>to the waters of
          the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>.—    I met with a
          singular plant today in blume of which I preserved a specemine;
          <ref target="n35060104" n="4"/>it grows on the steep sides of the fertile hills near
          this place, the radix is fibrous, not much branched, annual, woody, white and nearly
          smooth.    the stem is simple branching ascending, 2½ feet high celindric,
          villose and of a pale red colour.    the branches are but few and those near
          it's upper extremity.    the extremities of the branches are flexable and are
          bent down near their extremities with the weight of the flowers.    the leaf
          is sissile, scattered thinly, nearly linear tho' somewhat widest in the middle, two
          inches in length absolutely entire, villose, obtusely pointed and of an ordinary green.
             above each leaf a small short branch protrudes, supporting a tissue of four
          or five smaller leaves of the same apeparance with those discribed.    a leaf
          is placed underneath eah branch, and each flower.    the calyx is a one
          flowered spathe.    the corolla superior consists of four pale perple petals
          which are tripartite, the central lobe largest and all terminate obtusely; they are
          inserted with a long and narrow claw on the top of the germ, are long, smooth, &amp;
          deciduous.    there are two distinct sets of stamens the 1st or principal
          consist of four, the filaments of which are capillary, erect, inserted on the top of the
          germ alternately with the petals, equal short, membranous; the anthers are also four
          each being elivated with it's fillament, they are linear and reather flat, erect
          sessile, cohering at the base, membranous, longitudinally furrowed, twise as long as the
          fillament 〈and〉 naked, and of a pale perple colour.    the second set of
          stamens are very minute are also four and placed within and opposite to the petals,
          these are scarcely persceptable while the 1st are large and conspicuous; the filaments
          are capillary equal, very short, white and smooth.    the anthers are four,
          oblong, beaked, erect, cohering at the base, membranous, shorter than the fillaments,
          white naked and appear not to form pollen.    there is one pistillum; the germ
          of which is also one, cilindric, villous, inferior, sessile, as long as the 1st stamens,
          and marked with 8 longitudinal furrows.    the single style and stigma form a
          perfect monapetallous corolla only with this difference, that the style which elivates
          the stigma or limb is not a tube but solid tho' it's outer appearance is that of the
          tube of a monopetallous corolla swelling as it ascends and gliding in such manner into
          the limb that it cannot be said where the style ends, or the stigma begins; jointly they
          are as long as the corolla, white, the limb is four cleft, sauser shaped, and the
          margins of the lobes entire and rounded.    this has the appearance of a
          monopetallous flower growing from the center of a four petalled corollar, which is
          rendered more conspicuous in consequence of the 1st being white and the latter of a pale
          perple. I regret very much that the seed of this plant are not yet ripe and it is proble
          will not be so during my residence in this neighbourhood.—</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-06-01.02" ref="">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Sunday June 1st 1806.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>Late last evening 
          <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Shabono</name>&amp; 
          <name type="person" key="Lepage, Jean Baptiste">Lapage</name>returnd. haveing made a
          broken voyage.    they assended the river on this Side nearly opposit to the
          Village Eight miles above us, here their led horse who had on him their Stock of
          Merchindize fell into the river from the Side of a Steep Clift and swam over, they Saw
          an indian on the opposit side whome they provailed on to drive their horse back again to
          them; in swiming the horse lost a dressed Elk skin of 
          <name type="person" key="Lepage, Jean Baptiste">LaPages</name>and Several small
          articles, and their paint was distroyed by the water.    here they remained
          and dryed their articles the evening of the 30th ulto: the indians at the village
          learned their errand and not haveing a canoe, made an attempt Yesterday morning made an
          attempt to pass the river to them on a raft with a parcel of roots and bread in order to
          trade with them; the indian raft Struck a rock upset and lost their Cargo; the river
          haveing Swallowed both Merchindize &amp; roots, our traders returned with empty bags.
          This morning 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Geo: Drewyer</name>accompanied by 
          <name type="person" key="Hohots Ilppilp">Hohastillpilp</name>Set out in Serch of two
          tomahawks of ours which we have understood were in the possession of certain indians
          resideing at a distance in the Plains on the South Side of 
          <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Flat Head
          river</name>; one is a pipe tomahawk which 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt L.</name>left at our Camp on 
          <name type="place" key="Big Canyon (Mosquito) Creek">Musquetor Creek</name>and the other
          was stolen from me whilst we lay at the forks of this and 
          <name type="place" key="North Fork Clearwater (Chopunnish) River">
          Chopunnish</name>rivers last fall. 
          <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Willard, Alexander">Willard</name>Set out this morning on a
          hunting excurtion towards the 
          <name type="place" key="Weippe Prairie (Camas Flats, Quawmash Flats)">quawmash
          grounds</name>beyond 
          <name type="place" key="Lolo (Collins's) Creek (Idaho)">Colins creek</name>.
             we begin to feel Some anxiety with respect to 
          <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Sergt. Ordway</name>and party who were Sent to 
          <name type="place"
                        key="Salmon (Lewis's, Main Fork Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">
          Lewis's river</name>for salmon; we have receved no intilligence of them Sence they Set
          out.    we desired 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name>to make Some enquiry after
          the 
          <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">Twisted hair</name>;</hi>the old
          man has not been as good as his word with respect to encamping near us, and we fear we
          Shall be at a loss to procure guides to conduct us by the different routs we wish to
          pursue from 
          <name type="place" key="Travelers' Rest (Idaho)">Travillers rest</name>to the waters of
          the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>.—.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-06-01.03" ref="">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Sunday 1st day of June 1806</hi>.    we Set out eairly
             a young man went and put us on the road which he said was a near way &amp;
          a good road    we wrode thro the timbred country    struck the head
          of a creek
          <ref target="n35060105" n="5"/>in the plain    followed down Said creek
             passd. one lodge about noon the road left the creek and kept thro the high
          plain    a good road.    towards evening we came down the river
          hills to a large village above the forks on 
          <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">kooskooskee
          river</name>.
          <ref target="n35060106" n="6"/>   we halted a Short time to let our horses
          feed a little and git something to eat ourselves.    bought considerable uppah
          and couse from the natives and proceeded on to another village down the river near the
          forks.    night came on and we Camped
          <ref target="n35060107" n="7"/>here at the chiefs lodge that gave us so many horses
             they appeared verry friendly to us and gave us a large cake of uppah
             their is a vast site of excellent horses Scattered along this river which
          they offer to Sell for a Squaw axe pr peace &amp; 2 or 3 for a gun &amp; a little
          ammunt</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-06-01.04" ref="">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Sunday 1st June, 1806.</hi>   We had a fine morning after
          some light showers of rain during the night.— Since last evening the river rose eighteen
          inches. Two hunters
          <ref target="n35060108" n="8"/>went out this morning, and some of the natives came to
          see us. The sick Indian is getting much better. The officers got some bear-skins from
          the Indians, that are almost as white as a blanket.
          <ref target="n35060109" n="9"/>They say, that the bears from which they get these skins
          are a harmless kind, and not so bold and ferocious as the grizly and brown bear.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n35060101" n="1">Opposite 
        <name type="place" key="Kooskia, Idaho">Kooskia</name>in 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho County, Idaho">Idaho County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>. According to ethnographic investigations,
        this village was formerly located on both sides of the 
        <name type="place" key="Middle Fork Clearwater River">Middle Fork Clearwater</name>and
        known as 
        <hi rend="italic">tuke?ywewi.,</hi>which refers to the mouth of the 
        <name type="place" key="South Fork Clearwater River">South Fork</name>where it meets the 
        <name type="place" key="Middle Fork Clearwater River">Middle Fork</name>at this point.
        Abandoned house pits were photographed on the north side of the river in the 1890s; more
        recent archaeological investigations indicate that this village was occupied from 700
        years ago to the historic period. The portion of the village on the south side of the
        river was destroyed by construction of a lumber mill in the early twentieth century.
        Sappington &amp; Carley (AECR), 8, 11–14; Sappington &amp; Carley (AIK). A red vertical
        line begins at the start of this sentence and with others continues to "sauser shaped,"
        perhaps drawn by 
        <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n35060102" n="2">
               <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>says, "
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. L.</name>"</note>
            <note xml:id="n35060103" n="3">
               <name type="place" key="Big Canyon (Mosquito) Creek">Big Canyon, or Canyon, Creek</name>,
        in 
        <name type="place" key="Nez Perce County, Idaho">Nez Perce County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>; see 
        <ref n="1806-05-07" type="related">May 7, 1806</ref>. 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>map 72.</note>
            <note xml:id="n35060104" n="4">Ragged robin, see 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>entry of 
        <ref n="1806-05-29" type="related">May 29, 1806</ref>, presumably copied from
        here.</note>
            <note xml:id="n35060105" n="5">This could be any of a number of creeks in the area,
        perhaps 
        <name type="place" key="Deep Creek">Deep Creek</name>, the dividing line between 
        <name type="place" key="Lewis County, Idaho">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho County, Idaho">Idaho</name>counties, 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n35060106" n="6">To reach the 
        <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Clearwater (Kooskooske)
        River</name>Peebles has the men go nearly directly east to the 
        <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Clearwater River</name>,
        reaching it near 
        <name type="place" key="Kooskia, Idaho">Kooskia</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho County, Idaho">Idaho County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>. Wells has them proceed eastward, passing near
        
        <name type="place" key="Keuterville, Idaho">Keuterville</name>and 
        <name type="place" key="Cottonwood, Idaho">Cottonwood</name>in 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho County, Idaho">Idaho County</name>, then reach the 
        <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Clearwater</name>near 
        <name type="place" key="Stites, Idaho">Stites</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho County, Idaho">Idaho County</name>, south of 
        <name type="place" key="Kooskia, Idaho">Kooskia</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n35060107" n="7">Apparently the village of 
        <name type="person" key="Hohots Ilppilp">Hohots Ilppilp</name>, which 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>estimated to be six miles below 
        <name type="place" key="Camp Chopunnish (Idaho)">Camp Chopunnish</name>on the 
        <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Clearwater River</name>.
        See 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>entry of 
        <ref n="1806-05-10" type="related">May 10, 1806</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n35060108" n="8">
               <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Willard, Alexander">Willard</name>, say the captains.</note>
            <note xml:id="n35060109" n="9">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>discuss the characteristics of the
        bears and bearskins at some length on 
        <ref n="1806-05-31" type="related">May 31</ref>. 
        <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name>seems to have become confused, however;
        the white skins are from grizzly bears, while the relatively gentle bears are the
        "cinnamon" bears, a reddish-brown color phase of the black bear.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-05-31-1" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-06-02" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
