<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-01-22">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
January 22, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               
               
               
               
               
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml" n="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc" n="Clark, William">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 6</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">November 2, 1805–March 22, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1990</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">227-230</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo" n="Ordway, John">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf" n="Floyd, Charles">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">268</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jw" n="Whitehouse, Joseph">Joseph Whitehouse</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 11</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of Joseph Whitehouse, May 14, 1804–April 2, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1997</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">414</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
         <geoDecl datum="WGS" xml:id="lc.geo.1806-01-22.01">
            <placeName/>
            <geo>45.9833 -123.9167</geo>
            <note>Clark and his party return to the Fort Clatsop camp, Clatsop County, OR. Remained here until 03-23-1806.</note>
         </geoDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Journal Entries</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-08-16</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1806-01-22">January 22, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-01-22.01" n="lc.geo.1806-01-22.01">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Thursday</hi> [<hi rend="italic">NB: Wednesday</hi>]
<hi rend="italic">January 22nd 1806.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
The party<ref target="n28012201" n="1"/> sent for the meat this morning returned with it in the Evening; it was in very inferior order, in short the animals were poor. <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">Reubin Fields</name> also remained with the other hunters <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Labiche, François">Labuish</name> our late supply of salt is out.    we have not yet heared a sentence from the other two parties of hunter's<ref target="n28012202" n="2"/> who are below us towards <name type="place" key="Point Adams">Point Adams</name> and the Praries.</p>
               <p>
There are three speies of fern in this neighbourhood the root<ref target="n28012203" n="3"/> one of which the natves eat; this grows very abundant in the open uplands and praries where the latter are not sandy and consist of deep loose rich black lome.<ref target="n28012204" n="4"/>    the root is horizontal sometimes a little deverging or obliquely descending, frequently dividing itself as it proceded into two equal branches and shooting up a number of stems; it lies about 4 Inces beneath the surface of the earth.    the root is celindric, with few or no radicles and from the size of a goose quill to that of a man's finger; the center of the root is divided into two equal parts by a strong flat &amp; white ligament like a piece of thin tape    on either side of this there is a white substance which when the root is roasted in the embers is much like wheat dough and not very unlike it in flavour, though it has also a pungency which becomes more visible after you have chewed it some little time; this pungency was disagreeable to me, but the naives eat it very voraciously and I have no doubt but it is a very nutricious food.    the bark of the root is black, somewhat rough, thin and brittle, it easily seperates in flakes from the part which is eaten as dose also the internal liggament.    this root perennil. in rich lands this plant rises to the hight of from 4 to five feet.    the stem is smooth celindric, slightly groved on one side erect about half it's hight on the 2 first branches thence reclining backwards from the grooved side; it puts forth it's branches which are in reallyty long footstalks by pares from one side only and near the edges of the groove, these larger footstalks are also grooved cilindric and gradually tapering towards the extremity, puting forth alternate footstalks on either side of the grove near it's edge; these lesser footstalks the same in form as the first put forth from forty to fifty alternate pinate leaves which are sessile, horizontal, multipartite for half their length from the point of insertion and terminating in a long shaped apex, and are also revolute with the upper disk smoth and the lower slightly cottanny.    these alternate leaves after proceeding half the length of the footstalk cease to be partite and assume the tongue like form altogether.    this plant produces no flower or fruit whatever, is of a fine green colour in summar and a beautifull plant.    the top is annual and is of course dead at present.—
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-01-22.02" n="lc.geo.1806-01-22.01">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Friday</hi> [<hi rend="italic">EC: Wednes</hi>] <hi rend="italic">22nd January 1806</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
The party Sent for the meat this morning returned with it in the evening;    it was in verry inferior order, in Short the animals were pore. <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">Rieuben Field</name>
                  <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name> and <name type="person" key="Labiche, François">Labiech</name> remained in the woods to hunt.    our late Supply of Salt is out.    we have not heard a word of the other hunters who are below us towards <name type="place" key="Point Adams">point adams</name> and the Praries. Some rain this day at intervales—</p>
               <p>
there are three Species of fern in this neighbourhood the root one of which the nativs eate; that of which the nativs eate produce no flowers whatever or fruit of a fine green Colour and the top is annual, and in Course dead at present.<ref target="n28012205" n="5"/>
               </p>
               <p>
I observe no difference between the licorice<ref target="n28012206" n="6"/> of this Countrey and that Common to maney parts of the United States where it is sometimes Cultivated in our gardins—.    this plant delights in a deep lose Sandy Soil; here it grows verry abundant and large; the nativs roste it in the embers and pound it Slightly with a Small Stick in order to make it Seperate more readily from the Strong liggaments which forms the center of the root; this they discard and chew and Swallow the ballance of the root; this last is filled with a number of thin membrencies like network, too tough to be masticated and which I find it necessary also to discard. This root when roasted possesses an agreeable flavour not unlike the Sweet potato. The root of the thistle (described yesterday) after undergoing the process of Sweting or bakeing in a <hi rend="italic">kiln</hi> is Sometimes eaten with the train oil also, at other times pounded fine and mixed with Cold water, untill reduced to the Consistancy of Gruel; in this way I think it verry agreeable.    but the most valuable of all their roots is foreign to this neighbourhood I mean the <hi rend="italic">Wappetoe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
The <hi rend="italic">Wappetoe,</hi> or bulb of the Sagitifolia or common arrow head, which grows in great abundance in the marshey grounds of that butifull and fertile vally on the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> commenceing just above the <name type="place" key="Sandy (Quicksand) River">quick Sand River</name> and extending downwards for about 70 miles.    this <hi rend="italic">bulb</hi> forms a principal article of trafic between the inhabitents of the vally and those of their neighbourhood or Sea coast.

</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-01-22.03" n="lc.geo.1806-01-22.01">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Wednesday 22nd    I and 14 more of the party went with one canoe after the Elk meat.    a hard Storm of rain and verry high wind.    we had a disagreeable time of it.    three of the hunters<ref target="n28012207" n="7"/> Stayed out to hunt.


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-01-22.04" n="lc.geo.1806-01-22.01">
            <sp who="jw">
               <speaker>Whitehouse</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Wednesday Janry 22nd    A hard storm of Wind &amp; Rain    14 of our party &amp; myself went with a Canoe after the Elk meat, &amp; had a very disagreeable time of it.    Three of our hunters<ref target="n28012208" n="8"/> staid out hunting all this day.—


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n28012201" n="1">
               <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Sergeant Ordway</name> says he was with this party.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28012202" n="2">Apparently <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name> and <name type="person" key="Willard, Alexander">Willard</name> made up one of these parties. <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name> and <name type="person" key="Lepage, Jean Baptiste">Lepage</name> the other. See below, <ref n="lc.jrn.1806-01-24" type="related">January 24, 1806</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28012203" n="3">Western bracken fern.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28012204" n="4">Quaternary terrace deposits of sand and gravel underlie much of the <name type="place" key="Lewis and Clark (Fort, Netul) River">Lewis and Clark River</name> valley. Away from the river bluffs these deposits are commonly overlain by terrace deposits consisting mainly of silt and clay.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28012205" n="5">In the next two paragraphs red vertical lines cross out portions of the botanical descriptions, perhaps done by <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28012206" n="6">
               <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> is here borowing from <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> entry of <ref n="lc.jrn.1806-01-24" type="related">January 24</ref> and describing the sea-shore lupine. By the liquorice of the country he means the wild liquorice, <hi rend="italic">Glycyrrhiza lepidota</hi> (Nutt.) Pursh (as noted on <ref n="lc.jrn.1805-05-08" type="related">May 8, 1805</ref>), and in comparison to the cultivated liquorice, <hi rend="italic">G. glabra</hi> L. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> is mistaken in the lupine being large; it is actually a prostrate plant. He may have been seeing only the root at this point with additional information coming from the natives. Cutright (LCPN), 265, discusses the question of identifying the plant. See also the entries of <ref n="lc.jrn.1805-11-17" type="related">November 17</ref> and <ref n="lc.jrn.1805-12-27" type="related">December 27, 1805</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28012207" n="7">
               <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">Reubin Field</name>, <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name>, and <name type="person" key="Labiche, François">Labiche</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28012208" n="8">
               <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">Reubin Field</name>, <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name>, and <name type="person" key="Labiche, François">Labiche</name>.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-01-21" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-01-23" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
