<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-03-11">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">March 11, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic
        Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            6</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">November 2, 1805–March 22, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1990</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">401-406</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">276</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">197</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jw">Joseph Whitehouse</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            11</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of Joseph Whitehouse, May 14, 1804–April 2,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1997</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">427</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Journal Entries</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-09-01</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-04-12</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1806-03-11">March 11, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-03-11.01" ref="">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Tuesday March 11th 1806.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>Early this morning 
          <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Sergt. Pryor</name>arrived with a small
          canoe loaded with fish which he had obtained from the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Cathlamet Indians">Cathlahmah's</name>for a very small
          part of the articles he had taken with him.    the wind had prevented his
          going to the fisery on the opposite side of the river above the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Wahkiakum Indians">Wackiacums</name>, and also as we had
          suspected, prevented his return as early as he would otherwise have been back.— The dogs
          at the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Cathlamet Indians">Cathlahmahs</name>had bitten the
          trong assunder which confined his canoe and she had gone a drift.    he
          borrowed a canoe from the Indians in which he has returned.    he found his
          canoe on the way and secured her, untill we return the Indians their canoe, when she can
          be brought back. Sent Sergt. 
          <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name>and a party in surch of a canoe which
          was reported to have been sunk in a small creek on the opposite side of the 
          <name type="place" key="Lewis and Clark (Fort, Netul) River">Netul</name>a few miles
          below us, where she had been left by 
          <name type="person" key="Shields, John">Shields</name>
                  <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">R. Fields</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">Frazier</name>when they were lately sent out to
          hunt over the 
          <name type="place" key="Lewis and Clark (Fort, Netul) River">Netul</name>. They returned
          and reported that they could not find the canoe she had broken the cord by which she was
          attatched, and had been carried off by the tide. 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name>
                  <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Joseph Fields</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">Frazier</name>set out by light this morning to
          pass the bay in order to hunt as they had been directed the last evening.   
          we once more live in 
          <hi rend="italic">clover;</hi>Anchovies fresh Sturgeon and Wappetoe.    the
          latter 
          <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Sergt. Pryor</name>had also procured and
          brought with him. The reptiles of this country are the rattlesnake garter snake and the
          common brown Lizzard. The season was so far advanced when we arrived on this side of the
          
          <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">rocky mountain</name>s that but few
          rattlesnakes were seen I did not remark one particularly myself, nor do I know whether
          they are of either of the four speceis found in the different parts of the United
          States, or of that species before mentioned peculiar to the upper parts of the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>and it's branches. The garter
          snake
          <ref target="n28031101" n="1"/>so called in the United states is very common in this
          country; they are found in great numbers on the open and sometimes marshey grounds in
          this neighbourhood.    they differ not at all from those of the U' States.
             the black or dark brown lizzard
          <ref target="n28031102" n="2"/>we saw at the 
          <name type="place" key="Fort Rock Camp (Oreg.)">rock fort Camp</name>at the commencement
          of the woody country
          <ref target="n28031103" n="3"/>below the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">great
          narrows</name>and 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Great Falls of the">falls of the
          Columbia</name>; they are also the same with those of the United States. The snail
          <ref target="n28031104" n="4"/>is numerous in the woody country on this coast; they are
          in shape like those of the United States, but are at least five times their bulk. There
          is a speceis of water lizzard
          <ref target="n28031105" n="5"/>of which I saw one only just above the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Cascades (Great Rapids, Great Shute)">grand
          rapids of the Columbia</name>.    it is about 9 inches long the body is
          reather flat and about the size of a mans finger covered with a soft skin of a dark
          brown colour with an uneven surface covered with little pimples the neck and head are
          short, the latter terminating in an accute angular point and flat.    the fore
          feet each four toes, the hinder ones five unconnected with a web and destitute of
          tallons.    it's tail was reather longer than the body and in form like that
          of the Musk-rat, first rising in an arch higher than the back and decending lower than
          the body at the extremity, and flated perpendicularly.    the belley and under
          part of the neck and head were of a brick red every other part of the colour of the
          upper part of the body a dark brown.    the mouth was smooth, without
          teeth.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-03-11.02" ref="">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Tuesday March 11th 1806</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>Early this morning 
          <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Sergt. Pryor</name>arrived with a Small
          Canoe loaded with fish which he had obtained from the 
          <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Cathlamet Indians">Cath-lah-mah's</name>
                  </hi>for a very Small part of the articles he had taken with him.    the wind
          had prevented his going to the fishery on the opposit Side of the river above the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Wahkiakum Indians">Waukie-cum's</name>, and also as we
          had suspected, prevented his return as early as he otherwise would have been back. The
          dogs of the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Cathlamet Indians">Cathlahmah's</name>had bitten the
          throng assunder which confined his canoe and she had gorn adrift.    he
          borrowed a Canoe from the Indians in which he has returned.    he found his
          canoe on the way and Secured her, untill we return the Indians their Canoe—Sent Sergt. 
          <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name>and a party in Serch of one of our
          Canoes which was reported to have been lost from a hunting party of Shields 
          <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">R. Field</name>&amp; 
          <name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">Frazier</name>when they were last out on the
          opposit Side of the 
          <name type="place" key="Lewis and Clark (Fort, Netul) River">Netul</name>.   
          they returned and reported that they Could not find the Canoe which had broken the Cord
          with which it was attached, and was caried off by the tide. 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name>
                  <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Jo. Field</name>&amp; 
          <name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">Frazier</name>Set out by light this morning to
          pass the bay in order to hunt as they had been directed last evening.    we
          once more live in 
          <hi rend="italic">Clover;</hi>Anchovies fresh Sturgeon and Wappatoe.    the
          latter 
          <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Sergt. Pryor</name>had also procured a
          fiew and brought with him. The Deer of this Coust differ from the Common Deer, fallow
          Deer or Mule Deer as has beformentioned.</p>
               <p>The 
          <hi rend="italic">Mule Deer</hi>
                  <ref target="n28031106" n="6"/>we have never found except in rough Country; they prefer
          the Open Grounds and are Seldom found in the wood lands near the river; when they are
          met with in the wood lands or river bottoms and pursued, they imediately run to the
          hills or open country as the Elk do, the Contrary happens with the common Deer.
             there are Several differences between the mule and common deer as well as
          in form as in habits.    they are fully a third larger in general, and the
          male is particularly large; think there is Somewhat greater disparity of Size between
          the Male and Female of this Species than there is between the male and female fallow
          Deer; I am Convinced I have Seen a Buck of this Species twice the volume a Buck of the
          Common Deer.    the Ears are peculiarly large, I measured those of a large
          Buck 〈of this Species〉 which I found to be 
          <hi rend="italic">eleven</hi>inches long and 3½ in width at the widest part; they are
          not so delicately formed, their hair in winter is thicker longer and of a much darker
          grey, in Summer the hair is Still coarser longer and of a paler red, more like that of
          the Elk; in winter they also have a Considerable quantity of very fine wool intermixed
          with the hair and lying next to the Skin as the Antelope has.    the long hair
          which grows on the outer Side of the first joint of the hind legs, and which in the
          Common Deer do not usially occupy more than 2 inches in them occupy from 6 to 8; their
          horns also differ, those in the Common deer consist of two main beams gradually
          deminishing as the points proceed from it, with the mule deer the horns consist of two
          beams which at the distance of 4 or 6 inches from the head divide themselves into two
          equal branches which again either divide into two other equal branches or terminate in a
          Smaller, and two equal ones; haveing either 2, 4 or 6 points on a beam; the horn is not
          so rough about the base as the common deer, and are invariably of a much darker Colour.
          the most Strikeing differance of all, is the white rump and tail.    from the
          root of the tail as a center there is a circular Spot perfectly white of about 3½ inches
          radius, which occupy a part of the rump and the extremities of buttocks and joins the
          white of the belley underneath; the tail which is usially from 8 to 9 inches long for
          the first 4 or 5 inches from its upper extremity is covered with Short white hairs, much
          Shorter indeed than those hairs of the body; from hence for about one inch further, the
          hair is Still white but gradually becoms longer; the tail then termonates in a tissue of
          Black hair of about 3 inches long.    from this black hair of the tail they
          have obtained among the French engages the appelation of the 
          <hi rend="italic">black tailed Deer</hi>, but this I conceive by no means Characteristic
          of the Animal as much the larger portion of the tail is white.    the Ears and
          the tail of this Animale when Compared with those of the Common Deer, So well Comported
          with those of the 
          <hi rend="italic">Mule</hi>when compared with the Horse, that we have by way of
          distinction adapted the appellation of the mule Deer
          <ref target="n28031107" n="7"/>which I think much more appropriate.    on the
          inner corner of each eye there is a drane (like the Elk) or large recepticle which Seams
          to Answer as a drane to the eye which givs it the appearance of weeping, this in the
          Common Deer of the Atlantic States is scercely proceptable but becoms more Conspicious
          in the fallow Deer, and Still more So in the Elk; this recepticle in the Elk is larger
          than any of the Pecora order
          <ref target="n28031108" n="8"/>with which I am acquainted.</p>
               <p>I have Some reasons to believe that the Calumet Eagle
          <ref target="n28031109" n="9"/>is Sometimes found on this Side of the 
          <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky mountains</name>from the information of
          the Indians in whose possession I have Seen their plumage.    those are the
          Same with those of the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, and are the most butifull of
          all the family of the Eagle of America it's colours are black and white with which it is
          butifully varigated.    the feathers of the tail which is so highly prized by
          the Indians is composed of twelve broad feathers of equal length those are white except
          about two inches at the extremity which is of a jut black.    their wings have
          each a large circular white Spot in the middle when extended.    the body is
          variously marked with white and black.    the form is much that of the Common
          bald Eagle, but they are reather Smaller and much more fleet.    this Eagle is
          feared by all carnivarous birds, and on his approach all leave the carcase instantly on
          which they were feeding.    it breads in the inaccessable parts of the
          Mountains where it Spends the Summer, and decends to the plains and low country in the
          fall and winter when it is usially Sought and taken by the nativs.    two
          tails of this bird is esteemed by 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>, 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Minnetares</name>, 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Ricaras</name>, &amp;c. as the full
          value of a good horse, or Gun and accoutrements.    with the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Osage Indians">Osage</name>&amp; 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Kansa Indians">Kanzas</name>and those nations enhabiting
          Countrys where this bird is more rare, the price is even double of that mentioned.
             with these feathers the nativs deckerate the Stems of their Sacred pipes or
          
          <name type="native_nation" key="Calumet Indians">Calumets</name>; whence the name of
          Calumet Eagle, which has Generally obtained among the Engages. The 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Ricaras</name>have domesticated this
          bird in many instances for the purpose of obtaining its plumage.    the nativs
          in every part of the Continent who can precure those feathers attach them to their own
          hair and the mains and tail of their favorite horses by way of orniment.   
          they also deckerate their own caps or bonnets with those feathers.
          <ref target="n28031110" n="10"/>The Leather winged bat is found &amp;c.
          <ref target="n28031111" n="11"/>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-03-11.03" ref="">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>Tuesday 11th March 1806.    a little Snow fell last night.    the
          morning three hunters
          <ref target="n28031112" n="12"/>went out a hunting. 
          <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Sergt. Pryor</name>returned with a
          considerable quantity of Small fish and Sturgeon and a fiew wa-pa-toes &amp;C—
             4 men
          <ref target="n28031113" n="13"/>went to look for the lost canoe but could not find
          it.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-03-11.04" ref="">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Tuesday 11th.</hi>   The weather was nearly the same as
          yesterday. Three men went across the bay in a canoe to hunt. Two hunters came in but had
          killed nothing. At noon, our fishermen
          <ref target="n28031114" n="14"/>returned, with some ulken and sturgeon. The morning of
          the 12th was pleasant; but towards the evening the day became cloudy. Another hunter
          went out.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-03-11.05" ref="">
            <sp who="jw">
               <speaker>Whitehouse</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>Monday March 11th    We had during last night some Snow &amp; this morning
          we have fair Weather.    
          <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Serjeant Pryor</name>&amp; the two Men
          that went out with him returned with the Canoe to the fort.    They had wish
          them some Sturgeon &amp; a considerable quantity of small fish.    they also
          brought some Wa- pa-to or bread Root &amp;ca.    Three of our Men went out
          hunting.    four of our Men went also, to look for the lost Canoe.
             these four Men returned but had not found it.—</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n28031101" n="1">Perhaps 
        <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">the Pacific</name>red-sided garter snake; see
        below, 
        <ref n="1806-03-28" type="related">March 28</ref>and 
        <ref n="1806-03-29" type="related">29</ref>, 1806. Two red vertical lines go through the
        material about reptiles and garter snake, perhaps 
        <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle's</name>work.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28031102" n="2">Perhaps the western fence lizard, 
        <hi rend="italic">Sceloporus occidentalis.</hi>Benson (HLCE), 89; Cutright (LCPN), 288,
        428–29.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28031103" n="3">At 
        <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The
        Dalles</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Wasco County, Oreg.">Wasco County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>; see above, 
        <ref n="1805-10-25" type="related">October 25, 1805</ref>. 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>map 78.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28031104" n="4">Perhaps 
        <hi rend="italic">Monadenia fidelis,</hi>but more likely 
        <hi rend="italic">Allogona townsendiana.</hi>Cf. Coues (HLC), 3:898 n. 104.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28031105" n="5">The rough-skinned newt, 
        <hi rend="italic">Taricha granulosa.</hi>Benson (HLCE), 87. Cf. Burroughs, 280–81;
        Cutright (LCPN), 244, 429.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28031106" n="6">Columbian black-tailed deer. The "common deer" is 
        <hi rend="italic">Odocoileus virginianus,</hi>the white-tailed deer.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28031107" n="7">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>devised what remains the common name
        for this species; see above, 
        <ref n="1805-05-10" type="related">May 10, 1805</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28031108" n="8">Equivalent to present order 
        <hi rend="italic">Artiodactyla</hi>and suborder 
        <hi rend="italic">Ruminantia,</hi>including elk, deer, and moose.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28031109" n="9">Golden eagle.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28031110" n="10">Coues points out some inaccuracies in his description; see
        Coues (HLC), 3:878–79 n. 82.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28031111" n="11">See 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>entry for 
        <ref n="1806-03-12" type="related">March 12, 1806</ref>, below, for the full
        sentence.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28031112" n="12">According to the captains, 
        <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name>, 
        <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Joseph Field</name>, and 
        <name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">Frazer</name>went across 
        <name type="place" key="Youngs (Meriwether's) Bay">Youngs Bay</name>to hunt east of 
        <name type="place" key="Youngs (Kilhow-a-nah-kle) River">Youngs River</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28031113" n="13">Led by 
        <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name>, say the captains.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28031114" n="14">Led by 
        <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Pryor</name>.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-03-10" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-03-12" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
