<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-03-14">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
March 14, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               
               
               
               
               
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 6</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">November 2, 1805–March 22, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1990</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">414-416</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">277</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">198</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jw">Joseph Whitehouse</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 11</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of Joseph Whitehouse, May 14, 1804–April 2, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1997</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">428</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Journal Entries</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-09-01</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1806-03-14">March 14, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-03-14.01" n="">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Friday March 14th 1806.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
This morning we sent a party after the two Elk which <name type="person" key="Collins, John">Collins</name> killed last evening, they returned with them about noon. <name type="person" key="Collins, John">Collins</name>, <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Jos. Feilds</name> and <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name> went in quest of the flock of Elk of which <name type="person" key="Collins, John">Collins</name> had killed those two.    this evening we heared upwards of twenty shot, and expect that they have fallen in with and killed a number of them. <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">Reubin Fields</name> and <name type="person" key="Thompson, John B.">Thompson</name> returned this evening unsuccessfull having killed one brant only.    late in the evening <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name> arrived with a party of the <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsops</name> who brought an indifferent canoe some hats and roots for sale. the hats and roots we purchased, but could not obtain the canoe without giving more than our stock of merchandize would lisence us. I offered him my laced uniform coat but he would not exchange.<ref target="n28031401" n="1"/> The Salmon Trout are seldom more than two feet in length they are narrow in proportion to their length, at least much more so than the Salmon or red charr.    the jaws are nearly of the same length, and are furnished with a single series of small subulate streight teeth, not so long or as large as those of the Salmon.    the mouth is wide, and the tongue is also furnished with some teeth.    the fins are placed much like those of the salmon.    at the <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Great Falls of the">great falls</name> we met with this fish of a silvery white colour on the belley and sides, and a bluish light brown on the back and head. in this neighbourhood we have met with another speceis which dose not differ from the other in any particular except in point of colour.    this last is of a dark colour on the back, and it's sides and belley are yellow with transverse stripes of dark brown.    sometimes a little red is intermixed with these colours on the belley and sides towards the head.    the eye, flesh, and roes are like those discribed of the Salmon.    the white speceis which we found below the falls was in excellent order when the salmon were entirely out of season and not fit for uce.    the speceis which we found here on our arrival early in November had declined considerably, reather more so inded than the red Charr with which we found them ascociated in the little rivulets and creeks. I think it may be safely asserted that the red Charr and both speceis of the salmmon trout remain in season longer in the fall of the year than the common Salmon; but I have my doubts whether either of them ever pass the <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Great Falls of the">great falls of the Columbia</name>. The Indians tell us that the Salmon begin to run early in the next month; it will be unfortunate for us if they do not, for they must form our principal dependence for food in ascending the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>, above <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Great Falls of the">the falls</name> and it's <name type="place"
                        key="Salmon (Lewis's, Main Fork Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">S. E. branch</name> to the mountains. The mountain or speckled trout are found in the waters of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> within the mountains.    they are the same of those found in the upper part of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, but are not so abundant in the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> as on that river.    we never saw this fish below the mountains but from the transparency and coldness of the <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Kooskooske</name> I should not doubt it's existing in that stream as low as it's junction with the <name type="place"
                        key="Salmon (Lewis's, Main Fork Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">S E. branch of the Columbia</name>.— The <hi rend="italic">bottle nose</hi> is the same with that before mentioned on the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> and is found exclusiely within the mountains.
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-03-14.02" n="">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Friday March 14th 1806</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
This morning we dispatched a party after two Elk which <name type="person" key="Collins, John">Collins</name> killed last evening, they returned with them about noon. <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Jos: Field</name>, <name type="person" key="Collins, John">Collins</name>, <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Go: Shannon</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Labiche, François">Labiesh</name> went in quest of the Gang of Elk out of which <name type="person" key="Collins, John">Collins</name> had killed the 2 yesterday.    this evening we herd upwards of twenty Shot and expect they have fallen in with and killed Several of them. <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">Reuben Field</name> and <name type="person" key="Thompson, John B.">Thompson</name> returned this evening unsuksessfull haveing killed only one Brant.    late in the evening Geo: <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name> arrived with a party of the <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsops</name> who brought an indifferent Canoe, three hats and Some roots for Sale    we could not purchase the Canoe without giveing more than our Stock of merchandize would lisence us. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt Lewis</name> offered his laced uniform Coat for a verry indiferent Canoe, agreeable to their usial way of tradeing his price was double.    we are informed by the <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsops</name> that they have latterly Seen an Indian from the <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Makah Indians">Quin-na-chart</name>
                  </hi> Nation<ref target="n28031402" n="2"/> who reside Six days march to the N. W and that four vessels were there and the owners <name type="person" key="Hill, Samuel">Mr. Haley</name>, <name type="person" key="Moore, Hugh">Moore</name>, <name type="person" key="Callamon">Callamon</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Swepeton">Swipeton</name> were tradeing with that noumerous nation, whale bone Oile and Skins of various discription.

</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-03-14.03" n="">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Friday 14th March 1806. Cloudy.    four men went out a hunting and 7 of the party went for the Elk meat.    they soon returned with the meat of 2 doe Elk.    in the afternoon <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name> returnd. and a number of the <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clotsop Indians</name> came with him    brought a canoe to trade to us &amp; some Hats &amp;C.—

</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-03-14.04" n="">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Friday 14th.</hi>    We had a fine morning; and four hunters set out early. I went with a party and brought in the meat of the 2 elk which were killed last evening. Two hunters,<ref target="n28031403" n="3"/> who had gone out yesterday morning returned very much fatigued, and had killed nothing but a goose and a raven which they ate last night. While out to day I saw a number of musquitoes flying about. I also saw a great quanity of sheep-sorrel<ref target="n28031404" n="4"/> growing in the woods of a very large size.


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-03-14.05" n="">
            <sp who="jw">
               <speaker>Whitehouse</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Friday March 14th    This morning was Cloudy.    Seven of our party<ref target="n28031405" n="5"/> went in 2 Canoes across the River, in order to bring the Elk meat to the fort, And four of our Men went out to hunt, The party that went for the Elk meat soon returned with it to the fort.    In the afternoon, the Man<ref target="n28031406" n="6"/> that went to the <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsop</name> Village Yesterday; returned; with several <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsop Indians</name> to the fort.    these Indians brought a Canoe with them to trade with us.—



</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n28031401" n="1">The next few lines have a red vertical line through them, perhaps <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle's</name> work.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28031402" n="2">The <name type="native_nation" key="Makah Indians">Makah</name> people lived in the area of <name type="place" key="Cape Flattery">Cape Flattery</name>, <name type="place" key="Clallam County, Wash.">Clallam County</name>, <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>, at the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Strait of Juan de Fuca">Strait of Juan de Fuca</name>, where their reservation is now located. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> name comes from their self designation in <name type="native_nation" key="Makah Indians">Makah</name>, <hi rend="italic">q<hi rend="superscript">w</hi>idičča<hi rend="superscript">⊃</hi>a·tx̣,</hi> "people of the cape" (referring to <name type="place" key="Cape Flattery">Cape Flattery</name>). They belonged to the Nootka branch of the Wakashan language stock, and were the only <name type="native_nation" key="Wakashan Indians">Wakashans</name> in the present United States. Their culture was like that of the <name type="native_nation" key="Nootka Indians">Nootka</name>, including the hunting of whales. Hodge, 1:791–92; Spier, 28; Swanton, 427–28. For <name type="person" key="Hill, Samuel">Haley</name>, <name type="person" key="Moore, Hugh">Moore</name>, <name type="person" key="Callamon">Callamon</name>, and <name type="person" key="Swepeton">Swipeton</name>, see above, <ref n="1805-11-06" type="related">November 6, 1805</ref>, <ref n="1806-01-01" type="related">January 1</ref>, <ref n="1806-02-13" type="related">February 13, 1806</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28031403" n="3">
               <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">Reubin Field</name> and <name type="person" key="Thompson, John B.">Thompson</name>, who, according to the captains on <ref n="1806-03-13" type="related">March 13</ref>, left on the twelfth, not the thirteenth as <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name> indicates.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28031404" n="4">
               <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name> was acquainted with the introduced European species, garden sorrel, <hi rend="italic">Rumex acetosa</hi> L. Here he may be seeing either western dock, <hi rend="italic">R. occidentalis</hi> Wats., or seaside dock, <hi rend="italic">R. maritimus</hi> L. Hitchcock et al., <hi rend="italic">Vascular Plants of the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name> Northwest,</hi> 2:169, 171, 173, 175, 177.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28031405" n="5">Led by <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name>, as he says.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28031406" n="6">
               <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name>.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-03-13" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-03-15" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
