<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-03-25">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
March 25, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               
               
               
               
               
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml" n="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc" n="Clark, William">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 7</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">March 23–June 9, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1991</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">11-15</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo" n="Ordway, John">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf" n="Floyd, Charles">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">281</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg" n="Gass, Patrick">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">201-202</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jw" n="Whitehouse, Joseph">Joseph Whitehouse</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 11</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of Joseph Whitehouse, May 14, 1804–April 2, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1997</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">433-434</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
         <geoDecl datum="WGS" xml:id="lc.geo.1806-03-25.01">
            <placeName/>
            <geo>46 -123.0167</geo>
            <note>Campled below the mouth of the Clatskanie River, opposite Cape Horn, Columbia County, OR.</note>
         </geoDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Journal Entries</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-09-24</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1806-03-25">March 25, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-03-25.01" n="lc.geo.1806-03-25.01">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Tuesday March 25th 1806.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
The morning being disagreeably cold we remained and took breakfast.    at 7 A. M. we set out and continued our rout along the South Coast of the river against the wind and a strong current, our progress was of course but slow.    at noon we halted and dined.    here some <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsops</name> came to us in a canoe loaded with dryed anchovies, which they call Olthen', Wappetoe and Sturgeon.<ref target="n31032501" n="1"/>    they informed us that they had been up on a trading voyage to the <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skillutes</name>.—<ref target="n31032502" n="2"/> I observe that the green bryer<ref target="n31032503" n="3"/> which I have previously mentioned as being common on this river below tide water retains it's leaves all winter.—    the red willow<ref target="n31032504" n="4"/> and seven bark<ref target="n31032505" n="5"/> begin to pur fourth their leaves.—    after dinner we passed the river to a large Island<ref target="n31032506" n="6"/> 2 and continued our rout allong the side of the same about a mile when we arrived at a <name type="native_nation" key="Cathlamet Indians">Cathlahmah</name> fishing cam of one lodge; here we found 3 men 2 women and a couple of boys, who from appearances had remained here some time for the purpose of taking sturgeon, which they do by trolling.    they had ten or douzen very fine sturgeon which had not been long taken.<ref target="n31032507" n="7"/>    we offered to purchase some of their fish but they asked us such an extravegant price that we declined purchase.    one of the men purchased a sea Otterskin at this lodge, for which he gave a dressed Elkskin and an handkercheif.    near this lodge we met some <name type="native_nation" key="Cathlamet Indians">Cathlahmahs</name> who had been up the river on a fishing excurtion.    they had a good stock of fish on board, but did not seem disposed to sell them.    we remained at this place about half an hour and then continued our rout up the Island to it's head and passed to the south side.    the wind in the evening was very hard.    it was with some difficulty that we could find a spot proper for an encampment, the shore being a swamp for several miles back; at length late in the evening opposite to the place we had encamped on the 6th of November last; we found the entrance of a small creek which afforded us a safe harbour from the wind and encamped.<ref target="n31032508" n="8"/>    the ground was low and moist tho' we obtained a tolerable encampment.    here we found another party of <name type="native_nation" key="Cathlamet Indians">Cathlahmahs</name> about 10 in number who had established a temperary residence for the purpose of fishing and taking seal.    they had taken a fine parcel of sturgeon and some seal.    they gave us some of the fleese of the seal which I found a great improvement to the poor Elk.    here we found <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name> and the <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph and Reubin">Feildses</name> who had been seperated from us since morning; they had passed on the North side of the large Island which was much nearer.    the bottom lands are covered with cottonwood, the growth with a broad leaf which resembles ash except the leaf.<ref target="n31032509" n="9"/>    the underbrush red willow, broad leafed willow,<ref target="n31032510" n="10"/> sevenbark, goosburry,<ref target="n31032511" n="11"/> green bryer &amp; the larged leafed thorn;<ref target="n31032512" n="12"/> the latter is now in bloom; the natives inform us that it bears a freut about an inch in diameter which is good to eat.—
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-03-25.02" n="lc.geo.1806-03-25.01">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Tuesday 25th of March 1806</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
Last night and this morning are cool wend hard a head and tide going out, after an early brackfast we proceeded on about 4 miles and came too on the south side to worm and dry our Selves a little. Soon after we had landed two Indians Came from a <name type="native_nation" key="Wahkiakum Indians">War kia cum</name> village on the opposite Side with 2 dogs and a fiew Wappato to Sell neither of which we bought. Som <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsops</name> passed down in a Canoe loaded with fish and Wappato.    as the wind was hard a head and tide against us we Concluded to delay untill the return of the tide which we expected at 1 oClock, at which hour we Set out    met two Canoes of <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsops</name> loaded with dried anchovies and Sturgion which they had taken and purchased above    we crossed over to an Island on which was a <name type="native_nation" key="Cathlamet Indians">Cath lahmah</name> fishing Camp of one Lodge; here we found 〈one〉 3 man two woman and a couple of boys who must have for Some time for the purpose of taking Sturgeon which they do by trolling.    they had 10 or 12 very fine Sturgeon which had not been long taken; we wished to purchase some of their fish but they asked Such extravegent prices that we declined purchaseing.    one of our Party purchased a Sea otter Skin at this Lodge for which he gave a dressed Elk Skin &amp; a Handkerchief.    we remained at this place about half an hour and then Continued our rout.    the winds in the evening was verry hard, it was with Some dificuelty that we Could find a Spot proper for an encampment, the Shore being a Swamp for Several miles back; at length late in the evening opposit to the place we had encamped on the 6th of Novr. last; we fouond the enterance of a Small Creek which offered us a Safe harbour from the Winds and Encamped.    the Ground was low and moist tho' we obtained a tolerable encampment.    here we found another party of <name type="native_nation" key="Cathlamet Indians">Cathlahmahs</name> about 10 in number, who had established a temporary residence for the purpose of fishing and takeing Seal.    they had taken about 12 Sturgeon and Some Seal.    they gave us Some of the flesh of the Seal which I found a great improvement to the poor Elk.    here we found <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name> and the <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph and Reubin">2 Fields'</name> who had been Seperated from us Since Morning; they had passed on the North Side of the large Island which was much nearest.    the bottom lands are Covered with a Species of Arspine, the Growth with a broad leaf which resembles ash except the leaf.    the under brush red willow, broad leafed Willow, Seven bark, Goose berry, Green bryor, and the larged leaf thorn; the latter is Now in blume, the nativs inform us that it bears a 〈leaf〉 fruit about an Inch in diamieter which is a good to eate.    the red willow and 7 bark begin to put foth their leaves. The green bryor which I have before mentioned retains leaves all winter.    made 15 Miles.

</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-03-25.03" n="lc.geo.1806-03-25.01">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Tuesday 25th of March 1806.    we met a canoe of the <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsops</name> going down with their canoe loaded with fish and wa pa toes.    the winds hard a head and tide against us So we delayd untill 1 oClock P. M. at which time we set out    met 2 canoes of the <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clotsops</name> loaded with dried fish and wa pa toes &amp;C &amp; Sturgeon which they had purchased above.    we crossed over to an Island<ref target="n31032513" n="13"/> on which was a fishing Camp of the <name type="native_nation" key="Cathlamet Indians">Cath le mahs</name>.    they had a vast Site of Sturgeon    one of the men purchased a Sea otter Skin, the price of which was a dressed Elk Skin and a Silk hankerchief.    we proceeded on from thence    the after part of the day the wind rose high    after dark we arived at another fishing Camp of the <name type="native_nation" key="Cathlamet Indians">Cath le mahs</name> where we Camped<ref target="n31032514" n="14"/> for
the night.


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-03-25.04" n="lc.geo.1806-03-25.01">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Tuesday 25th.</hi>    We set out after breakfast and had a fair morning; proceeded on to 12 o'clock, when we again halted, the wind and tide being both against us. When the tide began to rise we went on again, saw some of the natives<ref target="n31032515" n="15"/> in canoes descending the river, and in the afternoon passed an Indian lodge,<ref target="n31032516" n="16"/> where one of the men purchased an otter skin.— At this time the wind rose and blew very hard accompanied with rain; notwithstanding we proceeded on till night, when we came to the mouth of a small creek,<ref target="n31032517" n="17"/> which formed a good harbour for our canoes. Here we found several of the natives<ref target="n31032518" n="18"/> encamped and catching sturgeon, of which they had taken 14 large ones.


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-03-25.05" n="lc.geo.1806-03-25.01">
            <sp who="jw">
               <speaker>Whitehouse</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Tuesday March 25th    This morning early a Canoe with some of the Natives of the <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsop Tribe</name> came to where our Canoes lay, their Canoe was loaded with fish &amp; Wapatoes roots.    the wind &amp; tide being against us, We had to delay at our encampment, until 1 o'clock P. M. at which time we proceeded on our voyage, and met two Canoes with Indians, who were descending the River.    We continued on, &amp; crossed over to an Island, on which we found a fishing Camp of the <name type="native_nation" key="Cathlamet Indians">Cath-le-mah</name> Indians, These Indians had a great number of Sturgeon laying tied at the Edge of the water, which were fastened to Stakes drove into the ground.    One of our party purchased a Sea otter Skin from these Natives.    the price he gave for it was a dressed Elk skin, &amp; an old silk handkerchief.    We proceeded on.    the remainder of the day proved Stormy.    we continued on till after dark, &amp; came to another Indian fishing Camp, laying on the South side of the River; where we encamped for the night


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n31032501" n="1">"Ol-then'," is Chinookan <hi rend="italic">ú-<seg n="uluslash">l\</seg>
                  <seg n="uxu803">x̣</seg>an,</hi> "dried eulachon." The "anchovies" are actually eulachon, or candle fish, <hi rend="italic">Thaleichthys pacificus.</hi> See <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> description at <ref n="1806-02-24" type="related">February 24, 1806</ref>. The sturgeon may be the white sturgeon, <hi rend="italic">Acipenser transmontanus.</hi> Lee et al., 42, 126. The <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsops</name> are discussed at <ref n="1805-11-21" type="related">November 21, 1805</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31032502" n="2">"<name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skillutes</name>" is probably from the Chinookan form <hi rend="italic">s(i)<seg n="uku787">k̓</seg>lútk,</hi> "look (at him)!" and not a tribal designation. See <ref n="1805-11-24" type="related">November 24, 1805</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31032503" n="3">Probably Pacific blackberry, <hi rend="italic">Rubus ursinus</hi> Cham. &amp; Schlecht. See <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> description at <ref n="1806-02-13" type="related">February 13, 1806</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31032504" n="4">Red osier dogwood, <hi rend="italic">Cornus sericea</hi> L. (or <hi rend="italic">C. stolonifera</hi> Michx.). Hitchcock et al., 3:588–90.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31032505" n="5">Ninebark, <hi rend="italic">Physocarpus capitatus</hi> (Pursh) Kuntze. See <ref n="1805-12-01" type="related">December 1, 1805</ref>. Hitchcock et al., 3:125–26.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31032506" n="6">The later <name type="place" key="Puget (Sea Otter, Sturgeon) Island">Puget Island</name>, in <name type="place" key="Wahkiakum County, Wash.">Wahkiakum County</name>, <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>, perhaps "[Sea] otter Isd." on <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 81; see <ref n="1805-11-06" type="related">November 6, 1805</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31032507" n="7">A vertical line runs through several lines to this point, perhaps done by <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31032508" n="8">In <name type="place" key="Columbia County, Oreg.">Columbia County</name>, <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>, below one of the mouths of the <name type="place" key="Clatskanie River">Clatskanie River</name>, opposite the point called <name type="place" key="Cape Horn">Cape Horn</name> on the <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name> shore. The exact position relates to identifying "Sturgeon Isd." on <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 81 as modern <name type="place" key="Wallace Island">Wallace Island</name>; see <ref n="1805-11-06" type="related">November 6, 1805</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31032509" n="9">The cottonwood is black cottonwood, <hi rend="italic">Populus trichocarpa</hi> T. &amp; G. Curiously, in <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> entry for this day he calls it a "Species of Arspine [aspen]." The tree which resembles an ash is bigleaf maple, <hi rend="italic">Acer macrophyllum</hi> Pursh. The confusion between the Oregon ash, <hi rend="italic">Fraxinus latifolia</hi> Benth., and the bigleaf maple is clarified at <ref n="1806-02-10" type="related">February 10, 1806</ref>. See also <ref n="1805-11-04" type="related">November 4, 1805</ref>. Little (CIH), 153-W, 95-W; Franklin &amp; Dyrness, 72.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31032510" n="10">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> is probably here using the term broad-leaved willow species with wide leaves, including the area's abundant peach-leaved willow, <hi rend="italic">Salix amygdaloides</hi> Anderss., also Pacific willow, <hi rend="italic">S. lasiandra</hi> Benth., yellow willow, <hi rend="italic">S. lutea</hi> Nutt., and perhaps northwest willow, <hi rend="italic">S. sessilifolia</hi> Nutt. The broad-leaved willow of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri River</name>, however, was either peach-leaved willow or diamond willow, <hi rend="italic">S. rigida</hi> Muhl. Little (MWH), 173-W, 180; Franklin &amp; Dryness, 125.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31032511" n="11">Possibly canyon gooseberry, <hi rend="italic">Ribes menziesii</hi> Pursh, or more probably straggly gooseberry, <hi rend="italic">R. divaricatum</hi> Dougl., which is found at lower levels on the west side of <name type="place" key="Cascade Range">the Cascades</name> and up the <name type="place" key="Columbia Gorge">Columbia Gorge</name> to <name type="place" key="Klickitat County, Wash.">Klickitat County</name>, <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>. Both were new to science, while the former was a plant collected by the party. Hitchcock et al., 3:71–73, 78–79; Cutright (LCPN), 289–90, 373, 417.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31032512" n="12">The "thorn" is likely salmonberry, <hi rend="italic">Rubus spectabilis</hi> Pursh, as indicated by fruit size and flowering time. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> collected the type specimen two days later near the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Cowlitz (Coweliskee) River">Cowlitz River</name>. However, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> may have been seeing some other species of <hi rend="italic">Rubus</hi> this day. See also <ref n="1805-12-01" type="related">December 1, 1805</ref>, and <ref n="1806-04-08" type="related">April 8, 1806</ref>. Hitchcock et al., 3:182; Cutright (LCPN), 278, 289–90, 418.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31032513" n="13">
               <name type="place" key="Puget (Sea Otter, Sturgeon) Island">Puget Island</name>, <name type="place" key="Wahkiakum County, Wash.">Wahkiakum County</name>, <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31032514" n="14">Below the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Clatskanie River">Clatskanie River</name>, <name type="place" key="Columbia County, Oreg.">Columbia County</name>, <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>; see the captains'
entries for this day.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31032515" n="15">
               <name type="place" key="Clatsop County, Oreg.">Clatsops</name>, say the captains.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31032516" n="16">A <name type="native_nation" key="Cathlamet Indians">Cathlamet</name> lodge on <name type="place" key="Puget (Sea Otter, Sturgeon) Island">Puget Island</name>, <name type="place" key="Wahkiakum County, Wash.">Wahkiakum County</name>, <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31032517" n="17">In <name type="place" key="Columbia County, Oreg.">Columbia County</name>, <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>, below one of the mouths of the <name type="place" key="Clatskanie River">Clatskanie River</name>, opposite <name type="place" key="Cape Horn">Cape Horn</name> on the <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name> shore; see the captains' entries for the day.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31032518" n="18">
               <name type="native_nation" key="Cathlamet Indians">Cathlamets</name>.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-03-24" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-03-26" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
