<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-10-15">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
October 15, 1805</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               
               
               
               
               
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml" n="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc" n="Clark, William">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 5</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">July 28–November 1, 1805</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1989</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">273-276</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo" n="Ordway, John">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf" n="Floyd, Charles">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">239</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg" n="Gass, Patrick">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">155</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jw" n="Whitehouse, Joseph">Joseph Whitehouse</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 11</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of Joseph Whitehouse, May 14, 1804–April 2, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1997</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">354</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
         <geoDecl datum="WGS" xml:id="lc.geo.1805-10-15.01">
            <placeName/>
            <geo>46.3149 -118.8361</geo>
            <note>Camped just above Fishhook Rapids, Franklin County, WA.</note>
         </geoDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Journal Entries</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-07-01</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1805-10-15">October 15, 1805</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-10-15.01" n="lc.geo.1805-10-15.01">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">October 15th 〈Monday〉 Tuesday 1805</hi>
                     <ref target="n23101501" n="1"/>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <figure rend="mhs">
                     <p>Indian Groups of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name> Basin,<lb/>
ca. October 15, 1805, Elkskin-bound Journal
<bibl>
                           <orgName>Missouri Historical Society</orgName>
                        </bibl>
                     </p>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>
a fair morning after a Cold night. Some frost this morning and Ice. Several hunters out Saw nothing    <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt Lewis</name> assended the hills &amp; Saw Mountain a head bearing S. E. &amp; N W.    a high point to the west.<ref target="n23101502" n="2"/> Plain wavering. Set out at 3 oClock—</p>
               <p>
                  <table rows="5" cols="3">
                     <head>Course</head>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">South</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  4 ½</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">miles to the lower point of a Island close under the Std<lb/>
Side    passed one on the Lard. &amp; one other in the middle of<lb/>
the river, 〈three〉 4 Small rapid at the low pt of 1st Isd. opsd.<lb/>
2d &amp; 3rd Islands—</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. E.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  1 ½</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">mile to the lower point of an Isd. close under the Lard.<lb/>
bend opsd. the upper pt. of an Isd. on Std. point a Small<lb/>
rapid opposit</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 35° W</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  9</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">miles to a Point of rocks on Lard. Sd.    passed a place of<lb/>
Swift water    at the lower point of the 1st Island a Small<lb/>
rapid a little below a Lard. point    at 2 miles a Stard. point<lb/>
at 4 miles, a Lard. point    at 5 miles a Stard. point    3 Small<lb/>
Isd. opsd. on Lard. &amp; 2 on Stard. Side at 6½ a Small rapid,<lb/>
Several Scafles of Split timber on the Stard. Side    in the<lb/>
bottom below the Islands    a Island in the river at 8½ miles<lb/>
on Std. Side    a fishing timber Scaffeled    a willow bottom<lb/>
on the Lard Side above the point Country low on each side<lb/>
90 to 100 [200?] feet is the hite of the plains    Some Swift<lb/>
water at the last Isds.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">South</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                           <hi rend="underline">  5    </hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">miles to an Island in the head of a rapid    Passed for 3 miles<lb/>
through good water in closed in Clifts of rocks 100 feet<lb/>
high.    below which the river widens into a Bay nearly<lb/>
round.    we Encamped at three Scaffles of Split timber on<lb/>
the Stard. Side.    here we found our Pilot &amp; one man wate-<lb/>
ing for us to Show us the 〈rout〉 best way thro those rapids,<lb/>
the evening cool, we saw no timber to day, except Small<lb/>
willow &amp; Srub of Hackberry—    Killed 2 Teel this evening.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                           <hi rend="double underline">20</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-10-15.02" n="lc.geo.1805-10-15.01">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">October 15th 〈Monday〉 Tuesday 1805</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
a far morning    Sent out hunters to hunt in the plains, about 10 oClock they returned and informed that they could not See any Signs of game of any kind    <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt Lewis</name> walked on the plains and informs that he could plainly See a rainge of mountains which bore S. E. &amp; N. W. the nearest point south about 60 miles, and becoms high toward the N. W. The plaines on each Side is wavering. <name type="person" key="Labiche, François">Labiesh</name> killed 2 gees &amp; 2 Ducks of the large kind.    at two oClock we loaded &amp; Set out, our Powder &amp; Provisions of roots not Sufficently 〈wet〉 dry.    〈but〉 we Shall put them out at the forks or mouth of this river which is at no great distance, and at which place we Shall delay to make Some Selestial observations &amp;c.    passed Eleven Island and Seven rapids to day. Several of the rapids verry bad and dificuelt to pass. The Islands of different Sizes and all of round Stone and Sand, no timber of any kind in Sight of the river, a fiew Small willows excepted; in the evening the countrey becomes lower not exceding 90 or 100 feet above the water and back is a wavering Plain on each Side, passed thro: narrows for 3 miles where the Clifts of rocks juted to the river on each Side compressing the water of the river through a narrow chanel; below which it widens into a kind of bason nearly round without any proceptiable current, at the lower part of this bason is a bad dificuelt and dangerous rapid to pass, at the upper part of this rapid we over took the three Indians<ref target="n23101503" n="3"/> who had Polited us thro the rapids from the forks. those people with our 2 Chiefs had proceeded on to this place where they thought proper to delay for us to warn us of the difficulties of this rapid.<ref target="n23101504" n="4"/> we landed at a parcel of Split timber, the timber of a house of Indians out hunting the Antilope in the plains; and raised on Scaffolds to Save them from the Spring floods.    here we were obliged for the first time to take the property of the Indians without the consent or approbation of the owner.    the night was cold &amp; we made use of a part of those boards and Split logs for fire wood. Killed two teel this evening. Examined the rapids which we found more dificuelt to pass than we expected from the Indians information.    a Suckcession of Sholes, appears to reach from bank to bank for 3 miles which was also intersepted with large rocks Sticking up in every direction, and the chanel through which we must pass crooked and narrow.    we only made 20 miles today, owing to he detention in passing rapids &amp;c.

</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-10-15.03" n="lc.geo.1805-10-15.01">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Tuesday 15th Oct. 1805.    a clear cool morning.    we delayed to dry the baggage which was wet. Some of the men went out and killed three geese and Several ducks.    about 3 oClock P. M. we loaded the canoes and Set out 
again and proceeded on    the current very rapid.    the country continues barron as usal. Came 27 miles this day and Camped little above a bad rapid—


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-10-15.04" n="lc.geo.1805-10-15.01">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Tuesday 15th.</hi>    This day was fine, clear and pleasant; and we continued here until the afternoon to dry our baggage that had been wet yesterday. The natives have great quantities of fish deposited on this island.<ref target="n23101505" n="5"/> At 3 o'clock P. M. we got all our effects on board and proceeded on. Passed down a beautiful part of the river; and killed some geese and ducks. This river in general is very handsome, except at the rapids, where it is risking both life and property to pass; and even these rapids, when the bare view or prospect is considered distinct from the advantages of navigation, may add to its beauty, by interposing variety and scenes of romantick grandeur where there is so much uniformity in the appearance of the country. We went 18 miles this evening and halted at an old Indian camp on the north side, where we had great difficulty in procuring wood to cook with, as none at all grows in this part of the country.


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-10-15.05" n="lc.geo.1805-10-15.01">
            <sp who="jw">
               <speaker>Whitehouse</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
〈<hi rend="italic">Sunday</hi>〉 Tuesday <hi rend="italic">15th Oct</hi>. <hi rend="italic">1805</hi>.    a clear cool morning.    we delayed here to dry the baggage.    Some of the men went out and killed three geese &amp; Several ducks.    about 3 oClock P. m. we loaded up the canoes and Set out and proceeded on over Several rapids and Swift water.    passed Several Scaffels of wood where it was put up to be Saved for the use of their fishing in the Spring.    the country continues as yesterday.    we came 17 miles and Camped above a bad rapid on a Sand bar    no wood except an Indians Scaffel    we had to take Some of the wood for our use this evening.</p>
               <p>
Tuesday October 15th    This morning we had clear &amp; cool weather; We delayed here in order to dry the wet baggage.    Some of our Men went out &amp; killed 3 Geese and Several ducks.—    About 3 o'Clock P. M. we loaded the Canoes &amp; set out, and proceeded on; &amp; passed several rapids &amp; places where the water run very swift, We also passed Scaffolds of wood, which the Natives had built for the use of this fishery in the Spring season.    The Country continued the same as Yesterday.    We encamped on a Sand barr above a bad Rapid, we found no Wood, excepting an Indian Scaffold &amp; we took some of it for our use.    We came about 17 Miles this day, our Course the same as Yesterday.    (West)




</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n23101501" n="1">Opposite this entry in the Elkskin-bound Journal is a sketch map (fig. 13) of Indian groups of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name> basin. Neither the tribal names nor geographic locations can be determined with any confidence.</note>
            <note xml:id="n23101502" n="2">Probably part of the <name type="place" key="Blue (Southwest, Southeast) Mountains">Blue Mountains</name> of southeast <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name> and northeast <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n23101503" n="3">These three were probably <name type="native_nation" key="Palouse Indians">Palouse Indians</name>. Trafzer &amp; Scheuerman, 3.</note>
            <note xml:id="n23101504" n="4">
               <name type="place" key="Fishhook (Bason) Rapids">Fishhook Rapids</name>. They camped just above the rapids ("<name type="place" key="Fishhook (Bason) Rapids">bason Rapids</name>" on <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 75), in <name type="place" key="Franklin County, Wash.">Franklin County</name>, <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>. At least two archaeological sites are known for the north shore of the <name type="place" key="Fishhook (Bason) Rapids">Fishhook Rapids</name> area. The downstream site appears to be the one illustrated in <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 75; this site as a late prehistoric pit-house village that was archaeologically tested in 1959 by Daugherty.</note>
            <note xml:id="n23101505" n="5">
               <name type="person" key="McKeehan, David">McKeehan's</name> note: "Immense numbers of salmon must ascend the western rivers every summer from <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">the Pacific</name>, and constitute a chief article in the food of the natives. <name type="person" key="McKenzie, Charles">Mr. McKenzie</name> informs us that in the river, by which he arrived at the ocean, where it empties itself four or five hundred miles northwest of the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>, the salmon are so abundant, that the natives have a constant and plentiful supply of that excellent fish. He also on his return states, under the date of the 6th and 7th of August, that the salmon in the waters of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> were driving up the current in such large shoals, that the water seemed to be covered with the fins of them."</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-10-14" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-10-16" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
