<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.1806-05-28">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">May 28, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic
        Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            7</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">March 23–June 9, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1991</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">297-302</biblScope>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">316</biblScope>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">233</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
         <geoDecl datum="WGS">
            <placeName/>
            <geo>45.9995 -116.6952</geo>
            <note>Same party continued exploring on Lawyer Creek. Camped near the Lewis-Nez Perce county line, ID, above Deer Creek's entrance into the Salmon River. </note>
            <note>Approximate location</note>
         </geoDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc/>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-10-25</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-04-12</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date>May 28, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.1806-05-28.01">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Wednesday May 28th 1806.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>We sent 
          <name type="person" key="Goodrich, Silas">Goodrich</name>to the village of the 
          <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="person" key="Broken Arm">broken arm</name>
                  </hi>this morning    he returned in the evening with some roots bread and a
          parsel of goats-hair for making our saddle pads. 
          <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">Reubin</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Joseph Feilds</name>set out this morning to hunt
          high up on a creek which discharges itself into this river about 8 miles above us.
             at Noon 
          <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbono</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="York">York</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Lepage, Jean Baptiste">Lapage</name>returned; they had obtained
          four bags of the dryed roots of Cows and some bread.    in the evening 
          <name type="person" key="Collins, John">Collins</name>
                  <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name>returned with eight deer.
             they had fortunately discovered a ford on 
          <name type="place" key="Lolo (Collins's) Creek (Idaho)">Collins's Creek</name>where they
          were enabled to pass it with their horses and had hunted at the 
          <name type="place" key="Weippe Prairie (Camas Flats, Quawmash Flats)">quawmash
          ground</name>where we first met with the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Chopunnish</name>last fall.
          <ref target="n35052801" n="1"/>   deer were very abundant they informed us,
          but there were not many bear. The sick Cheif was much better this morning he can use his
          hands and arms and seems much pleased with the prospect of recovering, he says he feels
          much better than he has for a great number of months. I sincerely wish these sweats may
          restore him; we have consented that he should still remain with us and repeat these
          sweats.    he set up a great proportion of the day.—    The Child is
          also better, he is free of fever, the imposthume is not so large but seems to be
          advancing to maturity.—    since my arrival here I have killed several birds
          <ref target="n35052802" n="2"/>of the 
          <hi rend="italic">corvus</hi>genus [
          <hi rend="italic">EC: Picicorvus</hi>] of a kind found only in the 
          <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">rocky mountains</name>and their neighbourhood.
          I first met with this bird above the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Three Forks of the">three forks of the
          Missouri</name>and saw them on the hights of the 
          <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">rocky Mountains</name>but never before had an
          opportunity of examining them closely.    the small 
          <hi rend="italic">corvus</hi>
                  <ref target="n35052803" n="3"/>[
          <hi rend="italic">EC: Perisoreus</hi>] discribed at 
          <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name>is a different speceis,
          tho' untill now I had taken it to be the same, this is much larger and has a loud
          squawling note something like the mewing of a cat.    the beak of this bird is
          1½ inches long, is proportionably large, black and of the form which characterizes the
          genus.    the upper exceeds the under chap a little.    the head and
          neck are also proportionably large.    the eye full and reather prominent, the
          iris dark brown and puple black.    it is about the size and somewhat the form
          of the Jaybird tho reather rounder or more full in the body.    the tail is
          four and a half inches in length, composed of 12 feathers nearly of the same length.
             the head neck and body of this bird are of a dove colour.    the
          wings are black except the extremities of six large fathers ocupying the middle joint of
          the wing which are white.    the under disk of the wing is not of the shining
          or grossy black which marks it's upper surface.    the two feathers in the
          center of the tail are black as are the two adjacent feathers for half their width the
          ballance are of a pure white.    the feet and legs are black and imbricated
          with wide scales.    the nails are black and remarkably long and sharp, also
          much curved.    it has four toes on each foot of which one is in the rear and
          three in front.    the toes are long particularly that in the rear.
             this bird feeds on the seed of the pine and also on insects.   
          it resides in the 
          <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">rocky mountains</name>at all seasons of the
          year, and in many parts is the only bird to be found.—    our hunters brought
          us a large hooting Owl
          <ref target="n35052804" n="4"/>[
          <hi rend="italic">EC: Scotiaptex cinerea</hi>] which differs considerably from those of
          the Atlantic States which are also common here.    the plumage of this owl is
          an uniform mixture of dark yellowish brown and white, in which the dark brown
          predominates.    it's colour may be properly termed a dark iron grey.
             the plumage is very long and remarkably silky and soft.    these
          have not the long feathers on the head which give it the appearance of ears or horns.
             the leathers of the head are long narrow and closely set, they rise
          upwright nearly to the extremity and then are bent back sudonly as iff curled.
             a kind of ruff of these feathers incircle the thoat.    the head
          has a flat appearance being broadest before and behind and is 1 foot 10 Is. in
          circumference.    incircling the eyes and extending from them like rays from
          the center a tissue of open hairy long feathers are placed of a light grey colour, these
          conceal the ears which are very large and are placed close to the eyes behind and
          extending below them.    these feathers meet over the beak which they nearly
          conceal and form the face of the owl.    they eyes are remarkably large and
          prominant, the iris of a pale goald colour and iris circular and of a deep sea green.
             the beak is short and wide at it's base. the upper chap is much curved at
          the extremity and comes down over and in front of the under chap.    this bird
          is about the size of the largest hooting Owl.    the tail is composed of
          eleven feathers, of which those in the center are reather the longest.    it
          is booted to the extremity of the toes, of which it has four on each foot, one in the
          rear one on the outer side and two in front.    the toes are short
          particularly that in rear, but are all armed with long keen curved nails of a dark brown
          colour.    the beak is white and nostrils circular large and unconnected.
             the habits and the note of this owl is much that of the common large
          hooting owl.—</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.1806-05-28.02">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Wednesday May 28th 1806</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>We sent 
          <name type="person" key="Goodrich, Silas">Goodrich</name>to the Village of the 
          <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="person" key="Broken Arm">broken Arm</name>
                  </hi>for hair to Stuff Saddle pads. 
          <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Jo.</name>&amp; 
          <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">R. Fields</name>Set out this morning to hunt
          towards the mountains.    at noon 
          <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Shabono</name>
                  <name type="person" key="York">York</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Lepage, Jean Baptiste">Lapage</name>returned.    they
          had obtained 4 bags of the dried roots of Cowse and Some bread.    in the
          evening 
          <name type="person" key="Collins, John">Collins</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name>&amp; 
          <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name>returned with 8 deer.   
          they fortunately discovered a ford on 
          <name type="place" key="Lolo (Collins's) Creek (Idaho)">Collin's Creek</name>where they
          were enable to pass it with there horses and had hunted at the 
          <name type="place" key="Weippe Prairie (Camas Flats, Quawmash Flats)">quawmash
          Grounds</name>where we first met with the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Chopunnish</name>last fall.
             deer were verry abundant they informed us, but there was not many bear. The
          Sick Chief is much better this morning    he can use his hands and arms and
          Seems much pleased with the prospects of recovering, he Says he feels much better than
          he has done for a great Number of Months. I Sincerly wish that the Swetts may restore
          him. I have Consented to repeet the Sweets.
          <ref target="n35052805" n="5"/>
               </p>
               <p>The Country along the 
          <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">rocky mountains</name>for Several hundred Miles
          in length and about 50 in width is leavel extremely fertile and in many parts Covered
          with a tall and opult. growth of the long leafed pine.    near the
          Watercourses the hills are lofty tho' are covered with a good Soil and not remarkably
          Stoney and possess more timber than the leavel country. the bottom lands on the Water
          courses are reather narrow and confined tho' fertile and Seldom inundated.   
          this Country would form an extensive Settlement; the Climate appears quit as mild as
          that of a Similar latitude on the 
          <name type="place" key="Atlantic Ocean">Atlantic</name>Coast; &amp; it cannot be
          otherwise than healthy; it possesses a fine dry pure air.    the grass and
          maney plants are now upwards of Knee high. I have no doubt that this tract of Country if
          Cultivated would produce in great abundance every article esentially necessary to the
          comfort and Subsistence of civillized man.    to it's present inhabitents
          nature Seems to have dealt with a liberal hand, for she has distributed a great variety
          of esculent plants over the face of the Country which furnish them a plentiful Store of
          provisions; those are acquired but little toil; and then prepared after the method of
          the nativs afford not only a nutricious but an agreeable food.    among other
          roots those Called by them the 
          <hi rend="italic">Quawmash</hi>and 
          <hi rend="italic">Cows</hi>are esteemd. the most agreeable and valuable as they are also
          the most abundant in those high plains.</p>
               <p>The 
          <hi rend="italic">Cows</hi>is a knobbed root of an erregularly rounded form not unlike
          the Gensang in form and Consistence; this root they Collect, rub off a thin black rhind
          which Covers it and pounding it exposes it in cakes to the Sun.    these Cakes
          are about an inch and ¼ thick and 6 by 18 in wedth, when dry they either eat this bread
          alone without any further preperation, or boil it and make a thick Musilage; the latter
          is most common &amp; much the most agreeable.    the flower of this root is
          not very unlike the gensang—.    this root they Collect as early as the Snow
          disappears in the Spring, and Continues to collect it untill the Quawmash Supplies it's
          place which happins about the Middle of June.    the quawmash is also
          Collected for a fiew weeks after it first makes it's appearance in the Spring, but when
          the scape appears it is no longer fit for use untill the Seed are ripe which happens
          about the time just mentioned.    and then the 
          <hi rend="italic">Cows</hi>declines. The Cows is also frequently dried in the Sun and
          pounded afterwards and used in thickening Supe and Makeing Mush.</p>
               <p>The 
          <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Chopunnish</name>
                  </hi>held a Council in the morning of the 12th among themselves in respect to the
          Subject on which we had Spoken to them the day before,
          <ref target="n35052806" n="6"/>the result as we learnt was favourable, they placed
          Confidence in the information they had recived and resolved to pursue our advise.
             after this Council was over the principal Chief or the 
          <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="person" key="Broken Arm">broken arm</name>,</hi>took the flour of the roots
          of Cows and thickened the Soup in the Kitiles and baskets of all his people, this being
          ended he made a harangue the purpote of which was makeing known the deliberations of
          their councils and impressing the necessity of unanimity among them, and a strict
          attention to the resolution which had been agreed on in Councell; he concluded by
          enviting all such men as had resolved to abide by the decree of the councill to come and
          eat, and requested Such as would not be So bound to Show themselves by not partakeing of
          the feast. I was told by one of our men who was present in the house, that there was not
          a decenting voice on this great National question, but all Swallowed their objections if
          any they had, very cheerfully with their mush—.    dureing the time of this
          loud animated harangue of the Chief the women Cryed wrung their hands, tore their hair
          and appeared to be in the utmost distress.    after this cerimoney was over,
          the Chiefs and considerate men came in a body to where we were Seated at a little
          distance from our tent, and two young men at the instance of the nation presented 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt L.</name>and myself each a fine horse.
             and informed us that they had listened with attentioned to what we had Said
          and were resolved to pursue our Counsels &amp;c.—    That as we had not seen
          the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Black foot</name>Indians and the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Atsina Indians">Minetaries of Fort dePrarie</name>they
          did not think it safe to venter over to the plains of the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, where they would fondly go
          provided those nations would not kill them.    that when we had established a
          tradeing house on the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>as we had promised they would
          Come over and trade for arms Amunition &amp;c. and live about us.    that it
          would give them much pleasure to be at peace with those nations altho' they had Shed
          much of their blood—. They Said that they were pore but their hearts were good.
             we might be assured of their sincerety. Some of their brave men would go
          over with us to the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>and bring them the news as we
          wished, and if we Could make a peace between them[Selves] and their enimies on the other
          Side of the mountains their nation would go over to the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>in the latter end of the Summer.
             on the Subject of one of their Chiefs accompanying us to the land of the
          White men they Could not yet determine, but that they would let us know before we left
          them. that the Snow was yet so deep in the Mountains that if we attempted to pass, we
          would Certainly perish, and advised us to remain untill after the next full Moon when
          the Snow would disappear on the South hill sides and we would find grass for our
          horses.—. 
          <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Jean Baptiste">Shabonos Child</name>is better this
          day that he was yesterday.    he is free from fever.    the
          imposthume is not So large but Seems to be advanceing to meturity—.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.1806-05-28.03">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>Wednesday 28th May 1806.    we Set out eairly    the old chief
          and an other Indn went with us.    we rode on a plain about 2 hours then left
          the road and bore South thro an unlevel timbred country untill towards evening. Saw
          Several big horn animel or mountain Sheep and Saw 14 deer in this timbred country
             Some Spots of Snow &amp; falling timber.    had a hard Thunder
          Shower.    towards evening we descended a bad hill down on a creek
          <ref target="n35052807" n="7"/>   followed it down Some distance and arived
          at a village where we Camped.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.1806-05-28.04">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Wednesday 28th.</hi>   There was a cloudy foggy morning.
          Some hunters
          <ref target="n35052808" n="8"/>went out this morning, and in the afternoon three of
          them
          <ref target="n35052809" n="9"/>came in with eight deer; at the same time three more of
          our men
          <ref target="n35052810" n="10"/>returned from the villages.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n35052801" n="1">
               <name type="place" key="Weippe Prairie (Camas Flats, Quawmash Flats)">Weippe
        Prarie</name>, in 
        <name type="place" key="Clearwater County, Idaho">Clearwater County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>. 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>map 71.</note>
            <note xml:id="n35052802" n="2">Clark's nutcracker, 
        <hi rend="italic">Nucifraga columbiana</hi>[AOU, 491], first observed on 
        <ref n="1805-08-22" type="related">August 22, 1805</ref>, and now given its first full
        description. Named for 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>by Alexander Wilson, who also
        included a drawing of it in his published ornithology. Coues's penciled term 
        <hi rend="italic">Picicorvus</hi>was the bird's genus name in his time. Coues (HLC),
        3:1028 n. 20; Cutright (LCPN), 383–87; Burroughs, 251–52; Holmgren, 29. It was probably
        Biddle who drew a red vertical line through the descriptive passage and two more through
        descriptive passages below.</note>
            <note xml:id="n35052803" n="3">Presumably the gray jay, 
        <hi rend="italic">Perisoreus canadensis</hi>[AOU, 484], described on 
        <ref n="1805-12-18" type="related">December 18, 1805</ref>. The "Jaybird" is the blue
        jay, 
        <hi rend="italic">Cyanocitta cristata</hi>[AOU, 477].</note>
            <note xml:id="n35052804" n="4">The great gray owl, a new species. See 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>brief description at 
        <ref n="1806-05-23" type="related">May 23, 1806</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n35052805" n="5">Much of what follows in this entry is copied from 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>entries of some weeks earlier;
        see 
        <ref n="1806-05-09" type="related">May 9</ref>and 
        <ref n="1806-05-12" type="related">12</ref>, 1806.</note>
            <note xml:id="n35052806" n="6">The words from the "12th" to about here appear to have
        replaced some erasures.</note>
            <note xml:id="n35052807" n="7">According to John J. Peebles, "The Return of 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>," 
        <hi rend="italic">Idaho Yesterdays</hi>10 (Summer 1966): 21, the party continued west on 
        <name type="place" key="Lawyer (Commearp) Creek">Lawyer Creek</name>, then overland
        southwesterly to 
        <name type="place" key="Deer Creek (Idaho)">Deer Creek</name>, descended it a ways, and
        camped for the night. The camp would have been near the 
        <name type="place" key="Lewis County, Idaho">Lewis</name>–
        <name type="place" key="Nez Perce County, Idaho">Nez Perce</name>county line, 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>, above 
        <name type="place" key="Deer Creek (Idaho)">Deer Creek's</name>entrance into the 
        <name type="place"
                     key="Salmon (Lewis's, Main Fork Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">
        Salmon River</name>. More recently, Merle Wells of the Idaho Historical Society has been
        at work tracing 
        <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway's</name>route. Personal communication,
        September 14, 1990. Wells has the party follow 
        <name type="place" key="Lawyer (Commearp) Creek">Lawyer Creek</name>west to 
        <name type="place" key="Mitchell Creek">Mitchell Creek</name>, move northwesterly up it a
        distance, then go overland to return to 
        <name type="place" key="Lawyer (Commearp) Creek">Lawyer Creek</name>, follow it a short
        distance before breaking off overland again, and finally descend to the 
        <name type="place"
                     key="Salmon (Lewis's, Main Fork Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">
        Salmon</name>along a route paralleling 
        <name type="place" key="Deer Creek (Idaho)">Deer Creek</name>but to the west of that
        stream. Both accounts have to rely on what seems the most plausible route since 
        <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway's</name>description is not detailed enough
        to allow a precise tracing. 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>summarizes 
        <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway's</name>journey in his entry for 
        <ref n="1806-06-02" type="related">June 2, 1806</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n35052808" n="8">According to 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, the 
        <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph and Reubin">Field brothers</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n35052809" n="9">
               <name type="person" key="Collins, John">Collins</name>, 
        <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name>, and 
        <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n35052810" n="10">
               <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name>, 
        <name type="person" key="York">York</name>, and 
        <name type="person" key="Lepage, Jean Baptiste">Lepage</name>.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-05-27" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-05-29" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
