<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-01-04">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
January 4, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               
               
               
               
               
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml" n="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc" n="Clark, William">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 6</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">November 2, 1805–March 22, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1990</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">164-166</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo" n="Ordway, John">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf" n="Floyd, Charles">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">264</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg" n="Gass, Patrick">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">186</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jw" n="Whitehouse, Joseph">Joseph Whitehouse</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 11</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of Joseph Whitehouse, May 14, 1804–April 2, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1997</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">410</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Journal Entries</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-08-05</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1806-01-04">January 4, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-01-04.01" n="">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Saturday January 4th 1806.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Coboway">Comowooll</name> and the <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsops</name> who visited us yesterday left us in the evening. These people the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinnooks</name> and others residing in this neighbourhood and speaking the same language have been very friendly to us; they appear to be a mild inoffensive people but will pilfer if they have an opportuny to do so where they conceive themselves not liable to detection.    they are great higlers in trade and if they conceive you anxious to purchase will be a whole day bargaining for a handfull of roots; this I should have thought proceeded from their want of knowledge of the comparitive value of articles of merchandize and the fear of being cheated, did I not find that they invariably refuse the price first offered them and afterwards very frequently accept a smaller quantity of the same article; in order to satisfy myself on this subject I once offered a <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinnook</name> my watch two knives and a considerable quantity of beads for a small inferior sea Otter's<ref target="n26010401" n="1"/> skin which I did not much want, he immediately conceived it of great value, and refused to barter except I would double the quantity of beads; the next day with a great deal of importunity on his part I received the skin in exchange for a few strans of the same beads he had refused the day before. I therefore believe this trait in their character proceeds from an avaricious all grasping disposition.    in this rispect they differ from all Indians I ever became acquainted with, for their dispositions invariably lead them to give whatever they are possessed off no matter how usefull or valuable, for a bauble which pleases their fancy, without consulting it's usefullness or value.    nothing interesting occurred today, or more so, than our wappetoe being all exhausted.
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-01-04.02" n="">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Saturday 4th January 1806</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Coboway">Comowool</name> and the <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsops</name> who visited us yesterday left us in the morning. Those people the <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinnook</name>
                  </hi> and others resideing in this neighbourhood and Speaking the Same language have been very friendly to us; they appear to be a mild inoffensive people but will pilfer if they have an oppertunity to do So when they Conceive themseles not liable to detection.    they are great higlers in trade and if they Conceive you anxious to purchase will be a whole day bargaining for a hand full of roots; this I Should have thought proceeded from their want of Knowledge of the Comparitive value of articles of merchindize and the fear of being Cheated, did I not find that they invariably refuse the price first offered them and afterwards very frequently accept a Smaller quantity of the Same article; in order to Satisfy myself on this point, I onc[e] offered a <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsop</name> man my watch a knife, a Dollar of the Coin of U State and hand full of beeds, for a Small Sea otter Skin, which I did not much want, he immediately Conceived it of great value, and refused to Sell unless I would give as maney more 〈blue〉 beads; the next day with a great deel of importunity on his part we receved the Skin in exchange for a fiew Strans of the Same beeds he had refused the day before.    I therefore beleive this threat in their Charector proceeds from an avericious all grasping disposition.    in this respect they differ from all Indians I ever became acquainted with, for their dispositions invariably lead them to give what ever they are possessed off no matter how usefull or valuable, for a bauble which pleases their fancy, without Consulting its usefulness or value. nothing occured to day, or more So, than our <hi rend="italic">wappato</hi> being all exhausted.

</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-01-04.03" n="">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Saturday 4th Jany. 1806. Small Showers of rain and hail as usal.    the <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsop</name> Indians trade to us Some excelent Sweet roots.    one of the party bought a dog also.—

</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-01-04.04" n="">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Saturday 4th.</hi>    The morning was wet; but we proceeded on, and passed the head of a creek<ref target="n26010402" n="2"/> which we supposed was the last in our rout to the <name type="place" key="Saltmaking Camp (Oreg.)">salt works</name>. Immediately after passing the creek, the man with me killed an elk; when we halted and took breakfast off it, and then went on. We got into low ground, passed through a marsh about ½ a mile in breadth, where the water was knee-deep; then got into a beautiful prairie,<ref target="n26010403" n="3"/> about 5 miles wide, and which runs along the sea shore about 30 miles from <name type="place" key="Point Adams">Point Adams</name>
                  <ref target="n26010404" n="4"/> on the south side of <name type="place" key="Baker (Haley's) Bay">Hayley's Bay</name>,<ref target="n26010405" n="5"/> in nearly a southwest course and ends at a high point of a mountain, called <name type="place" key="Tillamook Head (Clark's Point of View)">Clarke's View</name>
                  <ref target="n26010406" n="6"/> on the sea shore. Through this plain or prairie runs another creek,<ref target="n26010407" n="7"/> or small river which we could not pass without some craft: so we encamped on the creek and supped on the elk's tongue, which we had brought with us.


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-01-04.05" n="">
            <sp who="jw">
               <speaker>Whitehouse</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Saturday Janry 4th    We had small showers of rain &amp; some hail this morning.    a number of Indians belonging to the <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsop</name> Nation that came to the fort Yesterday staid near the Fort last night.    They sold our party some sweet Roots fish, 1 dog &amp;ca.    Towards evening they all left us.    The Rain continued the greater part of this day.—

</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n26010401" n="1">The sea otter, <hi rend="italic">Enhydra lutris.</hi>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="n26010402" n="2">Probably the head of <name type="place" key="Cullaby Creek">Cullaby Creek</name>, <name type="place" key="Clatsop County, Oreg.">Clatsop County</name>, <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n26010403" n="3">The coastal plain in <name type="place" key="Clatsop County, Oreg.">Clatsop County</name>, north of <name type="place" key="Gearhart, Oreg.">Gearhart</name>, in the vicinity of <name type="place" key="Sunset Beach, Oreg.">Sunset Beach</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n26010404" n="4">
               <name type="place" key="Point Adams">Point Adams</name> is the headland at the southern side of the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>, <name type="place" key="Clatsop County, Oreg.">Clatsop County</name>. It was named for then Vice President <name type="person" key="Adams, John">John Adams</name> in 1792 by <name type="person" key="Gray, Robert">Robert Gray</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n26010405" n="5">
               <name type="place" key="Baker (Haley's) Bay">Baker Bay</name>, on the north side of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> estuary, <name type="place" key="Pacific County, Wash.">Pacific County</name>, <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>, opposite <name type="place" key="Point Adams">Point Adams</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n26010406" n="6">
               <name type="place" key="Tillamook Head (Clark's Point of View)">Tillamook Head</name>, <name type="place" key="Clatsop County, Oreg.">Clatsop County</name>. It became <name type="place" key="Tillamook Head (Clark's Point of View)">Clark's Point of View</name> to the party after 
<name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> climbed it on <ref n="lc.jrn.1806-01-07" type="related">January 7</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n26010407" n="7">Probably <name type="place" key="Thompson Creek">Thompson Creek</name>, which meets <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">the Pacific</name> in <name type="place" key="Clatsop County, Oreg.">Clatsop County</name>, just north of <name type="place" key="Seaside, Oreg.">Seaside</name>.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-01-03" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-01-05" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
