<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-02-07">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
February 7, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               
               
               
               
               
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml" n="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc" n="Clark, William">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 6</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">November 2, 1805–March 22, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1990</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">284-287</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo" n="Ordway, John">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf" n="Floyd, Charles">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">270</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg" n="Gass, Patrick">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">192</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jw" n="Whitehouse, Joseph">Joseph Whitehouse</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 11</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of Joseph Whitehouse, May 14, 1804–April 2, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1997</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">418</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Journal Entries</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-08-23</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1806-02-07">February 7, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-02-07.01" n="">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Friday February 7th 1806.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
This evening <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Sergt. Ordway</name> and <name type="person" key="Weiser, Peter">Wiser</name> returned with a part of the meat which <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">R. Fields</name> had killed; the ballance of the party with Sergt. <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name> remained in order to bring the ballance of the meat to the river at a point agreed on where the canoe is to meet them again tomorrow morning. This evening we had what I call an excellent supper it consisted of a marrowbone a piece and a brisket of boiled Elk that had the appearance of a little fat on it.    this for <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name> is living in high stile. In this neighbourhood I observe the honeysuckle<ref target="n28020701" n="1"/> common in our country    I first met with it on the waters of the <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Kooskooske</name> near the <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Chopunnish</name> nation, and again below the <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Cascades (Great Rapids, Great Shute)">grand rappids</name> In the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbian</name> Valley on tidewater. The Elder<ref target="n28020702" n="2"/> also common to our country grows in great abundance in the rich woodlands on this side of the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">rocky Mountains</name>; tho' it differs Here in the colour of it's berry, this being of a pale sky blue while that of the U' States is a deep perple. The seven bark or nine-bark<ref target="n28020703" n="3"/> as it is called in the U' States is also common in this quarter. There is a species of huckleberry<ref target="n28020704" n="4"/> common to the piny lands from the commencement of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbian</name> valley to the seacoast; it rises to the hight of 6 or 8 feet.    is a simple branching some what defuse stem; the main body or trunk is cilindric and of a dark brown, while the colateral branches are green smoth, squar, and put forth anumber of alternate branches of the same colour and form from the two horizontal sides only.    the fruit is a small deep perple berry which the natives inform us is very good.    the leaf is thin of a pale green and small being ¾ of an inch in length and ⅜ in width; oval terminateing more accutely at the apex than near the insertion of the footstalk which is at the base; veined, nearly entire, serrate but so slightly so that it is scarcely perceptile; footstalk short and there position with rispect to each other is alternate and two ranked, proceeding from the horizontal sides of the bough only. The small pox has distroyed a great number of the natives in this quarter.<ref target="n28020705" n="5"/>    it prevailed about 4 years since among the <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsops</name> and distroy several hundred of them, four of their chiefs fell victyms to it's ravages.    those <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsops</name> are deposited in their canoes on the bay a few miles below us. I think the late ravages of the small pox may well account for the number of remains of vilages which we find deserted on the river and Sea coast in this quarter.—
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-02-07.02" n="">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Friday February 7th 1806</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
This evening Serjt <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> and <name type="person" key="Weiser, Peter">wiser</name> returned with a part of the meat which <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">R. Field</name> had killed; the balance of the Party with <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Serjt. Gass</name> remained in order to bring the ballance of the meat to the river at a point agreed on, where the Canoe is to meet them again tomorrow morning.    This evening we had what I call an excellent supper it consisted of a marrowbone, a piece of brisket of boiled Elk that had the appearance of a little fat on it.    this for <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name> is liveing in high Stile, and in fact fiesting—.</p>
               <p>
In this neighbourhood I observe the honeysuckle common in the U States, I first met with it on the waters of the <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Kooskooske</name> near the <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Chopunnish</name> Nation, and again below the <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Cascades (Great Rapids, Great Shute)">grand rapids</name> in the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbian</name> Vally on tide water. The Elder also common to our Countrey grows in great abundance in the rich wood land on this Side of the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">rocky mountain</name>s, tho it differs here in the Colour of its berry, this being of a pale Sky blue while that of the U, States is a deep purple. The Seven or nine bark as it is called in the U, States is also Common in this quarter. There is a Species of huckkleberry Common to the piney lands from the Commencement of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbian</name> Vally to the Sea coast; it rises to the hight of 6 or 8 feet, is a Simple branching, Somewhat defused Stem; the main body or trunk is cilindric    branches are green Smothe squar, and put foth a number of alternet branches of the Same Colour and form from the two horizontal Sides only.    the frute is a small deep purple berry which the nativs inform us is very good, the leaf is thin of a 〈deep〉 pale green and Small being ¾ of an inch in length and ⅜ in width; oval terminateing more accoutely at the apax, than near the insertion of the footstalk which is at the base vened nearly entire; footstalks Short and their position in respect to each other is alternate and too ranked, proceeding from the horizontal Side of the bough only.</p>
               <p>
The <hi rend="italic">Small Pox</hi> had distroyed a great number of the nativs in this quarter. it provailed about 4 or 5 yrs Sinc among the <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsops</name>, and distroy'd Several hundreds of them, four of their Chiefs fell a victym to it's ravages. these <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsops</name> are Deposited in their Canoes on the bay a fiew miles below us. I think the late ravages of the Small Pox, may well acount for the number of remains of villages which I Saw on my rout to the <name type="native_nation" key="Tillamook Indians">Kil a mox</name> in Several places—.

</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-02-07.03" n="">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Friday 7th Feby. 1806.    we packed the meat to the River or marsh. I and one man<ref target="n28020706" n="6"/> went to the Fort with the canoe and some meat    hard rain &amp;C.—


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-02-07.04" n="">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Friday 7th.</hi>    The morning was fair, and all hands engaged in bringing in 
the meat; we got some to the fort; but myself and part of the men<ref target="n28020707" n="7"/> had again 
to encamp out. It rained hard and we had a disagreeable night.


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-02-07.05" n="">
            <sp who="jw">
               <speaker>Whitehouse</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Friday Febry 7th    The weather continued pleasant.    the Men that went after the Elk meat, carried it on their backs to a marsh near to the River, where they could come with a Canoe.    they then encamped at that place.    Two Men were sent from that place with a Canoe &amp; part of the Meat to the fort.    Nothing worth mentioning happened at the fort this day.    The Men there were employ'd as Yesterday.    A short time after dark we had a hard Rain—



</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n28020701" n="1">Orange honeysuckle, <hi rend="italic">Lonicera ciliosa</hi> (Pursh) DC., a new species first observed on the <name type="place" key="Lolo Trail">Lolo Trail</name>. It has numerous medicinal uses among the tribes of western <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>. Hitchcock et al., 4:458; Gunther (EWW), 48; Cutright (LCPN), 212, 261 n. 19, 410.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28020702" n="2">The blue elderberry; the species used for comparison is the common elderberry, <hi rend="italic">Sambucus canadensis</hi> L. Fernald, 1342. This passage is struck through with a red vertical line, perhaps placed by Biddle.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28020703" n="3">The ninebark, first mentioned on <ref n="lc.jrn.1805-12-01" type="related">December 1, 1805</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28020704" n="4">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> huckleberry may be mountain huckleberry, <hi rend="italic">Vaccinium membranaceum</hi> Dougl. ex. Hook., a new species. Hitchcock et al., 4:32; Cutright (LCPN), 212, 422. However, oval-leaf blueberry, <hi rend="italic">Vaccinium 0valifolium</hi> Sm., may be a better candidate for <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> huckleberry than the mountain huckleberry, a montane species that <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> may have seen upriver near <name type="place" key="Cascade Range">the Cascades</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28020705" n="5">At least two smallpox epidemics occurred among the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookan</name> peoples of the Lower <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> Valley before the arrival of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>. The first, during the 1770s, was probably particularly devastating, as it presumably took hold upon populations previously unaffected by this disease. Smallpox was then reintroduced in 1800–1801 as <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> indicates. For an assessment of the effects of disease on the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookans</name> and other native Northwest Coast peoples, see Boyd.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28020706" n="6">
               <name type="person" key="Weiser, Peter">Weiser</name>, say the captains.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28020707" n="7">According to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> and <name type="person" key="Weiser, Peter">Weiser</name> returned while <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name> and the rest of the detachment stayed out.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-02-06" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-02-08" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
