<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.1805-05-31">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">May 31, 1805</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic
        Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            4</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">April7–July 27, 1805</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1987</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">224-234</biblScope>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">159-160</biblScope>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">96</biblScope>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            11</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of Joseph Whitehouse, May 14, 1804–April 2,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1997</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">180-181</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
         <geoDecl datum="WGS">
            <placeName/>
            <geo>47.9154 -110.0579</geo>
            <note>Above Eagle Creek in Chouteau County, MT.</note>
         </geoDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc/>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-01-23</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-04-12</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date>May 31, 1805</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.1805-05-31.01">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Friday May 31st 1805.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>This morning we proceeded at an early hour with the two perogues leaving the canoes
          and crews to bring on the meat of the two buffaloe that were killed last evening and
          which had not been brought in as it was late and a little off the river.   
          soon after we got under way it began to rain and continued untill meridian when it
          ceased but still remained cloudy through the ballance of the day. The obstructions of
          rocky points and riffles still continue as yesterday; at those places the men are
          compelled to be 〈much〉 in the water even to their armpits, and the water is yet very
          could, and so frequent are those point that they are one fourth of their time in the
          water, added to this the banks and bluffs along which they are obliged to pass are so
          slippery and the mud so tenacious that they are unable to wear their mockersons, and in
          that situation draging the heavy burthen of a canoe and walking ocasionally for several
          hundred yards over the sharp fragments of rocks which tumble from the clifts and garish
          the borders of the river; in short their labour is incredibly painfull and great, yet
          those faithfull fellows bear it without a murmur. The toe rope of the white perogue, the
          only one indeed of hemp, and that on which we most depended, gave way today at a bad
          point, the perogue swung and but slightly touched a rock, yet was very near overseting;
          I fear her evil gennii will play so many pranks with her that she will go to the bottomm
          some of those days.—    
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. C.</name>walked on shore this morning but
          found it so excessively bad that he shortly returned.    at 12 OCk. we came
          too for refreshment and gave the men a dram which they received with much cheerfullness,
          and well deserved.—</p>
               <p>
                  <ref target="n14053101" n="1">The hills and river Clifts which we passed today exhibit a
          most romantic appearance.</ref>The bluffs of the river rise to the hight of from 2 to
          300 feet and in most places nearly perpendicular; they are formed of remarkable white
          sandstone which is sufficiently soft to give way readily to the impression of water; two
          or thre thin horizontal stratas of white free-stone, on which the rains or water make no
          impression, lie imbeded in these clifts of soft stone near the upper part of them; the
          earth on the top of these Clifts is a dark rich loam, which forming a graduly ascending
          plain extends back from ½ a mile to a mile where the hills commence and rise abruptly to
          a hight of about 300 feet more. The water in the course of time in decending from those
          hills and plains on either side of the river has trickled down the soft sand clifts and
          woarn it into a thousand grotesque figures, which with the help of a little immagination
          and an oblique view at a disance, are made to represent eligant ranges of lofty
          freestone buildings, having their parapets well stocked with statuary; collumns of
          various sculpture both grooved and plain, are also seen supporting long galleries in
          front of those buildings; in other places on a much nearer approach and with the help of
          less immagination we see the remains or ruins of eligant buildings; some collumns
          standing and almost entire with their pedestals and capitals; others retaining their
          pedestals but deprived by time or accident of their capitals, some lying prostrate an
          broken othes in the form of vast pyramids of connic structure bearing a sereis of other
          pyramids on their tops becoming less as they ascend and finally terminating in a sharp
          point.    nitches and alcoves of various forms and sizes are seen at different
          hights as we pass.    a number of the 
          <ref target="n14053102" n="2">small martin</ref>which build their nests with clay in a
          globular form attatched to the wall within those nitches, and which were seen hovering
          about the tops of the 〈broken〉 collumns did not the less remind us of some of those
          large stone buildings in the U' States.    the thin stratas of hard freestone
          intermixed with the soft sandstone seems to have aided the water in forming this curious
          scenery. As we passed on it seemed as if those seens of visionary inchantment would
          never have and end; for here it is too that nature presents to the view of the traveler 
          <ref target="n14053103" n="3">vast ranges of walls of tolerable workmanship,</ref>so
          perfect indeed are those walls that I should have thought that nature had attempted here
          to rival the human art of masonry had I not recollected that she had first began her
          work. These walls rise to the hight in many places of 100 feet, are perpendicular, with
          two regular faces and are from one to 12 feet thick, each wall retains the same thickess
          at top which it possesses at bottom. The stone of which these walls are formed is black,
          dence and dureable, and appears to be composed of a large portion of earth intermixed or
          cemented with a small quantity of sand and a considerable portion of talk or quarts.
             these stones are almost invariably regular parallelepipeds, of unequal
          sizes in the walls, but equal in their horizontal ranges, at least as to debth.
             these are laid regularly in ranges on each other like bricks, each breaking
          or covering the interstice of the two on which it rests.    thus the
          purpendicular interstices are broken, and the horizontal ones extend entire throughout
          the whole exent of the walls. These stones seem to bear some proportion to the thickess
          of the walls in which they are employed, being larger in the thicker walls; the greatest
          length of the parallelepiped appears to form the thickess of the thiner walls, while two
          or more are employed to form that of the thicker walls. These walls pass the river in
          several places, rising from the water's edge much above the sandstone bluffs, which they
          seem to penetrate; thence continuing their course on a streight line on either side of
          the river through the gradually ascending plains, over which they tower to the hight of
          from ten to seventy feet untill they reach the hills, which they finally enter and
          conceal themselves.    these walls sometimes run parallel to each other, with
          several ranges near each other, and at other times interscecting each other at right
          angles, having the appearance of the walls of ancient houses or gardens. I walked on
          shore this evening and examined these walls minutely and preserved a specimine of the
          stone. I found the face of many of the river hills formed of Clifts of very excellent 
          <ref target="n14053104" n="4">free stone of a light yellowish brown colour;</ref>on
          these clifts I met with a 
          <ref target="n14053105" n="5">species of pine which I had never seen, it differs from
          the pitchpine in the particular of it's leaf and cone, the first being vastly shorter,
          and the latter considerably longer and more pointed.</ref>I saw near those bluffs the
          most beautifull fox that I ever beheld, the colours appeared to me to be a fine orrange
          yellow, white and black, I endevoured to kill this anamal but it discovered me at a
          considerable distance, and finding that I could get no nearer, I fired on him as he ran,
          and missed him; he concealed himself under the rocks of the clift; it appeared to me to
          be about the size of the common red fox of the Atlantic states, or reather smaller than
          the large fox common to this country; 
          <ref target="n14053106" n="6">convinced I am that it is a distinct species.</ref>
                  <ref target="n14053107" n="7">The appearance of coal continu[e]s but in small quanities,
          but litt[l]e appearance of birnt hills or pumice stones    the mineral salts
          have in some measure abated and no quarts.</ref>   we saw a great number of
          the Bighorn some mule deer and a few buffaloe and Elk, no antelopes or common deer. 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name>who was with me and myself
          killed two bighorned anamals; the sides of the Clifts where these anamals resort much to
          lodg, have the peculiar smell of the sheepfolds.    the party killed in
          addition to our hunt 2 buffaloe and an Elk.    the river today has been from
          150 to 250 yds. wide    but little timber today on the river.</p>
               <p>
                  <table rows="15" cols="3">
                     <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Courses and distances of May 31st 1805.</hi>
                        <ref target="n14053108" n="8"/>
                     </head>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 45° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  2</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">to a few trees in a bend on Stard. side</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 80° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">     ½</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">to a few trees on a Stard. point</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 80° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">     ¼</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">On the Stard. point</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 60° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  1 ¾</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">to the lower part of the timber in a Stard.
                bend</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">West</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">     ¼</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">to a few trees on the Stard. side.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 78° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  2</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">to some trees on the Stard. side.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">West</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  2</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">to a point on the Stard. side.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 45° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">     ¼</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Along the Stard. point.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 30° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">     ¼</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Along the Stard. point passing a 
                <ref target="n14053109" n="9">high wall of black rock</ref>
                           <lb/>on Lard. rising from the water's edge above the river clifts</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">North</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  1 ½</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">to a tree in a bend on Stard. opposite to a
                high open
                <lb/>bottom.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 42 W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  1</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">to a point on the Stard. side</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 10 E.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">     ¾</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">to a point on the Lard. side opposite to a
                wall of black
                <lb/>rock 200 feet high penetrating the bluff</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 20 W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  2</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">to four trees in a bend on Lard. side</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">North</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  3 ½</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">to the upper part of a timbered bottom on the
                Stard. side
                <lb/>above the entrance of 
                <ref target="n14053110" n="10">
                              <name type="place" key="Eagle (Stonewall) Creek">stone wall [
                <hi rend="italic">EC: Stonewall</hi>] creek</name>
                              <lb/>affording water and 28 yds. wide just above the mouth
                <lb/>of which we encamped.</ref>   at 1 m on this course passed a
                <lb/>
                           <ref target="n14053111" n="11">high stone wall</ref>on Std. 12 feet thick and
                rising 200 feet.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                           <hi rend="right">Miles</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="sum" rows="1" cols="1">18</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.1805-05-31.02">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">May 31st Friday 1805.</hi>
                     <ref target="n14053112" n="12"/>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>A cloudy morning    we dispatched all the Canoes to Collect the meat of 2
          Buffalow killed last night a head and a little off the river, and proceeded on with the
          perogues at an early hour. I attempted to walk on Shore    Soon found it verry
          laborious as the mud Stuck to my mockersons &amp; was verry Slippery. I return'd on
          board.    it continued to rain moderately untill about 12 oClock when it
          ceased, &amp; Continued Cloudy.    the Stone on the edge of the river continue
          to form verry Considerable rapids, we [which] are troublesom &amp; dificuelt to pass,
          our toe rope which we are obliged to make use of altogether broke &amp; we were in Some
          danger of turning over in the perogue in which I was, we landed at 12 and refreshed the
          men with a dram, our men are obliged to under go great labour and fatigue in assending
          this part of the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, as they are compelled from the
          rapidity of the Current in many places to walk in the water &amp; on Slippery hill Sides
          or the Sides of rocks, on Gravel &amp; thro' a Stiff mud bear footed, as they Cannot
          keep on Mockersons from the Stiffness of the mud &amp; decline of the Slipy. hills
          Sides—    The Hills and river Clifts of this day exhibit a most romantick
          appearance    on each Side of the river is a white Soft Sand Stone bluff which
          rises to about half the hight of the hills, on the top of this Clift is a black earth on
          points, in maney places this Sand Stone appears like antient ruins some like elegant
          buildings at a disance, Some like Towers &amp;c. &amp;c.    in maney places of
          this days march we observe on either Side of the river extraodanary walls of a black
          Semented Stone which appear to be regularly placed one Stone on the other, Some of those
          walls run to the hite of 100 feet, they are from about 1 foot to 12 feet thick and are
          perpendicular, those walls Commence at the waters edge &amp; in Some places meet at
          right angles—    those walls appear to Continue their Course into the Sand
          Clifts, the Stones which form those walls are of different Sizes all Squar edged, Great
          numbers has fallen off from the walls near the river which cause the walls to be of
          uneaquil hite, in the evening the Countrey becomes lower and the bottoms wider, no
          timber on the uplands, except a few Cedar &amp; pine on the Clifts a few Scattering
          Cotton trees on the points in the river bottoms, The apparance of Coal Continus
             
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt Lewis</name>walked on Shore &amp;
          observed a Species of Pine we had never before Seen, with a Shorter leaf than Common
          &amp; the bur different, he also Collected Some of the Stone off one of the walls which
          appears to be a Sement of Isin glass black earth    we Camped on the Stard
          Side in a Small timbered bottom above the mouth of a Creek on the Stard Side our hunters
          killed, 2 animals with big horns, 2 Buffalow &amp; an Elk, we Saw Great numbers of those
          big horned animals on the Clifts, but fiew Buffalow or Elk, no antelope, a fiew mule
          deer, Saw a fox to day. The river rises a little    it is from 150 to 250 yds.
          wide</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.1805-05-31.03">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">May 31st Friday 1805</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>Cloudy morning, we proceeded on at an early hour with the two Perogues leaving the
          Canoes and crews to bring on the meat of two Buffalow that were killed last evening and
          which had not been brought in as it was late and a little off the river. Soon after we
          got under way it began to rain and Continued untill 12 oClock when it Seased but Still
          remained cloudy through the ballance of the day.    the obstructions of rocky
          points and riffles Still continue as yesterday; at those places the men are compelled to
          be in the water even to their armpits, and the water is yet very cold, and So frequent
          are those points that they are one fourth of their time in the water.    added
          to this the bank and bluff along which they are obliged to pass are So Slippery and the
          mud So tenatious that they are unable to bare their mockersons, and in that Situation
          dragging the heavy burthen of a Canoe and Walking occasionally for Several hundred yards
          over the Sharp fragments of rocks which tumble from the Clifts; and in Short their
          labour is incredibly painfull and great, yet those faithfull fellows bear it without a
          murmer.</p>
               <p>The toe rope of the white perogue, the only one indeed of hemp, and that on which we
          most depended, gave way to day at a bad point, the perogue Swong and but slightly
          touched a rock, yet was very near oversetting; I fear her evil Ginnie will play So many
          pranks with her that She will go to the bottom Some of those days.</p>
               <p>I attempted to walk on Shore this morning but found it so excessivily bad that I Soon
          returned on board.    at 12 oClock we came too for refreshment and gave the
          men a dram which they received with much Chearfulness, and well deserved all wet and
          disagreeable. 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name>walked on Shore, he
          informed one that he Saw "the most butifull fox in the world" the Colour appeared to him
          to be of a fine Orrange yellow, white and black, he fired at this fox running and missed
          him, he appeared to be about the size of the common red fox of the united States, or
          rather smaller.</p>
               <p>The hills and river clifts which we pass to day exhibit a most romantic appearance.
          The Bluffs of the river rise to the hight of from 2 to 300 feet and in most places
          nearly perpendicular; they are formed of remarkable white Sandstone which is
          Sufficiently Soft to give way readily to the impression of water; two or three thin
          horizontal Stratas of white free Stone, on which the rains or water make no impression,
          lie imbeded in those clifts of Soft Stone near the upper part of them; the earth on the
          top of these clifts is a dark rich loam, which forming a gradual ascending plain extend
          back from ½ a mile to a mile where the hills commence and rise abruptly to the hight of
          about 300 feet more. The water in the Course of time acecending from those hills and
          plains on either Side of the river has trickled down the Soft Sand Clifts and woarn it
          into a thousand grotesque figures; which with the help of a little imagination and an
          oblique view at a distance are made to represent elegant ranges of lofty freestone
          buildings, haveing their parapets well Stocked with Statuary; Colloms of various
          Sculptures both Grooved and plain, are also Seen Supporting long galleries in part of
          those buildings; in other places on a much nearer approach and with the with the help of
          less immagination we See the remains of ruins of eligant buildings; Some Collumns
          Standing and almost entire with their pedestals and Capitals, others retaining their
          pedestals but deprived by time or accedint of their capitals, Some lying prostrate and
          broken, others in the form of vast Pyramids of connic Structure bearing a Serious of
          other pyramids on their tops becomeing less as they ascend and finally termonateing in a
          Sharp point.    nitches and alcoves of various forms and Sizes are Seen at
          different hights as we pass.    a number of the Small martin which build their
          nests with Clay of a globular form attached to the wall within those nitches, and which
          were Seen hovering about the top of the collumns did not the less remind us of Some of
          those large Stone buildings in the United States. The thin Stratas of hard free Stone
          intermixed with the Soft Sand Stone Seems to have aided the water in forming this
          Curious Scenery.</p>
               <p>as we passed on it Seemed as if those Seens of Visionary enchantment would never have
          an end; for here it is too that nature presents to the view of the traveler vast ranges
          of walls of tolerable workmanship, So perfect indeed are those falls [walls] that I
          Should have thought that nature had attempted here to rival the human art of Masonry had
          I not recollected that She had first began her work. These walls rise to the hight in
          many places of 100 feet, are perpindicular, with two regular faces, and are from one to
          12 feet thick, each wall retains the Same thickess to the top which it possesses at
          bottom. The Stone of which these walls are formed is black, dense and dureable, and
          appears to be Composed of a large portion of earth intermixed or Cemented with a Small
          quantity of Sand and a Considerable portion of quarts.    these Stones are
          almost invariably regular parallelepipeds, of unequal Sizes in the wall, but equal in
          their horizontal ranges, at least as to debth.    These are laid regularly in
          ranges on each other like bricks, each breaking or covering this interstice of the two
          on which it rests, thus the pirpendicular interstices are broken, and the horizontal
          ones extend entire throughout the whole extent of the walls. These Stones Seam to bear
          Some proportion to the thickness of the walls in which they are employd, being larger in
          the thicker walls; the greatest length of the parallelepiped appear to form the
          thickness of the thiner walls, while two or more are employed to form that of the
          thicker walls. Those walls pass the river in Several places rising from the waters edge
          much above the 
          <name type="place" key="Sandstone Bluffs">Sand Stone Bluffs</name>, which they Seam to
          penetrate; thence Continueing their course on a Streight line on either Side of the
          river thorough the gradually ascending plains over which they tower to the hight of from
          ten to 90 feet untill they reach the hills which they finally enter and Conceal
          themselves.    these walls Sometimes run parallel to each other, with Several
          ranges near each other, and at other times intersecting each other at right angles,
          haveing the appearance of the walls of ancient houses or gardins.    both 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt Lewis</name>and My self walked on Shore
          this evening and examined those walls minutely and preserved a Specimine of the Stone.—
             I found many clifts of very excellent free Stone of a light yellowish brown
          Colour. 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name>observed a Species of pine
          which I had never Seen, it differs from the pitch pine in the particular of its leaf and
          Cone, the first being partly Shorter, and the latter considerably longer and more
          pointed. The appearance of Coal Continues but in Smaller quantities, but little
          appearance of burnt hills or pumicestone.    the mineral Salt in Some measure
          have abated and no quarts.    we Saw a great number of the Big Horn, Some mule
          deer, and a few Buffalow and Elk, no antelopes or Common Deer—. 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name>killed a Big horn animal.
             the party killed 2 Buffalow one Elk and a Big horn or Ibex to day—. The
          river has been from 150 to 250 yards wide but little timber on the river to day.
             river less muddy than it was below.</p>
               <p>
                  <table rows="16" cols="3">
                     <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Course &amp; Distance May 31st 1805</hi>
                     </head>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">miles</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 45° W</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  2</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">to a fiew trees in a bend Stard. Side</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 80° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">     ½</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">to a fiew trees on the Stard. point</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 80° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">     ¼</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">on the Stard point</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 60° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  1 ¾</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">to the lower part of a timber in a Stard.
                bend.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">West</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">     ¼</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">to a fiew trees on the Stard. Side</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 78° W</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  2</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">to Some trees on the Stard. Side</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">West</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  2</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">to the point on the Stard. Side</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 45° W</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">     ¼</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">on the Stard. point</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 30° W</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">     ¼</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">on the Stard. point opsd. a high Steep black
                rock riseing
                <lb/>from the waters edge</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">North</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  1 ½</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">to a tree in a bend to the Stard. Side opsd. a
                high open
                <lb/>bottom</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 42° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  1</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">to the point on the Stard. Side</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 10° E</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">     ¾</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">to a point on the Lard Side a high black
                Conical rock of
                <lb/>200 feet high on the Std. Sd.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 20° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  2</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">to 4 trees in a bend to the Lard. Side</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">North</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rend="underline" rows="1" cols="1">  3 ½</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">to the upper part of a timbered bottom on the
                Stard. Side
                <lb/>above the mouth of 
                <ref target="n14053113" n="13">Stone wall</ref>Creek which Contains
                <lb/>water    passed a high Stone wall about 200 feet high &amp; 12
                <lb/>feet thick on the Std Side &amp; encamped at the mouth of the
                <lb/>Creek S. S. in a thickly timbered bottom of Small Cotton
                <lb/>Woods    this Creek is a bold Stream of Clear Water</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                           <hi rend="right">miles </hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                           <hi rend="double underline">18</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.1805-05-31.04">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">May 31st Friday 1805</hi>.    a Cloudy morning.   
          the canoes all dispached eairly to collect the meat of 2 buffalow killed last night.
             the perogues proceeded on    it continued to rain moderately
          untill about 12 oClock when it ceased &amp; continued cloudy.    the Stones on
          the edges of the river continue to form very considerable rapids.    we find
          them difficult to pass.    the tow rope of the white perogue which we were
          oblidge to make use of broke &amp; was in Some danger of turning over.    we
          landed at 12 oClock    the Capts. gave the or refreshed the party with a dram
             we are oblidged to undergo great labour and fatigue in ascending this part
          of the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missourie</name>as they are compelled from the
          rapidity of the current in many places to walk in the water &amp; on Slippery hill sides
          on the Sides of rocks &amp;.c.    on gravel &amp; thro Stiff mud, bear footed
          &amp; we cannot keep on moccasons from the Stiffness of the mud &amp; decline of the
          Steepp hill sides—    the hills and river cliffts of this day exhibit a most
          romantick appearence
          <ref target="n14053114" n="14"/>   on each Side of the river is a white Soft
          Sand Stone bluffs which rises to about half the hight of the hills, on the top of this
          Clift is a black earth.    on points in many places this sand Stone appears
          like antient ruins    Some like elegant buildings at a distance, Some like
          Towers &amp;.C. &amp;.C.    in many places of this days march we observe on
          either Side of the river extroardanary walls of a black semented stone which appear to
          be regularly placed one Stone on the other. Some of those walls rise to the hight of 100
          feet.    they are from about 9 foot to 12 feet deep or thick and are
          perpinticular.    those walls commence at the waters edge &amp; in some places
          meet at right angles.    those walls appear to continue thier course into the
          Sand clifts.    the Stone which for those walls are of different Sizes all
          Square edged.    great nombers has fallen from the walls near the river which
          causes the wall of unequal hite, in the hollars &amp; gullies I Saw Some Scrubby ceddr.
             the low walls Strait White &amp; handsom, like ancient elegant buildings.
          towards evening the country becomes lower and the bottoms wider.    no timber
          on the uplands, except a fiew ceddr &amp; pine on the clifts.    a fiew
          Scatering cottonwood trees on the points in the river bottoms. The appearence of coal
          continues. 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name>walked on Shore &amp;
          observed a Species of pine we had never before Seen, with a Shorter leaf than common
          &amp; The burr different, he also collected Some of the Stone of one of the walls which
          appears to be a Siment of Sun glass black earth. we Camped on the Stard. Side in a Small
          timberd handsom bottom above the mouth of a creek on the Stard. Side.    the
          hunters killed 2 animels with big horns.    2 buffalow an Elk &amp; a black
          taild or mule deer.    we Saw a nomber of those big horned animels on the
          clifts.    but fiew buffalow or Elk, no antilope, a fiew mule Deer. Saw a fox
          to day.    the river rises a little    it is from 150 to 
          <hi rend="italic">250</hi>yards wide. Came 18 miles to day.—</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.1805-05-31.05">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Friday 31st.</hi>   We embarked early in a cloudy morning;
          passed through a mountainous country, but the game is more plenty, and we killed some
          buffaloe in our way. About 11 o'clock it began to rain slowly, and continued raining two
          hours, when it cleared up. We passed some very curious cliffs and rocky peaks, in a long
          range. Some of them 200 feet high and not more than eight feet thick. They seem as if
          built by the hand of man, and are so numerous that they appear like the ruins of an
          antient city. We went 17½ miles and encamped at the mouth of a handsome creek on the
          North side.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.1805-05-31.06">
            <sp who="jw">
               <speaker>Whitehouse</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Friday 31st May 1805</hi>.    cloudy.    we Set
          off as usal.    the canoes crossed the river &amp; the men went for the meat
          which was killed last night.    one of the hunters killed an Elk.   
          we proceeded on.    abt. 11 oC. began to rain, rained moderately for Some
          time.    we passed verry high clifts of rocks, halted 〈abt. noon〉 at 12 oC. to
          dine.    our Captains gave each man a draughm of Spirits as it was wet.
             
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name>killed a fat buffaloe,
          &amp; Some of the hunters killed 2 more but lost one of them in the river.   
          abt 1 oC. we proceeded on    passed high white clifts of rocks &amp; Some
          pinecles which is 100 feet high from the Surface of the water.    Some verry
          high black walls of Stone also on each Side of the river, which is curious to See.
             we Saw a brown bear on the N. S.    Some of the hunters went out
          in order to kill it.    passed Straight white clifts of rocks on the S. Side
             Came 17½ miles &amp; Camped at a handsom bottom covered with c. wood timber
          on the N. S. which was the first timber we Saw to day except a fiew Scatering trees
          along the Shore and a fiew ceeders on the hills.    the current has been Swift
          all this day.    the hunters came in at dark had killed 1 black taild. Deer 2
          Ibex or mountain Sheep (rams) which had handsom large horns.    we took care
          of the horns in order to take them back to the U. States.    a pleasant
          evening.    (one man Saw a large pond or Small lake, out in the plains on
          South Side)</p>
               <p>Friday May 31st    We had cloudy weather this morning, one of our Hunters
          went out Early this morning and killed an Elk which was brought to us.—    We
          set off early and proceeded on our Voyage, still towing the Crafts; about 11 o'Clock A.
          M it began to rain, and rained moderately, for some time; We continued on, and passed
          some high Clifts of Rocks, lying on both sides of the River.—    About 12
          o'Clock A. M. we halted to dine, Our Officers gave each Man, a dram of Spirit, they
          being wet and Cold; 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Lewis</name>went out hunting, and
          killed a fat buffalo; and some of the Hunters that was out hunting killed 2 More of
          those Animals, but lost one of them in the River; the Buffalo being brought to us, about
          One o'Clock P. M. we proceeded on our Voyage, and passed high white Clifts of rocks, and
          some high pinnacles which was 100 feet high from the Surface of the Water, and some very
          high black Walls of Stone, lying on each side of the River, which appeared curious, We
          also saw a brown Bear, on the North side of the River; and some of our hunters went out
          in order to kill it, We went on and passed some straight white Clifts of rocks which lay
          on the South side of the River, The current of the River ran very strong, the whole of
          this day, The hunters returned to us in the Evening, they had killed 1 black Tailed
          deer, &amp; 2 Ibex or mountain Sheep, They were 2 Rams and had handsome large Horns,
          those Horns the Officers, had taken care of, in Order to carry them back with us, to the
          United States.—    One of our hunters mention'd of his having seen a very
          large lake, or pond, of water, on the South side of the River.—</p>
               <p>In the Evening, the weather cleared off, and became pleasant; and we encamped, at a
          handsome bottom, covered with Cotton wood, Timber lying on the North side of the River;
          which was the first growth of timber, that we had seen this day; excepting a few
          scattering Trees, along the Shores, and a few Cedar Trees, which grew on the hills, We
          came this day 17½ Miles</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n14053101" n="1">They were within the 
        <name type="place" key="Missouri River, White Cliffs of the">White Cliffs</name>area of
        the 
        <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Breaks of the">Missouri River Breaks</name>, in 
        <name type="place" key="Chouteau County, Mont.">Chouteau County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>. 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>maps 41, 53, 60, 61; MRC map 74. Subsequent travelers were
        also impressed with the "romantic appearance" of these cliffs and over the years names
        have been applied to the more prominent formations. The names are given in notes that
        follow as 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>make reference to the formations.
        During the glacial period, ice forced the 
        <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri River</name>to cut a new channel from
        near 
        <name type="place" key="Virgelle, Mont.">Virgelle</name>to 
        <name type="place" key="Fort Peck Dam">Fort Peck Dam</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>. The channel here has been cut more than
        three hundred feet deep through late Cretaceous formations of the Claggett Shale, 
        <name type="place" key="Eagle Sandstone">Eagle Sandstone</name>, and Marias River Shale.
        The most conspicuous of these is the nearly white sandstone of the Virgelle Member of the 
        <name type="place" key="Eagle Sandstone">Eagle Sandstone</name>. Red-brown iron
        concretions up to eight feet in diameter occur at the top of the Virgelle Member in many
        places. The concretions are very resistant to erosion and protect the softer, underlying
        sandstone. Sandstone not protected by concretions erodes away leaving columns and pillars
        of white sandstone. Various degrees of protection by overlying materials has produced a
        variety of geometric figures.</note>
            <note xml:id="n14053102" n="2">The cliff swallow, 
        <hi rend="italic">Hirundo pyrrhonota</hi>[AOU, 612]. Holmgren, 32.</note>
            <note xml:id="n14053103" n="3">Intruded into the Claggett Shale, 
        <name type="place" key="Eagle Sandstone">Eagle Sandstone</name>, and Marias River Shale
        that flank the river are numerous, near-vertical sheets of igneous rock (shonkinite)
        called dikes. Their average width is about four feet. The dikes greatly resist erosion
        and, consequently, stand out from the surrounding sedimentary formations rather like
        walls. They contain no talc or quartz.</note>
            <note xml:id="n14053104" n="4">The term "freestone" was used to describe any easily cut or
        quarried limestone or sandstone. The rock described here belongs to the 
        <name type="place" key="Eagle Sandstone">Eagle Sandstone</name>, especially the Virgelle
        Member. Someone, perhaps 
        <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>, drew a red vertical line through
        the passages that begin, "I found the face" to "kill this animal."</note>
            <note xml:id="n14053105" n="5">These are the needles and cones of 
        <hi rend="italic">Pinus flexilis</hi>James, limber pine. This locality is a range
        extension from the nearest present known locality in the 
        <name type="place" key="Little Belt Mountains">Little Belt Mountains</name>, approximately
        fifty miles to the south. Limber pine is typically found growing in exposed, rocky
        locations at middle elevations east of the continental divide and reaches outward onto the
        
        <name type="place" key="Great Plains">Great Plains</name>in this area of central 
        <name type="place" key="Chouteau County, Mont.">Chouteau County</name>. Little, 56-W;
        Hahn, 
        <hi rend="italic">Pinus</hi>map.</note>
            <note xml:id="n14053106" n="6">Not a distinct species as 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>supposed, but a cross fox, a color
        phase of the red fox, 
        <hi rend="italic">Vulpes vulpes.</hi>Burroughs, 91, 321 n. 7; Jones et al., 258–61.</note>
            <note xml:id="n14053107" n="7">The upper, unnamed, member of the 
        <name type="place" key="Eagle Sandstone">Eagle Sandstone</name>contains several thin beds
        of coal. The 
        <name type="place" key="Eagle Sandstone">Eagle Sandstone</name>contains a few salts and no
        selenite. Some salts are derived from the overlying Claggett Shale.</note>
            <note xml:id="n14053108" n="8">Also given on 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>map 41, in 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>hand.</note>
            <note xml:id="n14053109" n="9">Later 
        <name type="place" key="Citadel Rock">Citadel Rock</name>, in 
        <name type="place" key="Chouteau County, Mont.">Chouteau County</name>, and marked on 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>maps 41, 53, 60; MRC map 74.</note>
            <note xml:id="n14053110" n="10">
               <name type="place" key="Eagle (Stonewall) Creek">Stonewall Creek</name>is present 
        <name type="place" key="Eagle (Stonewall) Creek">Eagle Creek</name>, in 
        <name type="place" key="Chouteau County, Mont.">Chouteau County</name>. The camp was above
        its mouth on the same side. 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>maps 41, 53, 60; MRC map 74.</note>
            <note xml:id="n14053111" n="11">Probably later 
        <name type="place" key="Grand Natural Wall">Grand Natural Wall</name>, in 
        <name type="place" key="Chouteau County, Mont.">Chouteau County</name>. 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>maps 41, 53, 60; MRC map 74.</note>
            <note xml:id="n14053112" n="12">This entry is found at the end of 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>notebook journal Voorhis No. 1. His
        other entry for the day, which is the regular sequence of daily entries in the same
        journal, is largely copied from 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, but it is the only one of the
        two that has the courses and distances for the day. It is not clear which was composed
        first.</note>
            <note xml:id="n14053113" n="13">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>appears to have interpolated the
        words "Stone wall."</note>
            <note xml:id="n14053114" n="14">
               <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, copying from 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>who copied this passage from 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, describes the 
        <name type="place" key="Missouri River, White Cliffs of the">White Cliffs</name>area of
        the 
        <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Breaks of the">Missouri River Breaks</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Chouteau County, Mont.">Chouteau County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-05-30" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-05-31-1" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
