<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-01-14">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">January 14, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic
        Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            6</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">November 2, 1805–March 22, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1990</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">203-206</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">267</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">188</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jw">Joseph Whitehouse</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            11</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of Joseph Whitehouse, May 14, 1804–April 2,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1997</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">413</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Journal Entries</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-08-09</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-04-12</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1806-01-14">January 14, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-01-14.01" ref="">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Wednesday</hi>[
              <hi rend="italic">NB: Tuesday</hi>] 
              <hi rend="italic">January 14th 1806.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>This morning the Sergt. of the Guard reported the absence of one of the large
          perogues, it had broken the chord by which it was attatched and the tide had taken it
          off; we sent a party immediately in surch of her, they returned in about 3 hours having
          fortunately found her.    we now directed three of the perogues to be drawn up
          out of reach of the tide and the fourth to be mored in the small branch just above the
          landing and confined with a strong rope of Elk-skin.    had we lost this
          perogue also we should have been obliged to make three small ones, which with the few
          tools we have now left would be a serious undertaking.    a fatieuge of 6 men
          employed injerking the Elk beaf.</p>
               <p>From the best estimate we were enabled to make as we dscended the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>was conceived that the natives
          inhabiting that noble stream, for some miles above the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Great Falls of the">great falls</name>to the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Cascades (Great Rapids, Great Shute)">grand
          rappids</name>inclusive annually prepare about 30,000 lbs. of pounded sammon for market.
             but whether this fish is an article of comerce with the whites or is
          exclusively sold to and consumed by the natives of the sea Coast, we are at a loss to
          determine.    the first of those positions I am disposed to credit most, but,
          still I must confess that I cannot imagine what the white merchant's object can be in
          purchasing this fish, or wher they dispose of it.    and on the other hand the
          Indians in this neighbourhood as well as the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skillutes</name>have an abundance of
          dryed sammon which they take in the creeks and inlets, and I have never seen any of this
          pounded fish in their lodges, which I pesume would have been the case if they purchase
          this pounded fish for their own consumption.    the Indians who prepared this
          dryed and pounded fish, informed us that it was to trade with the whites, and shewed us
          many articles of European manufacture which they obtained for it.    it is
          true they obtain those articles principally for their fish but they trade with the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skillutes</name>for them and not
          immediately with the whites; the intermediates merchants and carryers, the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skillutes</name>, may possibly consume
          a part of this fish themselves and dispose of the ballance of it the natives of the sea
          coast, and from them obtain such articles as they again trade with the whites.
          <ref target="n27011401" n="1"/>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-01-14.02" ref="">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Tuesday 14th January 1806</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>This morning the Serjt. of the guard reported the absence of one of our Canoes
             it had broken the Cord by which it was attached and the tide had taken her
          off; we Sent a party imediately in Serch of her, they returned in about 3 hours haveing
          fortunately found her.    we now derect that 3 of the [canoes] be drawed up
          out of reach of the tide and the 4th to be tied with a long Strong Cord of Elk Skins,
          ready for use.    had we lost this large Canoe we Should have been obliged to
          make 3 other Small ones, which with the fiew tools we have now left would be a Serious
          undertakeing.    a fatiege of Six men employd in jurking the Elk beef. From
          the best estermate we were enabled to make as we decended the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>we Conceived that the natives
          inhabiting that noble Stream (from the enterance of 
          <name type="place" key="Lewis (Cahwahnakiooks) River">Lewis's river</name>to the
          neighbourhood of the falls the nativs Consume all the fish they Catch either for food or
          fuel)    From Tow ar ne hi ooks
          <ref target="n27011402" n="2"/>River or a fiew mils above the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Great Falls of the">Great falls</name>to the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Cascades (Great Rapids, Great Shute)">grand
          rapids</name>inclusive anually prepare about 30,000 lbs of pounded fish (Chiefly Salmon)
          for market, but whether this fish is an article of Commerce with their neighbours or is
          exclusively Sold to, and Consumed by the nativs of the Sea coast, we are at a loss to
          determine    the latter of those positions I am dispose to credit most, as I
          cannot imagine what the white merchents objet Could be in purchaseing fish, or where
          they Could dispose of it. on the other hand the Indians in this neighbourhood as well as
          the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skillutes</name>and those above have an
          abundance of Dryed Salmon which they take in the Creeks and inlets.    they
          are excessively fond of the pounded fish haveing frequently asked us for Some of it—.
             the Indians who prepared this pounded fish made Signs that they traded it
          with people below them for Beeds and trinkets &amp;c and Showed us maney articles of
          European manufacture which they obtained for it; The 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skillutes</name>and Indians about the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Cascades (Great Rapids, Great Shute)">great
          rapids</name>are the intermediate merchants and Carryers, and no doubt Consume a part of
          this fish themselves and dispose of the ballance of it to the natives of the Sea coast,
          and from this obtain Such articles as they again trade with the whites.</p>
               <p>The persons who usially visit the enterence of this river for the purpose of traffic
          or hunting, I believe is either English or Americans; the Indians inform us that they
          Speak the Same language with our Selves, and gave us proofs of their varacity by
          repeating maney words of English, Sun of a pitch &amp;c. [
          <hi rend="italic">NB: heave the lead</hi>
                  <ref target="n27011403" n="3"/>
                  <hi rend="italic">&amp; maney blackguard phrases</hi>] whether those traders are from 
          <name type="place" key="Nootka Sound">Nootka Sound</name>, from Some other late
          establishment on this Coast, or imediately from the U States or 
          <name type="place" key="Britain">Great Britain</name>, I am at a loss to determine, nor
          Can the Indians inform us.    the Indians whome I have asked in what direction
          the traders go when they depart from hence, allways point to the S. W. from which it is
          prosumeable that Nootka cannot be their distination, and from Indian information a
          majority of those traders annually visit them about the beginning of April and remain
          Some time and either remain or revisit them in the fall of which I cannot properly
          understand, from this Circumstance they Cannot Come directly from the U States or 
          <name type="place" key="Britain">Great Brittain</name>, the distance being to great for
          them to go and return in the ballance of a year. I am Sometimes induced to believe that
          there is Some other Establishment on the Coast of America 
          <hi rend="italic">South</hi>of this place of which little is but yet known to the world,
          or it may be perhaps on Some Island in 
          <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">the Pacific Ocian</name>between the Continant of
          America &amp; Asia to the S. W. of us. This traffic on the part of the whites Consist in
          vending, guns, principally old British or American Musquets, powder, balls and Shote,
          〈Copper and brass Kettles,〉 brass tea kettles, Blankets from two to three points,
          Scarlet and blue Cloth (Coarse), plates and Strips of Sheet Copper and brass, large
          brass wire Knives Beeds &amp; Tobacco with fishing hooks, buttons and Some other Small
          articles; also a considerable quantity of Salors Clothes, as hats, Coats, Trouses and
          Shirts.    for those they receive in return from the nativs Dressed and
          undresed Elk Skins, Skins of the Sea otter, Common Otter, beaver, common fox, 〈Speck,
          and〉 [
          <hi rend="italic">NB: Spotted or</hi>] tiger Cat, also Some Salmon dried or pounded and
          a kind of buisket, [
          <hi rend="italic">NB: the native dispose of some of these biscuits    not a
          great article of trade</hi>] which the nativs make of roots called by them Shappelell.
          The nativs are extra-vigantly fond of the most Common Cheap Blue and white beeds, of
          moderate Size, or Such that from 50 to 70 will way one pennyweight, the blue is usially
          prefured to the white; those beeds Constitute the principal Circulating medium with all
          the Indian tribes on this river; for those beeds they will dispose of any article they
          possess—.    the beeds are Strung on Strans of a fathom in length &amp; in
          that manner Sold by the breth [
          <hi rend="italic">NB: arms length or double arms length</hi>] or yard—.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-01-14.03" ref="">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>Tuesday 14th    the tide water took away one of our canoes but we Soon
          found it again.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-01-14.04" ref="">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Tuesday 14th.</hi>   The morning was pleasant; and two men
          were sent to the 
          <name type="place" key="Saltmaking Camp (Oreg.)">salt works</name>to assist in making
          salt. The rest of our people were employed in drying and taking care of the meat; and in
          dressing elk skins for mokasins, which is a laborious business, but we have no
          alternative in this part of the country.
          <ref target="n27011504" n="4"/>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-01-14.05" ref="">
            <sp who="jw">
               <speaker>Whitehouse</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>Tuesday Janry 14th    A fine pleasant morning.    One of our
          Canoes got loose from the landing last night, but we found her this morning up a Creek,
          where the Tide water had taken her.    Six of our Men are employed in Jerking
          Meat the remainder dressing Skins &amp;ca.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n27011401" n="1">Under this date Biddle has additional information on trade
        with Americans, probably from conversations with 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>in 1810. 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>Notes [ca. April 1810],
        Jackson, (LLC), 2:541.</note>
            <note xml:id="n27011402" n="2">The term appears to have been placed into a previously
        blank space.</note>
            <note xml:id="n27011403" n="3">To throw a weighted line from a ship to determine the
        water's depth.</note>
            <note xml:id="n27011504" n="4">
               <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name>means that the Indians of this region
        did not make moccasins, forcing the party to make their own.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-01-13" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-01-15" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
