<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.1806-08-30">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">August 30, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic
        Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            8</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">June 10–September 26, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1987</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">329-332</biblScope>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">355-356</biblScope>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">274</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
         <geoDecl datum="WGS">
            <placeName/>
            <geo>43.3667 -99.1</geo>
            <note>Camped between Gregory and Charles Mix Counties, SD, near the later Hot Springs Island.</note>
         </geoDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc/>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-12-20</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-04-12</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date>August 30, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.1806-08-30.01">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Saturday 30th of August 1806</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name>is mending Slowly.
             we set out at the usial hour and proceeded on very well a fiew miles
             
          <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Jo Field</name>who was on the Shore being behind
          I derected one of the Small Canoes with 
          <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">R. Fields</name>&amp; 
          <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name>to continue on the point of a
          Sand bar untill he coms up. I took 3 hunters and walked on the N E Shore with a view to
          kill Some fat meet.    we had not proceeded far before Saw a large plumb orchd
          of the most deelicious plumbs, out of this orchard 2 large Buck Elks ran the hunters
          killed them. I Stoped the Canoes and brought in the flesh which was fat and fine.
             here the party Collected as many plumbs as they could eate and Several
          pecks of which they put by &amp;c.    after a delay of nearly 2 hours we again
          proceeded on downwards    passed 3 Small Islands and as we were about to land
          at the place appointed to wait for the 
          <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph and Reubin">2 fields</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name>, I saw Several men on horseback
          which with the help of a Spie glass I found to be Indians on the high hills to the N E
             we landed on the S. W. Side and I sent out two men to a village of Barking
          Squirels to kill Some of those animals imedeatily after landing about 20 indians was
          discovered on an eminanc a little above us on the opposite Side.    one of
          those men I took to be a freinch man from his a blanket Capoe &amp; a handkerchief
          around his head.    imediately after 80 or 90 Indian men all armed with fusees
          &amp; Bows &amp; arrows Came out of a wood on the opposite bank about ¼ of a mile below
          us.    they fired of their guns as a Salute we returned the Salute with 2
          rounds.    we were at a loss to deturmin of what nation those indians were.
             from their hostile appearance we were apprehensive they were 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Tetons</name>.    but
          from the Country through which they roved we were willing to believe them eithe the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Yankton">Yanktons</name>, 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Ponca Indians">Ponars</name>or 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Mahars</name>
                  <ref target="n39083001" n="1"/>either of which nations are well disposed towards the
          white people. I deturmined to find out who they were without running any resque of the
          party and indians, and therefore took three french men
          <ref target="n39083002" n="2"/>who could Speak the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Mahar</name>
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Pawnee Indians">Pania</name>and some 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Seioux</name>and in a Small canoe I went
          over to a Sand bar which extended Sufficently near the opposite Shore to Converse.
             imedeately after I Set out 3 young men Set out from the opposite Side and
          Swam next me on the Sand bar. I derected the men to Speak to them in the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Pawnee Indians">Pania</name>and 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">mahar</name>Languages first neither of
          which they could understand    I then derected the man who could Speak a fiew
          words of 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Seioux</name>to inquire what nation or
          tribe they belong to they informed me that they were 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Tetons</name>and their Chief was 
          <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo">Tar-tack-kah-sabbar</name>
                  </hi>or the 
          <name type="place" key="Black Buffalo">black buffalow</name>
                  <ref target="n39083003" n="3"/>   This Chief I knew very well to be the one
          we had seen with his band at 
          <name type="place" key="Bad (Teton) River (S. Dak.)">Teton river</name>which band had
          attempted to detain us in the fall of 1804 as we assended this river and with whome we
          wer near comeing to blows. I told those Indians that they had been deef to our councils
          and ill treated us as we assended this river two years past, that they had abused all
          the whites who had visited them since. I believed them to be bad people &amp; Should not
          Suffer them to cross to the Side on which the party lay, and directed them to return
          with their band to their Camp, that if any of them come near our camp we Should kill
          them certainly. I lef them on the bear and returned to th party and examined the arms
          &amp;c.    those indians seeing Some Corn in the Canoe requested Some of it
          which I refused being deturmined to have nothing to do with those people. Several others
          Swam across one of which understood 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Pawnee Indians">pania</name>, and as our 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Pawnee Indians">pania</name>interpreter was a very good
          one we had it in our power to inform what we wished. I told this man to inform his
          nation that we had not forgot their treatment to us as we passed up this river &amp;c.
             that they had treated all the white people who had visited them very badly;
          robed them of their goods, and had wounded one man
          <ref target="n39083004" n="4"/>whome I had Seen. we viewed them as bad people and no
          more traders would be Suffered to come to them, and whenever the white people wished to
          visit the nations above they would Come Sufficiently Strong to whip any vilenous party
          who dare to oppose them and words to the Same purpote. I also told them that I was
          informed that a part of all their bands were gorn to war against the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>&amp;c, and that they
          would be well whiped as the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>&amp; 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Menetarres</name>&amp; had a plenty of
          Guns Powder and ball, and we had given them a Cannon to defend themselves.   
          and derected them to return from the Sand bar and inform their Chiefs what we had Said
          to them, and to keep away from the river or we Should kill every one of them &amp;c.
          &amp;c.    those fellows requested to be allowed to Come aecross and make
          Cumerads which we positively refused and I directed them to return imediately which they
          did and after they had informed the Chiefs &amp;c. as I Suppose what we had Said to
          them, they all Set out on their return to their Camps back of a high hill.   
          7 of them halted on the top of the hill and blackguarded us, told us to come across and
          they would kill us all &amp;c. of which we took no notice.    we all this time
          were extreamly anxious for the arival of the 
          <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph and Reubin">2 fields</name>&amp; 
          <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name>whome we had left behind, and
          were Some what consd. as to their Safty.    to our great joy those men hove in
          Sight at 6 P. M. 
          <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Jo. Fields</name>had killed 3 black tail or mule
          deer.    we then Set out, as I wished to See what those Indians on the hill
          would act.    we Steared across near the opposit Shore, this notion put them
          Some agitation as to our intentions, some Set out on the direction towards their Camps
             others walked about on the top of the hill and one man walked down the hill
          to meet us and invited us to land to which invitation I paid no kind of attention.
             this man I knew to be the one who had in the fall 1804 accompaned us 2 days
          and is Said to be the friend to the white people.
          <ref target="n39083005" n="5"/>   after we passd. him he returned on the top
          of the hill and gave 3 Strokes with the gun [
          <hi rend="italic">NB?: on the earth—this is swearing by the earth</hi>] he had in his
          hand    this I am informed is a great oath among the indians.
          <ref target="n39083006" n="6"/>   we proceeded on down about 6 miles and
          encamped on a large Sand bar in the middle of the river
          <ref target="n39083007" n="7"/>about 2 miles above our encampment on Mud Island on the
          10th Septr. 1804 haveing made 22 miles only to Day. Saw Several Indians on the hills at
          a distance this evening viewing us.    our 〈camp〉 encampment of this evening
          was a very disagreable one, bleak exposed to the winds, and the Sand wet. I pitched on
          this Situation to prevent being disturbed by those 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Scioux</name>in the Course of the night
          as well as to avoid the Musquetors—.    Killed 9 whisteling squirels.
          <ref target="n39083008" n="8"/>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.1806-08-30.02">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>Saturday 30th August 1806.    we set out eairly and procd on as usal
             abt. 9 A. M. we halted and killed one buffaloe and 2 deer.    the
          buffaloe verry pleanty.    procd. on Some distance further halted and killed
          two Elk and gathered a quantity of fine plumbs.    then procd. on.
             three of our hunters
          <ref target="n39083009" n="9"/>Stayed back with a Small canoe to try and kill Some
          black taild deer.    about [
          <hi rend="italic">blank</hi>] oClock P. M. we discovred a number of Indians on the hills
          on the North Side, and Soon gathered about two hundred on the Shore besides Some boys
          and young men    they were in a body and had a great number of horses
             we landed on the opposite side of the river.    the Savages
          hooping and fired &amp; we answered them by fireing our blunderbusses and Small arms 2
          rounds.    we concluded to wait here for the hunters to come up.   
          a number of Indians Set to Swiming the river to us but 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name>took three men in a Small
          canoe met them on a Sand bar which happened to be near our Side    one of our
          men Spoke to them in 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Pawnee Indians">pania</name>tongue and told them that we
          could not Speak their Language but Soon found that they were the Same band of 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Tetons</name>
                  <ref target="n39083010" n="10"/>that held our boat as we passed up the river
             
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name>told them and Signed to them
          that they were bad Indians and treated the white people bad and they might keep from us
          for we would have nothing to Say to them nor Suffer them to come to our Canoes.
             they then Signed to the rest of the nation to keep back and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name>returnd.    the
          most of the Indians returned to the nation    2 or three Stayed on the bar a
          while and Signed that they were friends to us and wished to have us come over to their
          Side but we Signed to them to keep off and to go back that we would not hear them
          &amp;C.    they then all returned to the band and called over to us. Mrs. 
          <name type="person" key="Jusseaume, René">Jessom</name>
                  <ref target="n39083011" n="11"/>could understand Some words they said and he heared
          them Say that if we came on their Side of the river they would kill us &amp; that we
          were good for to kill &amp;C.    at length the Savages or the main body of
          them went their way    our hunters came up    had killed three black
          taild deer.    we then set out and procd. on    several Indians
          remaining on Shore called to us and Signed and beckned to us to come to Shore but we
          passed them Safe and procd on untill dark and Camped on a large Sand bar   
          two Sentinels placed to guard the Camp.—</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.1806-08-30.03">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Saturday 30th.</hi>   We had a pleasant morning, and went on
          early, three hunters
          <ref target="n39083012" n="12"/>starting ahead. We killed some buffaloe and elk in our
          way, and about 2 o'clock, we met a band of the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teetons</name>, fifty or sixty in
          number, and halted on the opposite side of the river as we did not wish to have any
          intercourse with them. Here we waited for three hunters, who were behind; and during our
          stay eight or nine of the Indians swam to a sand-bar about sixty yards from us, and we
          found that they were the same rascals, who had given us trouble as we went up. We could
          not converse with them, but one of our men understanding the language of the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Pawnee Indians">Ponis</name>,
          <ref target="n39083013" n="13"/>of which they understood some words; we through him let
          them know that we wanted to have nothing to do with them; and that if they troubled us,
          we would kill every one of them. They then withdrew, and the whole party left the river
          and went off to the hills. Our three hunters returned, and we proceeded on, and in the
          evening encamped on a sand bar in the river.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n39083001" n="1">The last two would be 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Ponca Indians">Poncas</name>and 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Omahas</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n39083002" n="2">Two of them would surely be 
        <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Pierre Cruzatte</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Labiche, François">François Labiche</name>; the other might be 
        <name type="person" key="Jusseaume, René">Jusseaume</name>, or perhaps 
        <name type="person" key="Lepage, Jean Baptiste">Jean Baptiste Lepage</name>could speak one
        of these languages. 
        <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>seems to indicate that 
        <name type="person" key="Jusseaume, René">Jusseaume's</name>wife played an important part
        in this episode, though it is hard to tell from the manuscript whether the husband or wife
        was involved. 
        <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway's</name>words read, "Mrs 
        <name type="person" key="Jusseaume, René">Jessom</name>could understand Some words they
        Said and he heared them Say that if we came on their Side of the river they would kill us
        &amp; that we were good for to kill &amp;c."</note>
            <note xml:id="n39083003" n="3">For 
        <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo">Black Buffalo</name>, see 
        <ref n="1804-09-25" type="related">September 25</ref>–
        <ref n="1804-09-28" type="related">28</ref>, 1804.</note>
            <note xml:id="n39083004" n="4">
               <name type="person" key="Dickson, Joseph">Joseph Dickson</name>; See 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>entry, 
        <ref n="1806-08-11" type="related">August 11, 1806</ref>, and 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>entry for 
        <ref n="1806-08-12" type="related">August 12</ref>, 1806.</note>
            <note xml:id="n39083005" n="5">
               <name type="person" key="Buffalo Medicine (Tar-ton-gar-wa-ker)">Buffalo Medicine</name>;
        see 
        <ref n="1804-09-24" type="related">September 24, 1804</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n39083006" n="6">The earth was one of the four Superior Gods, together with
        the rock, the sky, and the sun. Hassrick, 207. 
        <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>underlined a few words in red ink
        in these passages about the oath; they are not so underlined here.</note>
            <note xml:id="n39083007" n="7">This camp was between 
        <name type="place" key="Gregory County, S. Dak.">Gregory</name>and 
        <name type="place" key="Charles Mix County, S. Dak.">Charles Mix</name>counties, 
        <name type="place" key="South Dakota">South Dakota</name>, in the vicinity of the later 
        <name type="place" key="Hot Springs Island">Hot Springs Island</name>, probably the "
        <name type="place" key="Bull Island">Bull Island</name>" of 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>map 20; the camp of 
        <ref n="1804-09-10" type="related">September 10, 1804</ref>, was on 
        <name type="place" key="Pocahontas Island">Pocahontas</name>, or 
        <name type="place" key="Toehead Island">Toehead Island</name>. The site would now be
        inundated by 
        <name type="place" key="Fort Randall Reservoir">Fort Randall Reservoir</name>. Cf. Mattes
        (FR), 505–6; MRC map 35.</note>
            <note xml:id="n39083008" n="8">"Whistling squirrel" seems to have been the captains' name
        for the Columbian ground squirrel of the Rocky Mountains. Here 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>means the prairie dog.</note>
            <note xml:id="n39083009" n="9">The 
        <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph and Reubin">Field brothers</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name>, according to 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n39083010" n="10">The incident with the 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton Sioux</name>occurred on 
        <ref n="1804-09-25" type="related">September 25, 1804</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n39083011" n="11">
               <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>may mean "Mr." here or he may have
        been using a form of "Messrs." incorrectly. Another possibility is that 
        <name type="person" key="Jusseaume, René">Jusseaume's</name>wife was aiding in the
        communication.</note>
            <note xml:id="n39083012" n="12">
               <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>says he accompanied this hunting
        party.</note>
            <note xml:id="n39083013" n="13">
               <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name>may mean either 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Ponca Indians">Ponca</name>or 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Pawnee Indians">Pawnee</name>, and the latter could refer
        to the 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name>, who were of the same
        Caddoan language family as the 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Pawnee Indians">Pawnees</name>. 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>is not much help here.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-08-29" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-08-31" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
