<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1804-11-29">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
November 29, 1804</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               
               
               
               
               
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml" n="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc" n="Clark, William">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 3</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">August 25, 1804–April 6, 1805</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1987</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">242-243</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo" n="Ordway, John">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf" n="Floyd, Charles">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">99</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg" n="Gass, Patrick">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">63-64</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
         <geoDecl datum="WGS" xml:id="lc.geo.1804-11-29.01">
            <placeName/>
            <geo>47.2893 -101.3295</geo>
            <note>The company backtracks to the site of Fort Mandan, between the first and second villages they came across. About 14 miles west of Washburn, ND. They remained here for the winter and set out again on 1805-04-07</note>
         </geoDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Journal Entries</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-03-25</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1804-11-29">November 29, 1804</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1804-11-29.01" n="lc.geo.1804-11-29.01">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>29th <hi rend="italic">November Thursday</hi> 1804</date>
               </ab>
               <p>
A verry Cold windey day wind from the N. W by W.    Some Snow last night    the Detpt of the Snow is various in the wood about 13 inches, The river Closed at the Village above and fell last night two feet    <name type="person" key="Larocque, François-Antoine">Mr. <hi rend="italic">La Rock</hi>
                  </name> and one of his men Came to visit us    we informed him what we had herd of his intentions of makeing Chiefs &amp;c. and forbid him to give meadels or flags to the Indians, he Denied haveing any Such intention, we agreeed that one of our interpeters Should Speak for him on Conditions he did not Say any thing more than what tended to trade alone—    he gave fair promises &amp;.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Sergeant Pryor</name> in takeing down the mast put his Sholder out of Place, we made four trials before we replaced it<ref target="n08112901" n="1"/>    a Cold after noon wind as usial N W.    river begin to rise a little—
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1804-11-29.02" n="lc.geo.1804-11-29.01">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Thursday 29th Nov</hi>.    the Snow fell yesterday and last night about 12 Inches on a level.    a cold Frosty clear morning.    2 or 3 men out hunting.    the River fell abt. 2 feet last night So that our Boat lay dry on Shore.    we took out the mast &amp; every thing which was in hir &amp; let hir lay as She appeared to be Safe.    one of the hunters killed an old Elk    brot. in the horns which were verry large, but it being poor we did not go for the meat.

</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1804-11-29.03" n="lc.geo.1804-11-29.01">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Thursday 29th.</hi>    This day was clear, but cold. We went to unrig the boat, and by an accident one of the sergeants had his shoulder dislocated.<ref target="n08112902" n="2"/> The 30th the weather continued the same. Early in the morning of this day we saw an Indian on the opposite side of the river, and brought him over. He informed us that, a few days ago, eight of his nation were out hunting, and were attacked by a party of the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name> tribe, who killed one and wounded two more; and also carried off their horses. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain Clarke</name> and twenty-three men immediately set out with an intention of pursuing the murderers. They went up to the first village of the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>, but their warriors did not seem disposed to turn out. They suggested the coldness of the weather; that the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name> were too far gone to be overtaken; and put off the expedition to the spring of the year. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain Clarke</name> and his party returned the same evening to the fort. We have been daily visited by the Indians since we came here. Our fort is called <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name>, and by observation is in latitude 47. 21. 32. 8.<ref target="n08112903" n="3"/>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n08112901" n="1">The treatment was apparently imperfect. <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Pryor</name> would suffer repeated dislocations of the shoulder during the expedition, and in 1827 <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> reported him as disabled by the injury. Chuinard (OOMD), 257–58 and n. 5; <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> to James Barbour, August 4, 1827, Jackson (LLC), 2:646.</note>
            <note xml:id="n08112902" n="2">
               <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Pryor</name>; see <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> entry for this date.</note>
           <note xml:id="n08112903" n="3">This latitude must be from the captains' observation of <ref n="lc.jrn.1804-11-11" type="related">November 11, 1804</ref>. <name type="person" key="McKeehan, David">McKeehan's</name> note: "The course of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, and distances of places on it appear to be very erroneously laid down upon the maps of Louisiana generally. On these the villages of the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name> are placed in about 43½ degrees north latitude and 112½ of west longitude from Greenwich. This would place them about 500 miles nearer the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> on <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">the Pacific</name> ocean, than the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>: supposing the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> to be about 124 degrees west of <name type="place" key="London">London</name>. But the nearest practicable route from the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> villages to the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>, according to <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain Clarke's</name> estimate, places them 335 miles nearer the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> than that of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>; and by the route actually taken by the expedition to the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>, they are 900 miles nearer the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>.
             
             <p>
           
"By <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Lewis's</name> observations these villages are in latitude 47. 21. 32. 8. and according to <name type="person" key="Mackenzie, Alexander">Mr. Mackenzie</name>, <name type="person" key="Thompson, David">Mr. Thompson</name> astronomer to the North West company, in the year 1798, determined the northern bend of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> to be in latitude 47. 32. north, and longitude 101. 25. west. Now this is probably near the longitude of the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> villages; for as it appears by the above statement, and by other observations of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Lewis</name> nearer the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, that the course up the river is, for a considerable distance, nearly due west, and afterwards nearly due north, the difference of longitude and latitude, between the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> and the point where <name type="person" key="Thompson, David">Mr. Thompson</name> took his observations, may be added together, in estimating the distance: and this will give about 8½ degrees of latitude [a]nd 9 degrees of longitude making in the whole 17½ degrees, which from the very meandring course of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, may be sufficient to include 1610 miles of it, the distance from the mouth to the villages. In the map of North America included in the Atlas accompanying Pinkerton's Geography, published in 1804, this part of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> appears pretty accurately laid down; but in the map of Louisiana in the same set it is equally erroneous with any other."
             </p> </note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1804-11-16-28" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1804-11-30" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
