<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.1805-06-18">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">June 18, 1805</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic
        Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            4</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">April7–July 27, 1805</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1987</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">305-309</biblScope>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">170</biblScope>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">103-104</biblScope>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            11</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of Joseph Whitehouse, May 14, 1804–April 2,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1997</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">202-203</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc/>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-02-04</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-04-12</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date>June 18, 1805</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.1805-06-18.01">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Tuesday June 18th 1805.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>This morning I employed all hands in drawing the perogue on shore in a thick bunch of
          willow bushes some little distance below our camp; fastened her securely, drove out the
          plugs of the gage holes of her bottom and covered her with bushes and driftwood to
          shelter her from the sun. I now scelected a place for a cash and set tree men at work to
          complete it, and employed all others except those about the waggons, in overhawling
          airing and repacking our indian goods ammunicion, provision and stores of every
          discription which required inspection.    examined the frame of my Iron boat
          and found all the parts complete except one screw, which the ingenuity of 
          <name type="person" key="Shields, John">Sheilds</name>can readily replace, a resource
          which we have very frequent occasion for.    about 12 O'Clk. the hunters
          returned; they had killed 10 deer but no Elk. I begin to fear that we shall have some
          difficulty in procuring skins for the boat. I wold prefer those of the Elk because I
          beleive them more durable and strong than those of the Buffaloe, and that they will not
          shrink so much in drying.    we saw a herd of buffaloe come down to water at
          the sulpher spring this evening, I dispatched some hunters to kill some of them, and a
          man also for a cask of mineral water.    the hunters soon killed two of them
          in fine order and returned with a good quantity of the flesh, having left the remainder
          in a situation that it will not spoil provided the wolves do not visit it. The waggons
          are completed this evening, and appear as if they would answer the purpose very well if
          the axetrees prove sufficiently strong.    the wind blew violently this
          evening, as they frequently do in this open country where there is not a tree to brake
          or oppose their force. 
          <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">The Indian woman</name>is recovering fast
             she set up the greater part of the day and walked out for the fist time
          since she arrived here; she eats hartily and is free from fever or pain. I continue same
          course of medecine and regimen except that I added one doze of 15 drops of the oil of
          vitriol
          <ref target="n15061801" n="1"/>today about noon.</p>
               <p>There is a species of 
          <ref target="n15061802" n="2">goosberry which grows very common about here in open
          situations among the rocks on the sides of the clifts.</ref>   they are now
          ripe of a pale red colour, about the size of a common goosberry, and like it is an ovate
          pericarp of soft pulp invelloping a number of smal whitish coloured seeds; the pulp is a
          yelloish slimy muselaginous substance of a sweetish and pinelike tast, not agreeable to
          me.    the surface of the berry is covered with a glutinous adhesive matter,
          and the frut altho' ripe retains it's withered corollar.    this shrub seldom
          rises more than two feet high and is much branched, the leaves resemble those of the
          common goosberry only not so large; it has no thorns.    the berry is
          supported by seperate peduncles or footstalks of half an inch in length.   
          immence quantities of small grasshoppers of a brown colour in the plains,
          <ref target="n15061803" n="3"/>they no doubt contribute much to keep the grass as low
          as we find it which is not generally more than three inches, the grass is a narrow leaf,
          soft, and affords a fine pasture for the Buffaloe.—
          <ref target="n15061804" n="4"/>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.1805-06-18.02">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">June 18th Tuesday 1805</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>we Set out early and arrived at the second great Cataract a[t] about 200 yds above
          the last of 19 feet pitch—    this is one of the grandest views in nature and
          by far exceeds any thing I ever Saw, the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>falling over a Shelveing rock for
          47 feet 8 Inches with a Cascade &amp;c of 14 feet 7 Inches above the Shoot for a ¼ mile
             I decended the Clift below this Cateract with ease measured the hight of
          the purpendicular fall of 47 feet 8 Inches at which place the river is 473 yards wide as
          also the hight of the Cascade &amp;c.    a continuel mist quite across this
          fall*    after which we proceeded on up the river a little more than a mile to
          the largest fountain or Spring I ever Saw,
          <ref target="n15061805" n="5"/>and doubt if it is not the largest in America Known,
          this water boils up from under th rocks near the edge of the river and falls imediately
          into the river 8 feet and keeps its Colour for ½ a mile which is emencely Clear and of a
          bluish Cast, proceeded on up the river    passed a Succession of rapids to the
          next great fall of 26 Ft. 5 I.    river 580 yards wide    this fall
          is not intirely perpdincular    a Short bench gives a Curve to the water as it
          falls    a butifull Small Island at the foot of this fall near the Center of
          the Channel Covered with trees, the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>at this fall is 36 yards wide, a
          Considerable mist rises at this fall ocasionally, from this pitch to the head of the
          rapids is one mile &amp; has a fall of 20 feet, this is also a handsome Scenery a fall
          in an open leavel plain, after takeing the hight &amp; measureing the river proceeded
          on, Saw a gange of Buffalow Swiming the river above the falls, Several of which was
          drawn in to the rapids and with dificuelty mad Shore half drowned, we killed one of
          those Cows &amp; took a[s] much meat as we wished.    emence herds of those
          animals in every direction, passed 2 groves in the Point just above the rapids &amp;
          dined in one opposit the mouth of 
          <name type="place" key="Sun (Mah-pah-pah,-ah-zhah, Medicine) River">Medison
          River</name>, which fails in on the Stard. Side and is 137 yards wide at its mouth
             the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>〈nearly one mile〉 above is 800
          yards wide, as the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">river [Missouri]</name>appears to bear S
          Easterley I assended about 4 miles high to a Creek which appeared to head in 
          <name type="place" key="Highwood (South) Mountains">South mountains</name>
                  <ref target="n15061806" n="6"/>   passed a Island of
          <ref target="n15061807" n="7"/>[
          <hi rend="italic">blank</hi>] and a little timber in an Easterly bend at 1 mile, passed
          Some timber in a point at 2 mile at or near the lower point of a large Island on which
          we Shot at a large white 
          <hi rend="italic">bear</hi>.    passed a Small Island in the middle and one
          close on the Lard Shore at 3 miles behind the head of which we Camped.
          <ref target="n15061808" n="8"/>   those 3 Islands are all opposit, Soon after
          we Camped two ganges of Buffalow crossed one above &amp; the other below    we
          killed 7 of them &amp; a calf and Saved as much of the best of the meat as we could this
          evening, one man 
          <name type="person" key="Willard, Alexander">A Willard</name>going for a load of meat at
          170 yards distance on an Island was attact by a white bear and verry near being Caught,
          prosued within 40 yards of Camp where I was with one man    I collected 3
          others of the party and prosued the bear (who had prosued my track from a buffalow I had
          killed on the Island at about 300 yards distance and chance to meet 
          <name type="person" key="Willard, Alexander">Willard</name>) for fear of his attacking
          one man 
          <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name>at the lower point of the Island,
          before we had got down the bear had allarmed the man and prosued him into the water, at
          our approach he retreated, and we relieved the man in the water, I Saw the bear but the
          bushes was So thick that I could not Shoot him and it was nearly dark, the wind from the
          S W &amp; Cool    killed a beaver &amp; an elk for their Skins this
          evening</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.1805-06-18.03">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Tuesday 18th June 1805</hi>.    this morning all hands
          halled out the long perogue.    we leave in a bunch of bushes below the Camp.
             we covered hir over with bushes &amp; dry wood. Secured hir Safe.
             3 men Sent to a knob a short distance out to dig a cash or hole to put a
          fiew heavey articles in which we can Spare, to deposite at this place.    the
          day pleasant we repacked the Indian goods &amp;.C.    moved all the baggage
          near to camp.    about 12 oClock the hunters came in    had killed
          10 deer but no Elk.    in the evening we saw some buffalow on the opposite
          Shore. Some of the hunters crossed and killed 2 of them    the little low
          waggons Compleated.    all made of wood &amp; of a ordinarry quallity though
          they may answer the purpose.    the wind high from the west.    
          <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">our Intrepters wife</name>Some what better than She
          has been for Some time past. we are now 2580¼ miles from the mouth of the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missourie River</name>.—</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.1805-06-18.04">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Tuesday 18th.</hi>   The periogue
          <ref target="n15061809" n="9"/>was hauled out of the water and laid safe; and some men
          went to dig a place for depositing more of our baggage. About 12 the two hunters came
          in, and could find no elk, but killed 10 deer. In the evening we compleated our waggons,
          which were made altogether of wood, and of a very ordinary quality; but it is expected
          they will answer the purpose.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.1805-06-18.05">
            <sp who="jw">
               <speaker>Whitehouse</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Tuesday 18th June 1805</hi>.    a fine pleasant day.
             in the morning all hands halled out the White perogue, in a thicked of
          bushes below the bank &amp; covered hir with bushes &amp;c. &amp; Secured hir Safe.
             3 men Sent out a Short distance to a knob to dig a carsh or hole to
          deposite Some of our baggage in, for we mean to leave all we can Spare at this place.
             Some men at Sorting &amp; repacking the Indian Goods &amp;c.   
          about 12 oC. the 2 hunters came in had killed 10 Deer but no Elk.    in the
          evening we Saw Some buffalow on the opposite Side of the River.    Some of the
          hunters went over and killed 2 of them.    the low waggons finished which are
          all made of wood, &amp; of an ordinarry quality though they may answer the purpose.
             the wind high from the West.</p>
               <p>Tuesday June 18th    A fine pleasant day, in the Morning all our Men who
          were in Camp, were employed hawling up our largest Pettyauger, into a thicket of bushes,
          which lay below our Camp, where they secured her, after doing of which 3 of our Men were
          sent a short distance to a knob, in order to dig a Cashe, or hole, to deposit some more
          of our baggage in, Our Officers intending to leave here, what baggage we can possibly do
          without, Some others of our party was employed in sorting and repacking the Indian Goods
          &amp;ca.—</p>
               <p>About 12 o'Clock A. M. the hunters that had went out Yesterday, returned to us, they
          had killed 10 deer, but no Elk, In the Evening we saw some buffalo on the opposite side
          of the River, some of our hunters went across and killed 2 of them, we this day
          compleated our Carriages, they were made out of wood of an ordinary quality, though we
          think they will answer the purpose that they were intended for; The wind rose &amp; blew
          from the West, we encamped
          <ref target="n15061810" n="10"/>at this place for the day.—</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n15061801" n="1">Sulphuric acid, used as a tonic and astringent. Chuinard
        (OOMD), 291–92.</note>
            <note xml:id="n15061802" n="2">
               <hi rend="italic">Ribes cereum</hi>Dougl. var. 
        <hi rend="italic">inebrians</hi>(Lindl.) C. L. Hitchc., squaw, or western red, currant. It
        is interesting that 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>refers to this currant as a
        gooseberry. Gooseberries are commonly distinguished from currants by the presence of
        spines or prickles on the stem. See also 
        <ref n="1805-07-25" type="related">July 25, 1805</ref>. Booth &amp; Wright, 107;
        Barkley, 134. It was probably 
        <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>who drew a red vertical line
        through this passage about the "gooseberry" to nearly the end of the entry.</note>
            <note xml:id="n15061803" n="3">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>is probably seeing several
        varieties of grasshoppers which are in their nymphal stage, most likely 
        <hi rend="italic">Ageneotetix deorum</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n15061804" n="4">The grass is probably blue grama, 
        <hi rend="italic">Bouteloua gracilis</hi>(HBK.) Lag., or possibly buffalograss, 
        <hi rend="italic">Buchloe dactyloides</hi>(Nutt.) Engelm. Fernald, 182, 184.</note>
            <note xml:id="n15061805" n="5">
               <name type="place" key="Giant Springs">Giant Springs</name>is now located in a park
        northeast of the city of 
        <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">Great Falls</name>, in 
        <name type="place" key="Cascade County, Mont.">Cascade County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>. 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>maps 42, 54, 61; MRC map 77. It has been said to discharge
        388,800,000 gallons of water every twenty-four hours, but more recent measurements
        indicate 174–213,000,000 gallons a day. Appleman (LC), 316–17; 
        <hi rend="italic">Montana Guide</hi>, 156–57; information of Robert N. Bergantino, July
        18, 1986. The asterisk in the preceding sentence cannot be explained.</note>
            <note xml:id="n15061806" n="6">
               <name type="place" key="Sand Coulee Creek (Flattery Run)">Flattery Run</name>on 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>maps 54, 62; later 
        <name type="place" key="Sand Coulee Creek (Flattery Run)">Sand Coulee Creek</name>. MRC
        map 77.</note>
            <note xml:id="n15061807" n="7">After this word, at the bottom of a page of Voorhis No.1, 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>has written the words "No.10." The
        meaning is unknown.</note>
            <note xml:id="n15061808" n="8">The "
        <name type="place" key="Upper portage camp (Mont.)">Upper Portage Camp</name>," occupied
        until July 12, is about three-quarters of a mile north of 
        <name type="place" key="Sand Coulee Creek (Flattery Run)">Sand Coulee Creek</name>. The "
        <name type="place" key="White Bear Islands">White Bear Islands</name>" themselves have
        virtually disappeared, merging with the banks of the 
        <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>in 
        <name type="place" key="Cascade County, Mont.">Cascade County</name>. Appleman (LC), 314; 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>maps 42, 54, 61; MRC map 77.</note>
            <note xml:id="n15061809" n="9">The white pirogue.</note>
            <note xml:id="n15061810" n="10">At the lower portage camp.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-06-17" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-06-19" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
