<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.1806-06-27">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">June 27, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic
        Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            8</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">June 10–September 26, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1987</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">55-59</biblScope>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">327</biblScope>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">245</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
         <geoDecl datum="WGS">
            <placeName/>
            <geo>46.5 -115.1333</geo>
            <note>Camped in Idaho County, ID, on the first high point west of Indian Grave Peak. Near the camp of 1805-09-17.</note>
         </geoDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc/>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-11-04</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-04-12</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date>June 27, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.1806-06-27.01">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Friday June 27th 1806.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>We collected our horses early and set out.    the road still continued on
          the heights of the same dividing ridge on which we had traveled yesterday for nine miles
          or to our encampment of the 〈18th〉 [
          <hi rend="italic">NB: 17th</hi>]
          <ref target="n36062701" n="1"/>of September last.    about one mile short of
          this encampment on an elivated point we halted by the request of the Indians a few
          minutes and smoked the pipe.    on this eminence the natives have raised a
          conic mound of stones of 6 or eight feet high and on it's summit erected a pine pole of
          15 feet long.
          <ref target="n36062702" n="2"/>   from hence they informed us that when
          passing over with their familes some of the men were usually sent on foot by the fishery
          at the entrance of 
          <name type="place" key="Colt Killed Creek">Colt Creek</name>in order to take fish and
          again met the main party at the 
          <name type="place" key="Packer Meadows (Quawmash Glades)">Quawmash glade</name>on the
          head of the 
          <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Kooskooske
          river</name>.
          <ref target="n36062703" n="3"/>   from this place we had an extensive view of
          these stupendous mountains principally covered with snow like that on which we stood; we
          were entirely surrounded by those mountains from which to one unacquainted with them it
          would have seemed impossible ever to have escaped; in short without the asssistance of
          our guides I doubt much whether we who had once passed them could find our way to 
          <name type="place" key="Travelers' Rest (Idaho)">Travellers rest</name>in their present
          situation for the marked trees on which we had placed considerable reliance are much
          fewer and more difficult to find than we had apprehended.    these fellows are
          most admireable pilots; we find the road wherever the snow has disappeared though it be
          only for a few hundred paces.    after smoking the pipe and contemplating this
          seene sufficient to have damp the sperits of any except such hardy travellers as we have
          become, we continued our march and at the distance of 3 ms. decended a steep mountain
          and passed two small branches of the 
          <name type="place" key="North Fork Clearwater (Chopunnish) River">Chopunnish
          river</name>just above their forks
          <ref target="n36062704" n="4"/>and again ascended the ridge on which we passed several
          miles and at a distance of 7 ms. arrived at our encampment [
          <hi rend="italic">NB: 16th</hi>] of September near which we passed 3 small branches
          <ref target="n36062705" n="5"/>of the 
          <name type="place" key="North Fork Clearwater (Chopunnish) River">Chopunnish
          river</name>and again ascended to the dividing ridge on which we continued nine miles
          when the ridge became lower and we arrived at a situation very similar to our encampment
          of the last evening tho' the ridge was somewhat higher and the snow had not been so long
          desolved of course there was but little grass.
          <ref target="n36062706" n="6"/>   here we encamped for the night having
          traveled 28 miles over these mountains without releiving the horses from their packs or
          their having any food.    the indians inform us that there is [
          <hi rend="italic">NB: in the mountains a little or our left</hi>] an abundance of the
          mountain sheep or what they call white buffaloe.
          <ref target="n36062707" n="7"/>   we saw three black-tailed or mule deer
          <ref target="n36062708" n="8"/>this evening but were unable to get a shoot at them.
             we also saw several tracks of those animals in the snow.    the
          indians inform that there is great abundance of Elk in the vally about the Fishery on
          the 
          <name type="place" key="Lochsa (Upper Kooskooske) River">Kooskooske River</name>.
          <ref target="n36062709" n="9"/>   our meat being exhausted we issued a pint
          of bears oil to a mess which with their boiled roots made an agreeable dish. 
          <name type="person" key="Potts, John">Potts's</name>legg which has been much swolen and
          inflamed for several days is much better this evening and gives him but little pain.
             we applyed the pounded roots and leaves of the wild ginger
          <ref target="n36062710" n="10"/>&amp; from which he found great relief.   
          neare our encampment we saw a great number of the yellow lilly with reflected petals in
          blume;
          <ref target="n36062711" n="11"/>this plant was just as forward here at this time as it
          was in the plains on the 10th of may.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.1806-06-27.02">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Friday June 27th 1806</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>We collected our horses early and Set out.    the road Still Continue on
          the hights of the Dividing ridge on which we had traveled yesterday for 9 Ms. or to our
          encampment of the 16th Septr. last.
          <ref target="n36062712" n="12"/>   about 1 m. Short of the encampment we
          halted by the request of the Guides a fiew minits on an ellevated point and Smoked a
          pipe    on this eminance the nativs have raised a conic mound of Stons of 6 or
          8 feet high and erected a pine pole of 15 feet long.    from hence they
          informed us that when passing over with their families some of the men were usually Sent
          on foot by the fishery at the enterance of 
          <name type="place" key="Colt Killed Creek">Colt Creek</name>in order to take fish and
          again meet the party at the 
          <name type="place" key="Packer Meadows (Quawmash Glades)">quawmash glade</name>on the
          head of 
          <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Kooskoske
          river</name>.    from this place we had an extencive view of these Stupendeous
          Mountains principally Covered with Snow like that on which we Stood; we were entirely
          Serounded by those mountains from which to one unacquainted with them it would have
          Seemed impossible ever to have escaped, in short without the assistance of our guides, I
          doubt much whether we who had once passed them could find our way to 
          <name type="place" key="Travelers' Rest (Idaho)">Travellers rest</name>in their present
          Situation for the marked trees on which we had placed Considerable reliance are much
          fewer and more difficuelt to find than we had apprehended.    those indians
          are most admireable pilots; we find the road wherever the Snow has disappeared tho' it
          be only fora fiew paces.    after haveing Smoked the pipe and Contemplating
          this Scene Sufficient to have dampened the Spirits of any except Such hardy travellers
          as we have become, we continued our march and at the dist. of 3 m. decended a Steep
          mountain and passed two Small branches of the 
          <name type="place" key="North Fork Clearwater (Chopunnish) River">Chopunnish
          river</name>just above their fok, and again assend the ridge on which we passed.
             at the distance of 7 m. arived at our Encampment of 16th Septr. last
             passed 3 Small branches    passed on a dividing ridge rugid and
          we arived at a Situation very Similar to our Situation of last night tho' the ridge was
          Somewhat higher and the Snow had not been So long disolved of course there was but
          little grass.    here we Encamped for the night haveing traveled 28 Ms. over
          these mountains without releiveing the horses from their packs or their haveing any
          food.    the Indians inform us that there is an abundance of the Mountain
          Sheep, or what they Call white Buffalow on those Mountains.    we Saw 3 black
          tail or mule deer this evening but were unable to get a Shoot at them.    we
          also Saw Several tracks of those animals in the snow.    our Meat being
          exhosted we 〈send 2〉 issued a point of 
          <hi rend="italic">Bears Oil</hi>to a mess which with their boiled roots made an
          agreeable dish. 
          <name type="person" key="Potts, John">Jo. Potts</name>leg which had been much Swelled
          and inflaimed for several days is much better this evening and givs him but little pain.
          we applied the poundd root &amp; leaves of wild ginger from which he found great relief.
          Near our encampment we saw great numbers of the Yellow lilly with reflected petals in
          blume; this plant was just as foward here at this time as it was in the plains on the
          10th of May. My head has not pained me so much to day as yesterday and last night.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.1806-06-27.03">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>Friday 27th June 1806.    a fair morning.    we took an eairly
          breakfast and proceeded on verry fast over the high banks of Snow    the most
          part of the day and bad mountains.    we came further to day than we went in 2
          when we came over.    and Camped
          <ref target="n36062713" n="13"/>on the South Side of a mountain where our horses find a
          little grass.    the day warm and Snow melts fast.—</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.1806-06-27.04">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Friday 27th.</hi>   We had a cloudy morning and at 8 o'clock
          we renewed our march, proceeding over some of the steepest mountains I ever passed. The
          snow is so deep that we cannot wind along the sides of these steps, but must slide
          straight down. The horses generally do not sink more than three inches in the snow; but
          sometimes they break through to their bellies. We kept on without halting to about 5
          o'clock in the evening, when we stopped at the side of a hill where the snow was off,
          and where there was a little grass; and we here encamped for the night. The day was
          plesant throughout; but it appeared to me somewhat extraordinary, to be travelling over
          snow six or eight feet deep in the latter end of June. The most of us, however, had
          saved our socks as we expected to find snow on these mountains.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n36062701" n="1">It appears that this was initially a blank space into which
        
        <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>put "18th," then crossed it out
        and substituted "17th," all in red ink. He also added "16th" later in the entry in an
        apaprent blank space.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36062702" n="2">In 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho County, Idaho">Idaho County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>, on the first high point west of 
        <name type="place" key="Indian Grave Peak">Indian Grave Peak</name>. 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>describes it as a mile short of
        the party's camp of 
        <ref n="1805-09-17" type="related">September 17, 1805</ref>, marked on 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>map 70. A rock mound stands there today, much smaller than the
        one described by 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>. Space, 37.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36062703" n="3">A reference to 
        <name type="place" key="Packer Meadows (Quawmash Glades)">Packer Meadows</name>, in 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho County, Idaho">Idaho County</name>, in the vicinity of the
        party's camp of 
        <ref n="1805-09-13" type="related">September 13, 1805</ref>. Space, 37; 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>map 69.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36062704" n="4">
               <name type="place" key="Gravey Creek">Gravey</name>and 
        <name type="place" key="Serpent Creek">Serpent</name>creeks, according to Space, 37. 
        <name type="place" key="Horseshoe Creek">Horseshoe</name>and 
        <name type="place" key="Serpent Creek">Serpent</name>creeks, according to Peebels (RLC),
        27; Peebles (LT), map.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36062705" n="5">Including 
        <name type="place" key="Howard Creek">Howard</name>and 
        <name type="place" key="Moon Creek (Idaho)">Moon</name>creeks. Space, 37; Peebles (LT),
        map.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36062706" n="6">On 
        <name type="place" key="Spring Hill">Spring Hill, or Spring Mountain</name>, a little
        south of the 
        <name type="place" key="Clearwater County, Idaho">Clearwater</name>-
        <name type="place" key="Idaho County, Idaho">Idaho</name>county line, roughly midway
        between the camps of 
        <ref n="1805-09-15" type="related">September 15</ref>and 
        <ref n="1805-09-16" type="related">16</ref>on 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>map 70. Space, 37; Peebles (LT), map; Peebles (RLC),
        27.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36062707" n="7">The mountain goat, 
        <hi rend="italic">Oreamnos americanus,</hi>of which they never obtained a complete
        specimen; see 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>description at 
        <ref n="1806-02-22" type="related">February 22, 1806</ref>. 
        <name type="person" key="Mackenzie, Alexander">Alexander Mackenzie</name>heard of the
        "small white buffalo" from Canadian Indians on his journey to the 
        <name type="place" key="Arctic Ocean">Arctic Ocean</name>in 1789, but he never saw one.
        Lamb, 209, 214; Cutright (LCPN), 444.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36062708" n="8">
               <hi rend="italic">Odocoileus hemionus,</hi>mule deer.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36062709" n="9">In the valley of the 
        <name type="place" key="Lochsa (Upper Kooskooske) River">Lochsa River</name>, near the
        mount of 
        <name type="place" key="Colt Killed Creek">White Sand Creek ("Killed Colt Creek</name>" on
        
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>map 70), in 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho County, Idaho">Idaho County</name>. Elk are more properly
        wapiti, 
        <hi rend="italic">Cervus elaphus.</hi>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="n36062710" n="10">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, or perhaps actually 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, now adds long-tailed wild ginger, 
        <hi rend="italic">Asarum caudatum</hi>Lindl., to 
        <name type="person" key="Potts, John">John Potts's</name>poultice of cous ("pounded
        roots") from 
        <ref n="1806-06-22" type="related">June 22</ref>. Wild ginger is not known to occur at
        this elevation, and would not have had expanded leaves on this early date if it did occur
        here. The party must have carried a supply of leaves from lower elevations where the
        species is common, perhaps for cooking. Hitchcock et al., 2:102; Cutright (LCPN), 306,
        403.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36062711" n="11">The dogtooth violet of 
        <ref n="1806-06-16" type="related">June 16</ref>. He collected it on 
        <ref n="1806-05-08" type="related">May 8</ref>, but made no mention of it on 
        <ref n="1806-05-10" type="related">May 10</ref>. A red vertical line crosses through
        this passage, perhaps 
        <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle's</name>mark, and a dark vertical line
        runs through preceding lines.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36062712" n="12">Actually 
        <ref n="1805-09-17" type="related">September 17</ref>; see 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>entry. It appears that someone
        has overwritten the number 15 to make it 16.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36062713" n="13">On 
        <name type="place" key="Spring Hill">Spring Hill, or Spring Mountain</name>, a little
        south of the 
        <name type="place" key="Clearwater County, Idaho">Clearwater</name>-
        <name type="place" key="Idaho County, Idaho">Idaho</name>county line, 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-06-26" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-06-28" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
