<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-05-04">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
May 4, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               
               
               
               
               
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 7</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">March 23–June 9, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1991</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">205-209</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">304-305</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">221-222</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
         <geoDecl datum="WGS" xml:id="lc.geo.1806-05-04.01">
            <placeName/>
            <geo>46.4028 -117.0425</geo>
            <note>Camped in Whitman County, WA, on the Snake below Clarkston.</note>
         </geoDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Journal Entries</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-10-11</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1806-05-04">May 4, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-05-04.01" n="lc.geo.1806-05-04.01">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Sunday May 4th 1806.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
Collected our horses and set out early; the morning was cold and disagreeable.    we ascended the Lard. hills of the creek and steered N. 60° E. 4 miles through a high level plain to a ravine which forms the source of a small creek,<ref target="n33050401" n="1"/> thence down this creek N. 75° E. 8 ms. to it's entrance into <name type="place"
                        key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Lewis's river</name> 7½ ms. below the entrance of the <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Kooskooske</name>.    on the river a little above this creek we arrived at a lodge of 6 families<ref target="n33050402" n="2"/> of which <name type="person" key="Apash Wyakaikt">We-ark-koomt</name> had spoken.    we halted here for breakfast and with much difficulty purchase 2 lean dogs.    the inhabitants were miserably poor.    we obtained a few large cakes of half cured bread made of a root which resembles the sweet potatoe, with these we made some soope and took breakfast.    the lands through which we passed today are fertile consisting of a dark rich loam.<ref target="n33050403" n="3"/>    the hills of the river are high and approach it nearly on both sides.    no timer in the plains.    the <name type="place" key="Blue (Southwest, Southeast) Mountains">S. W. Mountains</name> which appear to be about 15 Ms. above us still continue to become lower they are covered with snow at present nearly to their bases. <name type="place"
                        key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Lewis's river</name> appeas to pass through these mots. near their N. Eastern extremity. these hills terminate in a high level plain between the <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Kooskooske</name> and <name type="place"
                        key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Lewis's river</name>.    these plains are in many places well covered with the Longleafed pine, with some Larch and balsom fir.<ref target="n33050404" n="4"/>    the soil is extreemly fertile no dose it appear so thisty as that of the same apparent texture of the open plains.    it produces great quantities of the quawmash a root of which the natives are extreemly fond.    a great portion of the <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Chopunnish</name> we are informed are now distributed in small vilages through this plain collecting the quawmash and cows; the salmon not yet having arrived to call them to the river.    the hills of the creek which we decended this morning are high and in most parts rocky and abrupt.    one of our pack horses sliped from one of those hights and fell into the creek with it's load consisting principally of ammunition but fortunately neith the horse nor load suffered any material injury.    the amunition being secured in canesters the water did not effect it.—    after dinner we continued our rout up the West side of the river 3 Ms. opposite to 2 lodges the one containing 3 and the other 2 families of the <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Chopunnish</name> nation; here we met with <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="person" key="Tetoharsky">Te-toh, ar sky</name>,</hi>
                  <ref target="n33050405" n="5"/> the youngest of the two cheifs who accompanied us last fall the <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Great Falls of the">great falls of the Columbia</name>    here we also met with our pilot<ref target="n33050406" n="6"/> who decended the river with us as far as the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>.    these indians recommended our passing the river at this place and ascending the <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Kooskooske</name> on the N. E. side.    they said it was nearer and a better rout to the forkes of that river where the <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">twisted hair</name> resided in whose charge we had left our horses; thither they promised to conduct us.    we determined to take the advice of the indians and immediately prepared to pass the river which with the assistance of three indian canoes we effected in the course of the evening,<ref target="n33050407" n="7"/> purchased a little wood and some bread of cows [<hi rend="italic">NB: a root</hi>]<ref target="n33050408" n="8"/> from the natives and encamped<ref target="n33050409" n="9"/> having traveled 15 Ms. only today. <name type="person" key="Apash Wyakaikt">We-ark-koomt</name> whose people resided on the West side of <name type="place"
                        key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Lewis's river</name> above left us when we determined to pass the river and went on to his lodg.    the evening was cold and disagreeable, and the natives crouded about our fire in great numbers insomuch that we could scarcely cook of keep ourselves warm.    at all these lodges of the <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Chopunnish</name> I observe an appendage of a small lodg with one fire which seems to be the retreat of their women in a certain situation [<hi rend="italic">X: S M</hi>].<ref target="n33050410" n="10"/>    the men are not permitted to approach this lodge within a certain distance and if they have any thing to convey to the occupants of this little hospital they stand at the distance of 50 or 60 paces and throw it towards them as far as they can and retire.
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-05-04.02" n="lc.geo.1806-05-04.01">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Sunday May 4th 1806</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
Collected our horses and Set out early; the morning was Cold and disagreeable.    we assended the Lar board Hill of the Creek and Steared N 60° E 4 M. through a high leavil plain to a revine which forms the Source of a small creek, thence down the Creek N 75° E. 8 Ms. to it's enterance into <name type="place"
                        key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Lewis's river</name> 7½ ms. below the enterance of <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Koos koos ke</name>.    on the river a little above this Creek we arived at a lodge of 6 families of which <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="person" key="Apash Wyakaikt">We-ark'-koomt</name>
                  </hi> has Spoken. We halted here for brackfast and with much dificuelty purchased 2 lean dogs.    the inhabitents were miserably pore. we obtained a fiew large cakes of half cured bread made of a root which resembles the Sweet potatoe, with these we made Some Soope and took brackfast.    the lands through which we passed to day are fertile consisting of a dark rich loam.    the hills of the river are high and abrupt approaching it nearly on both Sides.    no timber in the plains.    the <name type="place" key="Blue (Southwest, Southeast) Mountains">S. W. Mountains</name> which appear to be about 15 Miles from us Still Continue to become lower, they are Covered with Snow at present nearly to their bases. <name type="place"
                        key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Lewis's river</name> appear to pass through those Mountains near the N Eastern extremity.    those hills termonate in a high leavil plain between the <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Kooskoske</name> &amp; <name type="place"
                        key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Lewis's river</name>.    these plains are in maney places well covered with the long leafed pine and Some balsom fir.    the Soil is extreamly fertile.    no does it appear So thirsty as that of the Same apparrant texture of the open plains.    it produces great quantities of the quawmash a root of which the natives are extreemly fond.    a Great portion of the <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Chopunnish</name> we are informed are now distributed in Small villages through this plain Collecting the <hi rend="italic">Cowse</hi> a white Meley root which is very fine in Soup after being dried and pounded; the Salmon not yet haveing arived to Call them to the river—. The hills of the Creek which we decended this morning are high and in most parts rocky and abrupt.    one of our pack horses Sliped from one of those hights and fell into the Creek with it's load Consisting principally of amunition, but fortunately neither the horse nor load Suffered any Matereal injury.    the ammunition being Secured in Canesters the water did not effect it.—</p>
               <p>
after dinner we Continued our rout up the West Side of the river 3 ms. opposit 2 Lodges the one Containing 3 and the other 2 families of the <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Chopunnish</name> Nation; here we met with <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="person" key="Tetoharsky">Te-toh-ar-sky</name>
                  </hi> the oldest of the two Chiefs who accompanied us last fall to the <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Great Falls of the">Great falls of the Columbia</name>.    here we also met with our old pilot who decended the river with us as low as the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>    these indians recommended our passing the river at this place and going up on the N E Side of the <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Kooskoske</name>.    they Sayed it was nearer and a better rout to the forks of that river where the <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">twisted hair</name> resided in whose charge we had left our horses; thither they promised to Conduct us.    we determined to take the advise of the indians and imediately prepared to pass the river which with the assistance of three indian Canoes we effected in the Course of the evening, purchased a little Wood, Some <hi rend="italic">Cows</hi> bread and encamped, haveing traveled <hi rend="italic">15</hi> miles to day only. <name type="person" key="Apash Wyakaikt">We ark koomt</name> whose people reside on the West Side of <name type="place"
                        key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Lewis's river</name> above left us when we deturmined to pass the river. before he left us he expressed his concern that his people would be deprived of the pleasure of Seeing us at the forks at which place they had assimbled to Shew us Sivilities &amp;c. I gave him a Small piece of tobacco and he went off Satisfied.    the evening was Cold and disagreeable, and the nativs Crouded about our fire in great numbers in so much that we Could Scercely Cook or keep ourselves worm.    at all those Lodges of the <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Chopunnish</name> I observe an appendage of a Small lodge with one fire, which Seames to be the retreat of their women in a certain Situation. the men are not permited to approach this Lodge within a certain distance, and if they have any thing to Convey to the Occupents of this little hospital they Stand at the distance of 50 or 60 paces and throw it towards them as far as they Can and retire.

</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-05-04.03" n="lc.geo.1806-05-04.01">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Sunday 4th of May 1806.    a hard frost &amp; verry cold this morning.    we Set out as usal and proced on    left the creek and assended high plains    came on a Small branch in a deep revean.    followed down it.    about noon we arived at a small village<ref target="n33050411" n="11"/> on the bank of <name type="place"
                        key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Lewises river</name> where we halted about 10 miles below the forks of <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">koos kooskee</name> &amp; <name type="place"
                        key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Lewises rivers</name>.    we bought a little dark couloured root bread<ref target="n33050412" n="12"/> which is not good but will Support nature.    bought 2 dogs &amp; a fiew Small fresh fish &amp;C.    we dined and proceed. on    Soon met one of the chiefs<ref target="n33050413" n="13"/> of the <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">flat head</name> or <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Chopennish</name> tribe who we left our horses with &amp; who went down to the narrows with us last fall.    he tells us that tobe our <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Snake Indn.</name> guide took 2 of our best horses away with him when he left us.<ref target="n33050414" n="14"/>    we crossed <name type="place"
                        key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Lewises river</name> to the N. Side to a Small village where we bought only one dog and Camped    the head chief of the <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Chopennish</name> tribe Camped with us and a number more of his tribe who came down to meet us, &amp;C—


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-05-04.04" n="lc.geo.1806-05-04.01">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Sunday 4th.</hi>    We had a severe frost last night; and the morning was cold and clear. We were early on our march over a handsome plain; and came to another creek, which we kept down until we came to <name type="place"
                        key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Lewis's river</name>,<ref target="n33050415" n="15"/> some distance below the forks of <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Koos-koos-ke</name>;<ref target="n33050416" n="16"/> where we halted at an Indian lodge, and could get nothing to eat, except some bread made of a kind of roots I was unacquainted with. We had, however, a dog, which we 
bought from the Indians, who met us last night; but this was a scanty allowance for thirty odd hungry men. We remained here about two hours, got a dog, and proceeded up the south side of <name type="place"
                        key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Lewis's river</name>, about three miles, when we met with one of our old chiefs,<ref target="n33050417" n="17"/> who had come down with us last fall; and who advised us to cross the river, as the best road is on the north side. We therefore were occupied in crossing, during the remainder of the day, as we could raise but four small canoes from the natives at this place. We, however, by dark got all safe over, and encamped on the north side, accompanied by a great many of the natives, who appear a friendly and well disposed people.



</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n33050401" n="1">
               <name type="place" key="Alpowa Creek">Alpowa Creek</name>, in <name type="place" key="Garfield County, Wash.">Garfield County</name>, <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>. It reaches the <name type="place"
                     key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Snake river</name> in <name type="place" key="Asotin County, Wash.">Asotin County</name>, <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>. They may first have struck its upper branches, <name type="place" key="Megginson Gulch">Megginson Gulch</name> and <name type="place" key="Stember Creek">Stember Creek</name> in <name type="place" key="Garfield County, Wash.">Garfield County</name>; the direction of travel to the creek would probably have been more nearly due east. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 73.</note>
            <note xml:id="n33050402" n="2">On the <name type="place"
                     key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Snake River</name> at <name type="place" key="Alpaweyma village">Alpowa</name> in the vicinity of former <name type="place" key="Silcott, Wash.">Silcott</name>, <name type="place" key="Asotin County, Wash.">Asotin County</name>, now inundated by <name type="place" key="Lower Granite Reservoir">Lower Granite Reservoir</name>. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 73. This same <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name> village was visited on <ref n="1805-10-11" type="related">October 11, 1805</ref>. Major archaeological excavations were conducted at three sites in this vicinity and a 6,000 year occupation sequence was defined, with houses dated from about 3000 B.C. to 1880 A.D. The <name type="place" key="Silcott, Wash.">Silcott</name> area has been heavily excavated for prehistoric and historic materials as well as burial relocation. The fifteen or more publications on the historical material have been best summarized by Adams. Accounts of <name type="place" key="Alpaweyma village">Alpowa</name> or <name type="place" key="Timothy's village">Timothy's village</name> are best summarized in Brauner. The burial relocation work of both prehistoric and historic <name type="place" key="Timothy's village">Timothy village</name> burials is described in Rodeffer, Rodeffer, &amp; Sprague. <name type="place" key="Timothy">Timothy or Timootsin</name> was one of the first Christian <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name> chiefs. According to Schwede, 37, and Spinden, 175, the village was known as <name type="place" key="Alpaweyma village">Alpaweyma</name>, from which comes modern <name type="place" key="Alpaweyma village">Alpowa</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n33050403" n="3">The soils on the areas above the stream valleys are residual soils that have developed from weathering of volcanic ash and <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name> Basalt.</note>
            <note xml:id="n33050404" n="4">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> is describing the forest vegetation zone in the northern <name type="place" key="Blue (Southwest, Southeast) Mountains">Blue Mountains</name> of southeastern <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>. The western larch (also called Montana larch, mountain larch, hackmatack, and tamarack), <hi rend="italic">Larix occidentalis</hi> Nutt., and grand fir are associates in some moister forest communities. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> description of the grand fir is at <ref n="1806-02-06" type="related">February 6, 1806</ref>. Franklin &amp; Dyrness, 44, 172; Hitchcock et al., 1:117, 121.</note>
            <note xml:id="n33050405" n="5">Tetoharsky, a chief of the <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perces</name>, whom they met in October 1805 but did not name until now. See <ref n="1805-10-07" type="related">October 7, 1805</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n33050406" n="6">Probably the unnamed "guide," apparently a <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>, who left the party on October 18, 1805. Several Indians accompanied the Corps of Discovery for part of the journey down the <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Clearwater</name> and <name type="place"
                     key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Snake</name> rivers and receive only casual mention in the journals.</note>
            <note xml:id="n33050407" n="7">They crossed the <name type="place"
                     key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Snake</name> above <name type="place" key="Silcott, Wash.">Silcott</name> into <name type="place" key="Whitman County, Wash.">Whitman County</name>, <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>, and continued upstream on the north bank. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 73.</note>
            <note xml:id="n33050408" n="8">
               <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name> also underlined the words "bread of cows," all in red.</note>
            <note xml:id="n33050409" n="9">In <name type="place" key="Whitman County, Wash.">Whitman County</name>, on the <name type="place"
                     key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Snake</name> some three miles below <name type="place" key="Clarkston, Wash.">Clarkston</name>. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 73.</note>
            <note xml:id="n33050410" n="10">The lodge for menstruating women; see <ref n="1806-04-30" type="related">April 30, 1806</ref>. The cryptic interlineation "S M," perhaps written by <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, may stand for "situation menses." The words "women in a certain situation" are underlined in red, perhaps by <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n33050411" n="11">In the vicinity of former <name type="place" key="Silcott, Wash.">Silcott</name>, <name type="place" key="Asotin County, Wash.">Asotin County</name>, <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>, on the <name type="place"
                     key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Snake ("Lewises")
River</name> and some miles below the entrance of the <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Clearwater ("Kooskooskee") River</name>, as <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> mentions. This is the same <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name> village that was visited on <ref n="1805-10-11" type="related">October 11, 1805</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n33050412" n="12">Probably the unidentified species that <name type="place"
                     key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Lewis</name> discusses on <ref n="1806-01-20" type="related">January 20, 1806</ref>, and this day, as resembling the sweet potato.</note>
            <note xml:id="n33050413" n="13">
               <name type="person" key="Tetoharsky">Tetoharsky</name>, a chief of the <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perces</name>, whom the party met in October 1805. The etymology of the term "<name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Chopunnish</name>" is discussed at <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> entry of <ref n="1805-09-17" type="related">September 17, 1805</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n33050414" n="14">
               <name type="person" key="Old Toby">Toby</name> left the party on <ref n="1805-10-09" type="related">October 9, 1805</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n33050415" n="15">
               <name type="place" key="Alpowa Creek">Alpowa Creek</name> reaches the <name type="place"
                     key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Snake (Lewis's) River</name> in <name type="place" key="Asotin County, Wash.">Asotin County</name>, <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>. The 
point is near former <name type="place" key="Silcott, Wash.">Silcott</name>, site of the <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name> village visited on <ref n="1805-10-11" type="related">October 11, 1805</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n33050416" n="16">The <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Koos-koos-ke</name> is the <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Clearwater River</name>; <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name> evidently means the point where it joins 
the <name type="place"
                     key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Snake</name> on the <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>-<name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name> border.</note>
            <note xml:id="n33050417" n="17">
               <name type="place" key="Tetoharsky">Tetoharsky</name>, the <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name> chief who, with <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">Twisted Hair</name>, accompanied them down the 
<name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Clearwater</name>, <name type="place"
                     key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Snake</name>, and <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> rivers some distance on the westbound journey.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-05-03" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-05-05" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
