<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-06-13">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">June 13, 1805</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic
        Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            4</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">April7–July 27, 1805</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1987</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">283-289</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">167</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">101-102</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jw">Joseph Whitehouse</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            11</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of Joseph Whitehouse, May 14, 1804–April 2,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1997</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">195-196</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
         <geoDecl datum="WGS" xml:id="lc.geo.1805-06-13.01">
            <placeName/>
            <geo>47.7736 -110.7757</geo>
            <note>Lewis arrived in Great Falls on this day, and Clark was still progressing up the
          Missouri. Camped in Chouteau County, MT, in the vacinity of Bird Coulee</note>
         </geoDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc/>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-02-04</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-04-12</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1805-06-13">June 13, 1805</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-06-13.01"
              ref="lc.geo.1805-06-13.01">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Thursday June 13th 1805.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>This morning we set out about sunrise after taking breakfast off our venison and
          fish.    we again ascended the hills of the river and gained the level
          country.    the country through which we passed for the first six miles tho'
          more roling than that we had passed yesterday might still with propryety be deemed a
          level country; our course as yesterday was generally S W.    the river from
          the place we left it appeared to make a considerable bend to the South.   
          from the extremity of this roling country I overlooked a most beatifull and level plain
          of great extent or at least 50 or sixty miles; in this there were infinitely more
          buffaloe than I had ever before witnessed at a view.    nearly in the
          direction I had been travling or S. W. two curious mountains presented themselves of
          square figures,
          <ref target="n15061301" n="1"/>the sides rising perpendicularly to the hight of 250
          feet and appeared to be formed of yellow clay; their tops appeared to be level plains;
          these inaccessible hights appeared like the ramparts of immence fortifications; I have
          no doubt but with very little assistance from art they might be rendered impregnable.
             fearing that the river boar to the South and that I might pass the falls if
          they existed between this an the 
          <name type="place" key="Lewis (Snowy) Range">snowey mountains</name>I altered my course
          nealy to the South leaving those insulated hills to my wright and proceeded through the
          plain; I sent Feels on my right and 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Gibson, George">Gibson</name>on my left with orders to kill
          some meat and join me at the river where I should halt for dinner. I had proceded on
          this course about two miles with 
          <name type="person" key="Goodrich, Silas">Goodrich</name>at some distance behind me whin
          my ears were saluted with the agreeable sound of a fall of water and advancing a little
          further I saw the spray arrise above the plain like a collumn of smoke which would
          frequently dispear again in an instant caused I presume by the wind which blew pretty
          hard from the S. W. I did not however loose my direction to this point which soon began
          to make a roaring too tremendious to be mistaken for any cause short of the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">great falls of the
          Missouri</name>.    here I arrived about 12 OClock having traveled by estimate
          about 15 Miles. I hurryed down the hill which was about 200 feet high and difficult of
          access, to gaze on this sublimely grand specticle.
          <ref target="n15061302" n="2"/>I took my position on the top of some rocks about 20
          feet high opposite the center of the falls.    this chain of rocks appear once
          to have formed a part of those over which the waters tumbled, but in the course of time
          has been seperated from it to the distance of 150 yards lying prarrallel to it and
          forming a butment against which the water after falling over the precipice beats with
          great fury; this barrier extends on the right to the perpendicular clift which forms
          that board [bound? border?] of the river but to the distance of 120 yards next to the
          clift it is but a few feet above the level of the water, and here the water in very high
          tides appears to pass in a channel of 40 yds. next to the higher part of the ledg of
          rocks; on the left it extends within 80 or ninty yards of the lard. Clift which is also
          perpendicular; between this abrupt extremity of the ledge of rocks and the perpendicular
          bluff the whole body of water passes with incredible swiftness.    immediately
          at the cascade the river is about 300 yds. wide; about ninty or a hundred yards of this
          next the Lard. bluff is a smoth even sheet of water falling over a precipice of at least
          eighty feet, the remaining part of about 200 yards on my right formes the grandest sight
          I ever beheld, the hight of the fall is the same of the other but the irregular and
          somewhat projecting rocks below receives the water in it's passage down and brakes it
          into a perfect white foam which assumes a thousand forms in a moment sometimes flying up
          in jets of sparkling foam to the hight of fifteen or twenty feet and are scarcely formed
          before large roling bodies of the same beaten and foaming water is thrown over and
          conceals them.    in short the rocks seem to be most happily fixed to present
          a sheet of the whitest beaten froath for 200 yards in length and about 80 feet
          perpendicular.    the water after decending strikes against the butment before
          mentioned or that on which I stand and seems to reverberate and being met by the more
          impetuous courant they role and swell into half formed billows of great hight which rise
          and again disappear in an instant.    this butment of rock defends a handsom
          little bottom of about three acres which is deversified and agreeably shaded with some
          cottonwood trees; in the lower extremity of the bottom there is a very thick grove of
          the same kind of trees which are small, in this wood there are several Indian lodges
          formed of sticks.    a few small cedar grow near the ledge of rocks where I
          rest.    below the point of these rocks at a small distance the river is
          divided by a large rock which rises several feet above the water, and extends downwards
          with the stream for about 20 yards.    about a mile before the water arrives
          at the pitch it decends very rappidly, and is confined on the Lard. side by a
          perpendicular clift of about 100 feet, on Stard. side it is also perpendicular for about
          three hundred yards above the pitch where it is then broken by the discharge of a small
          ravine, down which the buffaloe have a large beaten road to the water, [
          <hi rend="italic">NE: Qu.</hi>] for it is but in very few places that these anamals can
          obtain water near this place owing to the steep and inaccessible banks. I see several
          skelletons of the buffaloe lying in the edge of the water near the Stard. bluff which I
          presume have been swept down by the current and precipitated over this tremendious fall.
             about 300 yards below me there is another butment of solid rock with a
          perpendicular face and abot 60 feet high which projects from the Stard. side at right
          angles to the distance of 134 yds. and terminates the lower part nearly of the bottom
          before mentioned; there being a passage arround the end of this butment between it and
          the river of about 20 yardes; here the river again assumes it's usual width soon
          spreading to near 300 yards but still continues it's rappidity.    from the
          reflection of the sun on the spray or mist which arrises from these falls there is a
          beatifull rainbow produced which adds not a little to the beauty of this majestically
          grand senery.    after wrighting this imperfect discription I again viewed the
          falls and was so much disgusted with the imperfect idea which it conveyed of the scene
          that I determined to draw my pen across it and begin agin, but then reflected that I
          could not perhaps succeed better than pening the first impressions of the mind; I wished
          for the pencil of Salvator Rosa [
          <hi rend="italic">EC: a Titian</hi>] or the pen of 
          <name type="person" key="Thomson, James">Thompson</name>,
          <ref target="n15061303" n="3"/>that I might be enabled to give to the enlightened world
          some just idea of this truly magnifficent and sublimely grand object, which has from the
          commencement of time been concealed from the view of civilized man; but this was
          fruitless and vain. I most sincerely regreted that I had not brought a crimee obscura
          <ref target="n15061304" n="4"/>with me by the assistance of which even I could have
          hoped to have done better but alas this was also out of my reach; I therefore with the
          assistance of my pen only indeavoured to trace
          <ref target="n15061305" n="5"/>some of the stronger features of this seen by the
          assistance of which and my recollection aided by some able pencil I hope still to give
          to the world some faint idea of an object which at this moment fills me with such
          pleasure and astonishment, and which of it's kind I will venture to ascert is second to
          but one in the known world. I retired to the shade of a tree where I determined to fix
          my camp
          <ref target="n15061306" n="6"/>for the present and dispatch a man in the morning to
          inform 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. C.</name>and the party of my success in
          finding the falls and settle in their minds all further doubts as to the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>.    the hunters now
          arrived loaded with excellent buffaloe meat and informed me that they had killed three
          very fat cows about ¾ of a mile hence. I directed them after they had refreshed
          themselves to go back and butcher them and bring another load of meat each to our camp
          determining to employ those who remained with me in drying meat for the party against
          their arrival.    in about 2 hours or at 4 OClock P. M. they set out on this
          duty, and I walked down the river about three miles to discover if possible some place
          to which the canoes might arrive or at which they might be drawn on shore in order to be
          taken by land above the falls; but returned without effecting either of these objects;
          the river was one continued sene of rappids and cascades which I readily perceived could
          not be encountered with our canoes, and the Clifts still retained their perpendicular
          structure and were from 150 to 200 feet high; in short the river appears here to have
          woarn a channel in the process of time through a solid rock.    on my return I
          found the party at camp; they had butchered the buffaloe and brought in some more meat
          as I had directed. 
          <name type="person" key="Goodrich, Silas">Goodrich</name>had caught half a douzen very
          fine trout
          <ref target="n15061307" n="7"/>and a number of both species of the white fish.
             these trout [
          <hi rend="italic">NB: caught in the falls</hi>] are from sixteen to twenty three inches
          in length, precisely resemble our mountain or speckled trout in form and the position of
          their fins, but the specks on these are of a deep black instead of the red or goald
          colour of those common to the U.' States.    these are furnished long sharp
          teeth on the pallet and tongue and have generally a small dash of red on each side
          behind the front ventral fins; the flesh is of a pale yellowish red, or when in good
          order, of a rose red.—</p>
               <p>I am induced to believe that the Brown, the white and the Grizly bear of this country
          are the same species only differing in colour from age or more probably from the same
          natural cause that many other anamals of the same family differ in colour.   
          one of those which we killed yesterday was of a creemcoloured white while the other in
          company with it was of the common bey or rdish brown, which seems to be the most usual
          colour of them.    the white one appeared from it's tallons and teath to be
          the youngest; it was smaller than the other, and although a monstrous beast we supposed
          that it had not yet attained it's growth and that it was a little upwards of two years
          old.    the young cubs which we have killed have always been of a brownish
          white, but none of them as white as that we killed yesterday.    one other
          that we killed sometime since which I mentioned sunk under some driftwood and was lost,
          had a white stripe or list of about eleven inches wide entirely arround his body just
          behind the shoalders, and was much darker than these bear usually are.    the
          grizly bear we have never yet seen. I have seen their tallons in possession of the
          Indians and from their form I am perswaded if there is any difference between this
          species and the brown or white bear it is very inconsiderable. There is no such anamal
          as a black bear in this open country or of that species generally denominated the black
          bear</p>
               <p>my fare is really sumptuous this evening; buffaloe's humps, tongues and marrowbones,
          fine trout parched meal pepper and salt, and a good appetite; the last is not considered
          the least of the luxuries.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-06-13.02"
              ref="lc.geo.1805-06-13.01">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">June 13th Thursday 1805</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>a fair morning, Some dew this morning    
          <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">the Indian woman</name>Verry sick    I
          gave her a doste of Salts. We Set out early, at a mile &amp; ½ passed a Small rapid
          Stream on the Lard Side which heads in a mountain to the S. E 12 or 15 miles, which at
          this time covered with Snow, we call this stream 
          <ref target="n15061308" n="8">
                     <name type="place" key="Shonkin Creek (Snow River)">Snow river</name>,</ref>as it is the
          conveyance of the melted snow from that mountain at present.    numbers of
          gees &amp; goslings, the gees cannot fly at this Season—    goose berries are
          ripe and in great abundance, the yellow Current is also Common, not yet ripe
             Killed a buffalow &amp; 
          <ref target="n15061309" n="9">Campd on the Lard Side near an old Indian fortified
          camp</ref>   
          <ref target="n15061310" n="10">one man Sick</ref>&amp; 3 with Swellings, 
          <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">the Indian woman</name>verry Sick. Killed a goat
          &amp; 
          <name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">fraser</name>2 Buffalow</p>
               <p>
                  <table rows="15" cols="3">
                     <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Course and distance June 13th 1805</hi>
                        <ref target="n15061311" n="11"/>
                     </head>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">miles</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 45° W</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  1 ½</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">to the mouth of 
                <name type="place" key="Shonkin Creek (Snow River)">Snow river</name>on the Lard.
                Side opsd. an
                <lb/>Island    passed 2 Islands</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 60° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  1 ½</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">to the lower point of an Island [
                <hi rend="italic">overwritten,</hi>"Timber"] on
                <lb/>the Stard. Side    passed the Island</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">South</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">     ¼</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">on the Stard. Side to the point opposit a
                black Slate bluff.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S 45° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  1 ½</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">to the upper part of a wood Stard Side</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 20° W</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  1 ¼</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">to a black bluff on the Lard Side</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 30° W</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  1</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">to the lower point of an Island</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">West</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  1 ¾</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">to a Bush on the Side of a bluff in the Stard.
                bend    passed
                <lb/>2 Islds. &amp; a Lard point</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S 60° E</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">     ¾</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">to a hollow in the bluff in a Lard bend
                   passed 2 Small
                <lb/>Islands</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">South</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">     ¼</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">to a Lodge on a small Island</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 80° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  1</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">to the lower point of an Island</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 40° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">     ¼</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">to a Stoney bluff Stard. Side, at the head of
                the Island a
                <lb/>rapid across R</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">South</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  1 ¼</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">to a tree on a Small Island in the Lard. bend
                under a high
                <lb/>hill    passed 2 Islands</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 70° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rend="underline" rows="1" cols="1">  1 ½</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">to the Lower point of an Island   
                passed 2 Small Islands—
                <lb/>Camped on the Lard Shore</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">13</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>The river verry rapid maney Sholes great nos of large Stones    passed Some
          bluffs or low cliffts of Slate to day</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-06-13.03"
              ref="lc.geo.1805-06-13.01">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Thursday 13th June 1805</hi>.    a beautiful pleasant
          morning.    we Set out at an eairly hour    a heavy diew.
             proceeded on.    passed the mouth of a Small River
          <ref target="n15061312" n="12"/>on the Lard. Side about 50 yds. wide at the mouth of a
          muddy coulour and verry rapid.    bottoms of cotton timber for Some distance
          up    we named it 
          <name type="place" key="Shonkin Creek (Snow River)">Snowey River</name>as it heads in
          the mountain covred with Snow to our left.    we passed verry high bluffs on
          each Side of the River. Some Small bottoms of cotton timber. Saw abundance of wild or
          choke cherrys, the Goose berrys are now ripe &amp; abound in the River bottoms.
             also a yallow current
          <ref target="n15061313" n="13"/>the kind I never Saw before.    they are
          nearly as large as the goose berrys, but Sower &amp; yallow when ripe    we
          Came 14 miles to day and Camped on the South Side, Some of the hunters killed a buffalow
          and 2 Deer to day—</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-06-13.04"
              ref="lc.geo.1805-06-13.01">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Thursday 13th.</hi>We set out early in a fine morning. Some dew fell
          last night. We passed a large creek on the south side, called Snow creek. The water of
          the river is very clear and the current very rapid. We passed a number of islands
          covered with timber; but there is none to be seen on the hills on either side. We went
          14 miles and encamped on the south side.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-06-13.05"
              ref="lc.geo.1805-06-13.01">
            <sp who="jw">
               <speaker>Whitehouse</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Thursday 13th June 1805</hi>.    a beautiful pleasant
          morning.    we Set out at an eairly hour &amp; proceeded on.   
          passed the Mouth of a Small River on the South Side about 50 yards wide &amp; rapid
          current &amp; of a muddy coulour.    I went over the River to See it.
             large bottoms of cotton timber for Some distance up.    we named
          it 
          <name type="place" key="Shonkin Creek (Snow River)">Snowey River</name>, as we expect it
          comes from the 
          <name type="place" key="Lewis (Snowy) Range">Snowey Mountain</name>, to the South of us.
             passed verry high bluffs on each Side Some Small bottoms of cotton timber.
             we Saw abundance of wild or choke cherries &amp; a kind of yallow current,
          <ref target="n15061314" n="14"/>Such as I never Saw before.    the Goose
          berrys are now ripe &amp; abound in the River bottoms—    we came 14 miles to
          day &amp; Camped on the South Side.    I was taken verry Sick to day, &amp; a
          vilont head ack.    2 deer &amp; [
          <hi rend="italic">illegible</hi>] buffalow killed to day.</p>
               <p>Thursday June 13th    We had a Clear &amp; pleasant morning, and set out on
          our Voyage at sun rise, we proceeded on, and passed the mouth of a small River lying on
          the South side called 
          <name type="place" key="Shonkin Creek (Snow River)">Smiths</name>
                  <ref target="n15061315" n="15"/>River which was 〈and〉 about 50 Yards wide, 〈which was
          called 
          <name type="place" key="Smith River">Smiths River</name>〉 the current in this River runs
          rapid and its water was muddy, I was sent over to this small River by 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain Clark</name>in order to make what
          discoveries I could, I found large bottoms of land lying along the River, for some
          distance, and the Land very rich, the growth in those bottoms of Rich land being chiefly
          cotton wood.—    
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain Clark</name>called this River 
          <name type="place" key="Shonkin Creek (Snow River)">Smiths river</name>, and we expect
          its source lay in the Mountains; we saw some days past, covered with Snow;—   
          lying to the South west of us.    we continued on our way and passed some very
          high bluffs, lying on both sides of the River, and small bottoms of cotton wood Timber,
          and found a large quantity of wild Artichokes, Cherries, and Yellow currants, the last
          of which none of our party had ever seen before, &amp; also Goose berries growing in
          abundance which were ripe &amp; grew in the River bottoms, The land that we passed
          through, as we passed along this day; was extreamly Rich, and fertile, The hunters that
          was out killed one Buffalo this day.—    We came 14 Miles this day, and
          encamped in the Evening on the South side of the River.—</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n15061301" n="1">These are probably buttes just south of 
        <name type="place" key="Black Horse Lake">Black Horse Lake</name>along 
        <name type="place" key="Highway 87">Highway 87</name>north of 
        <name type="place" key="Great Falls, Mont.">Great Falls</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Cascade County, Mont.">Cascade County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n15061302" n="2">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>had arrived at the 
        <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">Great Falls</name>, first of a
        series of five falls in 
        <name type="place" key="Cascade County, Mont.">Cascade County</name>, northeast of the
        present city of 
        <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">Great Falls</name>. The
        spectacle he saw has been considerably reduced by 
        <name type="place" key="Ryan Dam">Ryan Dam</name>. Appleman (LC), 309–17; 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>maps 44, 54, 61; MRC map 77. The cliffs surrounding the 
        <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">Falls of the
        Missouri</name>are composed of the lower Cretaceous 
        <name type="place" key="Kootenai Formation">Kootenai Formation</name>. It contains
        light-brown and red-brown sandstone, red-to-purple shale, and green shale. The gorge was
        cut during the glacial period when ice diverted the 
        <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>from its former course.</note>
            <note xml:id="n15061303" n="3">
               <name type="person" key="Rosa, Salvator">Salvator Rosa</name>, seventeenth-century Italian
        landscape painter, generally painted wild, desolate scenes. 
        <name type="person" key="Thomson, James">James Thomson</name>, eighteenth-century Scottish
        poet, was a forerunner of the English Romantic movement; his best-known poem was "The
        Seasons."</note>
            <note xml:id="n15061304" n="4">A camera obscura, basically a box with a lens mounted on
        one wall; light entering through the lens would project an image on the opposite wall of
        the dark box, which an artist could then trace, getting an almost photographic
        image.</note>
            <note xml:id="n15061305" n="5">No drawing of the falls by 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>has ever been known to
        exist.</note>
            <note xml:id="n15061306" n="6">Near the 
        <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">Great Falls</name>, on the
        north side of the river, in 
        <name type="place" key="Cascade County, Mont.">Cascade County</name>. The area, but not
        the campsite, appears on 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>maps 54, 61; MRC map 77.</note>
            <note xml:id="n15061307" n="7">The cutthroat trout, 
        <hi rend="italic">Salmo clarkii</hi>after 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark</name>, a species new to science.
        Cutright (LCPN), 157–58; Lee et al., 105, 114. The fish used for comparison is the brook
        trout, 
        <hi rend="italic">Salvelinus fontinalis</hi>. It was probably Biddle who drew a red
        vertical line through this passage about the trout and part of the next about the
        bears.</note>
            <note xml:id="n15061308" n="8">
               <name type="place" key="Shonkin Creek (Snow River)">Shonkin Creek</name>; see above, 
        <ref n="1805-06-04" type="related">June 4, 1805</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n15061309" n="9">In 
        <name type="place" key="Chouteau County, Mont.">Chouteau County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>, perhaps in the vicinity of 
        <name type="place" key="Bird Coulee">Bird Coulee</name>. 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>maps 54, 61; MRC map 76.</note>
            <note xml:id="n15061310" n="10">
               <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse</name>says he was very sick and
        had "a violent head ack."</note>
            <note xml:id="n15061311" n="11">Also given on 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>map 42, in 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>hand.</note>
            <note xml:id="n15061312" n="12">
               <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>passed it on his trip on June 4; it
        is now 
        <name type="place" key="Shonkin Creek (Snow River)">Shonkin Creek</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Chouteau County, Mont.">Chouteau County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n15061313" n="13">Probably the buffalo currant, 
        <hi rend="italic">Ribes ordoratum</hi>Wendl. f., but possibly the golden currant, 
        <hi rend="italic">R. aureum</hi>Pursh. See 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>entry of 
        <ref n="1805-04-30" type="related">April 30, 1805</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n15061314" n="14">Probably the buffalo currant, 
        <hi rend="italic">Ribes ordoratum</hi>Wendl. f., but possibly the golden currant, 
        <hi rend="italic">R. aureum</hi>Pursh.</note>
            <note xml:id="n15061315" n="15">A clear misreading of 
        <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse's</name>"
        <name type="place" key="Shonkin Creek (Snow River)">Snowey River</name>."</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-06-12" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-06-14" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
