<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-05-13">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">May 13, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic
        Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            7</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">March 23–June 9, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1991</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">252-255</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">309</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">227</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
         <geoDecl datum="WGS" xml:id="lc.geo.1806-05-13.01">
            <placeName/>
            <geo>46.2299 -116.0186</geo>
            <note>Camped near the Kamiah railroad depot, Lewis County, ID.</note>
         </geoDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journal Entries</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-10-13</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-04-12</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1806-05-13">May 13, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-05-13.01"
              ref="lc.geo.1806-05-13.01">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Tuesday May 13th 1806.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>This morning 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. C.</name>as usual was busily engaged with
          his patients untill eleven OCk.    at 1 P. M. we collected our horses and set
          out for the river escorted by a number of the natives on horseback.    we
          followed the creek
          <ref target="n35051301" n="1"/>downwards about two miles, passing a stout branch
          <ref target="n35051302" n="2"/>at 1 m. which flowed in on the wright.    our
          course S. E.    we now entered an extensive open bottom of the 
          <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Kooskooske R.</name>
                  <ref target="n35051303" n="3"/>through which we passed nearly N. about 1½ miles and
          halted on the bank of the river at the place appointed to meet the canoe.   
          the man had set out early this morning for the purpose but had not yet arrived with the
          canoe we therefore unloaded our horses and turned them out to graize.    as
          the canoe did not arrive untill after sunset we remained here all night;
          <ref target="n35051304" n="4"/>a number of the natives continued with us.   
          in the evening we tryed the speed of several of our horses.    these horses
          are active strong and well formed.    these people have immence numbers of
          them    50, 60 or a hundred hed is not unusual for an individual to possess.
          The 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Chopunnish</name>are in general stout
          well formed active men.    they have high noses and many of them on the
          acqueline order with cheerfull and agreeable countenances; their complexions are not
          remarkable.    in common with other savage nations of America they extract
          their beards but the men do not uniformly extract the hair below, this is more
          particularly confined to the females. I observed several men among them whom I am
          convinced if they had shaved their beards instead of extracting it would have been as
          well supplyed in this particular as any of my countrymen.    they appear to be
          cheerfull but not gay; they are fond of gambling and of their amusements which consist
          principally in shooting their arrows at a bowling target made of willow bark, and in
          riding and exercising themselves on horseback, racing &amp;c.    they are
          expert marksmen and good riders. they do not appear to be so much devoted to baubles as
          most of the nations we have met with, but seem anxious always to obtain articles of
          utility, such as knives, axes, tommahawks, kettles blankets and mockerson alls.
             blue beads however may form an exception to this remark; this article among
          all the nations of this country may be justly compared to goald or silver among
          civilized nations. They are generally well cloathes in their stile.    their
          dress consists of a long shirt which reaches to the middle of thye, long legings which
          reach as high as the waist, mockersons, and robes.    these are formed of
          various skins and are in all rispects like those particularly discribed of the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshones</name>.    their
          women also dress like the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshones</name>.    their
          ornaments consist of beads shells and peices of brass variously attatched to their
          dress, to their ears arrond their necks wrists arms &amp;c.    a bando of some
          kind usually surrounds the head, this is most frequently the skin of some fir animal as
          the fox otter &amp;c. tho' they have them also of dressed skin without the hair.
             the ornament of the nose is a single shell of the wampum.    the
          pirl and beads are suspended from the ears.    beads are woarn arround their
          wrists necks and over their sholders crosswise in the form of a double sash.
             the hair of the men is cewed in two rolls which hang on each side in front
          of the body as before discribed of other inhabitants of the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>.    collars of bears
          claws are also common; but the article of dress on which they appear to bstow most pains
          and ornaments is a kind of collar or brestplate; this is most comonly a strip of
          otterskin of about six inches wide taken out of the center of the skin it's whole length
          including the head.    this is dressed with the hair on; a hole is cut
          lengthwise through the skin near the head of the animal sufficiently large to admit the
          head of the person to pass.    thus it is placed about the neck and hangs in
          front of the body the tail frequently reaching below their knees; on this skin in front
          is attatched peices of pirl, beads, wampum peices of red cloth and in short whatever
          they conceive most valuable or ornamental. I observed a tippit woarn by 
          <name type="person" key="Hohots Ilppilp">Hohâstillpilp</name>, which was formed of human
          scalps and ornamented with the thumbs and fingers of several men which he had slain in
          battle.    their women brade their hair in two tresses which hang in the same
          position of those of the men.    they also wear a cap or cup on the head
          formed of beargrass and cedar bark.    the men also frequently attatch some
          small ornament to a small plat of hair on the center of the crown of their heads</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-05-13.02"
              ref="lc.geo.1806-05-13.01">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Tuesday 13th May 1806.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>a fine morning    I administered to the Sick and gave directions.
             we collected all our horses and Set out at 1 P. M. and proceeded down the
          Creek to the 
          <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">
                     <hi rend="italic">Flat head</hi>River</name>
                  <ref target="n35051305" n="5"/>a Short distance below the enterance of the Creek at the
          distance of 3 miles from the Village.    at this place we expected to have met
          the Canoe which was promised to be furnished us, and for which an indian Set out very
          early this morning.    we halted at the 
          <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">
                     <hi rend="italic">Flat Head</hi>River</name>unloaded our horses and turnd. them out to
          feed. Several Indians accompanied us to the river and Continued untill evening. The man
          who Set out early this morning to the forks of this river for a Canoe and was to meet us
          at this place.    as the Canoe did not arive untill after Sun set we remained
          all night; in the evening we tried the Speed of Several of our horses.   
          these horses are strong active and well formed. Those people have emence numbers of them
          50 or 60 or a Hundred head is not unusial for an individual to possess.</p>
               <p>The 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Chopunnish</name>are in general Stout
          well formd active men.    they have high noses and maney of them on he
          acqueline order with chearfull and agreeable countinances; their complexions are not
          remarkable.    in common with other Indian Nations of America they extract
          their beard, but the men do not uniformly extract the hair below, this is more
          particularly confined to the females.    they appear to be cheerfull but not
          gay; they are fond of gambling and of their amusements which consists principally in
          shooting their arrows at a targit made of Willow bark, and in rideing and exersiseing
          themselves on horsback, raceing &amp;c.    they are expirt marks men &amp;
          good riders.    they do not appear to be So much devoted to baubles as most of
          the nations we have met with, but Seen anxious always to riceve articles of utility,
          Such as knives, axes, Kittles, blankets &amp; Mockerson awls.    blue beeds
          however may form an exception to this remark; This article among all the nations of this
          Country may be justly compared to gold and Silver among civilized nations. They are
          generally well clothed in their Stile.    their dress Consists of a long shirt
          which reaches to the middle of leg, long legins which reach as high as the waist,
          mockersons &amp; robe.    those are formed of various skins and are in all
          respects like those of the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshone</name>. Their orniments
          consists of beeds, Shells and peices of brass variously attached to their dress, to
          their ears arround theire necks wrists arms &amp;c.    a band of Some kind
          usially Serounds the head, this is most frequently the Skin of Some fer animal as the
          fox otter &amp;c.; I observed a tippet worn by 
          <name type="person" key="Hohots Ilppilp">Hohâstillpilp</name>, which was formed of
          Humane Scalps and ornemented with the thumbs and fingers of Several men which he had
          Slain in battle.    they also were a coller or breast plate of otter Skin
          orniminted with Shells beeds &amp; quills.    the women brade their hair in
          two tresses which hang in the same position of those of the men, which ar Cewed and hang
          over each sholder.    &amp;c</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-05-13.03"
              ref="lc.geo.1806-05-13.01">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>Tuesday 13th of May 1806.    a clear frosty morning.    we
          collected all our horses 60 in number now together and all good except 4 which has Sore
          backs, &amp;C.    a number of the natives went at playing the game
          <ref target="n35051306" n="6"/>as those below    had considerable property up
          on each Side Such as beed Strips of otter Skins which was filled with rich Shells,
          trinkets &amp; Spanish bridles &amp;C &amp;C.    about 12 oClock we set out
          and proced on down the creek.
          <ref target="n35051307" n="7"/>   a bold runing Stream about 15 yds wide.
             considerable of cotton &amp; cherry    servis berry also in the
          bottoms.    about 4 miles we came to its mouth a handsom low plain rich Soil
          &amp; timber around    went a short distance down the 
          <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">kooskooskee
          river</name>
                  <ref target="n35051308" n="8"/>and halted to wait for a canoe which we expect the
          natives to bring us from above this place.    we intend crossing the river
          here and Camp on the other Side untill Such times as the Snow will admit of our crossing
          the mountains.    a number of the natives followed us    we Swapped
          Several horses with them.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-05-13.04"
              ref="lc.geo.1806-05-13.01">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Tuesday 13th.</hi>   We had a fine morning with white frost.
          Having collected our horses, we found we had 60 and all pretty good except 4, which were
          studs and had sore backs. At noon we proceeded down the branch, which has a good deal of
          cotton wood, willow, and cherry tree
          <ref target="n35051309" n="9"/>on its banks; and is a bold rapid stream, about 15 yards
          wide. We kept down the branch about four miles; and then came to the river
          <ref target="n35051310" n="10"/>where it passes through a beautiful plain.— Here we
          halted to wait for a canoe, which we expected that some of the natives would bring up
          the river, to assist us in crossing; when we intended to encamp until the snow shall
          have sufficiently melted to admit of our crossing the mountains. At dark the canoe came,
          but it being too late to cross we encamped
          <ref target="n35051311" n="11"/>on the south side.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n35051301" n="1">Down the north bank of 
        <name type="place" key="Lawyer (Commearp) Creek">Lawyer Creek</name>, in 
        <name type="place" key="Lewis County, Idaho">Lewis County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>; not shown on 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>map 71. Space, 27; Peebles (RLC), 20; Peebles (LT),
        map.</note>
            <note xml:id="n35051302" n="2">
               <name type="place" key="Sevenmile Creek">Sevenmile Creek</name>, in 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho County, Idaho">Idaho County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>. Space, 27.</note>
            <note xml:id="n35051303" n="3">Just south of present 
        <name type="place" key="Kamiah, Idaho">Kamiah</name>, in 
        <name type="place" key="Lewis County, Idaho">Lewis County</name>. Ibid., 27.</note>
            <note xml:id="n35051304" n="4">Near the present 
        <name type="place" key="Kamiah, Idaho">Kamiah</name>railroad depot, in 
        <name type="place" key="Lewis County, Idaho">Lewis County</name>. Ibid., 27.</note>
            <note xml:id="n35051305" n="5">The 
        <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Clearwater</name>. The
        word may have been added to a blank space, as too, the next mention.</note>
            <note xml:id="n35051306" n="6">The Indian hand game again.</note>
            <note xml:id="n35051307" n="7">Down the north bank of 
        <name type="place" key="Lawyer (Commearp) Creek">Lawyer Creek</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Lewis County, Idaho">Lewis County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n35051308" n="8">Actually they went up the 
        <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Clearwater
        River</name>about 1½ miles and camped at 
        <name type="place" key="Kamiah, Idaho">Kamiah</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Lewis County, Idaho">Lewis County</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n35051309" n="9">Any of several varieties of cherry, 
        <hi rend="italic">Prunus</hi>sp.</note>
            <note xml:id="n35051310" n="10">The 
        <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Clearwater River</name>,
        their 
        <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">
        Kooskooske</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n35051311" n="11">Near the 
        <name type="place" key="Kamiah, Idaho">Kamiah</name>railroad depot, 
        <name type="place" key="Lewis County, Idaho">Lewis County</name>.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-05-12" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-05-14" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
