<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-05-06">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
May 6, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               
               
               
               
               
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml" n="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc" n="Clark, William">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 7</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">March 23–June 9, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1991</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">215-220</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo" n="Ordway, John">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf" n="Floyd, Charles">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">306</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg" n="Gass, Patrick">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">222</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
         <geoDecl datum="WGS" xml:id="lc.geo.1806-05-06.01">
            <placeName/>
            <geo>46.6 -116.5167</geo>
            <note>Camped on the Clearwater River, Nez Perce County, ID, near the mouth of Pine Creek.</note>
         </geoDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Journal Entries</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-10-11</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1806-05-06">May 6, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-05-06.01" n="lc.geo.1806-05-06.01">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Tuesday May 6th 1806.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
This morning the husband of the sick woman was as good as his word, he produced us a young horse in tolerable order which we immediately killed and butchered.    the inhabitants seemed more accomodating this morning; they sold us some bread.    we received a second horse for medecine and prescription for a little girl with the rheumatism. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. C.</name> dressed the woman again this morning who declared that she had rested better last night than she had since she had been sick.    sore eyes is an universal complaint with all the natives we have seen on the west side of the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky mountains</name>. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. C.</name> was busily engaged for several hours this morning in administering eye-water to a croud of applicants.    we once more obtained a plentifull meal, much to the comfort of all the party. I exchanged horses with <name type="person" key="Apash Wyakaikt">We-ark'-koomt</name> and gave him a small flag with which he was much gratifyed.    the sorrel I obtained is an eligant strong active well broke horse perfictly calculated for my purposes.    at this place we met with three men of a nation called the <name type="native_nation" key="Coeur d'Alene Indians">Skeets-so-mich</name>
                  <ref target="n33050601" n="1"/> who reside at the falls of a large river disharging itself into the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> on it's East side to the North of the entrance of <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">Clark's river</name>.    this river they informed us headed in a large lake in the mountains and that the falls below which they resided was at no great distance from the lake.    these people are the same in their dress and appearance with the <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Chopunnish</name>, tho' their language is intirely different a circumstance which I did not learn untill we were about to set out and it was then too late to take a vocabulary. The river here called <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">Clark's river</name> is that which we have heretofore called the <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">Flathead river</name>,<ref target="n33050602" n="2"/> I have thus named it in honour of my worthy friend and fellow traveller <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name>.    for this stream we know no indian name and no whiteman but ourselves was ever on it's principal branches.    the river which <name type="person" key="Fidler, Peter">Fidler</name> calls the great Lake river<ref target="n33050603" n="3"/> may possibly be a branch of it but if so it is but a very inconsiderable branch and may as probably empty itself into the <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">Skeetssomish</name> as into that river.    the stream which I have heretofore called <name type="place" key="Deschutes (Clark's, Towanahiook's) River">Clark's river</name>
                  <ref target="n33050604" n="4"/> has it's three principal sources in mountains <name type="place" key="Mount Hood (Timm, Falls Mountain)">Hood</name>, <name type="place" key="Mount Jefferson">Jefferson</name> &amp; the Northern side of the <name type="place" key="Blue (Southwest, Southeast) Mountains">S. W. Mountains</name> and is of course a short river.    this river I shall in future call the <name type="place" key="Deschutes (Clark's, Towanahiook's) River">To-wannahiooks river</name> it being the name by which it is called by the <name type="native_nation" key="Tenino Indians">Eneshur</name> nation. The <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Kooskooske river</name> may be safely navigated at present all the rocks of the shoals and rapids are perfectly covered; the current is strong, the water clear and cold.    this river is rising fast.— The timber of this river which consists principally of the long leafed pine commences about 2 miles below our present camp on <name type="place" key="Potlatch River (Colter's Creek)">Colter's Creek</name>. it was two oclock this evening before we could collect our horses.    at 3 P.M. we set out accompanyed by the brother of the <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">twisted hair</name> and <name type="person" key="Apash Wyakaikt">We arkkoomt</name>. I directed the horse which we had obtained for the purpose of eating to be led as it was yet unbroke, in performing this duty a quarrel ensued between <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name> and <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name>.    we continued our march this evening along the river 9 miles to a lodge of 6 families, built of sticks hats &amp; dryed hay in the same form of those heretofore discribed.    we passed a lodge of 3 families at 4 ms. on the road.    no provision of any discription was to be obtained of these people.    a little after dark our young horse broke the rope by which he was confined and made his escape much to the chagrine of all who recollected the keenness of their appetites last evening.    the brother of the <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">twisted hair</name> and <name type="person" key="Apash Wyakaikt">Wearkkoomt</name> with 10 or 12 others encamped with us this evening.—<ref target="n33050605" n="5"/>
               </p>
               <p>
the natives have a considerable salmon fishery up <name type="person" key="Potlatch River (Colter's Creek)">Colter's Creek</name>.    this stream extends itself to the pirs of the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">rocky mountain</name> and in much the greater part of it's course passes through a well timbered pine country it is 25 yds. wide and discharges a large body of water.    the banks low and bed formed of pebbles.—    had a small shower of rain this evening.—
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-05-06.02" n="lc.geo.1806-05-06.01">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Tuesday May 6th 1806</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
This morning the Susband of the Sick woman was as good as his word.    he produced us a young horse in tolerable order which we imedeately had killed and butchered.    the inhabitents Seemed more accommodating this morning.    they Sold us Some bread.    we received a Second horse for Medecine &amp; procription to a little girl with the rhumitism whome I had bathed in worm water, and anointed her a little with balsom Capivia.<ref target="n33050606" n="6"/> I dressed the woman again this morning who declared that She had rested better last night than She had Since She had been sick. Sore Eyes is an universal Complaint among all the nations which we have Seen on the West Side of the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">rocky Mountains</name>. I was busily imployed for several hours this morning in administering eye water to a Croud of applicants.    we once more obtained a plentiful meal, much to the Comfort of all the party. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt Lewis</name> exchanged horses with <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="person" key="Apash Wyakaikt">We ark koomt</name>
                  </hi> and gave him a small flag with which he was much pleased and gratifyed.    the Sorrel which <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Cap L.</name> obtained is a Strong active well broke horse—. At this place we met with <hi rend="italic">three</hi> men of a nation Called the <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Coeur d'Alene Indians">Skeets-so-mish</name>
                  </hi> who reside at the falls of a Small river dischargeing itself into the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> on its East Side to the South of the enterance of <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">Clarks river</name>.    this river they informed us headed in a large lake in the mountains and that the falls below which they reside was at no great distance from the lake.    these people are the Same in their dress and appearance with the <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Chopunnish</name>, tho' their language is entirely different.    one of them gave me his whip which was a twisted Stick 18 Ins. in length at one end a pice of raw hide Split So as to form two Strings about 20 inches in length as a lash, to the other end a String passed through a hole and fastened at each end for a loope to Slip over the wrist. I gave in return for this whip a fathom of narrow binding. The River here Calld. <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">Clarks river</name> is that which we have heretofore Called <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">Flathead river</name>. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name> has thought proper to Call this after myself for this Stream we know no indian name and no white man but our Selves was ever on this river. The river which <name type="person" key="Fidler, Peter">Fiddler</name> call's the great lake river may possiably be a branch of it, but if So it is but a very inconsiderable branch, and may as probably empty itself into the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> above as into <name type="place" key="Deschutes (Clark's, Towanahiook's) River">Clarks river</name>.    the Stream which the party has heretofore Called <name type="place" key="Deschutes (Clark's, Towanahiook's) River">Clarks river</name> imedeately above the great falls, has it's three principal branches in Mountains <name type="place" key="Mount Jefferson">Jefferson</name>, <name type="place" key="Mount Hood (Timm, Falls Mountain)">Hood</name> and the Northern Side of the <name type="place" key="Blue (Southwest, Southeast) Mountains">S. W. Mountains</name> and is of course a Short river.    this river is Called by the <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skillutes</name> &amp; <name type="native_nation" key="Tenino Indians">Eneshure</name> Nations <name type="place" key="Deschutes (Clark's, Towanahiook's) River">Towannahhiooks</name> which is also the name they Call those bands of <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Snake indians</name> who Come on this river every Spring to Catch the Salmon—.    The <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Kooskooske river</name> may be Safely navigated at present all the rocks of the Sholes and rapids are perfectly Covered; the Current is Strong, the water Clear and Cold.    this river is riseing fast—. The timber of this river which consists principally of the long leafed pine which commences about 2 miles below our present encampment on <name type="place" key="Potlatch River (Colter's Creek)">Colters Creek</name>.    it was 2 P M. this evening before we could collect our horses.    at 3 P M. we Set out accompanied by the brother of the <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">twisted hair</name> and <name type="person" key="Apash Wyakaikt">We-ark-koomt</name>.    we derected the horse which I had obtained for the purpose of eateing to be led as it was unbroke, in performing this duty a quarrel ensued between <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name> and <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name>—. We Continued our march along the river on its North Side 9 miles to a lodge of 6 families built of Sticks mats and dryed Hay.    of the Same form of those heretofore discribed.    we passed a Lodge of 3 families at 4 ms. on the river, no provisions of any discription was to be obtained of these people.    a little after dark our young horse broke the rope by which he was Confined and made his escape much to the chagrine of all who recollected the keenness of their appetites last evening.    the brother of the <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">twisted hair</name> &amp; <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="person" key="Apash Wyakaikt">wearkkoomt</name>
                  </hi> with 10 others encamped with us this evening—.</p>
               <p>
The nativs have a Considerable Salmon fishery up <name type="person" key="Potlatch River (Colter's Creek)">Colters Creek</name>.    this Stream extends itself to the Spurs of the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky Mountain</name> and in much the greater part of its Course passes through a well timbered pine Country.    it is 25 yds. wide and discharges a large body of water.    the banks low and bead formed of pebbles—. had a Small Shower of rain this evening. The <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Chopunnish</name> about the Mouth of the <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Kooskooske</name> bury their dead on Stoney hill Sides generally,<ref target="n33050607" n="7"/> and as I was informed by an Indian who made Signs that they made a hole in the Grown by takeing away the Stones and earth where they wished to deposit the dead body after which they laid the body which was previously raped in a robe and Secured with Cords.    over the body they placed Stones So as to form a Sort of arch on the top of which they put Stones and earth So as to Secure the body from the wolves and birds &amp;c.    they Sometimes inclose the grave with a kind of Sepulcher like the roof of a house formed of the canoes of the disceased.    they also Sacrifice the favorite horses of the disceased.    the bones of many of which we See on and about the graves.
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-05-06.03" n="lc.geo.1806-05-06.01">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Tuesday 6th</hi> of <hi rend="italic">May 1806</hi>.    a rainy wet morning    the natives brought us the young horse they promised to give us last night which we excepted and Shot him to eat, as some of the men are gitting Sick eating roots. Several of the natives gambled in the same way as those below    had buffaloe robes war axes &amp;C. Staked up    the war axes these Indians have they got from the <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Grousevauntares</name> on the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missourie</name> &amp; they got them from us at the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>.<ref target="n33050608" n="8"/>    about noon we Set out    proceeded on up the river    passd. a large lodge. Some part of the road is rockey &amp; rough    in the evening we Camped near a Small village.    the big horn chief and a number other Indians Camped with us.—



</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-05-06.04" n="lc.geo.1806-05-06.01">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Tuesday 6th.</hi>    There was a cloudy wet morning; and we stayed in our camp. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clarke</name> acted as physicians to the sick of the village or lodge, for which they gave us a small horse, that we killed and eat, as we had no other meat of any kind. We continued here until about 3 o'clock, when we started and went on about nine miles, and encamped close to a lodge of the natives.






</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n33050601" n="1">The <name type="native_nation" key="Coeur d'Alene Indians">Skitswish</name>, a <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Salish</name>an-language people now known as the <name type="native_nation" key="Coeur d'Alene Indians">Coeur d'Alenes</name> (from the French "Awl Hearts"). The term is Shahaptin <hi rend="italic">'iskí·cu'mix,</hi> for the tribe. They lived on <name type="place" key="Lake Coeur d'Alene">Lake Coeur d'Alene</name> and <name type="place" key="Coeur d'Alene River">Coeur d'Alene River</name> in northern <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>. By this period they had acquired horses and adopted some traits of the plains buffalo-hunters, as a consequence of hunts east of the mountains. The river runs into the lake, and from the lake issues the <name type="place" key="Spokane River">Spokane River</name>, that runs into the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> in eastern <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>, well to the south of the entrance of the <name type="place"
                     key="Pend Oreille (Clark's, Flathead, Lastaro, Lastaw) River">Pend Oreille (Clark's) River</name>. A problem in translation may have arisen here; <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> refers to the same river as a "small" river which runs into the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> south of the <name type="person" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">Clark's River</name>. To further confuse matters, on his 1810 map of the West (<hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 125) <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> shows a large lake, "<name type="place" key="Lake Pend Oreille">Wayton Lake</name>," in approximately the proper region (perhaps based on Indian information about both <name type="place" key="Lake Coeur d'Alene">Coeur d'Alene</name> and <name type="place" key="Lake Pend Oreille">Pend Oreille</name> lakes), from which "<name type="place"
                     key="Pend Oreille (Clark's, Flathead, Lastaro, Lastaw) River">Lautaw River</name>" runs into <name type="person" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">Clark's River</name>. The <name type="native_nation" key="Coeur d'Alene Indians">Skeetsomish</name> are shown living on another river to the southwest of the lake, and that river runs into the <name type="place"
                     key="Pend Oreille (Clark's, Flathead, Lastaro, Lastaw) River">Lautaw</name>. Hodge, 2:594; Coues (HLC), 3:990–92 nn. 12, 13.</note>
            <note xml:id="n33050602" n="2">The combination of the present <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">Bitterroot</name>, <name type="place"
                     key="Clark Fork (Clark's, East Fork Clark's, Flathead) River">Clark Fork</name>, and <name type="place"
                     key="Pend Oreille (Clark's, Flathead, Lastaro, Lastaw) River">Pend Oreille</name> rivers in western <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>, northern <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>, and northeastern <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>. Evidently they had decided by this time to give it that name. See the Introduction to the <hi rend="italic">Atlas,</hi> p. 10.</note>
            <note xml:id="n33050603" n="3">The "Great Lake River" appears on <name type="person" key="Arrowsmith, Aaron">Arrasmith's</name> map of 1802, based on information from <name type="person" key="Fidler, Peter">Peter Fidler</name>. It headed near the <name type="place" key="Saskatchewan River">Saskatchewan</name> and ran into <name type="person" key="Mackenzie, Alexander">Mackenzie's</name>
               <name type="place" key="Fraser (Tacoutche-Tesse) River">"Tacoutche-Tesse" River</name>, which was assumed to be the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> or a major tributary thereof. No known river really matches the description. The captains were now trying to fit this largely conjectural stream into their own increasing knowledge of Western geography by making it a tributary of either <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">Clark's River</name> or the "<name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">Skeetsomish</name>." Allen (PG), 79, 83, 342.</note>
            <note xml:id="n33050604" n="4">The <name type="place" key="Deschutes (Clark's, Towanahiook's) River">Deschutes River</name> in <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>, here definitely renamed the "<name type="place" key="Deschutes (Clark's, Towanahiook's) River">Towannahiooks</name>." <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 77.</note>
            <note xml:id="n33050605" n="5">On the <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Clearwater River</name>, in <name type="place" key="Nez Perce County, Idaho">Nez Perce County</name>, <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>, perhaps at the mouth of <name type="place" key="Pine Creek">Pine Creek</name>. Space, 25; Peebles (RLC), 17; <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 72. Peebles, however, finds a discrepancy of some two miles between this location, on which he and Space agree, and the site given on the map, which would put it some two miles below <name type="place" key="Pine Creek">Pine Creek</name>. The campsite, but not the creek, is indicated on the <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map. The map indicates that the camp of May 6, was located below a large island, probably <name type="place" key="Fir Island">Fir Island</name>, which is two miles below <name type="place" key="Pine Creek">Pine Creek</name>, so it is possible that this camp may actually have been near modern <name type="place" key="Cherrylane, Idaho">Cherrylane</name>. Either the map or the mileage figures are in error. During this day the expedition passed the locations of several villages recorded in October 1805, the largest of which extended for two miles from the vicinity of <name type="place" key="Pine Creek">Pine Creek</name> to below <name type="place" key="Fir Island">Fir Island</name>. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 72. This same site was also inhabited in May 1806 although it only consisted of a single lodge of six families, as <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> indicates. A historic <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name> village, <hi rend="italic">yatoynu,</hi> "over-ripe kouse," coincided with this location and an archaeological site has also been recorded here. Schwede, 34. The well-documented presence of the <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name> village at <name type="place" key="Pine Creek">Pine Creek</name>, plus the absence of a known village at <name type="place" key="Cherrylane, Idaho">Cherrylane</name>, supports the belief that the expedition camped at <name type="place" key="Pine Creek">Pine Creek</name> rather than at <name type="place" key="Cherrylane, Idaho">Cherrylane</name>, in opposition to <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 72.</note>
            <note xml:id="n33050606" n="6">Balsam copaiba is an oleoresin obtained from South American trees of the genus <hi rend="italic">Copaifera;</hi> it stimulates the mucous membranes.</note>
            <note xml:id="n33050607" n="7">This varies from <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> earlier description of <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name> burials farther down the <name type="place"
                     key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Snake</name>, given on <ref n="lc.jrn.1805-10-11" type="related">October 11, 1805</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n33050608" n="8">These <hi rend="italic">Gros Ventres</hi> are again the <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name>; see <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway's</name> entry of <ref n="lc.jrn.1804-10-29" type="related">October 29, 1804</ref>, and <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> entry of <ref n="lc.jrn.1806-05-11" type="related">May 11, 1806</ref>.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-05-05" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-05-07" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
