<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-09-19">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">September 19, 1805</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic
        Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            5</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">July 28–November 1, 1805</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1989</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">215-217</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">226</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">144-145</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jw">Joseph Whitehouse</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            11</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of Joseph Whitehouse, May 14, 1804–April 2,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1997</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">321-323</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
         <geoDecl datum="WGS" xml:id="lc.geo.1805-09-19.01">
            <placeName/>
            <geo>45.9 -114.6333</geo>
            <note>Clark camped on Cedar Creek, near present Lewis and Clark Grove, ID.</note>
         </geoDecl>
         <geoDecl datum="WGS" xml:id="lc.geo.1805-09-19.02">
            <placeName/>
            <geo>46.4 -115.5776</geo>
            <note>The group camped on Hungery Creek near a small, nameless stream, ID.</note>
         </geoDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc/>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-06-16</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-04-12</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1805-09-19">September 19, 1805</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-09-19.01" ref="">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Thursday September 19th 1805.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>Set out this morning a little after sun rise and continued our rout about the same
          course of yesterday or S. 20 W. for 6 miles when the ridge terminated and we to our
          inexpressable joy discovered a large tract of Prairie country lying to the S. W. and
          widening as it appeared to extend to the W.
          <ref target="n22091901" n="1"/>through that plain the Indian informed us that the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia river</name>, in which we were in surch
          run.    this plain appeared to be about 60 Miles distant, but our guide
          assured us that we should reach it's borders tomorrow    the appearance of
          this country, our only hope for subsistance greately revived the sperits of the party
          already reduced and much weakened for the want of food.    the country is
          thickly covered with a very heavy growth of pine of which I have ennumerated 8 distinct
          species. after leaving the ridge we asscended and decended several steep mountains in
          the distance of 6 miles further when we struck a Creek about 15 yards wide.
          <ref target="n22091902" n="2"/>   our course being S. 35 W. we continued our
          rout 6 miles along the side of this creek upwards passing 2 of it's branches which
          flowed in from the N. 1st at the place we struck the creek and the other 3 miles
          further.
          <ref target="n22091903" n="3"/>   the road was excessively dangerous along
          this creek being a narow rockey path generally on the side of steep precipice, from
          which in many places if ether man or horse were precipitated they would inevitably be
          dashed in pieces. 
          <name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">Fraziers</name>horse fell from this road in the
          evening, and roled with his load near a hundred yards into the Creek. we all expected
          that the horse was killed but to our astonishment when the load was taken off him he
          arose to his feet &amp; appeared to be but little injured, in 20 minutes he proceeded
          with his load.    this was the most wonderfull escape I ever witnessed, the
          hill down which he roled was almost perpendicular and broken by large irregular and
          broken rocks. the course of this Creek upwards due W.    we encamped on the
          Stard. side of it in a little raviene,
          <ref target="n22091904" n="4"/>having traveled 18 miles over a very bad road. we took a
          small quantity of portable soup, and retired to rest much fatiegued.   
          several of the men are unwell of the disentary.    brakings out, or irruptions
          of the Skin, have also been common with us for some time.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-09-19.02" ref="">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>
                  <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>
                  <ref target="n22091905" n="5"/>
               </speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <table rows="1" cols="2">
                     <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Cours Distance &amp; 19th Septr. Tuesday</hi>
                     </head>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S 60 W</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">nearly 〈30 22〉 12
                <ref target="n22091906" n="6"/>miles on a Direct Course &amp; at doubl the
                distance
                <lb/>wind around falling timber to a branch running to the left &amp; Camped
                <lb/>at 6 miles found a horse on the head of the Creek in Some glades, he
                <lb/>was not fat    the me[n] beg leave to kill him which I granted,
                after
                <lb/>they filled themselves, I had the ballance hung up for 
                <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt Lewis</name>and
                <lb/>proceeded on, in the time the one half of the party was skining Cook-
                <lb/>ing &amp;c. the others were hunting, without seeing a track of any ani-
                <lb/>mal. The road up this Creek is much wors than any other part as
                <lb/>the hills Sides are Steep and at maney places obliged for Several yds.
                <lb/>to pass on the Sides of rocks where one false Step of a horse would
                <lb/>be certan. destruction. Crossed over a mountain and the heads of a
                <lb/>branch of 
                <name type="place" key="Hungery Creek">hungary Creek</name>over ridges and much
                falling timber, and a
                <lb/>2d high mountain of like description to a large Creek running west
                <lb/>for 4 miles then turned South. I keped down 4 miles &amp; turned up to
                <lb/>the right over a mountain which was bad as usial to a branch which
                <lb/>runs to the left and Camped. The road to day wors than usial owing
                <lb/>to the falling timber &amp;c.    we killed 2 phsts. but few birds.
                   the Blue
                <lb/>jay &amp; Small white headed Hawk Some Crows &amp; ravins.</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-09-19.03" ref="">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Tuesday [NB: Thursday] 19th Septr. 1805</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>Set out early proceeded on up the 
          <name type="place" key="Hungery Creek">[
          <hi rend="italic">EC: Hungry</hi>] Creek</name>passing through a Small glade at 6 miles
          at which place we found a horse. I derected him killed and hung up for the party after
          takeing a brackfast off for our Selves which we thought fine    after
          Brackfast proceed on up the Creek two miles &amp; left it to our right passed over a
          mountain, and the heads of branch of 
          <name type="place" key="Hungery Creek">hungary Creek</name>,
          <ref target="n22091907" n="7"/>two high mountains, ridges and through much falling
          timber (which caused our road of to day to be double the derect distance on the
          Course[)]    Struck a large Creek
          <ref target="n22091908" n="8"/>passing to our left which I Kept down for 4 miles and
          left it to our left &amp; passed 〈over a〉 [
          <hi rend="italic">WC: down the</hi>] mountain bad falling timber to a Small Creek
          passing to our left and Encamped.
          <ref target="n22091909" n="9"/>I killed 2 Pheasents, but fiew birds [
          <hi rend="italic">WC: are to be Seen</hi>] Blue jay, Small white headed hawk,
          <ref target="n22091910" n="10"/>Some Crows &amp; ravins &amp; large hawks.   
          road bad. [
          <hi rend="italic">WC: as we decend the mountain the heat becomes more proseptable every
          mile</hi>]</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-09-19.04" ref="">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>Thursday 19th Sept 1805.    a clear norning.    we eat the verry
          last morcil of our provision except a little portable Soup, and proceeded on to the top
          of Sd. mountain
          <ref target="n22091911" n="11"/>and as we were descending the Same we discovred a very
          large plain
          <ref target="n22091912" n="12"/>a long distance a head, which we expect is on the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>, which puts us in good
          Spirits again.    the Mount. bad this day.    we descended a Mount.
          about 4 miles down where it was verry Steep    came down on a creek
          <ref target="n22091913" n="13"/>running abt. East.    we followed up the
          creek Some distance    the way very rockey and bad, then went along the side
          of a Mountain a little to the write of the creek.    high steep timbred
          mounts. on each side of Sd. creek.    one of our horses
          <ref target="n22091914" n="14"/>fell backwards out of the trail and rolled down over
          the Steep rocks abt. 200 feet with 2 boxes of Ammunition and plunged in to the creek
             with Some difficulty we got the horse up again and load    it
          hurt the horse but did not kill him.    we Came 17 miles this day and Camped
          <ref target="n22091915" n="15"/>at a Small run in a thicket of pine and balsom timber
          &amp;C—</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-09-19.05" ref="">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Thursday 19th.</hi>   Our hunters did not join us last
          night, which was disagreeably cold. About 8 this morning we set out, and proceeded on in
          our way over the mountains; the sun shining warm and pleasant. We travelled a west
          course, and about 12 o'clock halted at a spring to take a little more soup. The snow is
          chiefly gone except on the north points of the high mountains. At 2 P. M. we again went
          on, and descended a steep mountain into a cove on our left hand, where there is a large
          creek,
          <ref target="n22091916" n="16"/>which here runs towards the east. The hills on each
          side, along which the trail or path passes, are very steep. One of our horses fell down
          the precipice about 100 feet, and was not killed, nor much hurt: the reason was, that
          there is no bottom below, and the precipice, the only bank, which the creek has;
          therefore the horse pitched into the water, without meeting with any intervening object,
          which could materially injure him. We made 17 miles this day and encamped on a small
          branch of the creek. Having heard nothing from our hunters, we again supped upon some of
          our portable soup. The men are becoming lean and debilitated, on account of the scarcity
          and poor quality of the provisions on which we subsist: our horses' feet are also
          becoming very sore. We have, however, some hopes of getting soon out of this horrible
          mountainous desert, as we have discovered the appearance of a valley or level part of
          the country about 40 miles ahead. When this discovery was made there was as much joy and
          rejoicing among the corps, as happens among passengers at sea, who have experienced a
          dangerous and protracted voyage, when they first discover land on the long looked for
          coast.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-09-19.06" ref="">
            <sp who="jw">
               <speaker>Whitehouse</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Thursday 19th Sept. 1805</hi>.    a clear pleasant morning.
             we Set out as usal and assended up to the top of Sd. mout. and discovered a
          plain in a valley about 20 miles from us where we expect is the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbian River</name>which puts us in good
          Spirits again.    we descended down the mountn. which was verry Steep descent,
          for about three miles.    then assended another as bad as any we have ever
          been up before.    it made the Sweat run off of our horses &amp; ourselves.
             on the top the ground was froze a little and the ground mostly covred with
          Snow.    the Spruce pine &amp; bolsom timber continues on these motn. as usal.
             Some places thick bushes.    we descd. the mot. down in a narrow
          valley where we found a run of water and halted to bate our horses and to drink a little
          portable Soup.    one of the men killed a fessent.    their is not
          any kind of game or Sign of any to be Seen in these mout.    Scarsely any
          birds itself.    we delayed about 2 hours and proceeded on   
          descended the mountain about 4 miles came to a creek running about East.    we
          followed up the creek.    a bad peace of the road, Some places along Side of
          the mountn. which is high &amp; Steep on each Side of the creek.    one of our
          horses fell backward and roled about 100 feet down where it was nearly Steep and a Solid
          rock &amp; dashed against the rock in the creek, with a load of Ammunition.   
          but the powder being in canisters did not git damaged nor the horse killed, but hurt.
             we proceeded on.    Came about 17 miles this day and Camped at a
          run in Sd. mount., our course this day was generally west.    the timber
          continues as usal.    we Suped a little portable Soup.    the most
          of the party is weak and feeble Suffering with hunger.    our horses feet are
          gitting Sore and fall away in these mountains, but we are in hopes to git out of them
          Soon.</p>
               <p>Thursday Septemr 19th    A clear pleasant morning, we set out early, &amp;
          ascended the top of the Mountain on the side of which we lay last night, We discovered
          from the Top of this mountain; a plain which lay in a Valley, which we suppose to lay
          about 20 Miles from us, We expect this plain is where the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>is, this revived the
          drooping spirits of our party.    We descended down this Mountain, which we
          found dangerous for about 3 Miles, We then ascended another Mountain; which was as bad
          to ascend as any Mountain we had yet seen, this was very fataigueing to ourselves &amp;
          horses, the ground was covered with Snow &amp; froze, The Pine &amp; Spruce, balsam Fir
          timber on the Top of these Mountains, &amp; in some places thick bushes.—   
          We descended this Mountain &amp; came down into a narrow Valley, where we found a run of
          water.    We halted at that place to rest our horses &amp; to eat some
          portable soup.    One of our Men here killed a Pheasant, There was no kind of
          Game to be seen in these Mountains, &amp; scarcely any Birds.    We delayed
          about 2 hours—    &amp; proceeded on, &amp; descended a mountain about four
          Miles, and arrived at a Creek, whose course run east, we pursued our way up the Creek on
          a bad piece of Road, some places running along close under the Mountain; which is high
          &amp; steep on both sides of the Creek, One of our horses fell backwards, &amp; rolled
          about 100 feet down a steep solid Rock, and dashed against a Rock, in the Creek with his
          load; which was Ammunition; The Powder, being in leaden Cannisters, was not damaged, nor
          the horse killed, but much hurt.—    We proceeded on, and encamped at a run of
          Water in the said Mountain; In the evening, our party had a little portable Soup made to
          subsist on.    They all are very weak &amp; feeble &amp; suffer much for want
          of Provisions, Our horses feet are very much worn, &amp; they have fallen away very
          much, since we came into the Mountains.</p>
               <p>The Men still seem contented; &amp; flatter themselves of soon getting out of the
          Mountains.    Our course during this day, has been chiefly a West course &amp;
          we came about 17 Miles—</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n22091901" n="1">The same prairie country viewed by 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>party on 
        <ref n="1805-09-18" type="related">September 18</ref>, apparently seen from the same
        viewpoint, 
        <name type="place" key="Sherman Peak">Sherman Peak</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho County, Idaho">Idaho County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>. The route for about September 18–20 is
        sketched in fig. 8. Space, 14; 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>map 70.</note>
            <note xml:id="n22091902" n="2">
               <name type="place" key="Hungery Creek">Hungery creek</name>at the mouth of 
        <name type="place" key="Doubt Creek">Doubt Creek</name>. Space, 14; 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>map 70.</note>
            <note xml:id="n22091903" n="3">
               <name type="place" key="Doubt Creek">Doubt Creek</name>and 
        <name type="place" key="Bowl Creek">Bowl Creek</name>. Space, 14; Peebles (LT), 9; 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>map 70.</note>
            <note xml:id="n22091904" n="4">On 
        <name type="place" key="Hungery Creek">Hungery Creek</name>, near the mouth of a small,
        nameless stream. Space, 14; 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>map 70.</note>
            <note xml:id="n22091905" n="5">Opposite this entry in the Elkskin-bound Journal is a
        sketch map (
        <ref n="1805-09-20" type="related">fig. 8</ref>) showing the party's route for about
        September 18–20, with campsites of those days noted.</note>
            <note xml:id="n22091906" n="6">It is not clear whether 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>is choosing twelve or twenty-two
        miles.</note>
            <note xml:id="n22091907" n="7">
               <name type="place" key="Fish Creek (Idaho County, Idaho)">Fish Creek</name>. Space, 14; 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>map 70.</note>
            <note xml:id="n22091908" n="8">Present 
        <name type="place" key="Eldorado Creek">Eldorado Creek</name>. Space, 14; Peebles (LT),
        7.</note>
            <note xml:id="n22091909" n="9">
               <name type="place" key="Cedar Creek (Idaho)">Cedar Creek</name>, near the present 
        <name type="place" key="Lewis and Clark Grove">Lewis and Clark Grove</name>. Space, 14;
        Peebles (LT), 7; 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>map 71.</note>
            <note xml:id="n22091910" n="10">Perhaps the black-shouldered kite, 
        <hi rend="italic">Elanus caeruleus</hi>[AOU, 328]. Holmgren, 31.</note>
            <note xml:id="n22091911" n="11">Probably 
        <name type="place" key="Sherman Peak">Sherman Peak</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho County, Idaho">Idaho County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n22091912" n="12">Open prairies in 
        <name type="place" key="Lewis County, Idaho">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho County, Idaho">Idaho</name>counties, northwest of 
        <name type="place" key="Grangeville, Idaho">Grangeville</name>, including 
        <name type="place" key="Camas Prairie">Camas</name>and 
        <name type="place" key="Nez Perce Prairie">Nez Perce prairies</name>. See 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>entry of 
        <ref n="1805-09-18" type="related">September 18</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n22091913" n="13">This is probably 
        <name type="place" key="Hungery Creek">Hungery Creek</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho County, Idaho">Idaho County</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n22091914" n="14">
               <name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">Frazer's</name>horse, fortunately without 
        <name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">Frazer</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n22091915" n="15">On 
        <name type="place" key="Hungery Creek">Hungery Creek</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho County, Idaho">Idaho County</name>, near the mouth of a
        small, nameless stream.</note>
            <note xml:id="n22091916" n="16">
               <name type="place" key="Hungery Creek">Hungery Creek</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho County, Idaho">Idaho County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>; the name was bestowed by 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>on 
        <ref n="1805-09-18" type="related">September 18</ref>, "as at that place we had nothing
        to eate."</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-09-18" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-09-20" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
