<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1804-09-17">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">September 17, 1804</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic
        Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            3</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">August 25, 1804–April 6, 1805</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1987</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">80-86</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">61</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">4-</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jw">Joseph Whitehouse</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            11</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of Joseph Whitehouse, May 14, 1804–April 2,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1997</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">76-77</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journal Entries</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-03-11</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-04-12</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1804-09-17">September 17, 1804</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1804-09-17.01" ref="">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Monday September 17th 1804.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>Having for many days past confined myself to the boat, I determined to devote this
          day to amuse myself on shore with my gun and view the interior of the country lying
          between the river and the 
          <name type="place" key="American (Corvus) Creek">Corvus Creek</name>—   
          accordingly before sunrise I set out with six of my best hunters,
          <ref target="n06091701" n="1"/>two of whom I dispatched to the lower side of 
          <name type="place" key="American (Corvus) Creek">Corvus creek</name>, two with orders to
          hunt the bottoms and woodland on the river, while I retained two others to acompany me
          in the intermediate country.    one quarter of a mile in rear of our camp
          which was situated in a fine open grove of cotton wood passed a grove of plumb trees
          loaded with fruit and now ripe.    observed but little difference between this
          fruit and that of a similar kind common to the Atlantic States.
          <ref target="n06091702" n="2"/>   the trees are smaller and more thickly set.
             this forrest of plumb trees garnish a plain about 20 feet more lelivated
          than that on which we were encamped; this plain extends back about a mile to the foot of
          the hills one mile distant and to which it is gradually ascending    this
          plane extends with the same bredth from the creek below to the distance of near three
          miles above parrallel with the river, and is intirely occupyed by the burrows of the 
          <hi rend="italic">barking squril</hi>hertefore discribed; this anamal appears here in
          infinite numbers, and the shortness and virdue [verdure] of grass gave the plain the
          appearance throughout it's whole extent of beatifull bowlinggreen in fine order.
             it's aspect is S. E.    a great number of wolves of the small
          kind, halks and some pole-cats
          <ref target="n06091703" n="3"/>were to be seen. I presume that those anamals feed on
          this squirril.—    found the country in every direction for about three miles
          intersected with deep revenes and steep irregular hills of 100 to 200 feet high; at the
          tops of these hills the country breakes of as usual into a fine leavel plain extending
          as far as the eye can reach.    from this plane I had an extensive view of the
          river below, and the irregular hills which border the opposite sides of the river and
          creek.    the surrounding country had been birnt about a month before and
          young grass had now sprung up to hight of 4 Inches presenting the live green of the
          spring.    to the West a high range of hills,
          <ref target="n06091704" n="4"/>strech across the country from N. to S and appeared
          distant about 20 Miles; they are not very extensive as I could plainly observe their
          rise and termination    no rock appeared on them and the sides were covered
          with virdue similar to that of the plains    this senery already rich pleasing
          and beatiful, was still farther hightened by immence herds of Buffaloe deer Elk and
          Antelopes which we saw in every direction feeding on the hills and plains. I do not
          think I exagerate when I estimate the number of Buffaloe which could be compreed at one
          view to amount to 3000.    my object was if possible to kill a female Antelope
          having already procured a male; I pursued my rout on this plain to the west flanked by
          my two hunters untill eight in the morning when I made the signal for them to come to me
          which they did shortly after.    we rested our selves about half an hour, and
          regailed ourselves on half a bisquit each and some jirk of Elk which we had taken the
          precaution to put in our pouches in the morning before we set out, and drank of the
          water of a small pool which had collected on this plain from the rains which had fallen
          some days before. We had now after various windings in pursuit of several herds of
          antelopes which we had seen on our way made the distance of about eight miles from our
          camp.    we found the Antelope extreemly shye and watchfull insomuch that we
          had been unable to get a shot at them; when at rest they generally seelect the most
          elivated point in the neighbourhood, and as they are watchfull and extreemly quick of
          sight and their sense of smelling very accute it is almost impossible to approach them
          within gunshot; in short they will frequently discover and flee from you at the distance
          of three miles. I had this day an opportunity of witnessing the agility and superior
          fleetness of this anamal which was to me really astonishing. I had pursued and twice
          surprised a small herd of seven, in the first instance they did not discover me
          distinctly and therefore did not run at full speed, tho' they took care before they
          rested to gain an elivated point where it was impossible to approach them under cover
          except in one direction and that happened to be in the direction from which the wind
          blew towards them; bad as the chance to approach them was, I made the best of my way
          towards them, frequently peeping over the ridge with which I took care to conceal myself
          from their view    the male, of which there was but one, frequently incircled
          the summit of the hill on which the females stood in a group, as if to look out for the
          approach of danger. I got within about 200 paces of them when they smelt me and fled; I
          gained the top of the eminece on which they stood, as soon as possible from whence I had
          an extensive view of the country    the antilopes which had disappeared in a
          steep revesne now appeared at the distance of about three miles on the side of a ridge
          which passed obliquely across me and extended about four miles.    so soon had
          these antelopes gained the distance at which they had again appeared to my view I
          doubted at ferst that they were the same that I had just surprised, but my doubts soon
          vanished when I beheld the rapidity of their flight along the ridge before me
             it appeared reather the rappid flight of birds than the motion of
          quadrupeds. I think I can safely venture the asscertion that the speed of this anamal is
          equal if not superior to that of the finest blooded courser.—    this morning
          I saw
          <ref target="n06091705" n="5"/>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1804-09-17.02" ref="">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>
                  <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>
                  <ref target="n06091706" n="6"/>
               </speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>17th of Septr. Monday 1804    above 
          <name type="place" key="White River">White river</name>   Dried all those
          articles which had got wet by the last rain, a fine day    
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt Lewis</name>went hunting with a vew to
          see the Countrey &amp; its productions, he was out all Day    Killed a
          Buffalow &amp; a remarkable bird of the Spicies of Corvus, long tail of a Greenish
          Purple, Varigated    a Beck like a Crow    white round its neck
          comeing to a point on its back, its belley white    feet like a Hawk
             abt. the size of a large Pigeon
          <ref target="n06091707" n="7"/>   
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt Lewis</name>returned at Dark. I took
          the Meridian &amp; equal altitudes to day    made the Lattitude.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name>Killed a Goat, &amp; a Curious kind
          of Deer, a Darker grey than Common    the hair longer &amp; finer, the ears
          verry large &amp; long    a Small resepitical under its eye    its
          tail round and white to near the end which is black &amp; like a Cow    in
          every other respect like a Deer, except it runs like a goat.    large.
          <ref target="n06091708" n="8"/>
               </p>
               <p>The hunters brought in 8 fallow Deer &amp; 5 Common Deer to day, Great numbers of
          Buffalow in the Praries, also a light Coloured woolf Covered with hair &amp; corse fur,
          also a Small wolf with a large bushey tail—
          <ref target="n06091709" n="9"/>   Some Goats of a Different Kind Seen to
          day,—    Great many Plumbs, rabits, Porcupines &amp; barking Squrels, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt Lewis</name>Killed a rattle Snake in a
          village of the Squirel's and Saw a Hair to day. Wind from the S. W.    we
          finished Drying our Provisions    Some of which was wet and Spoiled,
          <ref target="n06091710" n="10"/>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1804-09-17.03" ref="">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="right">
                        <hi rend="italic">
                           <name type="place" key="White River">White River</name>
                        </hi>17th Septr. 
                <name type="place" key="Pleasant (Plum) Camp (S. Dak.)">
                           <hi rend="italic">Plomb Camp</hi>
                        </name>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="italic">Course Distance &amp; reffurence
                <lb/>17th of September</hi>Monday 1804</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>Dried all our wet articles this fine Day, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt Lewis</name>went out with a View to see
          the Countrey and its productions, he was out all day    he killed a Buffalow
          and a remarkable 
          <hi rend="italic">Bird</hi>[
          <hi rend="italic">WC: Magpy</hi>] of the 
          <hi rend="italic">Corvus</hi>Species long tail the upper part of the feathers &amp; also
          the wing is of a purplish variated Green, the black, [
          <hi rend="italic">X: back &amp;</hi>] a part of the wing feather are white edjed with
          black, white belley, white from the root of the wings to Center of the back is white,
          the head nake [neck] breast &amp; other parts are black the Becke like a Crow. abt. the
          Size of a large Pigion.    a butifull thing (See Suplement in No. 3)
          <ref target="n06091711" n="11"/>
               </p>
               <p>I took equal altitudes and a meridian altitude. 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name>returned at Dark, 
          <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name>Killed a Goat like the one I killed
          and a curious kind of deer [
          <hi rend="italic">WC: Mule Deer</hi>]
          <ref target="n06091712" n="12"/>of a Dark gray Colr. more so than common, hair long
          &amp; fine, the ears large &amp; long, a Small reseptical under the eyes; like an Elk,
          the Taile about the length of Common Deer, round (like a Cow) a tuft of black hair about
          the end, this Speces of Deer jumps like a goat or Sheep</p>
               <p>8 fallow Deer 5 Common &amp; 3 buffalow killed to day, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name>Saw a 
          <hi rend="italic">hare</hi>&amp; Killed a Rattle Snake in a village of B. squerels
             The wind from S. W.    Dryed our provisions, Some of which was
          much Damaged.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1804-09-17.04" ref="">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>Sept. 17th
              <ref target="n06091713" n="13"/>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>one of the hunters killed a bird of the 
          <hi rend="italic">Corvus genus</hi>[
          <hi rend="italic">EC: Pica pica hudsonica</hi>] and order of the pica &amp; about the
          size of a jack-daw with a remarkable long tale.    beautifully variagated.
             it 〈has an agreeable note something like goald winged Blackbird〉 note is
          not disagreeable though loud— it is twait twait twait, twait; twait, twait twait,
          twait.</p>
               <p>
                  <table rows="5" cols="3">
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  F</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  I</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">from tip to tip of wing</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  1</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">10</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Do. beak to extremity of tale</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  1</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  8 ½</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">of which the tale occupys</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">11</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">from extremity of middle toe to hip</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  5 ½</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>it's head, beak, and neck are large for a bird of it's size; the beak is black, and
          of a convex and cultrated figure, the chops nearly equal, and it's base large and beset
          with hairs—    the eyes are black encircled with a 〈small〉 narrow ring of
          yellowish black    it's head, neck, brest &amp; back within one inch of the
          tale are of a fine glossey black, as are also the short fathers of the under part of the
          wing, the thies and those about the root of the tale.    the 〈body〉 belly is
          of a beatifull white which passes above and arround the but of the wing, where the
          feathers being long reach to a small white spot on the rump one inch in width—
             the wings have nineteen feathers, of which the ten first have the longer
          side of their plumage white in the midde of the feather and occupying unequal lengths of
          the same from one to three inches, and forming when the wing is spead a kind [of]
          triangle    the upper and lower part of these party coloured feathers on the
          under side of the wing being of dark colour but not jut or shining black.   
          the under side of the remaining feathers of the wing are darker.    the upper
          side of the wing, as well as the short side of the plumage of the party coloured
          feathers is of a dark blackis or bluish green sonetimes presenting as light orange
          yellow or bluish 〈tinge〉 tint as it 〈rise〉 happens to be presented to different
          exposures of ligt—    the plumage of the tale consits of 12 feathers of equal
          lengths by pai[r]s, those in the center are the longest, and the others on each side
          deminishing about an inch each pair—    the underside of the feathers is a
          pale black, the upper side is a dark blueish green which like the 〈upper and〉 outer part
          of the wings is changable as it reflects different portions of light.   
          towards the the extremety of these feathers they become of an orrange green, then shaded
          pass to a redish indigo blue, and again at the extremity assume the predominant colour
          of changeable green—    the tints of these feathers are very similar and
          equally as beatiful and rich as the tints of blue and green of the peacock—   
          it is a most beatifull bird.—    the legs and toes are black and imbricated.
             it has four long toes, three in front and one in rear, each terminated with
          a black sharp tallon from ⅜ths to ½ an inch in length.—    these birds are
          seldom found in parties of more than three or four and most usually at this season
          single as the halks 〈ravens〉 and other birds of prey usually are—    〈from
          it's appearance I believe to〉    it's usual food is flesh— this bird dose not
          spread it's tail when it flys and the motion of it's wings when flying is much like that
          of a Jay-bird—    〈it's note—    tah, tah, tah, tah tah, tah, tah,
          tah〉</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">The White turkey of the 
          <name type="place" key="Black Hills">black hills</name>from information</hi>of a french
          lad who wintered with the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Cheyenne Indians">Chien</name>Indians [
          <hi rend="italic">EC: rara avis in terris!</hi>]    About the size of the
          common wild turkey    the plumage perfectly white—    this bird is
          booted as low as the toes—</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1804-09-17.05" ref="">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="right">
                        <hi rend="italic">Point of Obstn. No. 42.
                <lb/>Monday</hi>September 17th 1804.
                <ref target="n06091714" n="14"/>
                     </hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>On the Lard. shore, one mile and a haf above the mouth of 
          <name type="place" key="American (Corvus) Creek">Corvus Creek</name>observed equal
          Altitudes of 
          <seg n="u9737">☉</seg>with Sextant.— 
          <table rows="4" cols="5">
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">h     m   
               s</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">    </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">h     m   
               s</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">A. M.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">7    46    49</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">P.M.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">2    59   50</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> "    47    25</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">3     1    30</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> "    49    12</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> "     3     
              3</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>Altd. by sextant at the time of Observatn.    53° 17' 45"</p>
               <p>Observed meridian Altitude of 
          <seg n="u9737">☉</seg>'s L. L. with Octant by the back Observation 87° 31' 00"</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1804-09-17.06" ref="">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Monday 17th Sept. 1804</hi>. 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt Lewis</name>&amp; Several of the party
          went out hunting. 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name>caught 1 Beaver to day
             a pleasant day. The Boat loaded—    we remained here all day.—
             towards evening 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt Lewis</name>&amp; party retarned
             they had killed 13 common Deer. Some of them were handsome fauns—
             2 Black tailed Deer which differ from the other Deer.    verry
          large ears    Scarce any hair on their tail    only the bunch of
          black hair on the end of a grayish colour    they are pleanty in this Country
          but not discribed in any other parts—    they killed another kind of Deer
          <ref target="n06091715" n="15"/>with Small horns &amp; long tail. 
          <name type="person" key="Gibson, George">Gibson</name>killed 1    its tail is
          18 Inches long &amp; differ also from any yet seen by the party.    they
          killed 3 Buffalow.    one Goat which differs also (plenty[)] &amp; one curious
          Bird of a blackish &amp; greenish coullour Black Bill &amp; a verry long tail—
             resembling a bird that we call a magpy—    the hunters inform us
          that the Country back of the hills and on the hills are level &amp; Smooth but the
          Timber verry Scarce &amp;.C.—</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1804-09-17.07" ref="">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Monday 17th.</hi>   As the weather was fair we remained here
          during the day. 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Lewis</name>and some men went out to
          hunt, and killed thirteen common, and two black-tailed deer three buffaloe and a goat.
          The wild goat in this country differ from the common tame goat, and is supposed to be
          the real antelope. The black-tailed, or mule deer have much larger ears than the common
          deer and tails almost without hair, except at the end, where there is a bunch of black
          hair. There is another species of deer in this country with small horns and long tails.
          The tail of one which we killed was 18 inches long. One of our men caught a beaver, and
          killed a prairie wolf.—
          <ref target="n06091716" n="16"/>These are a small species of wolves, something larger
          than a fox, with long tails and short ears.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1804-09-17.08" ref="">
            <sp who="jw">
               <speaker>Whitehouse</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>Monday 17th Sept. 1804.    
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name>and Several more of the
          party went out a hunting.    they came in had killed 13 common Deer 2 black
          taild Deer 1 Goat &amp; 3 Buffaloe    the Goats in this is different from the
          Goats in the States    they have much longer ears and courser hair.
             
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name>caught 1 beaver.   
          killed a prarie wolf.    these wolves are larger than a fox—</p>
               <p>Monday Septemr 17th    We remained at 
          <name type="place" key="Pleasant (Plum) Camp (S. Dak.)">Pleasant Camp</name>, and Early
          this morning, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Lewis</name>, and several of the
          party went out hunting, They returned in the afternoon, having killed 13 common deer, 2
          black 〈Color'd〉 Tail'd deer, 8 Goats, and 3 Buffalo.    The Goats are not like
          those in the United States, they having much larger Ears &amp; Coarser hair,—
             One of our hunters returned in the Evening, having catch'd 1 Beaver in his
          Trap &amp; killed a Priari Wolf, The Priari Wolfes are not so large as those in the
          United States, being very little bigger than a Fox.—</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n06091701" n="1">They may have included 
        <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name>(see 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>entry, below), and probably 
        <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name>, the premier hunter of the
        party.</note>
            <note xml:id="n06091702" n="2">These plums are the same species, the common wild
        plum.</note>
            <note xml:id="n06091703" n="3">Skunks, 
        <hi rend="italic">Mephitis mephitis</hi>. Cutright (LCPN), 93.</note>
            <note xml:id="n06091704" n="4">These may include the later 
        <name type="place" key="Red Butte">Red Butte</name>. 
        <hi rend="italic">South Dakota Guide</hi>, 403.</note>
            <note xml:id="n06091705" n="5">Codex Ba ends abruptly at this point.</note>
            <note xml:id="n06091706" n="6">
               <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>has the notation "and 20" at the
        top of this document 55 of the Field Notes, indicating that the entries on this sheet go
        through that date.</note>
            <note xml:id="n06091707" n="7">
               <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>, and 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>longer account in Codex Q for
        this date, are the first descriptions of the black-billed magpie, 
        <hi rend="italic">Pica pica</hi>. Magpies had not previously been known to exist in the
        New World; the American bird is a subspecies of the European magpie. They named 
        <name type="place" key="American (Corvus) Creek">Corvus Creek</name>for this bird, one of
        the few uses of a Latin zoological term in the journals. Cutright (LCPN), 84–85.</note>
            <note xml:id="n06091708" n="8">The mule deer, 
        <hi rend="italic">Odocoileus hemionus</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n06091709" n="9">The latter was apparently their first specimen of the
        coyote, described in more detail on 
        <ref n="1804-09-18" type="related">September 18</ref>. Cutright (LCPN), 85.</note>
            <note xml:id="n06091710" n="10">
               <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>evidently combined his September 17
        and 18 entries in the Field Notes at this point. They are separated here and brought
        together in regular order.</note>
            <note xml:id="n06091711" n="11">
               <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>"No. 3" is the notebook now called
        Codex C, but the reference here is probably to 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>lengthy description of the
        magpie in Codex Q under this date. See 
        <ref n="v02.appendix.c" type="related">Appendix C</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n06091712" n="12">
               <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>probably inserted the phrase "Mule
        Deer" later, when the captains had adopted that name for 
        <hi rend="italic">Odocoileus hemionus</hi>, based on its large ears. He used red ink for
        this and the previous emendation. 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>may also have lined out in red the
        passage about the magpie. 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>use of the term on 
        <ref n="1805-04-23" type="related">April 23, 1805</ref>, is the first written use of
        today's common name of the animal, which 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>were the first to describe. See also 
        <ref n="1805-05-10" type="related">May 10, 1805</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n06091713" n="13">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>natural history notes from Codex
        Q. The bird is the black-billed magpie and the turkey may be the wild turkey, 
        <hi rend="italic">Meleagris gallopavo</hi>[AOU, 310], which Coues (in his interlineation)
        calls a rare bird in the area described. One authority suggests other possibilities,
        including the white-tailed ptarmigan, 
        <hi rend="italic">Lagopus leucurus</hi>[AOU, 304]. Holmgren, 34. The gold-winged blackbird
        mentioned for comparison of the magpie may be the red-winged blackbird, 
        <hi rend="italic">Agelaius phoeniceus</hi>[AOU, 498], or possibly some type of oriole (
        <hi rend="italic">Icterus</hi>sp.).</note>
            <note xml:id="n06091714" n="14">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>observation from Codex O.</note>
            <note xml:id="n06091715" n="15">Western white-tailed deer, 
        <hi rend="italic">Odocoileus virginianus dacotensis</hi>; see 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>entry for 
        <ref n="1804-09-16" type="related">September 16</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n06091716" n="16">The coyote, 
        <hi rend="italic">Canis latrans.</hi>
            </note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1804-09-16" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1804-09-18" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
