<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-03-02">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">March 2, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic
        Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            6</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">November 2, 1805–March 22, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1990</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">368-374</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">275</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">195</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jw">Joseph Whitehouse</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            11</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of Joseph Whitehouse, May 14, 1804–April 2,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1997</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">424-425</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journal Entries</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-08-30</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-04-12</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1806-03-02">March 2, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-03-02.01" ref="">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Sunday March 2cd</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>The diet of the sick is so inferior that they recover their strength but slowly.
             none of them are now sick but all in a state of convalessence with keen
          appetites and nothing to eat except lean Elk meat.    late this evening 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name>arrived with a most
          acceptable supply of fat Sturgeon, fresh Anchovies and a bag containing about a bushel
          of Wappetoe.    we feasted on Anchovies and Wappetoe.</p>
               <p>
                  <figure rend="aps">
                     <p>Head of Cock of the Plains
              <lb/>(sage grouse, 
              <hi rend="italic">Centrocercus urophasianus</hi>),
              <lb/>March 2, 1806, Codex J, p. 107 
              <bibl>
                           <orgName>(American Philosophical Society library,</orgName>
                           <note place="inline">used with permission.)</note>
                        </bibl>
                     </p>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>The 
          <hi rend="italic">Cock of the Plains</hi>
                  <ref target="n28030201" n="1"/>is found in the 
          <name type="place" key="Great Columbian Plain">plains of Columbia</name>and are in Great
          abundance from the entrance of the 
          <name type="place"
                        key="Salmon (Lewis's, Main Fork Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">
          S. E. fork of the Columbia</name>to that of 
          <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">Clark's river</name>.
             this bird is about ⅔rds the size of a turkey.    the beak is
          large short curved and convex.    the upper exceeding the lower chap.
             the nostrils are large and the b[e]ak black.    the colour is an
          uniform mixture of dark brown reather bordeing on a dove colour, redish and yellowish
          brown with some small black specks.    in this mixture the dark brown prevails
          and has a slight cast of the dove colour at a little distance.    the wider
          side of the large feathers of the wings are of a dark brown only.    the tail
          is composed of 19 feathers of which that in the center is the longest, and the remaining
          9 on each side deminish by pairs as they receede from the center; that is any one
          feather is equal in length to one equa distant from the center of the tail on the
          oposite side.    the tail when foalded comes to a very sharp point and appears
          long in proportion to the body.    in the act of flying the tail resembles
          that of a wild pigeon.    tho' the motion of the wings is much that of the
          pheasant and Grouse.    they have four toes on each foot of which the hinder
          one is short.    the leg is covered with feathers about half the distance
          between the knee and foot.    when the wing is expanded there are wide opening
          between it's feathers the plumeage being so narrow that it does not extend from one
          quill to the other.    the wings are also proportionably short, reather more
          so than those of the pheasant or grouse.    the habits of this bird are much
          the same as those of the grouse.    only that the food of this fowl is almost
          entirely that of the leaf and buds of the pulpy leafed thorn;
          <ref target="n28030202" n="2"/>nor do I ever recollect seeing this bird but in the
          neighbourhood of that shrub.    they sometimes feed on the prickley pear.
             the gizzard of it is large and much less compressed and muscular than in
          most fowls; in short it resembles a maw quite as much as a gizzard.    when
          they fly they make a cackling noise something like the dunghill fowl.    the
          following is a likeness of the head and beak.
          <ref target="n28030203" n="3"/>   the flesh of the cock of the Plains is
          dark, and only tolerable in point of flavor. I do not think it as good as either the
          Pheasant or Grouse.—    it is invariably found in the plains.— The feathers
          about it's head are pointed and stif some hairs about the base of the beak.   
          feathers short fine and stif about the ears.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-03-02.02" ref="">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Sunday March 2nd 1806</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>The diet of the Sick is So inferior that they recover their Strength but Slowly.
             none of them are now Sick but all in a State of Covelessence with keen
          appetites and nothing to eate except lean Elk meat.</p>
               <p>The nativs of this neighbourhood eate the root of the Cattail or Cooper's flag.
             it is pleasantly tasted and appears to be very nutrecious.    the
          inner part of the root which is eaten without any previous preperation is Composed of a
          number of capellary white flexable Strong fibers among which is a mealy or Starch like
          Substance which readily disolves in the mouth and Seperates from the fibers which are
          then rejected.    it appears to me that this Substance would make excellent
          Starch; nothing Can be of a pureer white than it is.—.</p>
               <p>This evening late 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Crusat</name>&amp; 
          <name type="person" key="Weiser, Peter">Wiser</name>returned with a most acceptable
          Supply of fat Sturgen, fresh anchoves and a bag Containing about a bushel of 
          <hi rend="italic">Wappato.</hi>   we feasted on the Anchovies and
          wappatoe.—.</p>
               <p>The 
          <hi rend="italic">Heath Cock</hi>or 
          <hi rend="italic">cock of the Plains</hi>is found in the 
          <name type="place" key="Great Columbian Plain">Plains of Columbia</name>and are in great
          abundance from the enterance of 
          <name type="place" key="Lewis (Cahwahnakiooks) River">Lewis's river</name>to the
          mountains which pass the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>between the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Great Falls of the">Great falls</name>and 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Cascades (Great Rapids, Great Shute)">
          Rapids</name>of that river.    this fowl is about ¾ths the Size of a turkey.
             the beak is large Short Curved and convex.    the upper exceeding
          the lower chap. the nostrils are large and the back black.    the Colour is a
          uniform mixture of dark brown reather bordering on a dove colour, redish and yellowish
          brown with Some Small black Specks.    in this mixture the dark brown provails
          and has a Slight cast of the dove colour at a little distance.    the wider
          side of the larger feathers of the wings are of a dark brown only.    the tail
          is composed of 19 feathers of which that in the center is the longest, and the remaining
          9 on each Side deminish by pairs as they receede from the Center; that is any one
          feather is equal in length to one of an equal distance from the Center of the tail on
          the opposit Side.    the tail when folded Comes to a very Sharp point and
          appears long in perpotion to the body in the act of flying the tail resembles that of a
          wild pigeon.    tho' the motion of the wings is much that of the Pheasant and
          Grouse.    they have four toes on each foot of which the hinder one is Short.
             the leg is covered with feathers about half the distance between the knee
          and foot.    when the wings is expanded there are wide opening between it's
          feathers, the plumage being So narrow that it does not extend from one quill to another.
             the wings are also propotionably Short, reather more So than those of the
          Pheasant or Grouse.    the habits of this bird is much the Same as those of
          the Prarie hen or Grouse.    only that the food of this fowl is almost
          entirely that of the leaf and buds of the pulpy leafed thorn, nor do I ever recollect
          Seeing this bird but in the neighbourhood of that Shrub. The gizzard of it is large and
          much less compressed and muscular than in most fowls, in Short it resembles a maw quite
          as much as a gizzard. When they fly they make a cackling noise Something like the
          dunghill fowl.    the flesh of this fowl is dark and only tolerable in point
          of flavour. I do not think it as good as wth the Pheasant or Prarie hen, or Grouse.
             the feathers above it's head are pointed and Stiff Some hairs about the
          base of the beak.    feathers Short fine and Stiff about the ears, and eye.
          This is a faint likeness of the 
          <hi rend="italic">Cock</hi>of the plains or Heath Cock
          <ref target="n28030204" n="4"/>   the first of those fowls which we met with
          was on the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>below and in the neighbourhood of
          the 
          <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky Mountains</name>and from to the mountain
          <ref target="n28030205" n="5"/>which passes the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>between the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Cascades (Great Rapids, Great Shute)">Great
          falls and Rapids</name>they go in large gangues or Singularly and hide remarkably close
          when pursued, make Short flights, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <figure rend="mhs">
                     <p>Cock of the Plains
              <lb/>(sage grouse, 
              <hi rend="italic">Centrocercus urophasianus</hi>),
              <lb/>March 2, 1806, Voorhis No. 2 
              <bibl>
                           <orgName>Missouri Historical Society</orgName>
                        </bibl>
                     </p>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>The large Black &amp; White 
          <hi rend="italic">Pheasant</hi>
                  <ref target="n28030206" n="6"/>is peculiar to that portion of the 
          <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky Mountains</name>watered by the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>.    at least we
          did not See them untill we reached the waters of that river, nor Since we have left
          those mountains.    they are about the Size of a well grown hen.   
          the contour of the bird is much that of the redish brown Pheasant common to our country.
             the tail is proportionably as long and is composed of 18 feathers of equal
          length, of a uniform dark brown tiped with black.    the feathers of the body
          are of a dark brown black and white.    the black is that which most
          prodomonates, and white feathers are irregularly intermixed with those of the black and
          dark brown on every part but in greater perpotion about the neck breast and belly.
             this mixture gives it very much the appearance of that kind of dunghill
          fowl, which the hen-wives of our Countrey Call 
          <hi rend="italic">dommanicker.</hi>
                  <ref target="n28030207" n="7"/>   in the brest of Some of those birds the
          white prodominates most.    they are not furnished with tufts of long feathers
          on the neck as other Pheasants are, but have a Space on each Side of the neck about 2½
          inches long and one inch in width on which no feathers grow, tho' it is consealed by the
          feathers which are insertedon the hinder and front part of the neck, this Space Seams to
          Serve them to dilate or contract the feathers of the neck, this Space Seams to Serve
          them to dilate or contract the feathers of the neck with more ease.    the eye
          is dark, the beak black, uncovered Somewhat pointed and the upper exceeds the under
          chap.    they have a narrow Strip of vermillion colour above each eye which
          consists of a fleshey Substance not protuberant but uneaven, with a number of minute
          rounded dots.    it has four toes on each foot of which three are in front, it
          is booted to the toes.    it feeds on wild fruits, particularly the berry of
          the 
          <hi rend="italic">Sac-a-com-mis,</hi>and much also on the Seed of the pine &amp; fir.
             this fowl is usially found in Small numbers two and three &amp; 4 together
          on the ground.    when Supprised flies up &amp; lights on a tree and is easily
          Shot    their flesh is Superior to most of the Pheasant Species which we have
          met with.    they have a gizzard as other Pheasants &amp;c.    feed
          also on the buds of the Small Huckleberry bushes</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-03-02.03" ref="">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>Sunday 2nd March 1806.    a rainy morning.    in the evening the
          three men returned from the village with a considerable quantity of the little fish
          <ref target="n28030208" n="8"/>resembling herren only a Size Smaller—and some Sturgeon
          <ref target="n28030209" n="9"/>and a fiew wapa-toes, which they purchased from them.
             the natives catch a vast quantity of fish &amp;C—</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-03-02.04" ref="">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>Sunday 2d—    This day was also wet. The fishing party
          <ref target="n28030210" n="10"/>returned at night, and brought with them some thousands
          of the same kind of small fish we got from the natives a few days ago, and also some
          sturgeon.
          <ref target="n28030211" n="11"/>
               </p>
               <p>The Indian name of the river we were up yesterday is 
          <name type="place" key="Youngs (Kilhow-a-nah-kle) River">Kil-hou-a-nak-kle</name>, and
          that of the small river which passes the fort, 
          <name type="place" key="Lewis and Clark (Fort, Netul) River">Ne-tul</name>.
          <ref target="n28030212" n="12"/>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-03-02.05" ref="">
            <sp who="jw">
               <speaker>Whitehouse</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>Sunday March 2d    This morning rainey &amp; Wet, In the evening, three of
          our men
          <ref target="n28030213" n="13"/>returned who had been trading at the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsop</name>Village.   
          they brought with them a considerable quantity of those small kind of fish,
          <ref target="n28030214" n="14"/>which we purchased from the Natives some days past;
          These fish were a size smaller than the herring.—    they likewise brought
          several Sturgeon
          <ref target="n28030215" n="15"/>Wapetoes Roots &amp;ca. which they had purchased from
          the Natives.    The natives gave them some fish without any recompence being
          made to them.    These Indians catch great quantities of different kinds of
          fish in a Creek lying a small distance above their Village.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n28030201" n="1">The sage grouse, 
        <hi rend="italic">Centrocercus urophasianus</hi>[AOU, 309], a new discovery. Burroughs,
        213–15; Cutright (LCPN), 432. The wild pigeon used for comparison is the passenger pigeon,
        
        <hi rend="italic">Ectopistes migratorius</hi>[AOU, 315]. The "dunghill fowl" mentioned
        later in the entry is the common chicken (see note below). A light red line runs
        vertically through the first few lines of this paragraph, perhaps done by 
        <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28030202" n="2">Greasewood, 
        <hi rend="italic">Sarcobatus vermiculatus</hi>(Hook.) Torr. in Emory. 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>remark on the close association
        between the sage grouse and greasewood may not be entirely correct. Hitchcock et al.,
        2:213; Franklin &amp; Dyrness, 227; Cutright (LCPN), 137. An interlineation at this point
        has been erased beyond legibility.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28030203" n="3">A sketch of the head of the sage grouse (fig. 43), in 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>Codex J, p. 107.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28030204" n="4">A full-length sketch of the sage grouse (fig. 44), from 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>Voorhis No. 2.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28030205" n="5">Presumably the 
        <name type="place" key="Cascade Range">Cascade Range</name>. 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>map 78.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28030206" n="6">See notes for 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>description of the three
        "pheasants" in the next entry. 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>words here were probably copied
        from that material.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28030207" n="7">A breed of chicken called the dominique, or dominecker,
        which resembles the Barred Plymouth Rock. Criswell, 33.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28030208" n="8">The eulachon, or candle fish, 
        <hi rend="italic">Thaleichthys pacificus</hi>. 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>called them anchovies and drew
        sketches of the fish in their journals; see 
        <ref n="1806-02-24" type="related">figs. 41</ref>and 
        <ref n="1806-02-25" type="related">42</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28030209" n="9">Either the white sturgeon, 
        <hi rend="italic">Acipenser transmontanus,</hi>or green sturgeon, 
        <hi rend="italic">A. medirostris</hi>. See 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>for 
        <ref n="1805-11-19" type="related">November 19, 1805</ref>, and 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>for 
        <ref n="1806-02-25" type="related">February 25, 1806</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28030210" n="10">
               <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name>, 
        <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Cruzatte</name>, and 
        <name type="person" key="Weiser, Peter">Weiser</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28030211" n="11">This could be green sturgeon, 
        <hi rend="italic">Acipenser medirostris,</hi>or white sturgeon, 
        <hi rend="italic">A. transmontanus.</hi>See 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>for 
        <ref n="1805-11-19" type="related">November 19, 1805</ref>, and 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>for 
        <ref n="1806-02-24" type="related">February 24, 1806</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28030212" n="12">The "
        <name type="place" key="Youngs (Kilhow-a-nah-kle) River">Kil-hou-a-nak-kle</name>" is 
        <name type="place" key="Youngs (Kilhow-a-nah-kle) River">Youngs River</name>, and the 
        <name type="place" key="Lewis and Clark (Fort, Netul) River">Netul</name>is 
        <name type="place" key="Lewis and Clark (Fort, Netul) River">Lewis and Clark River</name>,
        both in 
        <name type="place" key="Clatsop County, Oreg.">Clatsop County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>. The terms are both Chinookan, 
        <hi rend="italic">giławanax̣ł</hi>and 
        <hi rend="italic">ní'tul.</hi>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="n28030213" n="13">
               <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name>, 
        <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Cruzatte</name>, and 
        <name type="person" key="Weiser, Peter">Weiser</name>, who had left on February 26.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28030214" n="14">Eulachon.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28030215" n="15">Either the white sturgeon, 
        <hi rend="italic">Acipenser transmontanus</hi>, or green sturgeon. See 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>entries for 
        <ref n="1805-11-19" type="related">November 19, 1805</ref>, and 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>for 
        <ref n="1806-02-25" type="related">February 25, 1806</ref>.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-03-01" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-03-03" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
