<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-05-11">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">May 11, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic
        Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            7</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">March 23–June 9, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1991</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">242-246</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">309</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">225</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Journal Entries</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-10-12</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-04-12</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1806-05-11">May 11, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-05-11.01" ref="">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Sunday May 11th 1806.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>The last evening we were much crouded with the indians in our lodge, the whole floor
          of which was covered with their sleeping carcases.    we arrose early and took
          breakfast.    at 8 A. M. a cheif of great note among these people arrived from
          his village or lodge on the S. side of 
          <name type="place" key="Lewis (Cahwahnakiooks) River">Lewis's River</name>.   
          this is a stout fellow of good countenance about 40 years of age and has lost the left
          eye.    his name is 
          <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="person" key="Five Big Hearts">Yoom-park'-kar-tim.</name>
                  </hi>
                  <ref target="n34051101" n="1"/>   to this man we gave a medal of the smal
          kind.    those with the likeness of 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Mr. Jefferson</name>have all been disposed
          of except one of the largest size which we reserve for some great Cheif on the 
          <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellow rock river</name>.
          <ref target="n34051102" n="2"/>   we now pretty fully informed ourselves that
          
          <name type="person" key="Broken Arm">Tunnachemootoolt</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Cut Nose">Neeshneparkkeeook</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Five Big Hearts">Yoom-parkkartim</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Hohots Ilppilp">Hohâstillpilp</name>were the principal Cheif of
          the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Chopunnish</name>nation and ranked in
          the order here mentioned; as all those cheifs were present in our lodge we thought it a
          favourable time to repeat what had been said yesterday and to enter more minutely into
          the views of our government with rispect to the inhabitants of this western part of the
          continent, their intention of establishing trading houses for their releif, their wish
          to restore peace and harmony among the natives, the strength power and wealth of our
          nation &amp;c.    to this end we drew a map of the country with a coal on a
          mat in their way and by the assistance of the snake boy and our interpretters were
          enabled to make ourselves understood by them altho' it had to pass through the French, 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Minnetare</name>, 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshone</name>and 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Chopunnish</name>languages.
             the interpretation being tedious it ocupyed nearly half the day before we
          had communicated to them what we wished.    they appeared highly pleased.
             after this council was over we amused ourselves with shewing them the power
          of magnetism, the spye glass, compass, watch, air-gun and sundry other articles equally
          novel and incomprehensible to them.    they informed us that after we had left
          the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Minnetares</name>last spring that three
          of their people had visited that nation
          <ref target="n34051103" n="3"/>and that they had informed them of us and had told them
          that we had such things in our possession but that they could not place confidence in
          the information untill they had now witnessed it themselves.—    A young man,
          son of a conspicuous cheif among these people who was killed not long since by the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Atsina Indians">Minnetares</name>of 
          <name type="place" key="Fort des Prairies (Canada)">Fort de Prarie</name>,
          <ref target="n34051104" n="4"/>brought and presented us a very fine mare and colt.
             he said he had opened his ears to our councils and would observe them
          strictly, and that our words had made his heart glad.    he requested that we
          would accept this mear and colt which he gave in token of his determination to pursue
          our advise.—    about 3 P. M. 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name>arrived with 2 deer which he
          had killed.    he informed us that the snow still continued to cover the
          plain. many of the natives apply to us for medical aid which we gave them cheerfully so
          far as our skill and store of medicine would enable us.    schrofela,
          <ref target="n34051105" n="5"/>ulsers, rheumatism, soar eyes, and the loss of the uce
          of their limbs are the most common cases among them.    the latter case is not
          very common but we have seen thee instances of it among the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Chopunnish</name>.    it is
          a very extraordinary complaint.    a Cheif of considerable note at this place
          has been afflicted with it for three years,
          <ref target="n34051106" n="6"/>he is incapable of moving a single limb but lies like a
          corps in whatever position he is placed, yet he eats heartily, digests his food
          perfectly, injoys his understanding, his pulse are good, and has retained his flesh
          almost perfectly, in short were it not that he appears a little pale from having lain so
          long in the shade he might well be taken for a man in good health. I suspect that their
          confinement to a diet of roots may give rise to all those disorders except the
          rheumatism &amp; soar eyes, and to the latter of these, the state of debility incident
          to a vegetable diet may measureable contribute.—    The 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Chopunnish</name>notwithstanding they
          live in the crouded manner before mentioned are much more clenly in their persons and
          habitations than any nation we have seen since we left the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Oto Indians">Ottoes</name>on the 
          <name type="place" key="Platte River (Nebr.)">river Platte</name>.—    The 
          <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">Twisted hair</name>brought us six
          of our horses.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-05-11.02" ref="">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Sunday 11th May 1806</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>Some little rain last night.    we were Crouded in the Lodge with Indians
          who continued all night and this morning Great numbers were around us. The One Eyes
          Chief 
          <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="person" key="Five Big Hearts">Yoom-park-kar-tim</name>
                  </hi>
                  <ref target="n34051107" n="7"/>arived and we gave him a medal of the Small Size and
          Spoke to the Indians through a 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Snake</name>boy 
          <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Shabono</name>and his 
          <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">wife</name>.    we informed them who were
          were, where we Came from &amp; our intentions towards them, which pleased them very
          much.    a young man Son to the great Cheif who was killed not long Sence by
          the Indians from the N. E. brought an elegant mare and Coalt and Gave us.   
          and Said he had opend. his ears to what we had Said and his heart was glad and requested
          us to take this mare and Coalt as a token of his deturmination to pursue our Councels
          &amp;c. The 
          <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">twisted hair</name>brough Six of
          our horses all in fine order. Great numbers of Indians apply to us for medical aide
          which we gave them Cherfully So far as our Skill and Store of Medicine would enable us.
          Schrofla, ulsers, rhumitism, Sore eyes, and the loss of the use of their Limbs are the
          most common cases among them.    the latter Case is not very common but We
          have Seen 3 instances of it among the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Chopunnish</name>.    a
          very extraordinery complnt. about 3 P. M. 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Geo. drewyer</name>arived with 2 deer which
          he had killed.    he informed us that the Snow Still Continued to cover the
          plains. We are now pretty well informed that 
          <name type="person" key="Broken Arm">Tunnachemootoolt</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Hohots Ilppilp">Hohâstillpilp</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Cut Nose">Neshneparkkeeook</name>, and 
          <name type="person" key="Five Big Hearts">Yoomparkkartim</name>were the principal Chiefs
          of the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Chopunnish</name>Nation and ranked in
          the order here mentioned; as all those chiefs were present in our lodge we thought it a
          favourable time to repeet what had been said and to enter more minutely into the views
          of our government with respect to the inhabitents of this Western part of the Continent,
          their intention of establishing tradeing houses for their relief, their wish to restore
          peace and harmony and among the nativs, the Strength welth and powers of our Nation
          &amp;c.    to this end we drew a map of the Country with a coal on a mat in
          their way, and by the assistance of the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Snake</name>boy and our interpeters
          were enabled to make ourselves under stood by them altho' it had to pass through French,
          
          <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Minnetare</name>, 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshone</name>and 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Chopunnish</name>languages.
             the interpretation being tegious it occupied the greater part of the day,
          before we had communicated to them what we wished.    they appeared highly
          pleased.    after this Council was over 〈they〉 we amused ourselves with
          Shewing them the power of Magnetism, the Spye glass, compass, watch, 
          <hi rend="italic">air gun</hi>and Sundery other articles equally novel and
          incomprehensible to them.   they informed us that after we left the Menetares
          last Spring that 3 of their people had visited that nation, and that they had informed
          them of us, and had told them that we had Such things in our possession but that they
          Could not place Confidence in the information untill they had now witnessed it
          themselves—.</p>
               <p>In the evening a man was brought in a robe by four Indians and laid down near me.
             they informed me that this man was a Cheif of Considerable note who has
          been in the Situation I see him for 5 years.    this man is incapable of
          moveing a single limb but lies like a corps in whatever position he is placed, yet he
          eats hartily, dejests his food perfectly, enjoys his under standing, his pulse are good,
          and has retained his flesh almost perfectly; in Short were it not 〈for〉 that he appears
          a little pale from having been So long in the Shade, he might well be taken for a man in
          good health. I Suspect that their Confinement to a deet of roots may give rise to all
          the disordes of the Nativs of this quarter except the Rhumitism &amp; Sore eyes, and to
          the latter of those, the State of debility incident to a vegitable diet may measureably
          contribute.—. The 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Chopunnish</name>not withstanding
          they live in the Crouded manner before mentioned are much more clenly in their persons
          and habitations than any nation we have Seen Sence we left the 
          <name type="place" key="Illinois">Illinois</name>. These nativs take their fish in the
          following manner to wit.    a Stand Small Stage or warf consisting of Sticks
          and projecting about 10 feet into the river and about 3 feet above the water on the
          extremity of this the fisherman stands with his guig or a Skooping Net which differ but
          little in their form those Commonly used in our Country    it is formed thus
          <ref target="n34051108" n="8"/>   with those nets they take the Suckers
          <ref target="n34051109" n="9"/>and also the Salmon trout and I am told the Salmon
          also.</p>
               <p>
                  <figure rend="mhs">
                     <p>Fish Net, May 11, 1806, Voorhis No. 3 
              <bibl>
                           <orgName>Missouri Historical Society</orgName>
                        </bibl>
                     </p>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-05-11.03" ref="">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>Sunday 11th of May 1806.    a fair morning.    a number of the
          natives who were diseased came to our officers to be healed    
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name>applyed meddison and done all
          possable for them.    one of the Indians gave 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name>a fine horse. 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">George Drewyer</name>Came in from hunting.
             had killed two Deer.    the Indians brought us Several more of
          our horses &amp;C.    in the evening we fiddled and danced a while.
             the natives assembled to See us.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-05-11.04" ref="">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Sunday 11th.</hi>   This was a fine clear morning; and we
          lay here all day. The natives treat us very well; the officers practise as physicians
          among their sick, and they gave them a very handsome mare and colt. About 12 o'clock our
          hunter
          <ref target="n34051110" n="10"/>came in and brought two deer with him. We now find a
          great many more men among the Indians than when we went down last fall; and several
          chiefs, which had them been out at war. In the evening the natives brought in six more
          of our horses.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n34051101" n="1">His name apparently meant "
        <name type="person" key="Five Big Hearts">Five Big Hearts</name>;" the 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>term may be 
        <hi rend="italic">hiy
        <seg n="u243">ó</seg>·mpa·
        <seg n="uxu803">x̣</seg>atimina.</hi>Wheeler, 2:267; Josephy (NP), 11.</note>
            <note xml:id="n34051102" n="2">The medal would be the 105mm Jefferson medal; see 
        <ref n="1804-08-03" type="related">August 3, 1804</ref>. The captains expected that 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>would meet Indians on his exploration
        of the 
        <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone River</name>, and the medal was
        reserved for the most prominent chief among them. In fact, he did not encounter any
        Indians on the 
        <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n34051103" n="3">Another indication of the widespread intertribal trade
        routes; these 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perces</name>probably visited the 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name>in company with their
        sometime friends and allies the 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Crow Indians">Crows</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n34051104" n="4">The 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Atsina Indians">Atsinas</name>; see 
        <ref n="1805-05-28" type="related">May 28, 1805</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n34051105" n="5">Scrofula is tuberculosis of the lymph glands. It is
        sometimes accompanied by abscesses and fistulae, which may be the symptoms 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>is referring to here. See also 
        <ref n="1805-10-10" type="related">October 10, 1805</ref>. Chuinard (OOMD), 324 and n.
        11.</note>
            <note xml:id="n34051106" n="6">Perhaps a case of hysterical paralysis, since no organic
        problem could be detected. Another suggestion, however, is polymyositis. Cutright (LCPN),
        295; Ronda (LCAI), 286 n. 34.</note>
            <note xml:id="n34051107" n="7">The name appears to have been added to a blank
        space.</note>
            <note xml:id="n34051108" n="8">A sketch of the net in Voorhis No. 3 (fig. 16).</note>
            <note xml:id="n34051109" n="9">Perhaps the mountain sucker, 
        <hi rend="italic">Catostomus platyrhynchus,</hi>elsewhere called a bottlenose; see 
        <ref n="1806-03-12" type="related">March 12, 1806</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n34051110" n="10">
               <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name>.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-05-10" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-05-12" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
