<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-09-16">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">September 16, 1805</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic
        Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            5</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">July 28–November 1, 1805</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1989</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">207-210</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">224-225</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">143</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jw">Joseph Whitehouse</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            11</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of Joseph Whitehouse, May 14, 1804–April 2,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1997</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">318-319</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
         <geoDecl datum="WGS" xml:id="lc.geo.1805-09-16.01">
            <placeName/>
            <geo>46.5963 -114.7675</geo>
            <note>Camped at what was later called Indian Post Office. Perhaps camped on Moon Creek, Idaho County, ID.</note>
         </geoDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journal Entries</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-06-15</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-04-12</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1805-09-16">September 16, 1805</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-09-16.01"
              ref="lc.geo.1805-09-16.01">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Septr. 16th Satturday 1805</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <table rows="2" cols="3">
                     <head>Course &amp;c.</head>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 75° W</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                           <hi rend="underline">13</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">miles over the mountain passing emince
                Dificuelt Knobs
                <lb/>Stones much falling timber and emencely Steep with great
                <lb/>dificulty we proseeded on. The 
                <hi rend="italic">Snow</hi>began to fall about 3
                <lb/>hours before Day and Contd. all day. I found great dificulty
                <lb/>in finding the road in the evining as the Snow had fallen from
                <lb/>6 to 8 Inches deep, verry Cold and the pine which in maney
                <lb/>places verry thick So covered with Snow, as in passing I be-
                <lb/>came wet discover 8 distinct kinds of pine on those moun-
                <lb/>tains    We Encamped on a Small branch running to the right.
                <lb/>Killed a Coalt &amp; [eate it]
                <ref target="n22091601" n="1"/>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                           <hi rend="double underline">13</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <figure rend="mhs">
                     <p>On the 
              <name type="place" key="Lolo Trail">Lolo Trail</name>, 
              <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>, September 13–16, 1805,
              <lb/>Elkskin-bound Journal 
              <bibl>
                           <orgName>Missouri Historical Society</orgName>
                        </bibl>
                     </p>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-09-16.02"
              ref="lc.geo.1805-09-16.01">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Saturday [NB: Monday] Septr. 16th 1805</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>began to Snow about 3 hours before Day and Continud. all day    the Snow in
          The morning 4 Inches deep on The old Snow, and by night we found it from 6 to 8 Inches
          deep    I walked in front to keep the road and found great dificuelty in
          keeping it as in maney places the Snow had entirely filled up the track, and obliged me
          to hunt Several minits for the track    at 12 oClock we halted on the top of
          the mountain
          <ref target="n22091602" n="2"/>to worm &amp; dry our Selves a little as well as to let
          our horses rest and graze a little on Some long grass which I observed, (on) The South
          〈Knobs〉 Steep hills Side &amp; falling timber Continue to day, and a thickly timbered
          Countrey of 8 different kinds of pine,
          <ref target="n22091603" n="3"/>which are So covered with Snow, that in passing thro
          them we are continually covered with Snow, I have been wet and as cold in every part as
          I ever was in my life, indeed I was at one time fearfull my feet would freeze in the
          thin mockersons which I wore, after a Short delay in the middle of the Day, I took one
          man and proceeded on as fast as I could about 6 miles to a Small branch passing to the
          right, halted and built fires for the party agains their arrival which was at Dusk verry
          cold and much fatigued    we Encamped at this Branch in a thickly timbered
          bottom which was Scercely large enough for us to lie leavil,
          <ref target="n22091604" n="4"/>men all wet cold and hungary. Killed a Second Colt which
          we all Suped hartily on and thought it fine meat.</p>
               <p>I saw 4 Black tail Deer to day before we Set out which came up the mountain and what
          is Singular Snaped 7 tims at a large buck.    it is Singular as my gun has a
          Steel frisen
          <ref target="n22091605" n="5"/>and never Snaped 7 times before    in
          examining her found the flint loose    to describe the road of this day would
          be a repitition of yesterday excpt the Snow which made it much wors to proseed as we had
          in maney places to derect our Selves by the appearance of the rubbings of the Packs
          <ref target="n22091606" n="6"/>against the trees which have limbs quiet low and bending
          downwards</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-09-16.03"
              ref="lc.geo.1805-09-16.01">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>Monday 16th Sept 1805.    when we a woke this morning to our great Surprize
          we were covred with Snow, which had fell about 2 Inches deep the later part of last
          night, &amp; continues a cold Snowey morning. 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name>Shot at a deer but did not
          kill it.    we mended up our mockasons and Set out without any thing to eat,
          and proceeded on    could Scarsely keep the old trail for the Snow.
             kept on the Mountn. rather descending more than ascending.   
          about one oClock finding no water we halted
          <ref target="n22091607" n="7"/>and melted Some snow and eat or drank a little more
          Soup, and let our horses graze about one hour and a half then proceeded on. Saw
          considerable of old snow    passed several bald knobs and high points of rocks
          &amp;C.    towards evening we descended a Mountain down in to a deep cove
          where we Camped on a small creek in a thicket of Spruce pine and balsom fer timber.
             the Snow is now about 4 Inches deep on a levl.    we came about
          15 miles this day.    the clouds So low on the Mount that we could not See any
          distance no way.    it appeared as if we have been in the clouds all this day.
             we all being hungry and nothing to eat except a little portable soup which
          kept us verry weak, we killed another colt &amp; eat half of it.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-09-16.04"
              ref="lc.geo.1805-09-16.01">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Monday 16th.</hi>   Last night about 12 o'clock it began to
          snow. We renewed our march early, though the morning was very disagreeable, and
          proceeded over the most terrible mountains I ever beheld. It continued snowing until 3
          o'clock P. M. when we halted, took some more soup, and went on till we came to a small
          stream where we encamped for the night. Here we killed another colt and supped on it.
          The snow fell so thick, and the day was so dark, that a person could not see to a
          distance of 200 yards. In the night and during the day the snow fell about 10 inches
          deep.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-09-16.05"
              ref="lc.geo.1805-09-16.01">
            <sp who="jw">
               <speaker>Whitehouse</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Monday 16th Sept. 1805</hi>.    when we awoke this morning
          to our great Surprise we were covred with Snow which had fallen about 2 Inches the
          latter part of last night, and continues a verry cold Snow Storm.    
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name>Shot at a deer but did not
          kill it.    we mended up our mockasons.    Some of the men without
          Socks raped rags on their feet, and loaded up our horses and Set out without any thing
          to eat, and proceeded on.    could hardly See the old trail for the Snow.
             kept on the ridge of the mountain    Several high knobs to pass
          over but had more down hill than up.    about one oClock finding no water we
          halted and melted Snow and made a little more Soup, and let our horses graze 1 hour
          &amp; a half.    then proceeded on    the Snow is fell So fast that
          it is now in common 5 or 6 Inches deep.    Some places is considerable of old
          Snow on the moutn.    towards evening we descended the mountain down in a
          lonesome cove
          <ref target="n22091608" n="8"/>on a creek where we Camped in a thicket of Spruce pine
          &amp; bolsom fir timber.    all being tired &amp; hungry, obledged us to kill
          another colt and eat the half of it this evening.    it has quit Snowing this
          evening, but continues chilley and cold.    Came about 15
          <ref target="n22091609" n="9"/>miles to day over a rockey rough road.    Some
          places bare on the top high places of rocks &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Monday Septemr 16th    We were all surprized when we awoke this morning; to
          find ourselves covered with Snow, which was 2 Inches deep &amp; had fallen in the latter
          part of last night &amp; it still continuing to Snow.    
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain Clark</name>went out with his Gun &amp;
          shot a deer on the Mountain but did not get it.—    The Snow storm continued
          and the Men were employed in mending up their Moccasins.    some of our party
          are without Socks, and are forced to wrap Rags round their feet to keep out the cold.
             We loaded up our Horses, &amp; set out not having anything for to eat, We
          proceeded on our way, but had great difficulty to follow the Indian trail on account of
          the Snow that had fell, we still continued on our Journey, along the ridge of the
          Mountain; and we had several of the Nobs of the Mountain to pass over, but all the way
          on a descent, about 1 o'Clock P. M we finding no Water we halted, &amp; melted some Snow
          &amp; made some portable Soup for our party, and turned out our horses to Graze about
          One hour &amp; a half    The Snow fell so fast that it is now from 5 to 6
          inches deep &amp; where old the Snow remained it was considerably deeper, towards
          evening, we descended the mountain; down into a lonesome looking Cove on to a Creek,
          where we encamped in a thicket of spruce Pine timber.    The party were all
          much fataigued &amp; hungry, our officers had a Colt killed and the party eat the half
          of it this evening.    In the evening it quitted snowing, but the wind was
          very chilly &amp; Cold, We came about 15 Miles this day &amp; passed over a rough &amp;
          rockey road, &amp; on the tops of rocks which were quite bare.—</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n22091601" n="1">The bracketed material is from Thwaites (LC), 3:70, as it
        is not apparent on the damaged page of the Elksin-bound Journal.</note>
            <note xml:id="n22091602" n="2">Perhaps on 
        <name type="place" key="Spring Hill">Spring Hill</name>(or 
        <name type="place" key="Spring Hill">Spring Mountain</name>), in northern 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho County, Idaho">Idaho County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>, not marked on fig. 6 or 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>map 70. Space, 10.</note>
            <note xml:id="n22091603" n="3">
               <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>uses the general term "pine" for all
        the types of evergreen conifers. The species include: lodgepole pine, Douglas fir,
        subalpine fir, Engelmann spruce, whitebark pine, 
        <hi rend="italic">Pinus albicaulis</hi>Engelm., grand fir, 
        <hi rend="italic">Abies grandis</hi>(Dougl.) Lindl., western larch, and mountain hemlock, 
        <hi rend="italic">Tsuga mertensiana</hi>(Bong.) 
        <name type="person" key="Cann, E.">Carr</name>. Other possibilities at lower elevations
        are: ponderosa pine, western white pine, 
        <hi rend="italic">Pinus monticola</hi>Dougl., and western redcedar, 
        <hi rend="italic">Thuja plicata</hi>Donn. Space, 10–11; Cutright (LCPN), 203–4; Little
        (CIH), 43-W, 6-W, 62-W, 93-W, 90-W; Daubenmire, 301, 314–15; Pfister et al., 17.</note>
            <note xml:id="n22091604" n="4">Near the rock mounds later called 
        <name type="place" key="Indian Post Office">Indian Post Office</name>(which none of the
        journalists mentions), perhaps on 
        <name type="place" key="Moon Creek (Idaho)">Moon Creek</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho County, Idaho">Idaho County</name>. Space, 10; Peebles (LT),
        6; Cutright (LCPN), 205 n. 14; 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>map 70.</note>
            <note xml:id="n22091605" n="5">The frizzen is the upright piece of metal against which the
        flint in a flintlock firearm strikes to produce the spark that fires the powder. The
        repeated misfires were probably due to the wet conditions as well as the loose flint.
        Russell (GEF), 288–89.</note>
            <note xml:id="n22091606" n="6">The packs of the Indians who had passed by, going east or
        west. There is a blank half-page following this entry. The next entry starts at the top of
        a new page (p. 116) in Codex G.</note>
            <note xml:id="n22091607" n="7">Perhaps on 
        <name type="place" key="Spring Hill">Spring Hill</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho County, Idaho">Idaho County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n22091608" n="8">Another designation unique to 
        <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n22091609" n="9">The words "about 15" appear to have been squeezed into a
        blank space and perhaps written by another person.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-09-15" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-09-17" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
