<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-09-21">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">September 21, 1805</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic
        Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            5</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">July 28–November 1, 1805</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1989</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">225-228</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">227</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">146</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jw">Joseph Whitehouse</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            11</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of Joseph Whitehouse, May 14, 1804–April 2,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1997</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">325-326</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
         <geoDecl datum="WGS" xml:id="lc.geo.1805-09-21.01">
            <placeName/>
            <geo>46.4667 -115.7833</geo>
            <note>Clark camped on the Clearwater River about a mile above present Orofino, Clearwater County, ID.</note>
         </geoDecl>
         <geoDecl datum="WGS" xml:id="lc.geo.1805-09-21.02">
            <placeName/>
            <geo>46.2599 -115.8055</geo>
            <note>The group camped on Lolo Creek in Clearwater County, ID, along the boundary between Idaho and Clearwater counties.</note>
         </geoDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journal Entries</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-06-17</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-04-12</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1805-09-21">September 21, 1805</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-09-21.01" ref="">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Saturday September 21st 1805.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>We were detained this morning untill 11 OCk. in consequence of not being able to
          collect our horses.    we then set out and proceeded along the ridge on which
          we had encamped, leaving which at 1½ we passed a large creek runing to the left just
          above it's junction with another which run parrallel with and on the left of our road
          before we struck the creek;
          <ref target="n22092101" n="1"/>through the level wide and heavy timbered bottom of this
          creek we proceeded about 2½ miles when bearing to the right we passed a broken country
          heavily timbered great quantities of which had fallen and so obstructed our road that it
          was almost impracticable to proceed in many places.    though these hills we
          proceeded about 5 Ms. when we passed a small creek
          <ref target="n22092102" n="2"/>on which 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt Clark</name>encamped on the 19th
             passing this creek we continued our rout 5 Ms thro' a similar country when
          we struck a large creek at the forks,
          <ref target="n22092103" n="3"/>passed the Northen branch and continued down it on the
          West side 1 mile and encamped in a small open bottom
          <ref target="n22092104" n="4"/>where there was tolerable food for our horses. I
          directed the horses to be hubbled to prevent delay in the morning being determined to
          make a forced march tomorrow in order to reach if possible the open country. we killed a
          few Pheasants, and I killd a prarie woolf
          <ref target="n22092105" n="5"/>which together with the ballance of our horse beef and
          some crawfish
          <ref target="n22092106" n="6"/>which we obtained in the creek enabled us to make one
          more hearty meal, not knowing where the next was to be found.    the Arborvita
          [
          <hi rend="italic">NB: Copy for 
          <name type="person" key="Barton, Benjamin Smith">Dr Barton</name>
                  </hi>]
          <ref target="n22092107" n="7"/>increases in quantity and size. I saw several sticks
          today large enough to form eligant perogues of at least 45 feet in length.—   
          I find myself growing weak for the want of food and most of the men complain of a
          similar deficiency and have fallen off very much.    the general course of
          this day S 30 W 15 M.—</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-09-21.02" ref="">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Septr. 21st Saturday 1805</hi>
                     <ref target="n22092108" n="8"/>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>a fine morning    Sent out all the hunters early in different directions to
          Kill Something and delayed with the Indians to prevent Suspicion &amp; to acquire as
          much information as possible.    one of them Drew me a Chart of the river
          &amp; nations below informed of one falls below which the white men lived from whome
          they got white beeds cloth &amp;c. &amp;c. The day proved warm, 2 Chifs of Bands visited
          me to day—    the hunters all returned without any thing, I collected a horse
          load of roots &amp; 3 Sammon &amp; Sent 
          <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">R Fields</name>with one Indian to meet 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt Lewis</name>   at 4 oClock
          Set out with the other men to the river, passed thro a fine Pine Country   
          decended a Steep ruged hill verry long to a Small river which comes from our left and I
          suppose it to be [
          <hi rend="italic">blank</hi>] River    passed down the river 2 miles on a
          Steep hill side    at 11 oClock P. M. arrived at a camp of 5 Squars a boy
          &amp; 2 Children    those people were glad to See us &amp; gave us drid Sammon
             one had formerly been taken by the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Atsina Indians">Minitarries</name>of the north &amp;
          Seen white men, 
          <name type="person" key="Old Toby">our guide</name>called the Chief who was fishing on
          the other Side of the river, whome I found a Cherfull man of about 65    I
          gave him a Medal.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-09-21.03" ref="">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Thursday [NB: Saturday] 21st Septr. 1805</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>A fine morning    Sent out all the hunters in different directions to hunt
          deer, I myself delayd with the Chief to prevent Suspission and to Collect by Signs as
          much information as possible about the river and Countrey in advance. The Cheif drew me
          a kind of chart of the river, and informed me that a greater Cheif than himself was
          fishing at the river half a days march from his village called the 
          <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">twisted hare</name>, and that the
          river forked a little below his Camp
          <ref target="n22092109" n="9"/>and at a long distance below &amp; below 2 large forks
          one from the left &amp; the other from the right
          <ref target="n22092110" n="10"/>the river passed thro'gh the mountains at which place
          was a great fall of the water passing through the rocks,
          <ref target="n22092111" n="11"/>to those falls white people lived from whome they
          preceured the white Beeds &amp; Brass &amp;c. which the womin wore; a Chief of another
          band visit me to day and Smoked a pipe, I gave my handkerchief &amp; a Silver Cord with
          a little Tobacco to those Chiefs, The hunters all return without any thing, I purchased
          as much Provisions as I could with what fiew things I chaned to have in my Pockets, Such
          a Salmon Bread roots &amp; berries, &amp; Sent one man 
          <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">R. Fields</name>with an Indian to meet 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name>, and at 4 oClock P M. Set
          out to the river, met a man at dark on his way from the river to the village, whome I
          hired and gave the neck handkerchief of one of the men, to polit me to the Camp of the 
          <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">twisted hare</name>,
          <ref target="n22092112" n="12"/>we did not arrive at the Camp of the 
          <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">Twisted hare</name>but oppost,
          untill half past 11 oClock P M.
          <ref target="n22092113" n="13"/>   found at this Camp five Squars &amp; 3
          Children.    my guide called to the Chief who was Encamped with 2 others on a
          Small island in the river, he Soon joind me, I found him a Chearfull man with apparant
          Siencerity, I gave him a medal &amp;c. and Smoked untill 1 oClock a. m. and went to
          Sleep. The Countrey from the mountains to the river hills is a leavel rich butifull Pine
          Countrey badly watered, thinly timbered &amp; covered with grass—
          <ref target="n22092114" n="14"/>   The weather verry worm after decending
          into the low Countrey,—    the river hills are verry high &amp; Steep, Small
          bottoms    to this little river which is 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Flat head</name>
                  <ref target="n22092115" n="15"/>&amp; is 160 yards wide and Sholey    This
          river is the one we killed the first Coalt on near a fishing 
          <hi rend="italic">were</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I am verry Sick to day and puke which relive me.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-09-21.04" ref="">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>Saturday 21st Sept. 1805.    a clear pleasant morning.    we
          could not find all our horses untill about 10 oClock at which time we Set out, and
          proceed. on    Soon crossed a creek
          <ref target="n22092116" n="16"/>and proceed. on nearly a west course, over a rough
          trail. Some of the ridges the timber has been killed Some time past by fires, and is
          fell across the trail So that we have Some difficulty to pass.    towards
          evening we descended down a Mount. and came on a large creek running S. W.   
          we came down it a Short distance and Camped    had come 11 miles this day. 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name>killed a wolf   
          Some of the party killed three pheasants and a duck.    we eat them and caught
          a fiw craw fish in the creek and eat them.—</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-09-21.05" ref="">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Saturday 21st.</hi>   The morning was pleasant; but it was
          late before we got our horses collected. About 10 o'clock we were ready to start; and
          passed along the ridge with a great deal of difficulty and fatigue, our march being much
          impeded by the fallen timber. A great portion of the timber through which we passed
          along this ridge is dead, and a considerable part fallen; and our horses are weak and
          much jaded. One of them got into a small swamp, and wet a bale of merchandize. About 4
          o'clock in the afternoon we got down the mountain to a creek,
          <ref target="n22092117" n="17"/>which runs nearly southwest. This course we suppose is
          a very good one for us. We went down this creek about a mile, and encamped on it for the
          night in a small rich bottom. Here we killed a duck and two or three pheasants; and
          supped upon them and the last of our horse meat. We also killed a wolf and eat it. The
          hunters did not join us this evening, nor the two men who went to look for the
          horse.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-09-21.06" ref="">
            <sp who="jw">
               <speaker>Whitehouse</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Saturday 21st Sept. 1805</hi>.    a clear pleasant morning.
             we went out eairly to hunt up our horses, but they were much Scatered.
             we did not find them all untill about 10 oClock at which time we Set out
          and proceeded on    crossed a creek &amp; went on a west course over a hilley
          rough trail.    on Some of the ridges the timber has been killed by fire and
          fell across the trail So that we had Some difficulty to git a long the trail.
             in the after part of the day we descended down a hill &amp; came to the
          forks of a creek
          <ref target="n22092118" n="18"/>where it is large    we went down it a Short
          distance and Camped at a good place for feed near the creek.    had Come 11
          miles this day.    
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name>killed a wolf.
             Some of the men killed a duck and three Phesants.    we caught
          Some craw fish in the creek, and eat them.</p>
               <p>Saturday Septemr 21st    A Clear pleasant morning, some of our party were
          sent out to collect our horses.    they found them after much difficulty,
          which detained us 'till about 10 o'Clock A. M. at which time we set out, &amp; continued
          on our Journey.    We crossed a Creek, and went on a West course over a hilly
          rough trail, on a ridge of mountains    The timber on this trail, had been
          killed by fire, and fell across the path so that we had great difficulty to get along
          it.    In the afternoon we descended down a hill, &amp; came to the forks of a
          creek, where the Creek got to be large.—    We went down the Creek a short
          distance, &amp; encamped at a flatt piece of land which lay along the same Creek, where
          we found plenty of fine Grass for our horses.    
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Lewis</name>went out to hunt from
          this place, and took some of our party with him.    They killed a Wolf, a duck
          &amp; 3 Pheasants, &amp; some of the party catched some craw fish in the Creek.—
             We came about 11 Miles this day.—</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n22092101" n="1">The first is 
        <name type="place" key="Eldorado Creek">Eldorado Creek</name>, the second 
        <name type="place" key="Dollar Creek">Dollar Creek</name>, in 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho County, Idaho">Idaho County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>. Space, 18; Peebles (LT), 9; 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>map 71.</note>
            <note xml:id="n22092102" n="2">
               <name type="place" key="Cedar Creek (Idaho)">Cedar Creek</name>. Space, 18; Peebles (LT),
        9; 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>map 71.</note>
            <note xml:id="n22092103" n="3">Present 
        <name type="place" key="Lolo (Collins's) Creek (Idaho)">Lolo (Collins) Creek</name>.
        Space, 18; Peebles (LT), 9; 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>map 71.</note>
            <note xml:id="n22092104" n="4">On 
        <name type="place" key="Lolo (Collins's) Creek (Idaho)">Lolo Creek</name>, in 
        <name type="place" key="Clearwater County, Idaho">Clearwater County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>; the creek is at this point the boundary
        between 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>and 
        <name type="place" key="Clearwater County, Idaho">Clearwater</name>counties. Space 19; 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>map 71.</note>
            <note xml:id="n22092105" n="5">The coyote, 
        <hi rend="italic">Canis latrans.</hi>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="n22092106" n="6">Some variety of 
        <hi rend="italic">Astacus,</hi>crayfish. Pennack, 461.</note>
            <note xml:id="n22092107" n="7">It was apparently 
        <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>who drew a red vertical line
        through this material.</note>
            <note xml:id="n22092108" n="8">From this point the entries in the Elkskin-bound Journal
        become more like those of a regular daily journal. See the 
        <ref n="introduction.general" type="related">Introduction</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n22092109" n="9">The junction of the 
        <name type="place" key="North Fork Clearwater (Chopunnish) River">North Fork
        Clearwater</name>with the main stream, in 
        <name type="place" key="Clearwater County, Idaho">Clearwater County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>, west of present 
        <name type="place" key="Orofino, Idaho">Orofino</name>. 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>map 71.</note>
            <note xml:id="n22092110" n="10">The first is probably the 
        <name type="place"
                     key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Snake
        River</name>, the second the 
        <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n22092111" n="11">
               <name type="place" key="Celilo (Great) Falls">Celilo Falls</name>; see below, 
        <ref n="1805-10-22" type="related">October 22, 1805</ref>. The chief was probably
        misinformed about white men living there at the time. Ronda (LCAI), 159.</note>
            <note xml:id="n22092112" n="12">Apparently his name was 
        <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">Walamottinin</name>, meaning "hair of
        forelock bunched and tied." Josephy (NP), 5 and n. 3. In 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>it is 
        <hi rend="italic">wa
        <seg n="ulu787">l̓</seg>amo
        <hi rend="superscript">
                     <seg n="u8835">⊃</seg>
                  </hi>tktáyni
        <seg n="unu787">n̓</seg>,</hi>"with hair carelessly tied."</note>
            <note xml:id="n22092113" n="13">This camp was on the 
        <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Clearwater
        River</name>on the "
        <name type="place" key="Fish Island">Fishing Island</name>" on fig. 9 and 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>map 71, about a mile above present 
        <name type="place" key="Orofino, Idaho">Orofino</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Clearwater County, Idaho">Clearwater County</name>. Space, 17.
        While there is no archaeological information on this specific locality of 
        <name type="place" key="Fish Island">Fish Island</name>, a major concentration of 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perces</name>lived at the
        confluence of the 
        <name type="place" key="North Fork Clearwater (Chopunnish) River">North Fork</name>and the
        
        <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Clearwater</name>because
        of the salmon fishing. The area has been extensively modified by construction of 
        <name type="place" key="Dworshak Dam">Dworshak Dam</name>on the 
        <name type="place" key="North Fork Clearwater (Chopunnish) River">North Fork</name>just
        above the confluence, and an associated fish hatchery at the confluence itself. However,
        limited archaeological research in the area has exposed archaeological remains extending
        back several thousand years. Ames; Mattson.</note>
            <note xml:id="n22092114" n="14">
               <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>is describing parkland vegetation of
        the ponderosa pine where widely scattered trees appear as in an open park, with drought
        tolerant grasses covering the spaces between the trees. The dominant grasses of the area
        are Idaho fescue, 
        <hi rend="italic">Festuca idahoensis</hi>Elmer, and bluebunch wheatgrass, 
        <hi rend="italic">Agropyron spicatum</hi>(Pursh) Scribn. &amp; Smith, the latter plant
        being new to science. Küchler, map; Daubenmire, 307; Cutright (LCPN), 306, 408.</note>
            <note xml:id="n22092115" n="15">Their first name for the combination of 
        <name type="place" key="Killed Colt Creek">Whitesand (Killed colt) Creek</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Lochsa (Upper Kooskooske) River">Lochsa River</name>, and the 
        <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Clearwater River</name>;
        they changed the name later to 
        <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Kooskooskee
        River</name>, as on 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>map 71. The word appears to have been added to a blank
        space.</note>
            <note xml:id="n22092116" n="16">Either 
        <name type="place" key="Eldorado Creek">Eldorado Creek</name>or 
        <name type="place" key="Dollar Creek">Dollar Creek</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho County, Idaho">Idaho County</name>, Idaho.</note>
            <note xml:id="n22092117" n="17">
               <name type="place" key="Lolo (Collins's) Creek (Idaho)">Lolo Creek</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho County, Idaho">Idaho County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>, which the captains called 
        <name type="place" key="Lolo (Collins's) Creek (Idaho)">Collins Creek</name>after 
        <name type="person" key="Collins, John">John Collins</name>of the party.</note>
            <note xml:id="n22092118" n="18">
               <name type="place" key="Lolo (Collins's) Creek (Idaho)">Lolo Creek</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho County, Idaho">Idaho County</name>, which the captains
        called 
        <name type="place" key="Lolo (Collins's) Creek (Idaho)">Collins Creek</name>after 
        <name type="person" key="Collins, John">John Collins</name>of the party.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-09-20" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-09-22" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
