<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-06-25">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">June 25, 1805</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic
        Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            4</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">April7–July 27, 1805</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1987</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">331-333</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">174</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">106</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jw">Joseph Whitehouse</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            11</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of Joseph Whitehouse, May 14, 1804–April 2,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1997</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">211-212</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journal Entries</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-02-05</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-04-12</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1805-06-25">June 25, 1805</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-06-25.01" ref="">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>Tuesday June 25th 1805.</date>
               </ab>
               <p>This morning early I sent the party back to 
          <name type="place" key="Lower portage camp">the lower camp</name>; dispatched 
          <name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">Frazier</name>down with the canoe for 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name>and the meat he had
          collected, and 
          <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Joseph Fields</name>up the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>to hunt Elk.    at
          eight OClk. sent 
          <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Shields, John">Sheilds</name>over to the large Island for bark
          and timber.    about noon 
          <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Fields</name>returned and informed me that he
          had seen two white bear near the river a few miles above and in attempting to get a
          shoot them had stumbled uppon a third which immediately made at him being only a few
          steps distant; that in runing in order to escape from the bear he had leaped down a
          steep bank of the river on a stony bar where he fell cut his hand bruised his knees and
          bent his gun.    that fortunately for him the bank hid him from the bear when
          he fell and that by that means he had escaped.    this man has been truly
          unfortunate with these bear, this is the second time that he has narrowly escaped from
          them.    about 2 P. M 
          <name type="person" key="Shields, John">Shields</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name>returned with but a small quantity of
          both bark and timber and informed me that it was all they could find on the Island; they
          had killed two Elk the skins of which and a part of the flesh they brought with them.
             in the evening 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">Frazier</name>arrivd with about 800 Ibs. of
          excellent dryed meat and about 100 Ibs of tallow. The river is about 800 yds. wide
          opposite to us above these islands, and has a very gentle current    the
          bottoms are hadsome [
          <hi rend="italic">NB: Qu</hi>] level and extensive on both sides; the bank on this side
          is not more than 2 feet above the level of the water; it is a pretty little grove in
          which our camp is situated.    there is a 
          <ref target="n16062501" n="1">species of wild rye</ref>which is now heading it rises to
          the hight of 18 or 20 inches, the beard is remarkably fine and soft    it is a
          very handsome grass    the culm is jointed and is in every rispect the wild
          rye in minuture.    
          <ref target="n16062502" n="2">great quantities of mint also are here</ref>  
          it resemble the pepper mint very much in taste and appearance.    the young
          blackbirds which are almost innumerable in these islands just begin to fly.   
          see a number of 
          <ref target="n16062503" n="3">water tarripens.</ref>I have made an unsuccessfull attempt
          to catch fish, and do not think there are any in this part of the river. The party that
          returned this evening to 
          <name type="place" key="Lower portage camp">the lower camp</name>reached it in time to
          take one canoe on the plain and prepare their baggage for an early start in the morning
          after which such as were able to shake a foot amused themselves in dancing on the green
          to the music of the violin which 
          <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Cruzatte</name>plays extreemly well.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. C.</name>somewhat unwell today.
             he made 
          <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbono</name>kook for the party
          against their return.    it is worthy of remark that the winds are sometimes
          so strong in these plains that the men informed me that they hoisted a sail in the canoe
          and it had driven her along on the truck wheels.    this is really sailing on
          dry land.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-06-25.02" ref="">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">June 25th Tuesday 1805</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>a fair worm morning, Clouded &amp; a few drops of rain at 5 oClock A. M. fair
             I feel my Self a little unwell with a looseness &amp;c. &amp;c.
             put out the Stores to dry &amp; Set 
          <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Chabonah</name>&amp;c to Cook for the
          party against their return—he being the only man left on this Side with me   
          I had a little Coffee for brackfast which was to me a riarity as I had not tasted any
          Since last winter. The wind from the N. W. &amp; worm. This Countrey has a romantick
          appearance river inclosed between high and Steep hills Cut to pieces by revines but
          little timber and that Confined to the Rivers &amp; Creek, the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missourie</name>has but a fiew Scattering trees
          on its borders, and only one Solitary Cotton tree in sight of my Camp    the
          wood which we burn is drift wood which is broken to pieces in passing the falls, not one
          large tree longer than about 8 or 10 feet to be found drifted below 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">the falls</name>  
          the plains are inferior in point of Soil to those below, more Stone on the sides of the
          hill, grass but a few inches high and but few flowers in the Plains, great quantites of
          Choke Cheries, Goose burres, red &amp; yellow berries, &amp; red &amp; Purple Currents
          on the edges of water Courses in bottoms &amp; damp places, about my Camp the 
          <ref target="n16062504" n="4">Cliffs or bluffs are a hard red or redish brown earth
          Containing Iron.</ref>   we Catch great quantities of Trout, and a 
          <ref target="n16062505" n="5">kind of mustel, flat backs</ref>&amp; a Soft fish
          resembling a Shad and a few Cat.    at 5 oClock the party returned, fatigued
          as usial, and proceeded to mend their mockersons &amp;c. and 
          <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">G Shannon</name>&amp; 
          <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">R, Fds.</name>to of the men who ware Sent up the
          
          <name type="place" key="Sun (Mah-pah-pah,-ah-zhah, Medicine) River">medison
          river</name>to hunt Elk, they killed no Elk, Several Buffalow &amp; Deer, and reports
          that the river is 120 yds wide and about 8 feet deep Some timber on its borders—
             a powerfull rain fell on the party on their rout yesterday Wet Some fiew
          articles, and Caused the rout to be So bad wet &amp; Deep thay Could with dificuelty
          proceed, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name>&amp; the men with him
          much employd with the Iron Boat in fitting it for the water, dispatched one man to 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">George Drewyers</name>Camp below medison
          river for meat &amp;c.    a fair after noon—    great numbers of
          buffalow water opposit to my Camp everry day—    it may be here worthy of
          remark that the Sales were hoised in the Canoes as the men were drawing them and the
          wind was great relief to them being Sufficently Strong to move the Canoes on the Trucks,
          this is Saleing on Dry land in every Sence of the word, 
          <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Serjeant N Pryor</name>Sick, the party
          amused themselves with danceing untill 10 oClock all Chearfullness and good humer, they
          all tied up their loads to make an early Start in the morning.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-06-25.03" ref="">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Tuesday 25th June 1805</hi>.    a cloudy morning.
             we Set out with the 2 truck waggons and returned back to the lower Camp for
          another load.    took 2 canoes up the hill on the high plains    the
          day proved pleasant and warm the men much fatigued.    we Saw large gangs of
          buffalow and antelopes to day.    we got our loads ready for a Start in the
          morning.    below the falls the plains are inferior in point of Soil to those
          below, more Stones on the Sides of the hills, grass but a fiew Inches long or high and
          but a fiew flowers in the plains. Great quanties of choke cherryes Goose berrys red
          &amp; yallow berrys &amp; red purple currents on the Edges of the water. we catch great
          quantitites of Trout and a kind of muttel [mussel] flat backs and a Soft fish resembling
          Shad.
          <ref target="n16062506" n="6"/>   caught but fiew cat fish this Season. 
          <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Sergt. Pryor</name>Sick    the
          party amused themselves dancing untill 10 oClock    all in cheerfulness and
          good humour.    we tied up all the baggage ready for an eairly Steart in the
          morning—</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-06-25.04" ref="">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Tuesday 25th.</hi>   A cloudy morning. The men went back for
          more canoes and baggage; and one
          <ref target="n16062507" n="7"/>went down to the hunter's camp below 
          <name type="place" key="Sun (Mah-pah-pah,-ah-zhah, Medicine) River">Medicine
          river</name>to bring him up in a canoe. Another
          <ref target="n16062508" n="8"/>went up the river to look for elk. When he had gone
          about three miles, he was attacked by 3 brown bears, that were near devouring him; but
          he made his escape by running down a steep bank into the water. In this adventure he
          fell, injured his gun, and hurt one of his hands; therefore returned to camp. One of the
          men
          <ref target="n16062509" n="9"/>and myself went over to an island to look for stuff for
          the canoe, but could find nothing but bark, which perhaps will answer. We killed two elk
          on the island. There is in the bottoms a great quantity of spear-mint and currant
          bushes.
          <ref target="n16062510" n="10"/>Also multitudes of blackbirds.
          <ref target="n16062511" n="11"/>The musquitoes
          <ref target="n16062512" n="12"/>are very troublesome, though the snow is on the
          mountains so near. In the evening the two men
          <ref target="n16062513" n="13"/>came up the river with a quantity of good meat and 100
          pounds of tallow.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-06-25.05" ref="">
            <sp who="jw">
               <speaker>Whitehouse</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Tuesday 25th June 1805</hi>.    a cloudy morning.
             we Set out with the 2 truck waggons, and returned back to 
          <name type="place" key="Lower portage camp">the lower camp</name>for another load.
             took up 2 canoes on the high plains.    the day proved pleasant
          and warm    the party much fatigued halling the truck waggons &amp; the
          baggage.    Saw large gangs of buffalow and antelopes to day.    the
          evening clear and pleasant    we got our loads ready to Start from this for
          the 
          <name type="place" key="Upper portage camp (Mont.)">upper Camp</name>.   
          mended our mockasons &amp;c.    below 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">the falls</name>the plains
          are inferior in point of Soil to those below, more Stones on the Sides of the hills,
          Grass but a fiew inches high and but a fiew flowers in the plains.    Great
          quantities of choke cherries, goose berrys, red &amp; yallow berrys &amp; red and purple
          currents on the Edges of the water.    we catch great quantities of Trout, and
          a kind of mullet flat backs, &amp; a Soft fish resembling a Shad, and fiew cat fish
          &amp;c.    
          <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Sergt. pryor</name>Sick.   
          the party all of us amused ourselves with dancing untill 10 oC.    all in
          cheerfulness and good humor.    we all harnised up our back loads of the
          baggage to make an eairly Steart in the morning.</p>
               <p>Tuesday June 25th    We had a cloudy morning; we set out with the two truck
          waggons, and returned back to 
          <name type="place" key="Lower portage camp">the lower camp</name>, in order to bring on
          another load, the party hawled up two of our Crafts, to the high plains in our absence,
          the weather cleared up at about 10 o'Clock A. M; and the day proved warm, and pleasant,
          the party that had hawl'd the trucks Yesterday, were all very much fataigued yet, We saw
          large Gangs of Buffalo &amp; Antelopes this day, This evening was pleasant, and we
          prepared our loading, ready to start for the 
          <name type="place" key="Upper portage camp (Mont.)">upper Camp</name>&amp;ca.—
             below the falls, the soil on the plains, are inferior to the plains below;
          and more stoney on the sides of the hills, the Grass on them but a few Inches high, and
          but few flowers.—    We found in those plains growing Choke cherries, Goose
          berries, red &amp; Yellow berries, and red &amp; purple Currants growing on the edges of
          the water, in great quantities, and we Catched in the River near 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">the falls</name>a great
          Quantity of Salmon trout, [
          <hi rend="italic">blank</hi>] and a kind of fish which were soft, and resembling a Shad
          &amp; a few Cat fish &amp;ca.—    The party all amused themselves, &amp; was
          very chearfull waiting till the morning, in Order to start off for the loads of baggage
          &amp;ca.—</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n16062501" n="1">
               <hi rend="italic">Hordeum jubatum</hi>L., foxtail barley, or possibly 
        <hi rend="italic">Sitanion hystrix</hi>(Nutt.) J. G. Smith, squirrel tail. Hahn, 
        <hi rend="italic">Hordeum</hi>and 
        <hi rend="italic">Sitanion</hi>maps. It was probably 
        <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>who drew a red vertical line
        through this passage and those about the mint and turtle.</note>
            <note xml:id="n16062502" n="2">
               <hi rend="italic">Mentha arvensis</hi>L., field mint. Booth &amp; Wright, 211.</note>
            <note xml:id="n16062503" n="3">Probably 
        <hi rend="italic">Chrysemys picta</hi>, painted turtle. Benson (HLCE), 88.</note>
            <note xml:id="n16062504" n="4">This is the lower Cretaceous 
        <name type="place" key="Kootenai Formation">Kootenai Formation</name>. The reddish color
        comes from oxidized iron compounds.</note>
            <note xml:id="n16062505" n="5">The mussels could be either 
        <hi rend="italic">Margaritanidae</hi>or 
        <hi rend="italic">Unionidae</hi>. Pennak, 704–10. 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>mention of "flat backs" is unclear.
        Perhaps it is a regionalism for suckers (family 
        <hi rend="italic">Catostomidae</hi>). See 
        <ref n="1804-08-16" type="related">August 16, 1804</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n16062506" n="6">The mussels could be from either the family Margaritanidae
        or Unionidae. "Flat backs" are unknown, but perhaps suckers, of the family Catostomidae.
        Much of this entry is from 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>and many of the sergeant's entries
        during the portage period are taken from the captains' journals.</note>
            <note xml:id="n16062507" n="7">
               <name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">Frazer</name>, to pick up 
        <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n16062508" n="8">
               <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Joseph Field</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n16062509" n="9">
               <name type="person" key="Shields, John">Shields</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n16062510" n="10">
               <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass's</name>spearmint is probably field mint, 
        <hi rend="italic">Mentha arvensis</hi>L., while the currants could be any of a number of
        species.</note>
            <note xml:id="n16062511" n="11">Perhaps rusty blackbird, 
        <hi rend="italic">Euphagus carolinus,</hi>or Brewer's blackbird, 
        <hi rend="italic">E. cyanocephalus</hi>. The party also apparently called the common
        grackle, 
        <hi rend="italic">Quisculus quiscula,</hi>a blackbird.</note>
            <note xml:id="n16062512" n="12">Probably 
        <hi rend="italic">Aedes vexans</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n16062513" n="13">
               <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">Frazer</name>.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-06-24" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-06-26" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
