<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.1805-08-16">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">August 16, 1805</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic
        Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            5</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">July 28–November 1, 1805</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1989</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">102-108</biblScope>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">203-204</biblScope>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">126</biblScope>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            11</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of Joseph Whitehouse, May 14, 1804–April 2,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1997</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">270-272</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
         <geoDecl datum="WGS">
            <placeName>Present-Day Clark Canyon Dam</placeName>
            <geo>44.9833 -112.85</geo>
            <note>Camped four miles below the forks of the Beaverhead River, Beaverhead County, MT.</note>
         </geoDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc/>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-06-07</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-04-12</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date>August 16, 1805</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.1805-08-16.01">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Friday August 16th 1805.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>I sent 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Shields, John">Shields</name>before this morning in order to
          kill some meat as neither the Indians nor ourselves had any thing to eat. I informed the
          Ceif of my view in this measure, and requested that he would keep his young men wih us
          lest by their hooping and noise they should allarm the game and we should get nothing to
          eat, but so strongly were there suspicions exited by this measure that two parties of
          discovery immediately set out one on ech side of the valley to watch the hunters as I
          beleive to see whether they had not been sent to give information of their approach to
          an enemy that they still preswaided themselves were lying in wait for them. I saw that
          any further effort to prevent their going would only add strength to their suspicions
          and therefore said no more.    after the hunters had been gone about an hour
          we set out.    we had just passed through the narrows when we saw one of the
          spies comeing up the level plain under whip, the chief pawsed a little and seemed
          somewhat concerned. I felt a good deel so myself and began to suspect that by some
          unfortunate accedent that perhaps some of there enimies had straggled hither at this
          unlucky moment; but we were all agreeably disappointed on the arrival of the young man
          to learn that he had come to inform us that one of the whitemen had killed a deer.
             in an instant they all gave their horses the whip and I was taken nearly a
          mile before I could learn what were the tidings; as I was without tirrups and an Indian
          behind me the jostling was disagreeable    I therefore reigned up my horse and
          forbid the indian to whip him who had given him the lash at every jum for a mile fearing
          he should loose a part of the feast.    the fellow was so uneasy that he left
          me the horse dismounted and ran on foot at full speed, I am confident a mile.
             when they arrived where the deer was which was in view of me they
          dismounted and ran in tumbling over each other like a parcel of famished dogs each
          seizing and tearing away a part of the intestens which had been previously thrown out by
          
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name>who killed it; the seen was
          such when I arrived that had I not have had a pretty keen appetite myself I am confident
          I should not have taisted any part of the venison shortly.    each one had a
          peice of some discription and all eating most ravenously.    some were eating
          the kidnies the melt
          <ref target="n19081601" n="1"/>and liver and the blood runing from the corners of their
          mouths, others were in a similar situation with the paunch and guts but the exuding
          substance in this case from their lips was of a different discription.    one
          of the last who attacted my attention particularly had been fortunate in his allotment
          or reather active in the division, he had provided himself with about nine feet of the
          small guts one end of which he was chewing on while with his hands he was squezzing the
          contents out at the other. I really did not untill now think that human nature ever
          presented itself in a shape so nearly allyed to the brute creation. I viewed these poor
          starved divils with pity and compassion    I directed 
          <name type="person" key="McNeal, Hugh">McNeal</name>to skin the deer and reserved a
          quarter, the ballance I gave the Chief to be divided among his people; they devoured the
          whole of it nearly without cooking. I now boar obliquely to the left in order to
          interscept the creek where there was some brush to make a fire, and arrived at this
          stream where 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name>had killed a second deer;
          here nearly the same seene was encored.    a fire being kindled we cooked and
          eat and gave the ballance of the two deer to the Indians who eat the whole of them even
          to the soft parts of the hoofs. 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name>joined us at breakfast with a
          third deer.    of this I reserved a quarter and gave the ballance to the
          Indians.    they all appeared now to have filled themselves and were in a good
          humour.    this morning early soon after the hunters set out a considerable
          part of our escort became allarmed and returned    28 men and three women only
          continued with us.    after eating and suffering the horses to graize about 2
          hours we renued our march and towads evening arrived at the lower part of the cove
             
          <name type="person" key="Shields, John">Shields</name>killed an Antelope on the way a
          part of which we took and gave the remainder to the Indians.    being now
          informed of the place at which I expected to meat 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt C.</name>and the party they insisted on
          making a halt, which was complyed with.    we now dismounted and the Chief
          with much cerimony put tippets about our necks such as they temselves woar I redily
          perceived that this was to disguise us and owed it's origine to the same cause already
          mentioned.    to give them further confidence I put my cocked hat with feather
          on the chief and my over shirt being of the Indian form my hair deshivled and skin well
          browned with the sun I wanted no further addition to make me a complete Indian in
          appearance    the men followed my example and we were son completely
          metamorphosed. I again repeated to them the possibility of the party not having arrived
          at the place which I expected they were, but assured them they could not be far below,
          lest by not finding them at the forks their suspicions might arrise to such hight as to
          induce them to return precipitately.    we now set out and rode briskly within
          sight of the forks making one of the Indians carry the flag that our own party should
          know who we were.    when we arrived in sight at the distance of about 2 miles
          I discovered to my mortification that the party had not arrived, and the Indians
          slackened their pace. I now scarcely new what to do and feared every moment when they
          would halt altogether, I now determined to restore their confidence cost what it might
          and therefore gave the Chief my gun and told him that if his enimies were in those
          bushes before him that he could defend himself with that gun, that for my own part I was
          not affraid to die and if I deceived him he might make what uce of the gun he thought
          proper or in other words that he might shoot me.    the men also gave their
          guns to other indians which seemed to inspire them with more confidence; they sent their
          spies before them at some distance and when I drew near the place
          <ref target="n19081602" n="2"/>I thought of the notes which I had left and directed 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name>to go with an Indian man and
          bring them to me which he did.    the indian seeing him take the notes from
          the stake on which they had been plased I now had recource to a stratagem in which I
          thought myself justifyed by the occasion, but which I must confess set a little awkward.
             it had it's desired effect.   after reading the notes which were
          the same I had left I told the Chief that when I had left my brother Chief with the
          party below where the river entered the mountain that we both agreed not to bring the
          canoes higher up than the next forks of the river above us wherever this might happen,
          that there he was to wait my return, should he arrive first, and that in the event of
          his not being able to travel as fast as usual from the difficulty of the water, that he
          was to send up to the first forks above him and leave a note informing me where he was,
          that this note was left here today and that he informed me where he was, that this note
          was left here today and that he informed me that he was just below the mountains and was
          coming on slowly up, and added that I should wait here for him, but if they did not
          beleive me that I should send a man at any rate to the Chief and they might also send
          one of their young men with him, that myself and two others would remain with them at
          this place.    this plan was readily adopted and one of the young men offered
          his services; I promised him a knife and some beads as a reward for his confidence in
          us.    most of them seemed satisfyed but there were several that complained of
          the Chief's exposing them to danger unnecessarily and said that we told different
          stories, in short a few were much dissatisfyed. I wrote a note to 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name>by the light of some willow
          brush and directed 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name>to set out early being
          confident that there was not a moment to spare.    the chief and five or six
          others slept about my fire and the others hid themselves in various parts of the willow
          brush to avoid the enimy whom they were fearfull would attack them in the course of the
          night. I now entertained various conjectures myself with rispect to the cause of 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clarks</name>detention and was even
          fearfull that he had found the river so difficult that he had halted below the 
          <name type="place" key="Rattlesnake Cliffs">Rattlesnake bluffs</name>. I knew that if
          these people left me that they would immediately disperse and secrete themselves in the
          mountains where it would be impossible to find them or at least in vain to pursue them
          and that they would spread the allarm to all other bands within our reach &amp; of
          course we should be disappointed in obtaining horses, which would vastly retard and
          increase the labour of our voyage and I feared might so discourage the men as to defeat
          the expedition altogether.    my mind was in reallity quite as gloomy all this
          evening as the most affrighted indian but I affected cheerfullness to keep the Indians
          so who were about me.    we finally laid down and the Chief placed himself by
          the side of my musquetoe bier. I slept but little as might be well expected, my mind
          dwelling on the state of the expedition which I have ever held in equal estimation with
          my own existence, and the fait of which appeared at this moment to depend in a great
          measure upon the caprice of a few savages who are ever as fickle as the wind. I had
          mentioned to the chief several times that we had with us a woman of his nation who had
          been taken prisoner by the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Minnetares</name>, and that by means of
          her I hoped to explain myself more fully than I could do by signs. some of the party had
          also told the Indians that we had a man with us who was black and had short curling
          hair, this had excited their curiossity very much.    and they seemed quite as
          anxious to see this monster as they wer the merchandize which we had to barter for their
          horses.</p>
               <p>at 7 A M. 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. C.</name>set out after breakfast.
             he changed the hands in some of the canoes; they proceeded with more ease
          than yesterday, yet they found the river still rapid and shallow insomuch that they were
          obliged to drag the large canoes the greater part of the day.    considerable
          quantities of the buffaloe clover grows along the narrow bottoms through which they
          passed.    there was no timber except a few scatiring small pine on the hills.
             willow service berry and currant bushes were the growth of the river
          bottoms.    they geathered considerable quantities of service berries, and
          caught some trout.    one deer was killed by the hunters who slept out last
          night.    and did not join the party until 10 A. M. 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name>sent the hunters this evening
          up to the forks of the river which he discovered from an eminence; they mus have left
          this place but a little time before we arrived.    this evening they encamped
          on the Lard. side only a few miles below us.
          <ref target="n19081603" n="3"/>   and were obliged like ourselves to make use
          of small willow brush for fuel.    the men were much fatigued and exhausted
          this evening.</p>
               <p>
                  <table rows="5" cols="3">
                     <head>Courses and distances traveled by 
              <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="italic">August 16th 1805.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 18° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">3</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">to a Lard. bend under a low bluff, distance by
                water 7 M.
                <lb/>the river bending to the Stard. under some high land, very
                <lb/>crooked narrow shallow and small.    passed several Islands
                <lb/>4 of which were opposite to each other.    called this 
                <name type="place" key="Serviceberry Valley">service
                <lb/>berry Valley</name>, from the great abundance of that fruit found
                <lb/>here.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 12° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">2</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">to a high Clift on the Stard. side, distance
                by water 4 M.
                <lb/>passed several Islds. and bayous on either Side.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 50° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">1</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">to the entrance of a bold running stream on
                Lard. side, dis-
                <lb/>tance by water 2½ M.    at this place there is a very consider-
                <lb/>able rapid and clifts near on both sides</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 45° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                           <hi rend="underline">   ½</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">mile to the lower point of an Island near the
                center of the
                <lb/>Valley and river.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                           <hi rend="right">Miles</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                           <hi rend="double underline">6 ½</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.1805-08-16.02">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">August 16th Friday 1805</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>as this morning was cold and the men fatigued Stiff and Chilled deturmined me to
          detain &amp; take brackfast before I Set out. I changed the hands and Set out at 7
          oClock    proceeded on Something better than yesterday for the fore part of
          the Day    passed Several rapids in the latter part of the day near the hills
          river    passed between 2 hills    I saw a great number 
          <hi rend="italic">of Service berries</hi>now ripe.    the Yellow Current are
          also Common    I observe the long leaf Clover
          <ref target="n19081604" n="4"/>in great plenty in the vallie below this vallie—
             Some fiew tres on the river    no timber on the hills or mountn.
          except a fiew Small Pine &amp; Cedar.
          <ref target="n19081605" n="5"/>The Thmtr. Stood at 48° a. 0 at Sunrise wind S W. The
          hunters joined me at 1 oClock, I dispatched 2 men to prosue an Indian roade over the
          hills for a fiew miles, at the narrows I assended a mountain from the top of which I
          could See that the river forked near me    the left hand appeared the largest
          &amp; bore S. E.    the right passed from the West thro' an extensive Vallie,
          I could See but three Small trees in any Direction from the top of this mountain.
             passed an Isld. and Encamped ion the Lard. Side the only wood was Small
          willows</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.1805-08-16.03">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Friday 16th August 1805</hi>.    a clear morning but verry
          cold.    the Thurmometer Stood at 47°.    the water So cold that we
          delayed until after we took breakfast.    one hunter out this morning.
             2 hunters Stayed out last night.    we proceeded on as usal.
             passed a 
          <name type="place" key="Gallagher Creek">handsom Spring run</name>
                  <ref target="n19081606" n="6"/>on L. Side. Some timber on it.    we find the
          current Swift the river Shallow    we are oblidged to hall the large canoes
          the most of the time. 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name>
                  <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">our Intrepter</name>&amp; 
          <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">wife</name>walked on Shore and found a great
          quantity of Servis berrys the largest &amp; best I ever Saw.    they gethered
          a pale full &amp;C. Gave them out to the party at noon where we halted to dine at a
          grove of cotton trees on L. Side. Saw a nomber of bald &amp; grey Eagles &amp;C.
             our hunter who went out this morning killed a verry large buck.
             the bottoms on the River narrow    we name this place 
          <name type="place" key="Serviceberry Valley">Servis berry valley</name>.   
          the 2 hunters who Stayed out last night joined us here and informed us that the River
          forks
          <ref target="n19081607" n="7"/>again only about 6 miles by land from this &amp; that
          each fork was Shallow.    2 hunters sent on to the forks to hunt   
          we proceeded on    passed up Sholes &amp; rapids    towards evening
          we passed up a verry bad rockey rapid which was difficult to pass over.    we
          were oblidged to waid and hale the canoes over the large rocks &amp;C.    we
          passed a fine Spring on S. Side and a run
          <ref target="n19081608" n="8"/>on L. Side    high clifts of rocks &amp; hills
          on each Side    found pleanty of currents on the banks.    the water
          not So Swift above the bad rapid.    we Came [
          <hi rend="italic">blank</hi>] miles and Camped on a narrow bottom on L. Side
             no timber.    we gethered Small willow Sticks only to boil our
          vension.    the beaver very pleanty &amp;C—</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.1805-08-16.04">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Friday 16th.</hi>   We did not set out till after breakfast,
          and while here one of the men went out and killed a fine buck. We proceeded through
          rapid water; the river is very narrow, crooked and shallow. This morning we passed a
          place where the hills come close to the river for a short distance, and then open on
          each side of a small valley, which, on account of the great quantity of service berries
          in it, we called 
          <name type="place" key="Serviceberry Valley">Service-berry valley</name>. We passed over
          a rapid of about a quarter of a mile, and encamped
          <ref target="n19081609" n="9"/>on the South side, having come 15 miles.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.1805-08-16.05">
            <sp who="jw">
               <speaker>Whitehouse</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Friday 16th August 1805</hi>.    a clear but verry cold
          morning.    the Thurmometer Stood at 47°.    the water So cold that
          we delayed untill after breakfast.    one hunter out on a head.   
          we proceeded on as usal    the current Swift    passed a 
          <name type="place" key="Gallagher Creek">handsom Spring run</name>
                  <ref target="n19081610" n="10"/>on L. Side on which is a fiew cotton trees.
             
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name>
                  <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">our Intrepter</name>&amp; 
          <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">wife</name>walked on Shore and found a great nomber
          of fine berrys which is called Servis berrys.    our Ints. wife gethered a
          pale full &amp; gave them to the party at noon where we halted at a grove of cotton
          trees on L. S.    our hunter who went out this morning killed a verry large
          buck.    two of our hunters Stayed out last night, &amp; have not returned yet
             we name this place 
          <name type="place" key="Serviceberry Valley">Servis valley</name>, from the abundance of
          these berrys along under the hills &amp;c.    the 2 hunters joined us here
          &amp; Informed us that the River forks
          <ref target="n19081611" n="11"/>in about 5 miles a Strait course by land &amp; they
          think we can go no further than the forks with the crafts.    2 hunters Sent
          on to the forks to kill meat.    we proceeded on over verry Shallow &amp;
          Swift water    passed up a verry bad rockey rapid where we had to waid up to
          our middle &amp; hale the canoes over the rapid.    Saw Several fine Springs
          &amp; a run above the bad rapid    passed high clifts of rocks and high hills
          on each Side.    found pleanty of currents    the water not So bad
          above the rapid.    Came [
          <hi rend="italic">blank</hi>] miles this day and Camped on a narrow bottom on L. Side.
             no timber    we could Scarsely find any but Small willow to boil
          our venison</p>
               <p>Friday August 16th    We had a Clear, but very cold morning, the
          Thermometer stood at 47°—    from 0, and the water in the River so cold, that
          we delayed starting 'till after breakfast; One of our hunters was sent on a head, We
          proceeded on our Voyage at 8 o'Clock A. M. the Current of the River running very
          strong,—    We passed a handsome spring run, lying on the South side of the
          River, near to which was a few Cotton wood trees.    Our 
          <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">interpreters Wife (the Indian Woman)</name>went on
          Shore &amp; found a great number of fine berries, which is call'd service berries.
             the 
          <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Indian Woman</name>gathered a pailfull of those
          berries, which she brought to our party at noon, where we had halted which was at a
          Grove of Cotton trees lying on the South side of the River.    Our hunter that
          went out this morning, killed a very fine buck Deer, which he brought to us.
             Two of our Hunters that went out Yesterday had not yet returned.
             This place being a Valley, 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain Clark</name>named 〈this place〉 it 
          <name type="place" key="Serviceberry Valley">Service Valley</name>, on account of the
          number of berries, that grew in it called Service berries, Our two hunters that were out
          came to us, just as we were starting; and informed us that the River forked about 5
          Miles ahead, on a strait Course by land, and that it is their opinion, that we can go no
          further than those forks with our crafts, 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain Clark</name>dispatch'd two of our
          hunters off, to those forks, to provide some Meat for us, against we arrived there.
             We proceeded on at 2 oClock P. M. &amp; found the River running very Rapid
          &amp; shallow.    We passed up a bad Rapid which was very Rockey; the party
          had to wade up to their middles in Order to hall the Canoes over it.—</p>
               <p>We saw several fine springs, &amp; a run which lay above this bad rapid, and high
          Clifts of rocks &amp; high hills lying on both sides of the River; We found a great
          plenty of currants, growing along the Shore, The current of the River did not run so
          strong, nor the River is not so shallow above the rapids, as it was for some distance
          below.—    We came 13 Miles this day, and encamped in a narrow bottom, lying
          on the South side of the River.    We found no timber here, and was obiged to
          use small dry Willow bushes, for fuel to boil our meat</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n19081601" n="1">The spleen.</note>
            <note xml:id="n19081602" n="2">The junction of 
        <name type="place" key="Horse Prairie Creek (West Fork Jefferson River)">Horse Prairie
        Creek</name>and 
        <name type="place" key="Red Rock (East Fork Jefferson) River">Red Rock River</name>to form
        
        <name type="place" key="Beaverhead (Jefferson) River">Beaverhead River</name>. 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>map 66.</note>
            <note xml:id="n19081603" n="3">This camp does not appear on 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>map 66. It was in 
        <name type="place" key="Beaverhead County, Mont.">Beaverhead County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>, four miles by 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>estimate below the forks of 
        <name type="place" key="Beaverhead (Jefferson) River">the Beaverhead</name>and the present
        
        <name type="place" key="Clark Canyon Dam and Reservoir">Clark Canyon Dam</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n19081604" n="4">
               <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>"long leaf Clover" is the same as 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>"buffaloe clover" of this day
        and of August 8. The term long leaf describes the elongate, trifoliate leaflets of the
        mountain thermopsis. The species is common in this area growing in wet meadows as
        described. Since the plant was in fruit at this time of the year and lacked the typical
        flower head of a clover, 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>apparently chose the term
        "buffalo" to distinguish either its tall stature or grazing preference by bison, and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>chose the descriptive "long leaf" to
        note the long leaflets, atypical of other clover or 
        <hi rend="italic">Trifolium</hi>species. Booth &amp; Wright, 138.</note>
            <note xml:id="n19081605" n="5">The small pine is the limber pine and the cedar is Rocky
        Mountain juniper. Both species grow together on the rocky slopes above the 
        <name type="place" key="Beaverhead (Jefferson) River">Beaverhead River</name>in this area
        and in similar habitats in the region. Pfister et al., 17.</note>
            <note xml:id="n19081606" n="6">Perhaps the "bold run" on 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>map 66, which may be 
        <name type="place" key="Gallagher Creek">Gallagher Creek</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Beaverhead County, Mont.">Beaverhead County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n19081607" n="7">
               <name type="place" key="Red Rock (East Fork Jefferson) River">Red Rock River</name>, the
        party's 
        <name type="place" key="Red Rock (East Fork Jefferson) River">East Fork Jefferson</name>,
        and 
        <name type="place" key="Horse Prairie Creek (West Fork Jefferson River)">Horse Prairie
        Creek</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Horse Prairie Creek (West Fork Jefferson River)">West Fork
        Jefferson</name>to the party, in 
        <name type="place" key="Beaverhead County, Mont.">Beaverhead County</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n19081608" n="8">Probably 
        <name type="place" key="Clark Canyon Creek">Clark Canyon Creek</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Beaverhead County, Mont.">Beaverhead County</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n19081609" n="9">In 
        <name type="place" key="Beaverhead County, Mont.">Beaverhead County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>, about four miles below the forks of 
        <name type="place" key="Beaverhead (Jefferson) River">the Beaverhead</name>and 
        <name type="place" key="Clark Canyon Dam and Reservoir">Clark Canyon Dam</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n19081610" n="10">Perhaps 
        <name type="place" key="Gallagher Creek">Gallagher Creek</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Beaverhead County, Mont.">Beaverhead County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n19081611" n="11">The forks of 
        <name type="place" key="Beaverhead (Jefferson) River">the Beaverhead</name>; see 
        <ref n="1805-08-17" type="related">the next day's</ref>entry.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-08-15" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-08-17" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
