<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-05-09">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">May 9, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic
        Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            7</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">March 23–June 9, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1991</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">233-237</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">307-308</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">224</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
         <geoDecl datum="WGS" xml:id="lc.geo.1806-05-09.01">
            <placeName/>
            <geo>46.5333 -116.4833</geo>
            <note>Camped in Clearwater County, ID, naming location at Wheeler Draw. Actual location is quite disputed.</note>
         </geoDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journal Entries</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-10-12</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-04-12</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1806-05-09">May 9, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-05-09.01"
              ref="lc.geo.1806-05-09.01">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Friday May 9th 1806.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>We sent out several hunters early this morning with instructions to meet us at the
          lodge of the 
          <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">Twisted hair</name>. Collecting our
          horses detained us untill 9 A. M. when we charged our packhorses and set out.
             our rout lay through a level rich country similar to that of yesterday;
          <ref target="n34050901" n="1"/>at the distance of 6 miles we arrived at the lodge of
          the 
          <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">twisted hair</name>; this
          habitation was built in the usual form with sticks mats and dryed hay, and contained 2
          firs and about 12 persons.    even at this small habitation there was an
          appendage of the soletary lodge, the retreat of the tawny damsels when nature causes
          them to be drive into coventry;
          <ref target="n34050902" n="2"/>here we halted as had been previously concerted, and one
          man with 2 horses accompayed the 
          <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">twisted hair</name>to the 
          <name type="place" key="Canoe Camp (Idaho)">canoe camp</name>,
          <ref target="n34050903" n="3"/>about 4 ms. in quest of the saddles.    the 
          <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">Twisted hair</name>sent two young
          men in surch of our horses agreeably to his promis. The country along the 
          <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">rocky mountains</name>for several hundred miles
          in length and about 50 in width is level extreemly fertile and in many parts covered
          with a tall and open growth of the longleafed pine.    near the watercouses
          the hills are steep and lofty tho' are covered with a good soil not remarkably stony
          <ref target="n34050904" n="4"/>and possess more timber than the level country.
             the bottom lands on the watercourses are reather narrow and confined tho'
          fertile &amp; seldom inundated.    this country would form an extensive
          settlement; the climate appears quite as mild as that of similar latitude on the 
          <name type="place" key="Atlantic Ocean">Atlantic</name>coast if not more so and it
          cannot be otherwise than healthy; it possesses a fine dry pure air.    the
          grass and many plants are now upwards of knee high. I have no doubt but this tract of
          country if cultivated would produce in great abundance every article essentially
          necessary to the comfort and subsistence of civillized man.    to it's present
          inhabitants nature seems to have dealt with a liberal hand, for she has distributed a
          great variety of esculent plants over the face of the country which furnish them a
          plentifull store of provision; these are acquired with but little toil, and when
          prepared after the method of the natives afford not only a nutricious but an agreeable
          food.    among other roots those called by them the Quawmash and Cows are
          esteemed the most agreeable and valuable as they are also the most abundant.
             the cows is a knobbed root of an irregularly rounded form not unlike the
          Gensang
          <ref target="n34050905" n="5"/>in form and consistence.    this root they
          collect, rub of a thin black rhind which covers it and pounding it expose it in cakes to
          the sun.    these cakes ate about an inch and ¼ thick and 6 by 18 in width,
          when dryed they either eat this bread alone without any further preperation, or boil it
          and make a thick muselage; the latter is most common and much the most agreeable.
             the flavor of this root is not very unlike the gensang.—    this
          root they collect as early as the snows disappear in the spring and continue to collect
          it untill the quawmash supplys it's place which happens about the latter end of June.
             the quawmash is also collected for a few weaks after it first makes it's
          appearance in the spring, but when the scape
          <ref target="n34050906" n="6"/>appears it is no longer fit for use untill the seed are
          ripe which happens about the time just mentioned, and then the cows declines.
             the latter is also frequently dryed in the sun and pounded afterwards and
          then used in making soope.—    I observed a few trees of the larch and a few
          small bushes of the balsam fir near the lodge of the 
          <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">Twisted hair</name>.   
          at 2 P. M. our hunters joined us 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name>killed a deer but lost it in
          the river.    a few pheasants was the produce of the hunt.    we
          procured a few roots of cows of which we made soope.    late in the evening
          The 
          <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">Twisted hair</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Willard, Alexander">Willard</name>returned; they brought about
          half of our saddles, and some powder and lead which had been buried at that place.
             my saddle was among the number of those which were lost.    about
          the same time the young men arrived with 21 of our horses.    the greater part
          of our horses were in fine order.    five of them appeared to have been so
          much injured by the indians riding them last fall that they had not yet recovered and
          were in low order.    three others had soar backs.    we had these
          horses caught and hubbled.    the situation of our camp was a disagreeable one
          in an open plain;
          <ref target="n34050907" n="7"/>the wind blew violently and was cold.    at
          seven P. M. it began to rain and hail, at 9 it was succeeded by a heavy shower of snow
          which continued untill the next morning.—    several indians joined us this
          evening from the village of the 
          <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="person" key="Broken Arm">broken arm</name>
                  </hi>or 
          <name type="person" key="Broken Arm">Tunnachemootoolt</name>and continued all night. The
          man who had imposed himself on us as a relation of the 
          <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">twisted hair</name>rejoined us this
          evening we found him an impertinent proud supercilious fellow and of no kind of
          rispectability in the nation, we therefore did not indulge his advances towards a very
          intimate connection. The 
          <name type="person" key="Cut Nose">Cutnose</name>lodged with the 
          <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">twisted hair</name>I beleive they
          have become good friends again.    several indians slept about us.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-05-09.02"
              ref="lc.geo.1806-05-09.01">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Friday 9th May 1806</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>The hunters Set out very early agreeable to their derections.    we were
          detained untill 9 A. M. for our horses which were much Scattered at which time we
          Collected our horses and Set out and proceeded on through a butifull open rich Country
          for 6 miles to the Camp of the 
          <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">twisted hair</name>.   
          this Campment is formed of two Lodges built in the usial form of mats and Straw.
             the largest and principal Lodge is Calculated for 2 fires only and Contains
          about [
          <hi rend="italic">blank</hi>] persons.    the Second lodge is Small &amp;
          appears to be intended for the Sick women who always retire to a Seperate lodge when
          they have the [
          <hi rend="italic">blank</hi>]    this Custom is Common to all the nations on
          this river as well as among all other Indian nations with whom I am acquainted.
             at the distance of 2 miles we passd. a lodge of 2 fires on a fork of the
          road which leads to the 〈lef〉 right Situated on a Small branch which falls into 
          <name type="place" key="Big Canyon (Mosquito) Creek">Musquetor Creek</name>.
             before 2 P M all our hunters joined us haveing killed only one deer which
          was lost in the river and a pheasent. Soon after we halted at the lodge of the 
          <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">twisted hair</name>he Set out with
          two boys and 
          <name type="person" key="Willard, Alexander">Willard</name>with a pack horse down to the
          river near the place we made the Canoes for our Saddles and a Cannister of powder and
          Some lead buried there, also a part of our horses which resorted near that place.
             late in the evening they returned with 21 of our horse and about half of
          our Saddles with the powder and ball. The greater part of the horses were in fine order,
          tho' five of them had been rode &amp; worsted in Such a manner last fall by the Inds.
          that they had not recovered and are in very low order, and 3 with Sore backs.
             we had all the recovered horses Cought &amp; hobbled.    we
          precured Some pounded roots of which a Supe was made thick on which we Suped.
             the wind blew hard from the S. W. accompanied with rain untill from 7
          oClock untill 9 P. M. when it began to Snow and Continued all night. Several Indians
          Came from the village of the Chief with whome we had left a flag and Continued with us
          all night.    they slept in the house of the 
          <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">twisted hair</name>and two of them
          along Side of us.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-05-09.03"
              ref="lc.geo.1806-05-09.01">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>Friday 9th of May 1806.    we Set out &amp; proced. on about 6 miles to the
          
          <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">twisted hairs</name>village where
          we Camped.
          <ref target="n34050908" n="8"/>   the chief Sent for our horses &amp; pack
          Saddles    one of our men went for the ammunition we left at canoe Camp
          <ref target="n34050909" n="9"/>   a band of Indians came from another village
          to See us.    towards evening 
          <name type="person" key="Willard, Alexander">Willard</name>returnd. with the ammunition
          and the pack Saddles    the Indians brought up the most of our horses. Some of
          them in good order.    we caught &amp; hobbled them. Some of them had been
          rode after Deer &amp;C.    these plains are Smooth Soil rich &amp; filled with
          commass wild onions and white roots calld. halse
          <ref target="n34050910" n="10"/>&amp; other roots good for food which the natives live
          on at this Season of the year.    the evening cold rainy &amp; windy.—</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-05-09.04"
              ref="lc.geo.1806-05-09.01">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Friday 9th.</hi>   There was a cloudy morning; and some
          hunters
          <ref target="n34050911" n="11"/>went out, and we proceeded on for about six miles, when
          we came to the old chief's lodge,
          <ref target="n34050912" n="12"/>where his family is encamped to gather roots. We are
          now got into a part of the country where timber is plenty, chiefly pitch pine.
          <ref target="n34050913" n="13"/>
               </p>
               <p>Between the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Great Falls of the">great falls of the
          Columbia</name>and this place, we saw more horses, than I ever before saw in the same
          space of country. They are not of the largest size of horses, but very good and active.
          <ref target="n34050914" n="14"/>At noon two of the Indians went to look for our horses,
          and the old chief with one of our men who knew where some powder and ball was buried,
          went to bring our packsaddles. In the evening they returned with 21 horses, and about as
          many packsaddles. Our horses are generally in good order. Our hunters also returned but
          had killed nothing.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n34050901" n="1">Heading southeasterly and crossing into 
        <name type="place" key="Clearwater County, Idaho">Clearwater County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>, along the divide between the 
        <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Clearwater
        River</name>and 
        <name type="place" key="Little Canyon Creek">Little Canyon Creek</name>. The area, but not
        the route, appears on 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>map 71.</note>
            <note xml:id="n34050902" n="2">Coventry here meaning exclusion from social contact during
        the women's menstrual period.</note>
            <note xml:id="n34050903" n="3">The expedition's camp of September–October 1805 where the
        men built canoes for the downriver trip; see entry of 
        <ref n="1805-09-26" type="related">September 26, 1805</ref>. It is located opposite 
        <name type="place" key="Ahsahka, Idaho">Ahsahka</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Clearwater County, Idaho">Clearwater County</name>, at the
        confluence of the 
        <name type="place" key="North Fork Clearwater (Chopunnish) River">North Fork</name>with
        the main stem of the 
        <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Clearwater River</name>.
        
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>map 71. Major excavations have recently been conducted at this
        historic 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>village and house pits
        dating to 3,000 years ago have been investigated. Sappington, Cochran, &amp; Ozbun;
        Sappington (AIA). Archaeologists tested the area of 
        <name type="place" key="Canoe Camp (Idaho)">Canoe Camp</name>in 1988 and the remains of a
        late prehistoric site were encountered. House pits, net sinkers, and hunting tools were
        recovered, but no artifacts that could be associated with the expedition were found.
        Sappington &amp; Wegars.</note>
            <note xml:id="n34050904" n="4">The Columbia River Basalt covers most of the uplands west
        of the foot of the mountains near the junction of the north and south forks of the 
        <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Clearwater River</name>.
        Streams in this area have cut into the basalt layers leaving plateaus of varying sizes in
        the interstream areas. These plateaus stand as much as 1,800 feet above the nearby stream
        bottoms in this area. The soil lying upon the basalts commonly is rich but not especially
        deep, except where the windblown Palouse silt composed of glacial rock-flour and volcanic
        ash occurs.</note>
            <note xml:id="n34050905" n="5">American ginseng, 
        <hi rend="italic">Panax quinquefolius</hi>L., familiar to 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>from eastern U.S. forests. Bailey,
        745. Two red vertical lines run through these passages about ginseng and camas, perhaps 
        <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle's</name>doing.</note>
            <note xml:id="n34050906" n="6">The peduncle.</note>
            <note xml:id="n34050907" n="7">In 
        <name type="place" key="Clearwater County, Idaho">Clearwater County</name>, southwest of 
        <name type="place" key="Orofino, Idaho">Orofino</name>; not shown on 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>map 71. Space places the site at 
        <name type="place" key="Wheeler Draw">Wheeler Draw</name>, but Peebles finds this location
        incompatible with the description in the journals. Space, 27; Peebles (RLC), 19–20;
        Peebles (LT), map. According to a local pioneer, "a truckload of artifacts" were exposed
        here during development of a spring and Space later found a pestle and other artifacts.
        Space, 27. Archaeologists have not examined this locale and no site has been recorded
        here.</note>
            <note xml:id="n34050908" n="8">In 
        <name type="place" key="Clearwater County, Idaho">Clearwater County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>, southwest of 
        <name type="place" key="Orofino, Idaho">Orofino</name>, but the exact location is
        disputed. See the captains' entries for this day.</note>
            <note xml:id="n34050909" n="9">The camp of September–October 1805, where the party built
        canoes for the down-river trip.</note>
            <note xml:id="n34050910" n="10">A word not used by 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>or 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>; it is probably the plant cous and
        perhaps a 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>term. See also the term
        "uppah" at 
        <ref n="1806-05-29" type="related">May 29</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n34050911" n="11">As usual, 
        <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name>was one.</note>
            <note xml:id="n34050912" n="12">The party camped here for the night. The site was in 
        <name type="place" key="Clearwater County, Idaho">Clearwater County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>, southwest of 
        <name type="place" key="Orofino, Idaho">Orofino</name>. It may have been on 
        <name type="place" key="Wheeler Draw">Wheeler Draw</name>, but see the captains'
        entries.</note>
            <note xml:id="n34050913" n="13">Probably lodgepole pine; see 
        <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass's</name>entry for 
        <ref n="1805-09-04" type="related">September 4, 1805</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n34050914" n="14">The 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perces</name>and other tribes of
        the Northwest Plateau became famous for their breeding of the Appaloosa horse.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-05-08" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-05-10" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
