<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1803-09-01">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">September 1, 1803</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2003</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic
               Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
                  2</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">August 30, 1803–August 24, 1804</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1986</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">67-68</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
         <geoDecl datum="WGS" xml:id="lc.geo.1803-09-01.01">
            <placeName>Woollery's Trap</placeName>
            <geo>40.5206 -80.1571</geo>
            <note>Camped just downstream from Woollery's Trap</note>
         </geoDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Journal Entries</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2003-12-09</date>
            <date/>
            <name>Brian L. Pytlik Zillig</name>
            <name/>Initial creation Transcribed</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-04-12</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name> Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1803-09-01">September 1, 1803</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1803-09-01.01"
              ref="lc.geo.1803-09-01.01">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>September 1st—</date>
               </ab>
               <p>The Pilott informed me that we were not far from a ripple which was much worse
                  than any we had yet passed, and as there was so thick a fogg on the face of the
                  water that no object was visible 40 paces he advised remaining untill the sun
                  should acquire a greater altitude when the fogg would asscend and disappear; I
                  conscented; we remained untill eight Oclock this morning when we again set out—   
                  these Foggs are very common on the <name type="place" key="Ohio River">Ohio</name>at this season of the year as also in the spring but do not think them
                  as freequent or thick in the spring.    perhaps this may in some measure assist us
                  to account for the heavy dues which are mor remarkable for their freequency and
                  quantity than in any country I was ever in—    they are so heavy the drops falling
                  from the trees from about midknight untill sunrise gives you the eydea of a
                  constant gentle rain, this continues untill the sun has acquired sufficient
                  altitude to dessipate the fogg by it's influence, and it then ceases.    the dues
                  are likewise more heavy during summer than elsewhere but not so much so as at this
                  season.—    the Fog appears to owe it's orrigin to the difference of temperature
                  between the <hi rend="italic">air</hi>and <hi rend="italic">water</hi>the latter
                  at this seson being much warmer than the former; the water being heated by the
                  summer's sun dose not undergo so rapid a change from the absence of the sun as the
                  air dose consiquently when the air becomes most cool which is about sunrise the
                  fogg is thickest and appears to rise from the face of the water like the steem
                  from boiling water— <ref target="n02090101" n="1"/>   we passed the <hi rend="italic">little horsetale</hi>ripple or riffle with much deficulty, all
                  hands laboured in the water about two hours before we effected a passage; the next
                  obstruction we met was the <name type="place" key="Big Horsetail Ripple">
                     <hi rend="italic">big-horse tale</hi>riffle</name>, <ref target="n02090102" n="2"/>here we wer obliged to unload all our goods and lift the emty Boat over,
                  about 5 OCock we reach the riffle called <name type="place" key="Woolery's Ripple">Woollery's trap</name>, <ref target="n02090103" n="3"/>here after unloading
                  again and exerting all our force we found it impracticable to get over, I
                  therefore employed a man with a team of oxen with the assistance of which we at
                  length got off    we put in and remained all night having made only ten miles this
                  day.— <ref target="n02090104" n="4"/>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n02090101" n="1">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>reflections on fog and dew
               and their determinants over the next several days bring him to posit a theory for the
               occurrence and to test his hypothesis by taking temperature readings of air and river
               during the time. Apparently cold air is moving down the valley sides and passing
               across the warm water of the <name type="place" key="Ohio River">Ohio River</name>in
               a situation known as cold air drainage. Since the air is heated from below as well as
               moistened, the fog takes the form of rising streamers, and the phenomenon is
               generally called steam fog. Neiburger, Edinger, &amp; Bonner, 123–24.</note>
            <note xml:id="n02090102" n="2">
               <name type="person" key="Cramer, Zadoc">Zadoc Cramer's</name>guide to the <name type="place" key="Ohio River">Ohio River</name>refers to the first ripple and the
               second, which he calls <name type="place" key="Big Horsetail Ripple">Horsetail
                  ripple</name>; he places them along today's <name type="place" key="Neville Island">Neville Island</name>, in <name type="place" key="Allegheny County, Pa.">Allegheny County</name>, <name type="place" key="Pennsylvania">Pennsylvania</name>. Cramer (5th), 29–30.</note>
            <note xml:id="n02090103" n="3">
               <name type="person" key="Cramer, Zadoc">Cramer</name>calls this <name type="place" key="Woolery's Ripple">Woolery's ripple</name>. Ibid., 30; Baily, 55.</note>
            <note xml:id="n02090104" n="4">Apparently just downstream from <name type="place" key="Woolery's Ripple">Woollery's Trap</name>, in <name type="place" key="Allegheny County, Pa.">Allegheny County</name>.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1803-08-30" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1803-09-02" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
