<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-07-09">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">July 9, 1805</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic
        Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            4</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">April7–July 27, 1805</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1987</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">368-371</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">181</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">110</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jw">Joseph Whitehouse</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            11</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of Joseph Whitehouse, May 14, 1804–April 2,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1997</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">221-222</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journal Entries</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-02-09</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-04-12</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1805-07-09">July 9, 1805</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-07-09.01" ref="">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Tuesday July 9th 1805.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>The morning was fair and pleant.    the Islands seem crouded with
          blackbirds; the young brude is now completely feathered and flying in common with the
          others.    we corked the canoes and put them in the water and also launched
          the boat, she lay like a perfect cork on the water.    five men would carry
          her with the greatest ease. I now directed seats to be fixed in her and oars to be
          fitted.    the men loaded the canoes in readiness to depart.    just
          at this moment a violent wind commenced and blew so hard that we were obliged to unload
          the canoes again; a part of the baggage in several of them got wet before it could be
          taken out.    the wind continued violent untill late in the evening, by which
          time we discovered that a greater part of the composition had seperated from the skins
          and left the seams of the boat exposed to the water and she leaked in such manner that
          she would not answer. I need not add that this circumstance mortifyed me not a little;
          and to prevent her leaking without pich was impossible with us, and to obtain this
          article was equally impossible, therefore the evil was irraparable    I now
          found that the section formed of the buffaloe hides on which some hair had been left,
          answered much the best purpose; this leaked but little and the parts which were well
          covered with hair about ⅛th of an inch in length retained the composition perfectly and
          remained sound and dry.    from these circumstances I am preswaided, that had
          I formed her with buffaloe skins singed not quite as close as I had done those I
          employed, that she would have answered even with this composition.    but to
          make any further experiments in our present situation seemed to me madness; the buffaloe
          had principally dserted us, and the season was now advancing fast. I therefore
          relinquished all further hope of my favorite boat and ordered her to be sunk in the
          water, that the skins might become soft in order the better to take her in peices
          tomorrow and deposite the iron fraim at this place as it could probably be of no further
          service to us.    had I only singed my Elk skins in stead of shaving them I
          beleive the composition would have remained and the boat have answered; at least untill
          we could have reached the pine country which must be in advance of us from the pine
          which is brought down by the water and which is probably at no great distance where we
          might have supplyed ourselves with the necessary pich or gum.    but it was
          now too late to introduce a remidy and 
          <ref target="n16070901" n="1">I bid a dieu to my boat, and her expected
          services.—</ref>   The next difficulty which presented itself was how we
          should convey the stores and baggage which we had purposed carrying in the boat.
             both 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. [
          <hi rend="italic">NB: Capt</hi>] Clark</name>and myself recollected having heard the
          hunters [
          <hi rend="italic">NB: 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt Clark</name>had previously sent them in
          quest of timber for the purpose</hi>] mention that the bottoms of the river some few
          miles above us were much better timbered than below and that some of the trees were
          large.    the idea therefore suggested itself of building two other canoes
          sufficiently large to carry the surplus baggage.    on enquiry of the hunters
          it seemed to be the general opinion that trees sufficiently a large for this purpose
          might be obtained in a bottom on the opposite side about 8 miles distant by land and
          reather more than double that distance by water; accordingly 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name>determined to set out early
          in the morning with ten of the best workmen and proceede by land to that place while the
          others would in the mean time be employed by myself in taking the Boat in peices and
          depositing her, toge[the]r with the articles which we had previously determined to
          deposit at this place, and also in trasporting all the baggage up the river to that
          point in the six small canoes.    this plan being settled between us orders
          were accordingly given to the party, and the ten men who were to accompany 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name>had ground and prepared their
          axes and adds this evening in order to prepare for an early departure in the morning.
             we have on this as well as on many former occasions found a small
          grindstone which I brought with me from 
          <ref target="n16070902" n="2">
                     <name type="place" key="Harpers Ferry, W. Va.">Harper's ferry</name>
                  </ref>extreemly convenient to us.    if we find trees at the place mentioned
          sufficiently large for our purposes it will be extreemly fortunate; for we have not seen
          one for many miles below the entrance of 
          <name type="place" key="Musselshell (Mah-tush,-ah-zhah, Shell) River">musselshell
          River</name>to this place, which would have answered.—</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">
                     <hi rend="right">July 9th 1805.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>Observed Magnetic Azimuth of the 
          <seg n="u9737">☉</seg>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <table rows="5" cols="5">
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                           <hi rend="center">Azimuth by
                  <lb/>Circumferenter</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                           <hi rend="center">time by the
                  <lb/>Chronometer</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                           <hi rend="center">Altd. of 
                  <seg n="u9737">☉</seg>'s
                  <lb/>U. L. by Sextant.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">        
                   h    m    s</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 73° E.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">A. M.    8    40
                   7</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">62°    38'   15"</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="2" cols="1">}</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="2" cols="1">Variation of the
                <lb/>Magnetic nedle.
                <lb/>° " E</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 74° E.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">        
                   8    44    47</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">63°    10    00</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>Equal Altitudes of the 
          <seg n="u9737">☉</seg>with Sextant.</p>
               <p>
                  <table rows="4" cols="6">
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">h    m   
                  s</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">A. M.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">8    48    15</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="3" cols="1">}</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">P. M.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="3" cols="1">lost by the
                <lb/>interferce.
                <lb/>of Clouds</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="3" cols="1">}</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="3" cols="1">Altitude at the time
                <lb/>of observation
                <lb/>65° 22' 15"</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">"    49    48</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">"    51    25</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>Obseved Meridian Altd. of 
          <seg n="u9737">☉</seg>'s L. L. with octant back Obsn.    55° 4'—"</p>
               <p>Latitude deduced from this observation    N. 47° 3' 56. 1/10"</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-07-09.02" ref="">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">July 9th Tuesday 1805</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>a clear worm morning wind from the S W. Lanced the Leather boat, and found that it
          leaked a little; Corked Lanced &amp; loaded the Canoes, burried our truk wheels, &amp;
          made a Carsh for a Skin &amp; a fiew papers I intend to leave here</p>
               <p>on trial found the leather boat would not answer without the addition of Tar which we
          had none of, haveing Substituted 
          <hi rend="italic">Cole &amp; Tallow</hi>in its place to Stop the Seams &amp;c. which
          would not answer as it Seperated from the Skins when exposed to the water and left the
          Skins naked &amp; Seams exposed to the water    this falire of our favourate
          boat was a great disapointment to us, we haveing more baggage than our Canoes would
          Carry. Concluded to build Canoes for to Carry them; no timber near our Camp. I
          deturmined to proceed on up the river to a bottom in which our hunters reported was
          large Trees &amp;c.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-07-09.03" ref="">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">July 9th Tuesday 1805</hi>.    a beautiful pleasant morning.
             the Island near the Camp is covered with black birds.
          <ref target="n16070903" n="3"/>   we put the Iron boat which we covered with
          green hides in to the water. Corked Some of the canoes in order to git in readiness to
          depart from this place    in the afternoon we loaded the 6 canoes but did not
          load the Iron boat as it leaked considerable    Soo[n] after we got the canoes
          loaded Thunder and high wind came on So that we had to unload again.    our
          officers concludes for to leave &amp; burry the Iron boat, as we cannot git tar or pitch
          to pay the over the out Side of the Skins. the coal Tallow &amp; bease wax would not
          stick to the hides as they were Shaved the time is So far expended that they did not
          think proper to try any more experiments with it. So we Sank hir in the water So that
          She might be the easier took to peaces tomorrow.    our officers conclude to
          build 2 canoes more So that we can carry all our baggage without the Iron boat. about 10
          men got ready to up the river to build 2 canoes.—</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-07-09.04" ref="">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Tuesday 9th.</hi>   A fine morning, and heavy dew. In the
          forenoon we loaded our canoes, and put the Experiment into the water. She rides very
          light but leaks some. In the afternoon a storm of wind, with some rain came on from the
          north west, and we had again to unload some of our canoes, the waves ran so high. After
          the storm we had a fine evening. The tallow and coal were found not to answer the
          purpose; for as soon as dry, it cracked and scaled off, and the water came through the
          skins. Therefore for want of tar or pitch we had, after all our labour, to haul our new
          boat on shore, and leave it at this place.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-07-09.05" ref="">
            <sp who="jw">
               <speaker>Whitehouse</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">July 9th Tuesday 1805</hi>.    a beautiful morning.
             the Island near our Camp is covered with black birds.    the
          musquetoes verry troublesome.    we put the Iron boat in to the water corked
          Some of the canoes and git in readiness to depart from this place.    in the
          afternoon we loaded the 6 canoes but did not load the Iron boat for She leaked Some.
             Soon after we got the canoes loaded there came up a Storm of wind &amp;
          Thunder.    the waves dashed over in the canoes So that we had to unload
          again.    our officers conclude that the Iron boat will not answer our purpose
          as we cannot git Tar nor pitch to pay the hir over the hides.    the coal
          Tallow &amp; bease wax would not Stick to the hides, &amp;c.    the time being
          So far Spent they concluded to burry hir at this place and go about 20 miles up the
          River and make 2 canoes which would answer much better.    So we Sunk
          <ref target="n16070904" n="4"/>Sd. Iron boat in the River So that Shee may be taken
          apart the better tomorrow.    about 10 men got ready to go with 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name>to make the canoes, about 20
          mls. by water and only about 5 by land from this place.</p>
               <p>Tuesday July 9th    A beautiful morning, the Island near our Camp 〈is〉 were
          covered with black birds, we found the Musketoes very troublesome at our Camp during
          last night; &amp; till after sunrise this morning, We were all employed, in calking of
          our Crafts; and putting our Iron boat into the waters and getting every thing in
          readiness to leave this place—    In the afternoon we loaded the 6 large
          Canoes; the Iron boat leaked so much, that we did not put any load into her,—
             soon after, we had got the Canoes loaded, &amp; a Violent storm of Wind and
          thunder came on.—</p>
               <p>The waves rose to such a height, as to wash over into the Canoes, so that all hands
          were employed to unload them as quick as possible—    Our officers found that
          the Iron boat would not answer our purpose, we not being able, to get sufficient
          quantity of tar or pitch, to pay her bottom &amp; sides, and that the Coal, tallow,
          &amp; grease would not prevent her from leaking, which she did very much; The Season
          being far advanced for the crossing the 
          <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">rocky mountains</name>, the officers concluded
          to bury the Iron boat at this place; and to proceed about 20 Miles up the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Mesouri</name>, and to make 2 large canoes, to
          answer our purpose, so they had the Iron boat sunk in the River, that she might be more
          easily taken apart, which they intend having done tomorrow.—    Ten of our
          party got themselves in readiness to go with 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain Clark</name>, in Order to make the
          Canoes; they intend going by land the distance being about 5 Miles &amp; 20 Miles by
          water—</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n16070901" n="1">Apparently the boat was abandoned for good; there is no
        record of its recovery on the return trip in 1806. Rose.</note>
            <note xml:id="n16070902" n="2">The federal armory at 
        <name type="place" key="Harpers Ferry, W. Va.">Harpers Ferry</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Virginia">Virginia</name>(now 
        <name type="place" key="West Virginia">West Virginia</name>), where 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>obtained weapons, the iron boat
        frame, and various other equipment for the expedition.</note>
            <note xml:id="n16070903" n="3">Perhaps rusty blackbird, 
        <hi rend="italic">Euphogus carolinus</hi>, or Brewer's blackbird, 
        <hi rend="italic">E. cyanocephalus.</hi>The party also apparently called the common
        grackle, 
        <hi rend="italic">Quisculus quisculus</hi>, a blackbird.</note>
            <note xml:id="n16070904" n="4">The word "Sunk" is written over "put."</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-07-08" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-07-10" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
