<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-06-04">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">June 4, 1805</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic
        Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            4</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">April7–July 27, 1805</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1987</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">253-257</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">162-163</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">98-99</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jw">Joseph Whitehouse</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            11</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of Joseph Whitehouse, May 14, 1804–April 2,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1997</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">186-187</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc/>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-02-03</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-04-12</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1805-06-04">June 4, 1805</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-06-04.01" ref="">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Tuesday, June 4th 1805</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>This morning early 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. C.</name>departed, and at the same time I
          passed the wright hand fork opposite to our camp below a small Island; from hence I
          steered N. 30 W. 4½ to a 
          <ref target="n14060401" n="1">commanding eminence;</ref>here I took the following
          bearings of the mountains which were in view. The 
          <ref target="n14060402" n="2">
                     <name type="place" key="Bears Paw (North) Mountains">North Mountains</name>
                  </ref>appear to change their direction from that of being parallel with the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>turning to the North and
          terminating abruptly; their termineation bearing N. 48° E distant by estimate 30 mes.
          The 
          <ref target="n14060403" n="3">
                     <name type="place" key="Highwood (South) Mountains">South Mountains</name>
                  </ref>appear to turn to the S. also terminating abrubtly, their extremity bearing S. 8
          W. distant 25 mes. The 
          <ref target="n14060404" n="4">
                     <name type="place" key="Square Butte (Barn Mountain)">Barn Mountain</name>,</ref>a lofty
          mountain so called from it's resemblance to the roof of a large Barn, is a seperate
          Mountain and appears reather to the wright of and retreating from the extremity of the
          S. mts.; this boar S. 38 W. distant 35 ms. The North fork which I am now ascending lies
          to my left and appears to make a considerable bend to the N. W.    on it's
          Western border a range of hills about 10 mes. long appear to lye parallel with the river
          and from hence bear N. 60° W.    to the N. of this range of hills an Elivated
          point of the river bluff on it's Lard. side boar N. 72° W. distant 12 mes.   
          to this last object I now directed my course through a high level dry open plain.
             the whole country in fact appears to be one continued plain to the foot of
          the mountains or as far as the eye can reach; the soil appears dark rich and fertile yet
          the grass is by no means as high nor dose it look so luxurient as I should have
          expected, it is short just sufficient to conceal the ground.    great
          abundance of prickly pears which are extreemly troublesome; as the thorns very readily
          perce the foot through the Mockerson; they are so numerous that it requires one half of
          the traveler's attention to avoid them    In these plains I [
          <hi rend="italic">NB: we</hi>] observed great numbers of the brown Curloos, a small
          species of curloo or plover of a brown colour about the size of the common snipe and not
          unlike it in form with a long celindric curved and pointed beak; it's wings are
          proportionately long and the tail short; in the act of liteing this bird lets itself
          down by an extention of it's wings without motion holding their points very much
          together above it's back, in this rispect differing ascentially from any bird I ever
          observed.
          <ref target="n14060405" n="5"/>   a number of sparrows also of three distinct
          species I observed.    also a 
          <ref target="n14060406" n="6">small bird which in action resembles the lark,</ref>it is
          about the size of a large sparrow of a dark brown colour with some white fathers in the
          tail; this bird or that which I take to be the male rises into the air about 60 feet and
          supporting itself in the air with a brisk motion of the wings sings very sweetly, has
          several shrill soft notes reather of the plaintive order which it frequently repeats and
          varies, after remaining stationary about a minute in his aireal station he descends
          obliquely occasionly pausing and accomnying his decension with a note something like 
          <hi rend="italic">twit twit twit;</hi>on the ground he is silent.    thirty or
          forty of these birds will be stationed in the air at a time in view, these larks as I
          shall call them add much to the gayety and cheerfullness of the scene. All those birds
          are now seting and laying their eggs in the plains; their little nests are to be seen in
          great abundance as we pass.    there are meriads of small grasshoppers in
          these plains which no doubt furnish the principal aliment of this numerous progeny of
          the feathered creation. after walking about eight miles I grew thisty and there being no
          water in the plains I changed my direction and boar obliquely in towards the river, on
          my arrival at which about 3 mes. below the point of observation, we discovered two deer
          at feed at some distance near the river; I here halted the party and sent 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name>to kill one of them for
          breakfast; this excellent hunter so[o]n exceded his orders by killing of them both; they
          proved to be two Mule Bucks in fine order; we soon kindled a fire cooked and made a
          hearty meal.    it was not yet twelve when we arrived at the river and I was
          anxious to take the Meridian Altd. of the sun but the clouds prevented my obtaining the
          observation.    after refreshing ourselves we proceded up the river to the
          extremity of the first course, from whence the river boar on it's general course N. 15°
          W. 2 M. to a bluff point on Stard.    here 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name>killed four other deer of the
          common kind; we skined them and hung up a part of the meat and the skins as we did also
          of the first, and took as much of the meat as we thought would answer for our suppers
          and proceeded N. 30 W. 2 m. to the entrance of a 
          <ref target="n14060407" n="7">large creek on Lard. side</ref>   the part of
          the river we have passed is from 40 to 60 yds. wide, is deep, has falling banks, the
          courant strong, the water terbid and in short has every appearance of the missouri
          b[e]low except as to size.    it's bottoms narrow but well timbered. Salts
          coal and other mineral appearances as usual; the bluffs principally of dark brown,
          yellow and some white clay; some freestone also appears in places.
          <ref target="n14060408" n="8"/>The river now boar N. 20° E. 12 mes. to a bluff on Lard.
          At the commencement of this course we ascended the hills which are about 200 feet high,
          and passed through the plains about 3 m. but finding the dry ravines so steep and
          numerous we determined to return to the river and travel through it's bottoms and along
          the foot and sides of the bluffs, accordingly we again reached the river about 4 miles
          from the commencement of the last course and encamped a small distanc above on the
          Stard. side in a bend among the willow bushes which defended us from the wind which blew
          hard from the N. W.    it rained this evening and wet us to the skin; the air
          was extremely could.    just before we encamped 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name>fired at a large brown bar
          across the river and wounded him badly but it was too late to pursue him.   
          killed a braro and a beaver, also at the place of our encampment, a very fine Mule deer.
             we saw a great number of Buffaloe, Elk, wolves and foxes today.
             the river bottoms form one emence garden of roses, now in full bloe.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-06-04.02" ref="">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">June 4th Tuesday 1805</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name>&amp; my Self each with a
          Small party of men Set out early—    those who accompanied 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt Lewis</name>were 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">G. Drewyer</name>
                  <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Serjt. Pryor</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Shields, John">J Shields</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">P. Crusat</name>
                  <name type="person" key="Lepage, Jean Baptiste">J. B. de Page</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Windsor, Richard">R. Winser</name>, went up the N. side of the 
          <name type="place" key="Jefferson River (North, Southwest Fork)">N. fork</name>.
             those who accompanied me were 
          <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Serjt. Gass</name>
                  <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Jos:</name>&amp; 
          <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">Ruben Fields</name>
                  <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">G. Shannon</name>&amp; my black man 
          <name type="person" key="York">York</name>, and we Set out to examine the 
          <name type="place" key="Gallatin (South, Southeast Fork) River">South fork</name>, our
          first Course was S. 25° W. 7 miles to the S. fork at a 
          <ref target="n14060409" n="9">Spring, at which place the little river which falls into
          the N. fork is 100 yards distant only Seperated from the 〈right〉 
          <name type="place" key="Gallatin (South, Southeast Fork) River">South fork</name>by a
          narrow ridge.</ref>   our course from thence S. 20° W. 8 miles to the river at
          an Island where we dined below a 
          <ref target="n14060410" n="10">Small river falls in on the S E Side which heads in a
          mountain to the S. E about 20 miles.</ref>North of this place about 4 miles the little
          river brakes thro' a high ridge into the open Leavel plain thro which we have passd.
          from the point, this plain is covered with low grass &amp; prickley pear, emence number
          of Prarie dogs or barking Squirel are thro this plain—    after eating we
          proceeded on N. 45° W. Struck the river at 3 miles 5, 9 &amp; 13 miles at which place we
          encamped in an old Indian lodge made of Stiks and bark
          <ref target="n14060411" n="11"/>   at the river near our camp we Saw two
          white Bear, one of them was nearly catching 
          <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Joseph Fields</name>
                  <ref target="n14060412" n="12"/>who could not fire, as his gun was wet    the
          bear was So near that it Struck his foot, and we were not in a Situation to give him
          assistance, a Clift of rocks Seperated us    the bear got allarmed at our Shot
          &amp; yells &amp; took the river.—    Some rain all the afternoon   
          Saw Several Gangues of Buffalow at a distance in the open plains on each Side, Saw Mule
          deer antilopes &amp; wolves—    The river is rapid &amp; Closely himed on one
          or the other Side with high bluffs, Crouded with Islands &amp; graveley bars Containing
          but a Small quantity of timber on its bottoms &amp; none on the high land.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-06-04.03" ref="">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">June 4th Tuesday 1805</hi>. 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name>and 6 men Set out to go up
          the right hand fork.
          <ref target="n14060413" n="13"/>   
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt Clark</name>&amp; 5 more Set out at the
          Same time to go up the left hand fork in order to go one day &amp; a halfs march up the
          River and see if they can find out which will be our best River to proceed on. Some of
          the men at Camp killed 2 faun Elk near the point for their Skins to dress.   
          the day proved Cloudy.    2 men who had been from Camp a hunting returned
          towards evening.    had killed one Elk &amp; a Deer &amp; Set traps for beaver
          &amp;C.    a fiew drops of rain towards evening &amp; high cold wind from the
          North.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-06-04.04" ref="">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Tuesday 4th.</hi>   
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Lewis</name>with six men
          <ref target="n14060414" n="14"/>went up the North branch, to see if they could find any
          certain marks to determine whether that was the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>or not; and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain Clarke</name>myself and four others
          <ref target="n14060415" n="15"/>went up the South branch, for the same purpose with
          regard to that branch. About eight miles above the confluence, the South branch and the
          small river which falls into the 
          <name type="place" key="Jefferson River (North, Southwest Fork)">North branch</name>,
          are not more than 200 yards apart. Near this place and close on the bank of the South
          branch is a beautiful spring where we refreshed ourselves with a good drink of grog
          <ref target="n14060416" n="16"/>and proceeded on through the high plains. Here nothing
          grows but prickly pears,
          <ref target="n14060417" n="17"/>which are in abundance, and some short grass. We sent
          on about thirty miles and found the river still extending in a South West direction. We
          saw a mountain
          <ref target="n14060418" n="18"/>to the South about 20 miles off, which appeared to run
          East and West, and some spots on it resembling snow. In the evening we went towards the
          river to encamp, where one of the men
          <ref target="n14060419" n="19"/>having got down to a small point of woods on the bank,
          before the rest of the party, was attacked by a huge he-bear, and his gun missed fire.
          We were about 200 yards from him, but the bank there was so steep we could not get down
          to his assistance: we, however, fired at the animal from the place where we stood and he
          went off without injuring the man. Having got down we all encamped
          <ref target="n14060420" n="20"/>in an old Indian lodge for the night.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-06-04.05" ref="">
            <sp who="jw">
               <speaker>Whitehouse</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Tuesday 4th June 1805</hi>.    
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name>&amp; 6 men Set out to go
          up the Right hand fork.    
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name>&amp; 5 more Set out to go up
          the left hand fork.    they intend to go about one day &amp; a halfs walk up
          the rivers &amp; See what discoveries they can make.    Some of the men at
          camp killed 2 faun Elk close by the camp for the Skins, to dress.    the day
          proved cloudy.    a fiew drops of rain towards evening, &amp; high cold wind
          from the N. E.    2 men who had been from camp a hunting returned had killed
          an Elk &amp; a Deer, &amp; had Set 2 traps for beaver.    cloudy all day.—</p>
               <p>Tuesday June 4th    We remained this day at the place, we encamped at
          Yesterday; in the forks of the Rivers, The weather was Cloudy, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Lewis</name>and Six hunters, set out
          to go up 
          <name type="place" key="Jefferson River (North, Southwest Fork)">the North fork</name>of
          the River; and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain Clark</name>and five hunters, also set
          out to go up the 
          <name type="place" key="Gallatin (South, Southeast Fork) River">South fork</name>, they
          intend going about One &amp; a half days Journey up each River, in Order to make
          discoveries, and to ascertain our right Course, and to determine which of those forks
          was the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Mesouri River</name>, Some of the Men at our
          Camp killed 2 fawn Elk near it; those Fawn Skins, we prepar'd to dress, to make
          moccasins, towards Evening the Wind rose from the North east, and was Cold, Two of our
          Men that had went hunting from our Camp, returned.    They had killed an Elk,
          and one deer.—and had set 2 Traps to catch beaver.—</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n14060401" n="1">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>courses and distances for this
        day and the next are summarized in 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>entry of 
        <ref n="1805-06-08" type="related">June 8</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n14060402" n="2">Probably the 
        <name type="place" key="Bears Paw (North) Mountains">Bears Paw Mountains</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n14060403" n="3">Probably the 
        <name type="place" key="Highwood (South) Mountains">Highwood Mountains</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n14060404" n="4">
               <name type="place" key="Square Butte (Barn Mountain)">Square Butte</name>, east of the 
        <name type="place" key="Highwood (South) Mountains">Highwood Mountains</name>and south of 
        <name type="place" key="Geraldine, Mont.">Geraldine</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Chouteau County, Mont.">Chouteau County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>. 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>"S. 38 W." should read "S. 38
        E."; he says that 
        <name type="place" key="Square Butte (Barn Mountain)">Barn Mountain</name>is "reather to
        the wright [
        <hi rend="italic">east</hi>]" of the 
        <name type="place" key="Highwood (South) Mountains">Highwoods</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n14060405" n="5">The long-billed curlew, although Holmgren believes 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>describes two birds: "brown
        Curloos" and a "small species of curloo." The latter she supposes to be the Eskimo curlew,
        
        <hi rend="italic">Numenius borealis</hi>[AOU, 266]. Holmgren, 29.</note>
            <note xml:id="n14060406" n="6">McCown's longspur, 
        <hi rend="italic">Calcarius mccownii</hi>[AOU, 539], then new to science. Cutright (LCPN),
        157. Someone, perhaps 
        <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>, drew a red vertical line through
        these passages, beginning with "I observed" to "numerous progeny."</note>
            <note xml:id="n14060407" n="7">
               <name type="place" key="Sheep Coulee">Sheep Coulee</name>, some distance above which 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>camped on the opposite
        side.</note>
            <note xml:id="n14060408" n="8">Like the 
        <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, the 
        <name type="place" key="Marias River">Marias River</name>was forced by glacial ice to cut
        a new channel. The formations exposed in this trench-like channel are the Claggett Shale, 
        <name type="place" key="Eagle Sandstone">Eagle Sandstone</name>, and Marias River Shale.
        The Claggett Shale is covered by glacial till. The salts are derived from the shale and
        the till. The coal occurs in the upper member of the 
        <name type="place" key="Eagle Sandstone">Eagle Sandstone</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n14060409" n="9">The 
        <name type="place" key="Teton (Rose, Tansy) River">Teton River</name>is separated from the
        
        <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>by a ridge or high ground which was
        later called 
        <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="place" key="Vimy Ridge">Cracon du Nez</name>
               </hi>by French rivermen and may be loosely translated, "bridge of the nose." It is now
        called 
        <name type="place" key="Vimy Ridge">Vimy Ridge</name>. Wheeler, 1:302; Coues (HLC), 1:346
        n. 29; 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>maps 42, 53, 61; MRC map 75.</note>
            <note xml:id="n14060410" n="10">
               <name type="place" key="Shonkin Creek (Snow River)">"Snow River"</name>on 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>maps 42, 53, 61; later 
        <name type="place" key="Shonkin Creek (Snow River)">Shonkin Creek</name>, in 
        <name type="place" key="Chouteau County, Mont.">Chouteau County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>. MRC map 75.</note>
            <note xml:id="n14060411" n="11">Marked on 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>maps 42 and 54 as "my old camp" and on map 61 as "W. Cs Camp 4
        June." The last does not quite agree with the other two, which are probably correct. About
        a mile and one-half upstream of present 
        <name type="place" key="Carter Ferry, Mont.">Carter Ferry</name>, in 
        <name type="place" key="Chouteau County, Mont.">Chouteau County</name>. MRC map 76.</note>
            <note xml:id="n14060412" n="12">Apparently 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>added the man's name a second time
        here, as "
        <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Joseph Field</name>."</note>
            <note xml:id="n14060413" n="13">
               <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>listed the men in each of the
        detachments in his entry for this day. 
        <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>remained behind with the main
        party.</note>
            <note xml:id="n14060414" n="14">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>party included 
        <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Pryor</name>, 
        <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name>, 
        <name type="person" key="Shields, John">Shields</name>, 
        <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Cruzatte</name>, 
        <name type="person" key="Lepage, Jean Baptiste">Jean Baptiste Lepage</name>, and 
        <name type="person" key="Windsor, Richard">Windsor</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n14060415" n="15">With 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, besides 
        <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name>, were 
        <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Joseph</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">Reubin Field</name>, 
        <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name>, and 
        <name type="person" key="York">York</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n14060416" n="16">The "
        <name type="place" key="Grog Spring">Grog Spring</name>" does not appear on any 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>maps, but is mentioned by 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>on June 12; the site, as 
        <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name>says, is at the place where 
        <name type="place" key="Teton (Rose, Tansy) River">Teton</name>and 
        <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>rivers approach very closely, in 
        <name type="place" key="Chouteau County, Mont.">Chouteau County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>. Grog is generally taken to be a mixture
        of rum and water.</note>
            <note xml:id="n14060417" n="17">Probably plains prickly pear, 
        <hi rend="italic">Opuntia polyacantha</hi>Haw.</note>
            <note xml:id="n14060418" n="18">The 
        <name type="place" key="Highwood (South) Mountains">Highwood Mountains</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Chouteau County, Mont.">Chouteau County</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n14060419" n="19">
               <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Joseph Field</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n14060420" n="20">About a mile and a half upstream from 
        <name type="place" key="Carter Ferry, Mont.">Carter Ferry</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Chouteau County, Mont.">Chouteau County</name>.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-06-03" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-06-05" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
