<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-04-13">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
April 13, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               
               
               
               
               
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml" n="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc" n="Clark, William">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 7</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">March 23–June 9, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1991</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">115-117</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo" n="Ordway, John">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf" n="Floyd, Charles">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">291</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg" n="Gass, Patrick">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">210</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
         <geoDecl datum="WGS" xml:id="lc.geo.1806-04-13.01">
            <placeName/>
            <geo>45.7167 -121.7</geo>
            <note>Camped in Skamania County, WA, south of Dog Mountain, between Collins Creek and Dog Creek.</note>
         </geoDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Journal Entries</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-10-04</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1806-04-13">April 13, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-04-13.01" n="lc.geo.1806-04-13.01">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Sunday April 13th 1806.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
The loss of one of our perogues rendered it necessary to distribute her crew and cargo among the 2 remaining perogues and 2 canoes, which being done we loaded and set out 8 A. M.    we passed the village immediately above the rapids<ref target="n31041301" n="1"/> where only one house at present remains entire, the other 8 having been taken down and removed to the oposite side of the river as before mentioned.    we found the additional laiding which we had been compelled to put on board rendered our vessels extreemly inconvenient to mannage and in short reather unsafe in the event of high winds; I therefore left <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. C.</name> with the two Perogues to proceede up the river on the N. side, and with the two canoes and some additional hands passed over the river above the rapids of the <name type="place" key="Y-eh-huh village">Y-eh-huh village</name>
                  <ref target="n31041302" n="2"/> in order to purchase one or more canoes. I found the village consisting of 11 houses crouded with inhabitants; it appeared to me that they could have mustered about 60 fighting men then present.    they appeared very friendly disposed, and I soon obtained two small canoes from them for which I gave two robes and four elkskins. I also purchased four paddles and three dogs from them with deerskins.    the dog now constitutes a considerable part of our subsistence and with most of the party has become a favorite food; certain I am that it is a healthy strong diet, and from habit it has become by no means disagreeable to me, I prefer it to lean venison or Elk, and is very far superior to the horse in any state.    after remaining about 2 hours at this Village I departed and continued my rout with the four canoes along the S. side of the river the wind being too high to pass over to the entrance of <name type="place" key="Wind (Cruzatte's) River (Wash.)">Cruzatts river</name>
                  <ref target="n31041303" n="3"/> where I expected to have overtaken <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. C.</name>    not seing the perogues on the opposite side I ascended the river untill one oclock or about 5 ms. above the entrance of <name type="place" key="Wind (Cruzatte's) River (Wash.)">Cruzat's river</name>.    being convinced that the perogues were behind I halted and directed the men to dress the dogs and cook one of them for dinner; a little before we had completed our meal <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. C.</name> arrived with the perogues and landed opposite to us.<ref target="n31041304" n="4"/>    after dinner I passed the river to the perogues and found that <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. C.</name> had halted for the evening and was himself hunting with three of the party.    the men in formed me that they had seen nothing of the hunters whom we had sent on the 11th ints. to the Entrance of <name type="place" key="Wind (Cruzatte's) River (Wash.)">Cruzatt's Riv</name>. I directed Sergt. <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">ordway</name> to take the two small canoes for his mess and the loading which he had formerly carried in the perogue we lost yesterday, and to have them dryed this evening and payed with rozin. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name> returned in about an hour and being convinced that the hunters were yet behind we dispatched <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Sergt. Pryor</name> in surch of them with two men and an empty canoe to bring the meat they may have killed. <name type="person" key="Shields, John">John Sheilds</name> returned a little after six P. M. with two deer which he had killed.    these were also of the blacktailed fallow deer; there appears to be no other speceis of deer in these mountains. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. C.</name> informed me that the wind had detained him several hours a little above <name type="place" key="Wind (Cruzatte's) River (Wash.)">Cruzatt's river</name>; that while detained here he sent out some men to hunt; one of them wounded two deer but got neither of them.    the wind having lulled in the evening and not seing anything of <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name> and the <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph and Reubin">Feildses</name> he had proceeded on to this place where he intended waiting for me, and as he did not see my canoes when he landed had taken a hunt with some of the men as before mentioned.—
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-04-13.02" n="lc.geo.1806-04-13.01">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Sunday April 13th 1806</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
The loss of one of our large Canoes rendered it necessary to divide the loading and men of that Canoe between the remaining four, which was done and we loaded and Set out at 8 oClock A. M.    passed the village imediately above the rapids, where only one house remains entire the other 8 haveing been taken down and moved to the opposit Side of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> as already mentioned.    the additional men and baggage in each Canoe renders them Crouded and unsafe. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name> with 2 of the Smallest Canoes of <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Sergt. Pryor</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Gibson, George">gibson</name> and Crossed above the Rapids to the Village on the S E Side with a view to purchase a Canoe of the nativs if possible.    he took with him Some Cloth and a fiew Elk skins and Deer Skins. I with the two large Canoes proceeded on up the N. W. Side with the intention of gitting to the Encampment of our hunters who was derected to hunt in the bottom above <name type="place" key="Wind (Cruzatte's) River (Wash.)">Crusats River</name>, and there wait the arrival of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name>. I proceeded on to the bottom in which I expected to find the hunters but Could See nothing of them.    the wind rose and raised the wavs to Such a hight that I could not proceed any further.    we landed and I sent out <name type="person" key="Shields, John">Shields</name> and <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name> to hunt; <name type="person" key="Shields, John">Shields</name> Shot two deer but Could get neither of them. I walkd. to <name type="place" key="Wind (Cruzatte's) River (Wash.)">Crusats river</name> and up it ½ a mile    on my return to the party found that the wind had lulled and as we Could See nothing of our hunters. I deturmined to proceed on to the next bottom where I thought it probable they had halted    at ½ passed 2 P M Set out and proceeded on to the bottom 6 miles and halted    at the next bottom formed a Camp and Sent out all the hunters. I also walked out my self on the hills but saw nothing.    on my return found <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name> at Camp with two canoes which he had purchased at the <name type="native_nation" key="Y-eh-huh village">
                     <hi rend="italic">Y-ep-huh</hi> village</name> for two robes and four elkskins.    he also purchased 4 paddles and 〈fo〉 three Dogs from the nativs with deer Skins.    the dogs now constitutes a considerable part of our Subsistance &amp; with most of the party has become a favourable food. Certain I am that is a helthy Strong diet, 〈and〉 derected <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Serjt. ordway</name> to take the 2 Small Canoes purchased by <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name> for his mess and the loading he had in his Canoe which we lost yesterday, and drawed up and paid with rozin.</p>
               <p>
I was convinced that the hunters must have been up <name type="place" key="Wind (Cruzatte's) River (Wash.)">River Cruzatt</name>. despatched <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Sergt. Pryor</name> with 2 men in a Canoe, with directions to assend <name type="place" key="Wind (Cruzatte's) River (Wash.)">Crusats River</name> and if he found the hunters to assist them in with the meat. <name type="person" key="Shields, John">Jo: Shields</name> returned about Sunset with two deer which he had killed, those were of the Black tail fallow Deer.    〈the〉 there appears to be no other Species of Deer in those mountains. We proceeded on 12 miles.<ref target="n31041305" n="5"/>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-04-13.03" n="lc.geo.1806-04-13.01">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Sunday 13th of April 1806.    we loaded up our canoes took a light breakfast of a little dog meat and departed    Soon passed the village    only one house remaining covred in it which lives a number of the natives. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name> and the Small canoes crossed over to the South Side to 2 villages<ref target="n31041306" n="6"/> little above the Shoote in order to purchace a canoe from the natives if possable.    the current Swift.    we proceeded on little above <name type="place" key="Wind (Cruzatte's) River (Wash.)">cruzattes River</name>    the wind rose So high that obledged us to halt at this bottom where we expected to find our Hunters    2 men<ref target="n31041307" n="7"/> went out a hunting    the day proved fair    the wind cold and Snow laying low on the Mountains near the River.    the hunters soon came in had killd. nothing but a bald Eagle    we then proceed. on about 5 miles and halted again at a bottom on the N. Side<ref target="n31041308" n="8"/>    3 men went out a hunting. <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Sergt. Pryor</name> &amp; 2 men Sent back to <name type="place" key="Wind (Cruzatte's) River (Wash.)">cruzattes River</name> to look again for the hunters    one of the hunters killed two Deer. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name> &amp; party overtook us had purchased two Small canoes the price of which was 2 Small peaces of blue cloath and two Elk hides, &amp; bought three dogs also.    we dryed the 2 Small canoes by fire and pitched them &amp;c.


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-04-13.04" n="lc.geo.1806-04-13.01">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Sunday 13th.</hi>    There was a cloudy morning. Having divided the load of the lost canoe among the 4 that were left, we renewed our voyage and passed a large deserted village on the north side. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Lewis</name> with the two small canoes, crossed to the south side, where there is a large village inhabited, to endeavour to purchase a small canoe or two, as we were very much crowded in the four we had. Capt. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clarke</name> with the two large canoes continued on along the northern shore, till we passed <name type="place" key="Wind (Cruzatte's) River (Wash.)">Crusatte's river</name>, when the wind rose so high we could not go on, so we halted and waited for <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name>. Two hunters went out about 3 hours, but killed nothing. By this time the wind fell and we went on 3 miles to a better harbour, where we halted on the north side of the river. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clarke</name> and 3 men went out to hunt; and <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name> having come up and crossed over to us, we fixed our camp for the night. He got 2 canoes and 3 dogs from the inhabitants of the large village.— They are of the <name type="native_nation" key="Yehuh Indians">Wey-eh-hoo nation</name> and have twelve lodges here. At dark Capt. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clarke</name> and party returned, and had killed two deer.



</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n31041301" n="1">The <name type="native_nation" key="Y-eh-huh village">"Yehuh" village</name> on <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 79, in <name type="place" key="Skamania County, Wash.">Skamania County</name>, <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>. See <ref n="1805-10-30" type="related">October 30, 1805</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31041302" n="2">Evidently on the south side of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>, in <name type="place" key="Hood River County, Oreg.">Hood River County</name>, <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>, but not marked on <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 78 and 79.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31041303" n="3">
               <name type="place" key="Wind (Cruzatte's) River (Wash.)">Wind River</name>, <name type="place" key="Skamania County, Wash.">Skamania County</name>. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 78. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> explored the bottomland east of the mouth of <name type="place" key="Wind (Cruzatte's) River (Wash.)">Wind River</name>. Archaeological investigations in this vicinity at <name type="place" key="Home Valley Park">Home Valley Park</name> documented evidence of seasonal campsites occupied over the last several thousand years. Minor &amp; Beckham.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31041304" n="4">In <name type="place" key="Skamania County, Wash.">Skamania County</name>, south of <name type="place" key="Dog Mountain">Dog Mountain</name>, the party's camp for the night; apparently between <name type="place" key="Collins Creek (Wash.)">Collins Creek</name> and <name type="place" key="Dog Creek (Wash.)">Dog Creek</name>, which are marked but not named on <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 78.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31041305" n="5">The number 12 was apparently written over 16.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31041306" n="6">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> calls it the "<name type="place" key="Y-eh-huh village">Y-eh-huh village</name>," but it is not shown on expedition maps in <name type="place" key="Hood River County, Oreg.">Hood
River County</name>, <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31041307" n="7">
               <name type="person" key="Shields, John">Shields</name> and <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name>, reports <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31041308" n="8">Where they camped in <name type="place" key="Skamania County, Wash.">Skamania County</name>, apparently between <name type="place" key="Collins Creek (Wash.)">Collins</name> and <name type="place" key="Dog Creek (Wash.)">Dog</name> creeks.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-04-12" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-04-14" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
