<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-07-15">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
July 15, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               
               
               
               
               
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml" n="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc" n="Clark, William">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 8</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">June 10–September 26, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1987</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">109-111, 183-188</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo" n="Ordway, John">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf" n="Floyd, Charles">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">336</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg" n="Gass, Patrick">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">253-254</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
         <geoDecl datum="WGS" xml:id="lc.geo.1806-07-15.01">
            <placeName/>
            <geo>46.6667 -110.4</geo>
            <note>Clark camped on the north side of the Yellowstone River, Park County, MT, just south of Sheep Mountain and a few miles below the mouth of Shields River.</note>
         </geoDecl>
         <geoDecl datum="WGS" xml:id="lc.geo.1806-07-15.02">
            <placeName/>
            <geo>47.4591 -111.3151</geo>
            <note>The rest of the party returned to the camp of 1806-07-12. Party remained here until 07-27.</note>
         </geoDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Journal Entries</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-11-11</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1806-07-15">July 15, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-07-15.01" n="lc.geo.1806-07-15.02">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">15 July 1806.</hi>
                     <ref target="n37071501" n="1"/>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
Sent <name type="person" key="McNeal, Hugh">McNeal</name> down this morning to the lower part of the portage to see whether the large perogue and cash were safe.—<ref target="n37071502" n="2"/>
                  <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name> returned without the horses and reported that he had tracked them to beyond our camp of the 
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-07-15.02" n="lc.geo.1806-07-15.02">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Tuesday July 15th 1806.</hi>
                     <ref target="n37071503" n="3"/>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
Dispatched <name type="person" key="McNeal, Hugh">McNeal</name> early this morning to the lower part of portage in order to learn whether the Cash and white perogue remained untouched or in what state they were.    the men employed in drying the meat, dressing deerskins and preparing for the reception of the canoes.    at 1 P. M. <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name> returned without the horses and reported that after a diligent surch of 2 days he had discovered where the horses had passed <name type="place" key="Dearborn River">Dearborn's river</name> at which place there were 15 lodges that had been abandoned about the time our horses were taken; he pursued the tracks of a number of horses from these lodges to the road which we had traveled over the mountains which they struck about 3 ms. South of our encampment of the 7th inst. and had pursued this road Westwardly; I have no doubt but they are a party of the <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Tushapahs</name> who have been on a buffaloe hunt. <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name> informed that there camp was in a small bottom on the river of about 5 acres inclosed by the steep and rocky and lofty clifts of the river and that so closely had they kept themselves and horses within this little spot that there was not a track to be seen of them within a quarter of a mile of that place.    every spire of grass was eaten up by their horses near their camp which had the appearance of their having remained here some time.    his horse being much fatiegued with the ride he had given him and finding that the indians had at least 2 days the start of him thought it best to return.    his safe return has releived me from great anxiety. I had already settled it in my mind that a whitebear had killed him and should have set out tomorrow in surch of him, and if I could not find him to continue my rout to <name type="place" key="Marias River">Maria's river</name>. I knew that if he met with a bear in the plains even he would attack him.    and that if any accedent should happen to seperate him from his horse in that situation the chances in favour of his being killed would be as 9 to 10. I felt so perfectly satisfyed that he had returned in safety that I thought but little of the horses although they were seven of the best I had.    this loss great as it is, is not intirely irreparable, or at least dose not defeat my design of exploring <name type="place" key="Marias River">Maria's river</name>. I have yet 10 horses remaining, two of the best and two of the worst of which I leave to assist the party in taking the canoes and baggage over the portage and take the remaining 6 with me; these are but indifferent horses most of them but I hope they may answer our purposes. I shall leave three of my intended party, (viz ) <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name>, <name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">Frazier</name> and <name type="person" key="Werner, William">Werner</name>, and take the <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph and Reubin">two Feildses</name> and <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name>.    by having two spare horses we can releive those we ride.    having made this arrangement I gave orders for an early departure in the morning, indeed I should have set out instantly but <name type="person" key="McNeal, Hugh">McNeal</name> road one of the horses which I intend to take and has not yet returned.    a little before dark <name type="person" key="McNeal, Hugh">McNeal</name> returned with his musquet broken off at the breech,<ref target="n37071504" n="4"/> and informed me that on his arrival at <name type="place" key="Box Elder Creek (Willow Run)">willow run</name> [<hi rend="italic">NB?: on the portage</hi>] he had approached a white bear within ten feet without discover him the bear being in the thick brush, the horse took the allarm and turning short threw him immediately under the bear; this animal raised himself on his hinder feet for battle, and gave him time to recover from his fall which he did in an instant and with his clubbed musquet he struck the bear over the head and cut him with the guard of the gun<ref target="n37071505" n="5"/> and broke off the breech, the bear stunned with the stroke fell to the ground and began to scratch his head with his feet; this gave <name type="person" key="McNeal, Hugh">McNeal</name> time to climb a willow tree which was near at hand and thus fortunately made his escape.    the bear waited at the foot of the tree untill late in the evening before he left him, when <name type="person" key="McNeal, Hugh">McNeal</name> ventured down and caught his horse which had by this time strayed off to the distance of 2 ms. and returned to camp.    these bear are a most tremenduous animal; it seems that the hand of providence has been most wonderfully in our favor with rispect to them, or some of us would long since have fallen a sacrifice to their farosity.    there seems to be a sertain fatality attatched to the neighbourhood of these falls, for there is always a chapter of accedents prepared for us during our residence at them.    the musquetoes continue to infest us in such manner that we can scarcely exist; for my own part I am confined by them to my bier at least ¾ths of my time.    my dog even howls with the torture he experiences from them, they are always most insupportable, they are so numerous that we frequently get them in our thrats as we breath.—
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-07-15.03" n="lc.geo.1806-07-15.01">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>[July 15, 1806]</date>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <table rows="10" cols="3">
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 45d E.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">3</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">miles to the top of the gap of a mountain passing up on the N<lb/>
W. Side of the branch, Some thick under brush Such as young<lb/>
Cotton wood &amp; W Thorn passing on a plain old buffalow<lb/>
road.    the assent of the mtn. is very gradl.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">East</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">3</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">miles to the top of a dividig ridge between the waters of the<lb/>
                           <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> from those of the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">rochejhone</name> passing down a branch<lb/>
and at 2½ miles Crossed a branch of the <name type="place"
                                 key="Jackson Creek (Middle Branch of East Fork of Gallatin's River)">Middle fork of the<lb/>
East branch of Galitins river</name> about ½ mile above the branch<lb/>
we Came down.    runng to the right</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S 45° E.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">1</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">miles down a Small branch a road Coms in form the left lead-<lb/>
ing over to the Easterly branch.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 75° E</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">8</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Miles to the river <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Rochejhone</name> passing down a branch on the<lb/>
North Side through a kind of vally    Passed 3 Small Streams<lb/>
from the left &amp; one at 6 ms. from the right and Struck the<lb/>
lower 〈one〉 ½ mile below the branch    we Came down &amp;<lb/>
1½ miles below the plain    the river Passes out of the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">rocky<lb/>
mountains</name> high on each Side    bottom in those mountains<lb/>
narrow.    river about 120 yds wide bold and deep    the water<lb/>
of a whiteish blue Colour    a mountan which is ruged N. W<lb/>
has Snow on parts of it. Those above &amp; on the East Side of the<lb/>
river is rugid and covered with Snow    those on the West<lb/>
is also high but have no Snow.    much Dead timber on its<lb/>
N. Side.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                           <hi rend="right">From the gap of the Mtn. river</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">North</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">2</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">miles to a few Cotton under the bank and halted to let our horses<lb/>
graze &amp; Dine.    passed a very Small branch at 〈½〉 a<lb/>
mile below the one we Came down. I marked my 〈the two first<lb/>
letters of〉 my name and the day of the year &amp;c. on one of the<lb/>
Cotton trees with red paint 〈and Cut it in allso.〉 The valley is<lb/>
open and extensive—    watr. 3 ms.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">North</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">1</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">mile Down river to a clump of trees in a gulley    passed Som<lb/>
tall timber killed by fire, Saw a gang of Elk    L.<ref target="n37071506" n="6"/> Killed one<lb/>
psd. an Island    (2½ ms.)</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 15° E</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">4</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">miles to a bend of the at a deep bend to the West    passed two<lb/>
Small runs and a large Isd. on which there was tall treess<lb/>
Several of them would make Small Canoes    Saw a large Gang<lb/>
of Elk feeing on an Isld    main Chanel on the E. Side    Passed<lb/>
11 Islands the 2 last of them large the others Small    (6 ms)</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 30° E</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">2</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">miles to the Enterans of [<hi rend="italic">blank</hi>] river<ref target="n37071507" n="7"/>   35 yds wide boald<lb/>
Current &amp; Deep from the N W    much timber on the Creek &amp;<lb/>
beaver    passed Several Islands Small    road forks one Cross-<lb/>
ing this R about a Mile about its mouh    the other passing<lb/>
over a high rocky hill below the Creek    (2½)</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 50° E.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">3</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">miles    river passing under a high hill rocky &amp; Steep on the N<lb/>
W Side, an extensive low bottom opposit in which I Saw 3<lb/>
gangues of Elk.    passd Several Small Islands and Encamped<lb/>
on the bank of the river opposit to an Island    (5)</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-07-15.04" n="lc.geo.1806-07-15.01">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Tuesday 15th July 1806</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
we collected our horses and after an early brackft at 8 A M Set out and proceeded up the branch to the head    thence over a low gap in the mountain    thence across the heads of the <name type="place" key="East Gallatin River (East Fork Gallatin's River)">N E. branch of the [<hi rend="italic">NB: Easterly</hi>]<ref target="n37071508" n="8"/> fork of Gallitins river</name> which we Camped near last night passing over a low dividing ridge to the head of a water Course which runs into the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Rochejhone</name>, prosueing an old buffalow road which enlargenes by one which joins it from the most <name type="place" key="East Gallatin River (East Fork Gallatin's River)">Easterly [<hi rend="italic">NB: Northerly</hi>] branch of the Gallatin River East fork of Galetins R.</name>
                  <ref target="n37071509" n="9"/> proceeding down the branch a little to the N. of East keeping on the North Side of the branch to the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">River <hi rend="italic">rochejhone</hi>
                  </name> at which place I arrived at 2 P M.<ref target="n37071510" n="10"/> The Distance from the three forks of the <name type="place" key="East Gallatin River (East Fork Gallatin's River)">Easterly fork of Galletines river</name> (from whence it may be navigated down with Small Canoes) to the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">river Rochejhone</name> is 18 miles on an excellent high dry firm road with very incoiderable hills.    from this river to the nearest part of the main fork of <name type="place" key="Gallatin (South, Southeast Fork) River">Gallitine</name> is 29 miles mostly through a leavel plain.    from the head of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Three Forks of the">Missouri at the 3 forks</name> 48 miles through a leavel plain the most of the way as may be seen by the remarks</p>
               <p>
                  <table rows="10" cols="3">
                     <head>Course Distance &amp; Remarks from the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Three Forks of the">Three forks of Missouri</name> to the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">River<lb/>
Rochejhone</name> where it enters the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky Mounts.</name>
                        <ref target="n37071511" n="11"/>
                     </head>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S 85° E</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  6</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Miles through an open plain crossing a ridge to <name type="place" key="Gallatin (South, Southeast Fork) River">galletines<lb/>
river</name>, it haveing made a bend to the S W.    campd.    the hill<lb/>
Sides over which we passed contain a hard white rock which<lb/>
lies in an inclined position and shows only in Stratus.<ref target="n37071512" n="12"/> Several<lb/>
roads leading to a Gap in the mountain to my left.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S 78° E.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  6</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Miles to a part of the river which is divided by numbers of<lb/>
beaver dams on one channel of the    river.    passed through<lb/>
an open leavel butifull plain covered with low grass.    river<lb/>
makeing a bend to the N. E. from the place I crossed it this<lb/>
morning.    passed numbers of buffalow roads which do not<lb/>
appear to be very old leading to the before mentioned gap.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 70° E.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  6</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Miles to the main principal Stream of the river which we<lb/>
crossed having crossed Several Streams near the Crossing.    a<lb/>
leavel firm plain on the Island.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 78° E.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">12</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Miles to the most Southerly of the three easterly branches of<lb/>
the <name type="place" key="East Gallatin River (East Fork Gallatin's River)">Easterly fork of Galletines river</name>.    passed through an<lb/>
open leavel plain in which there is three Small Streams of<lb/>
water from the <name type="place" key="Gallatin Range">Snow Mountains</name> to the South.<ref target="n37071513" n="13"/> Great quan-<lb/>
tities of Snow yet remains on the Mountains to the S. E South,<lb/>
S W. West, and at a distance to the N W.    a very small quan-<lb/>
tity is also to be Seen on a nacked mountain to the East<lb/>
marked my W. C July 14th 1806 with powder on a Cotton tree<lb/>
at the river.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 80° E.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  3</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Miles to the enterance of a Small branch which falls into the<lb/>
                           <name type="place"
                                 key="Jackson Creek (Middle Branch of East Fork of Gallatin's River)">Middle branch of the East fork of Galletine River</name> having<lb/>
Crossed the middle branch at 2 miles, passed great numbers<lb/>
of beaver dams and ponds on the branch, and encamped.<lb/>
here the mountain forms a kind of half circle in which the<lb/>
three branches enter them.    from which the mountains ap-<lb/>
pear to run N W. from one extremity and W. from the othr</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 45° E</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  3</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Miles to the top of the mountain in a low gap passing up the<lb/>
branch on which we encamped last night, on a well beaten<lb/>
buffalow road, through Some thick under growth Such as<lb/>
young Cottonwood &amp; thorn. Several beaver dams across this<lb/>
branch.    the assent gradual.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">East</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  3</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Miles to the top of the dividing ridge between the waters of<lb/>
the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> from those of the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">river Rochehone</name>.    passing<lb/>
down a Small branch and at 2½ miles crossing a larger branch<lb/>
of the <name type="place"
                                 key="Jackson Creek (Middle Branch of East Fork of Gallatin's River)">middle fork of the East fork of Galletins</name> about ½ a Mile<lb/>
above the branch I came down, running to the right    a road<lb/>
coms in from the left, which passes through a low gap of the<lb/>
mtn. from the most easterly branch of the East fork.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 45° E.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  1</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Mile down a Small branch crossed two runs from the left<ref target="n37071514" n="14"/>
                           <lb/>
passing on the hill Side to the left of the branch.    the road<lb/>
firm and through an open country.    high mountains on each<lb/>
side partially Covered with pine.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 75° E</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                           <hi rend="underline">  8</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Miles to the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">River Rochejhone</name> passing down on the Northerly<lb/>
side of the Same branch across which there is Several beaver<lb/>
dams. Crossed three Small Streams from the left with running<lb/>
water one of which is crouded with beaver dams.<ref target="n37071515" n="15"/>    a Small<lb/>
stream coms in on the right at 6 ms.<ref target="n37071516" n="16"/> Struck the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Rochejhone</name>
                           <lb/>
½ a mile below the branch we came down &amp; 1½ ms. below<lb/>
where it passed out of the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky mountains</name>.    river 120 yds<lb/>
wide bold, rapid and deep.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                           <hi rend="right">ms.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">48</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>
in the evening after the usial delay of 3 hours to give the horses time to feed and rest and allowing our Selves time also to Cook and eate Dinner, I proceeded on down the river on an old buffalow road    at the distance of 9 miles below the mountains <name type="place" key="Shields River">Shield River</name>
                  <ref target="n37071517" n="17"/> discharges itself into the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Rochejhone</name> on it's N W. side above a high rocky Clift, this river is 35 yards wide deep and affords a great quantity of water    it heads in those <name type="place" key="Gallatin Range">Snowey Mountains</name> to the N W with <name type="place" key="Sixteenmile (Howard's) Creek">Howards Creek</name>,<ref target="n37071518" n="18"/> it contains some Timber Such as Cotton &amp; willow in it's bottoms, and Great numbers of beaver    the river also abounds in those animals as far as I have Seen. passed the creek and over a high rocky hill and encamped in the upper part of a large bottom.<ref target="n37071519" n="19"/> The horses <hi rend="italic">feet</hi> are very sore many of them Can Scercely proceed on over the Stone and gravel<ref target="n37071520" n="20"/> in every other respect they are Sound and in good Sperits. I saw two black bear on the side of the mountains this morning. Several gangs of Elk from 100 to 200 in a gangue on the river, great numbers of Antelopes.    one Elk only killed to day.</p>
               <p>
The <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Roche</name> passed out of a high rugid mountain covered with Snow.<ref target="n37071521" n="21"/> the bottoms are narrow within the mountains but widen from ½ a m. to 2 ms. in the Vally below, those bottoms are Subject to over flow, they contain Some tall Cotton wood, and willow rose bushes &amp; rushes Honey suckle &amp;c.    a Second bottom on the N E. Side which rises to about 20 feet    higher the first &amp; is 1 m. wide    this bottom is coars gravel pebils &amp; Sand with Some earth<ref target="n37071522" n="22"/> on which the grass grow very Short and at this time is quit dry    this 2d bottom over flows in high floods<ref target="n37071523" n="23"/>    on the opposit Side of the river the plain is much higher and extendes quite to the foot of the mountain. The mountains to the S. S. E on the East side of the river is rocky rugid and on them are great quantities of Snow.<ref target="n37071524" n="24"/>    a bold Snow mountain which bears East<ref target="n37071525" n="25"/> &amp; is imediately at &amp; N W of the 3 forks of the <name type="place" key="East Gallatin River (East Fork Gallatin's River)">East fork of Gallitins river</name> may be Seen, there is also a high rugid Mtn. on which is Snow bearing North 15 or 20 miles.<ref target="n37071526" n="26"/>    but fiew flowers to be Seen in those plains.    low grass in the high plains, and the Common corse grass, rushes and a species of rye<ref target="n37071527" n="27"/> is the growth of the low bottoms.    the mountains have Some scattering pine on them, and on the Spurs and hill Sides there is some scrubby pine. I can See no timber Sufficient large for a Canoe which will Carry more than 3 men and Such a one would be too Small to answer my purpose
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-07-15.05" n="lc.geo.1806-07-15.01">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Tuesday 15th July 1806.    a fair morning.    we Set out at light and proceed on verry well    overtook <name type="person" key="Collins, John">Collins</name> who had killed three deer    about 9 A. M. we halted for breakfast &amp; <name type="person" key="Collins, John">Collins</name> killed a fat buck &amp; <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">P. Cruzatte</name> killed a goat or antelope.    we proced. on verry well    the currents are common &amp; ripe. <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name> killed a panther a deer and a rattle Snake.    in the evening we Camped in the mountains. <name type="person" key="Collins, John">Collins</name> killed 4 Elk.    the Musquetoes verry troublesom in deed.—

</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-07-15.06" n="lc.geo.1806-07-15.02">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Tuesday 15th.</hi>    We had pleasant weather. One of our men<ref target="n37071528" n="28"/> started to go down to the other end of the portage, to see if the periogue was safe, which we had left there; and, in the afternoon, the man<ref target="n37071529" n="29"/> who had gone after the horses returned unsuccessful; but as he saw some fresh Indian signs he supposes they were stolen and taken back over the dividing ridge.<ref target="n37071530" n="30"/>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name> therefore concluded to take fewer men and horses with him than he had intended on his excursion up <name type="place" key="Marias River">Maria's river</name>. In the evening, the man<ref target="n37071531" n="31"/> who had started to go to the other end of the portage, returned without being there. A white bear met him at <name type="place" key="Box Elder Creek (Willow Run)">Willow creek</name>, that so frightened his horse that he threw him off among the feet of the animal; but he fortunately (being too near to shoot) had sufficient presence of mind to hit the bear on the head with his gun; and the stroke so stunned it, that it gave him time to get up a tree close by before it could seize him. The blow, however, broke the gun and rendered it useless; and the bear watched him about three hours and went away; when he came down, caught his horse about two miles distant, and returned to camp. These bears are very numerous in this part of the country and very dangerous, as they will attack a man every oportunity.



</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n37071501" n="1">The last entry in Codex La. After <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> writing, and at right angles to it, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> has added, "a part of M. L. notes to Come into the book No. 12—after the 4' July." The word "after" may be Coues's insertion. "No. 12" would be Codex L in <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle's</name> numbering system, and the meaning is that Codex La fits into the gap in Codex L. Coues has continued <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> sentence with these words: "where ten blank leaves were left by M. L. for the insertion of this matter. Dec. 20, 1892. Coues." See <ref n="lc.jrn.v02.appendix.c" type="related">Appendix C</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37071502" n="2">The "lower portage camp" on the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, in <name type="place" key="Chouteau County, Mont.">Chouteau County</name>, <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>, below the mouth of <name type="place" key="Belt (Portage) Creek">Belt creek</name>; see <ref n="lc.jrn.1805-06-16" type="related">June 16, 1805</ref>. It appears as the camp of June 16–29, 1805, on <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> maps 42, 54, and 61.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37071503" n="3">Codex L resumes on this date; see <ref n="lc.jrn.1805-07-04" type="related">July 4, 1806</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37071504" n="4">Presumably the U.S. Model 1795 musket, caliber .69; obviously it was not designed for the use to which <name type="person" key="McNeal, Hugh">McNeal</name> put it. Russell (GEF), 150–57; Russell (FTT), 36–37.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37071505" n="5">Probably the trigger guard.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37071506" n="6">"L." is probably <name type="person" key="Labiche, François">François Labiche</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37071507" n="7">
               <name type="place" key="Shields River">Shields River</name>, see below.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37071508" n="8">
               <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name> added bracketes around <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> words "N E. branch of the" and interlined his word above it, all in red ink.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37071509" n="9">
               <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> went easterly up <name type="place" key="Kelly Creek">Kelly Creek</name>, then crossed <name type="place"
                     key="Jackson Creek (Middle Branch of East Fork of Gallatin's River)">Jackson Creek</name> and went through <name type="place" key="Bozeman Pass">Bozeman Pass</name> in the <name type="place" key="Bridger Range">Bridger Range</name>, passing from <name type="place" key="Gallatin County, Mont.">Gallatin County</name> to <name type="place" key="Park County, Mont.">Park County</name>, <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>. The route is clearly marked on <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> maps 106 and 113.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37071510" n="10">He went east down the north side of <name type="place" key="Billman Creek">Billman Creek</name>, reaching the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone River</name> at present <name type="place" key="Livingston, Mont.">Livingston</name> in <name type="place" key="Park County, Mont.">Park County</name>. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> maps 106, 107, 113.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37071511" n="11">Here in Codex M <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> inserts his cumulative courses and distances from the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Three Forks of the">Three Forks</name> to the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone</name> for July 13–15, 1806.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37071512" n="12">The strata of hard, white, rock lying in an inclined position was the limestone observed on <ref n="lc.jrn.1806-07-13" type="related">July 13, 1806</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37071513" n="13">
               <name type="place" key="Hyalite Creek">Hyalite</name>, <name type="place" key="McDonald Creek">McDonald</name>, and <name type="place" key="Baxter Creek">Baxter creeks</name>, in <name type="place" key="Gallatin County, Mont.">Gallatin County</name> west of <name type="place" key="Bozeman, Mont.">Bozeman</name>, coming from the <name type="place" key="Gallatin Range">Gallatin Mountains</name>; nameless on <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> maps 106, 113.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37071514" n="14">
               <name type="place" key="Quinn Creek">Quinn Creek</name> and an unnamed stream in <name type="place" key="Park County, Mont.">Park County</name>. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> maps 106, 113.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37071515" n="15">
               <name type="place" key="Flynn Creek">Flynn Creek</name>, <name type="place" key="Area Creek">Area Creek</name>, and an unnamed stream, all in <name type="place" key="Park County, Mont.">Park County</name>. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> maps 106, 113.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37071516" n="16">
               <name type="place" key="Miner Creek">Miner Creek</name> in <name type="place" key="Park County, Mont.">Park County</name>. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> maps 106, 113.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37071517" n="17">After <name type="person" key="Shields, John">John Shields</name> of the party; unlike so many streams the captain named for members of the Corps of Discovery, <name type="place" key="Shields River">Shields River</name>, which meets the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone</name> in <name type="place" key="Park County, Mont.">Park County</name> a few miles northeast of <name type="place" key="Livingston, Mont.">Livingston</name> and west of <name type="place" key="Sheep Mountain">Sheep Mountain</name>, retains the same name today. It is named on <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 106 but not on map 113.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37071518" n="18">
               <name type="place" key="Shields River">Shields River</name> heads in the <name type="place" key="Crazy Mountains">Crazy Mountains</name> in northern <name type="place" key="Park County, Mont.">Park County</name>; near there is the head of <name type="place" key="Sixteenmile (Howard's) Creek">Sixteenmile Creek</name>, the captains' <name type="place" key="Sixteenmile (Howard's) Creek">Howard's Creek</name>, which flows west to meet the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri River</name> in <name type="place" key="Gallatin County, Mont.">Gallatin County</name>. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 64.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37071519" n="19">
               <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> camped on the north side of the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone River</name> in <name type="place" key="Park County, Mont.">Park County</name>, just south of <name type="place" key="Sheep Mountain">Sheep Mountain</name> and some three miles below the mouth of <name type="place" key="Shields River">Shields River</name>. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> maps 106, 107, 113.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37071520" n="20">The gravel likely was both alluvium and slopewash deposits that cap the lower terrace on the northwest side of the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone River</name>. The stone may be either the larger cobbles in those deposits or the blocky-weathering, Tertiary-Cretaceous <name type="place" key="Livingston Formation">Livingston Formation</name> over which <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> party passed just before making camp.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37071521" n="21">From where <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> viewed it the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone</name> emerged from between the <name type="place" key="Gallatin Range">Gallatin Range</name> on the west and the <name type="place" key="Absaroka Range">Absaroka Range</name> on the east. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> maps 106, 113.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37071522" n="22">This terrace is actually on the northwest side of the river. Although the most conspicuous components of the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone</name> terrace deposits are gravel and cobbles, sand- and silt-sized materials make up more than half the deposits.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37071523" n="23">It was probably <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name> who drew a red line through this sentence to strike it out.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37071524" n="24">The <name type="place" key="Absaroka Range">Absaroka Range</name> and the <name type="place" key="Beartooth Mountains">Beartooth Mountains</name> to the east of them.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37071525" n="25">This is impossible from <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> position on the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone</name>, but if he means "west," then <name type="place" key="Saddle Peak">Saddle Peak</name> in the <name type="place" key="Bridger Range">Bridger Range</name> could be the mountain.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37071526" n="26">The <name type="place" key="Crazy Mountains">Crazy Mountains</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37071527" n="27">
               <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> has returned to the shortgrass prairie of the high plains east of the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky Mountains</name>, which is dominated by blue grama, <hi rend="italic">Bouteloua gracilis</hi> (HBK.) Lag., buffalograss, <hi rend="italic">Buchloe dactyloides</hi> (Nutt.) Engelm., and a variety of other species. The rye is probaly basin wildrye, <hi rend="italic">Elymus cinereus</hi> Scribn. &amp; Merrill. Fernald, 182, 184; Mueggler &amp; Stewart.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37071528" n="28">
               <name type="person" key="McNeal, Hugh">McNeal</name>, says <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37071529" n="29">
               <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37071530" n="30">That is, taken back west of the <name type="place" key="Continental Divide">Continental Divide</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37071531" n="31">
               <name type="person" key="McNeal, Hugh">McNeal</name>.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-07-14" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-07-16" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
