<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-08-11">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
August 11, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               
               
               
               
               
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml" n="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc" n="Clark, William">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 8</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">June 10–September 26, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1987</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">154-157, 288-289</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo" n="Ordway, John">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf" n="Floyd, Charles">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">347-348</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg" n="Gass, Patrick">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">265</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
         <geoDecl datum="WGS" xml:id="lc.geo.1806-08-11.01">
            <placeName/>
            <geo>48.3 -102.3</geo>
            <note>Clark camped on the present Little Knife River, Mountrail County, ND, which the party had passed on 1805-04-15. </note>
         </geoDecl>
         <geoDecl datum="WGS" xml:id="lc.geo.1806-08-11.02">
            <placeName/>
            <geo>48.1465 -102.7815</geo>
            <note>The party camped in southwestern Mountrail County, ND, a little above the mouth of present White Earth River.</note>
         </geoDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Journal Entries</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-12-09</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1806-08-11">August 11, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-08-11.01" n="lc.geo.1806-08-11.02">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Monday August 11th 1806.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
We set out very early this morning.    it being my wish to arrive at the <name type="place" key="Crow Hills">birnt hills</name>
                  <ref target="n37081101" n="1"/> by noon in order to take the latitude of that place as it is the most northern point of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, enformed the party of my design and requested that they would exert themselves to reach the place in time as it would save us the delay of nearly one day; being as anxious to get forward as I was they plyed their oars faithfully and we proceeded rapidly. I had instructed the small [c]anoes that if they saw any game on the river to halt and kill it and follow on; however we saw but little game untill about 9 A. M. when we came up with a buffaloe swiming the river which I shot and killed; leaving the small canoes to dress it and bring on the meat I proceeded.    we had gone but little way before I saw a very large grizzly bear and put too in order to kill it, but it took wind of us and ran off.    the small canoes overtook us and informed that the flesh of the buffaloe was unfit for uce and that they had therefore left it    half after 11 A. M. we saw a large herd of Elk on the N. E. shore and I directed the men in the small canoes to halt and kill some of them and continued on in the perogue to the <name type="place" key="Crow Hills">birnt hills</name>; when I arrived here it was about 20 minutes after noon and of course the observation for the <seg n="u9737">☉</seg>'s meridian Altitude was lost; jus opposite to the <name type="place" key="Crow Hills">birnt hills</name> there happened to be a herd of Elk on a thick willow bar and finding that my observation was lost for the present I determined to land and kill some of them    accordingly we put too and I went out with <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Cruzatte</name> only.<ref target="n37081102" n="2"/>    we fired on the Elk I killed one and he wounded another, we reloaded our guns and took different routs through the thick willows in pursuit of the Elk; I was in the act of firing on the Elk a second time when a ball struck my left thye about an inch below my hip joint, missing the bone it passed through the left thye and cut the thickness of the bullet across the hinder part of the right thye; the stroke was very severe; I instantly supposed that <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Cruzatte</name> had shot me in mistake for an Elk as I was dressed in brown leather and he cannot see very well; under this impression I called out to him damn you, you have shot me, and looked towards the place from whence the ball had come, seeing nothing I called <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Cruzatte</name> several times as loud as I could but received no answer; I was now preswaded that it was an indian that had shot me as the report of the gun did not appear to be more than 40 paces from me and <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Cruzatte</name> appeared to be out of hearing of me; in this situation not knowing how many indians there might be concealed in the bushes I thought best to make good my retreat to the perogue, calling out as I ran for the first hundred paces as loud as I could to <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Cruzatte</name> to retreat that there were indians hoping to allarm him in time to make his escape also; I still retained the charge in my gun which I was about to discharge at the moment the ball struck me.    when I arrived in sight of the perogue I called the men to their arms to which they flew in an instant, I told them that I was wounded but I hoped not mortally, by an indian I beleived and directed them to follow me that I would return &amp; give them battle and releive <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Cruzatte</name> if possible who I feared had fallen into their hands; the men followed me as they were bid and I returned about a hundred paces when my wounds became so painfull and my thye so stiff that I could scarcely get on; in short I was compelled to halt and ordered the men to proceed and if they found themselves overpowered by numbers to retreat in order keeping up a fire. I now got back to the perogue as well as I could and prepared my self with a pistol my rifle and air-gun being determined as a retreat was impracticable to sell my life as deerly as possible.    in this state of anxiety and suspense remained about 20 minutes when the party returned with <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Cruzatte</name> and reported that there were no indians nor the appearance of any; <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Cruzatte</name> seemed much allarmed and declared if he had shot me it was not his intention, that he had shot an Elk in the willows after he left or seperated from me. I asked him whether he did not hear me when I called to him so frequently which he absolutely denied. I do not beleive that the fellow did it intentionally but after finding that he had shot me was anxious to conceal his knowledge of having done so.<ref target="n37081103" n="3"/>    the ball had lodged in my breeches which I knew to be the ball of the short rifles such as that he had,<ref target="n37081104" n="4"/> and there being no person out with me but him and no indians that we could discover I have no doubt in my own mind of his having shot me.    with the assistance of <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Sergt. Gass</name> I took off my cloaths and dressed my wounds myself as well as I could, introducing tents of patent lint into the ball holes,<ref target="n37081105" n="5"/> the wounds blead considerably but I was hapy to find that it had touched neither bone nor artery. I sent the men to dress the two Elk which <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Cruzatte</name> and myself had killed which they did in a few minutes and brought the meat to the river.    the small canoes came up shortly after with the flesh of one Elk.    my wounds being so situated that I could not without infinite pain make an observation I determined to relinquish it and proceeded on.    we came within eight miles of our encampment of the 15th of April 1805 and encamped on N. E. side.<ref target="n37081106" n="6"/>    as it was painfull to me to be removed I slept on board the perogue; the pain I experienced excited a high fever and I had a very uncomfortable night.    at 4 P. M. we passed an encampment which had been evacuated this morning by <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name>, here I found a note from <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. C.</name> informing me that he had left a letter for me at the entrance of the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yelow stone river</name>, but that <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Sergt. Pryor</name> who had passed that place since he left it had taken the letter; that <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Sergt. Pryor</name> having been robed of all his horses had decended the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yelowstone river</name> in skin canoes and had over taken him at this encampment.    this I fear puts an end to our prospects of obtaining the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name> Cheifs to accompany us as we have not now leasure to send and enjage <name type="person" key="Heney, Hugh">Mr. Heney</name> on this service, or at least he would not have time to engage them to go as early as it is absolutely necessary we should decend the river.
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-08-11.02" n="lc.geo.1806-08-11.01">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Wednesday 11th August 1806</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
I set out early this morning.    at 10 A. M. landed on a Sand bar and brackfast dureing brackfast and my delay at this place which was 2 hours had the Elk meat exposed to the Sun.    at Meridian I set out and had not proceeded more than 2 miles before I observed a Canoe near the Shore. I derected the Canoes to land here I found two men from the <name type="place" key="Illinois">illinoies</name>
                  <name type="person" key="Dickson, Joseph">Jos. Dixon</name>, and [<hi rend="italic">blank</hi>] <name type="person" key="Hancock, Forrest">Handcock</name>
                  <ref target="n37081107" n="7"/>    those men are on a trapping expedition up the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">River Rochejhone</name>. They inform me that they left the <name type="place" key="Illinois">Illinois</name> in the Summer 1804.    the last winter they Spent with the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Tetons</name> in Company with a <name type="person" key="Courtin, Charles">Mr. <hi rend="italic">Coartong</hi> [<hi rend="italic">NB: Qu: Coautoin</hi>
                  </name>]<ref target="n37081108" n="8"/> who brought up goods to trade    The <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">tetons</name> robed him of the greater part of the goods and wounded this <name type="person" key="Dixon, Joseph">Dixon</name> in the leg with a hard wad.<ref target="n37081109" n="9"/> The <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Tetons</name> gave <name type="person" key="Courtin, Charles">Mr. <hi rend="italic">Coartong</hi>
                  </name> Some fiew robes for the articles they took from him. Those men further informed me that they met the Boat and party we Sent down from <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name> near the <name type="place" key="Kansas (Decaugh, Kaw) River">Kanzas river</name> on board of which was a Chief of the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Ricaras</name>,<ref target="n37081110" n="10"/> that he met the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Yankton">Yankton</name> Chiefs with <name type="person" key="Dorion, Pierre, Sr.">Mr. Deurion</name>,<ref target="n37081111" n="11"/>
                  <name type="person" key="McClellan, Robert">McClellen</name>
                  <ref target="n37081112" n="12"/> &amp; Several other traders on their way down.    that the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Menitarrais</name> wer at war with the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Ricaras</name> and had killed two of the latter.    the <name type="native_nation" key="Assiniboine Indians">Assinniboins</name> were also at war with the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name> &amp;c and had prohibited the N W. traders from Comeing to the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> to trade.<ref target="n37081113" n="13"/>    they have latterly killed one Trader near the <name type="place" key="Souris (Mouse) River">Mous River</name>
                  <ref target="n37081114" n="14"/> and are now in wait for <name type="person" key="McKenzie, Charles">Mr. McKenzey</name>
                  <ref target="n37081115" n="15"/> one of the Clerks who have been for a long time with <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Menetarias</name>. Those dificulties if true will I fear be a bar to our expectations of having the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Minetarra</name> &amp; <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Ricara</name> Chief to acompany us to the U. States. Tho we Shall endeaver to bring abot a peace between <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Mennetaries</name> &amp; <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Ricaras</name> and provail on Some of their Cheifs to accompany us to the U. States.    proceeded on to a point on the S W Side nearly opposit the enterance of <name type="place" key="Little Knife River (Goat Pen Creek)">Goat pen creek</name> and encamped<ref target="n37081116" n="16"/>    found the Musquetors excessively troublesom.



</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-08-11.03" n="lc.geo.1806-08-11.02">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Monday 11th August 1806.    a fair morning    we Set out as usal and procd. on verry well    we killed a buffaloe in the river.    about 12 oClock <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name> halted at a bottom on S. Side to kill Some Elk    <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Peter Cruzatte</name> a frenchman went out with <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name> they Soon found a gangue of Elk in a
thicket. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name> killed one and <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">cruzatte</name> killed two, and as he Still kept firing one of his balls hit <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name> in his back side and the ball passed through one Side of his buttock and the ball went out of the other Side of the other buttock and lodged at his overalls which wounded him bad.<ref target="n37081117" n="17"/>    he instantly called to <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">peter</name> but <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Peter</name> not answering he Supposd. it to be Indians and run to the canoes and ordered the men to their armes.    they were in readiness in a moment and <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name> attempd. to go back for battle but being faint the men purswaded him not to go himself but the party run out    found <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Cruzatte</name> and he had Seen no Indians    then <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">peter</name> knew that it must have been him tho an exidant.    we dressed the wound prepared a place for him to lay in the white perogue    <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Jo. Fields</name> killed one Elk.    we then took the best of the meat on board and proced. on    about 4 P. M. we passd. a Camp of <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name>
                  <ref target="n37081118" n="18"/> where we found a note or line informing us that <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Sergt. pryor</name> &amp; party had joined them here as the Indians had Stole all the horses &amp; they came down in leather canoes.    they had left here to day.    we procd. on untill about Sunset and Camped on a Sand beach on Ld Side    high winds.—



</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-08-11.04" n="lc.geo.1806-08-11.02">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Monday 11th.</hi>    The morning was pleasant; and we set out early; passed <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain Clarke's</name> encampment of the night of the 8th instant, and proceeded on to the <name type="place" key="Crow Hills">burnt bluffs</name>, where we saw a gang of elk feeding. The canoes were then sent to shore with a party of men to endeavour to kill some of them; and we proceeded on with the periogue. In about half a mile further we saw another gang; when we halted<ref target="n37081119" n="19"/> and <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Lewis</name> and one of the men<ref target="n37081120" n="20"/> went out after them. In a short time <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Lewis</name> returned wounded and very much alarmed; and ordered us to our arms, supposing he had been shot at by Indians.<ref target="n37081121" n="21"/> Having prepared for an attack, I went out with three men to reconnoitre and examine the bushes, which are very thick at this place, and could see no Indians; but after some time met with the man who went out with <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Lewis</name>, and found on inquiry that he had shot him by accident through the hips, and without knowing it pursued the game.— Having made this discovery we returned to the periogue; examined and dressed <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Lewis's</name> wound; and found the ball, which had lodged in his overalls. The canoes having come down, we proceeded on, after dressing two elk that had been killed at this place, and passed an encampment which <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain Clarke</name> had left in the morning. We found a note here informing us, that the Indians had stolen all the horses which he had sent with a serjeant and party,<ref target="n37081122" n="22"/> from <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellow Stone river</name>, and that the serjeant with the party came down in skin canoes and met him at this place. We then proceeded on some distance, and encamped.

</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n37081101" n="1">The present <name type="place" key="Crow Hills">Crow Hills</name> in southeastern <name type="place" key="Williams County, N. Dak.">Williams County</name>, <name type="place" key="North Dakota">North Dakota</name>, which they had passed on <ref n="lc.jrn.1805-04-17" type="related">April 17, 1805</ref>. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 34; MRC map 58.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37081102" n="2">This area in <name type="place" key="McKenzie County, N. Dak.">McKenzie County</name>, <name type="place" key="North Dakota">North Dakota</name>, opposite the <name type="place" key="Crow Hills">Crow Hills</name>, would now be inundated by <name type="place" key="Garrison Reservoir">Garrison Reservoir</name>. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 34; MRC map 58.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37081103" n="3">Both <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> and <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name> seem to believe that <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Cruzatte</name> was entirely ignorant of having shot <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>; see their entries for this day.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37081104" n="4">The .54 caliber Model 1803 rifle.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37081105" n="5">As noted in another instance on <ref n="lc.jrn.1806-05-05" type="related">May 5, 1806</ref>, the tents were rolls of lint used to keep the wound open to allow new tissue to grow from the inside out and promote drainage. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> was fortunate to escape serious infection. Cutright (LCPN), 285, 324; Chuinard (OOMD), 392–94.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37081106" n="6">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> camped in southwestern <name type="place" key="Mountrail County, N. Dak.">Mountrail County</name>, <name type="place" key="North Dakota">North Dakota</name>, a little above the mouth of present <name type="place" key="Little Muddy (White Earth) River">White Earth River</name>. The site would now be inundated by <name type="place" key="Garrison Reservoir">Garrison Reservoir</name>. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 34; MRC map 57.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37081107" n="7">For <name type="person" key="Dickson, Joseph">Dickson</name> and <name type="person" key="Hancock, Forrest">Hancock</name> see <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> entry for <ref n="lc.jrn.1806-08-12" type="related">August 12, 1806</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37081108" n="8">This could be <name type="person" key="Courtin, Charles">Charles Courtin</name>, whom the party apparently met on <ref n="lc.jrn.1806-09-14" type="related">September 14, 1806</ref>. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> may have added his name here and below to blank spaces. See also <ref n="lc.jrn.1804-08-02" type="related">August 2</ref> and <ref n="lc.jrn.1804-09-15" type="related">September 15, 1804</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37081109" n="9">A plug or patch of leather, paper, or other material might be used to pack the ball in a muzzle-loading rifle or musket more tightly. Somehow <name type="person" key="Dickson, Joseph">Dickson</name> was struck by one of these instead of a ball, hard enough to cause some injury.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37081110" n="10">The party sent back in the keelboat under <name type="person" key="Warfington, Richard">Corporal Richard Warfington</name>; see <ref n="lc.jrn.1805-04-07" type="related">April 7, 1805</ref>. For the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> chief, see <ref n="lc.jrn.1804-10-09" type="related">October 9, 1804</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37081111" n="11">For <name type="person" key="Dorion, Pierre, Jr.">Pierre Dorion</name> see <ref n="lc.jrn.1804-06-12" type="related">June 12, 1804</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37081112" n="12">For <name type="person" key="McClellan, Robert">Robert McClellan</name> see <ref n="lc.jrn.1806-09-12" type="related">September 12, 1806</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37081113" n="13">For North West Company troubles with the <name type="native_nation" key="Assiniboine Indians">Assinboines</name> in 1805, see Wood &amp; Thiessen, 162, 199, 242.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37081114" n="14">The <name type="place" key="Souris (Mouse) River">Souris River</name> in <name type="place" key="Saskatchewan">Saskatchewan</name>, <name type="place" key="North Dakota">North Dakota</name>, and <name type="place" key="Manitoba">Manitoba</name>; see <ref n="lc.jrn.1804-12-26" type="related">December 26, 1804</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37081115" n="15">
               <name type="person" key="McKenzie, Charles">Charles McKenzie</name> of the North West Company; see <ref n="lc.jrn.1804-12-27" type="related">November 27, 1804</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37081116" n="16">"<name type="place" key="Little Knife River (Goat Pen Creek)">Goat pen Creek</name>," which the party passed going west on April 15, 1805, is the present <name type="place" key="Little Knife River (Goat Pen Creek)">Little Knife River</name> in <name type="place" key="Mountrail County, N. Dak.">Mountrail County</name>, <name type="place" key="North Dakota">North Dakota</name>. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> camp would have been in <name type="place" key="McKenzie County, N. Dak.">McKenzie County</name>, near where <name type="place" key="North Dakota">North Dakota</name>
               <name type="place" key="North Dakota Highway 23">Highway 23</name> crosses the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>; the site would now be inundated by <name type="place" key="Garrison Reservoir">Garrison Reservoir</name>. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> maps 34, 47, 56; MRC map 56.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37081117" n="17">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> recounts the incident in more detail in his entry for this day.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37081118" n="18">
               <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had been at this camp since August 9 and had left it just this morning. It was
approximately ten miles above <name type="place" key="Tobacco (Hall's Strand) Creek">Tobacco Creek</name>, <name type="place" key="Williams County, N. Dak.">Williams County</name>, <name type="place" key="North Dakota">North Dakota</name>, putting the camp in <name type="place" key="McKenzie County, N. Dak.">McKenzie County</name>; see <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> entry for <ref n="lc.jrn.1806-08-09" type="related">August 9</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37081119" n="19">In an area in <name type="place" key="McKenzie County, N. Dak.">McKenzie County</name>, <name type="place" key="North Dakota">North Dakota</name>, opposite the <name type="place" key="Crow Hills">Crow Hills</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37081120" n="20">
               <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Cruzatte</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37081121" n="21">See <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> account of the incident at this date.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37081122" n="22">
               <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Pryor</name>, accompanied by <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name>, <name type="person" key="Windsor, Richard">Windsor</name>, and <name type="person" key="Hall, Hugh">Hall</name>, left <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> party near <name type="place" key="Billings, Mont.">Billings</name>, 
<name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>, on <ref n="lc.jrn.1806-07-24" type="related">July 24, 1806</ref>, taking an easterly route on horseback toward the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>-<name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> villages on the <name type="place" key="Knife River">Knife River</name> in <name type="place" key="North Dakota">North Dakota</name>. He was to deliver a message to North West Company trader <name type="person" key="Heney, Hugh">Hugh Heney</name>, there or on the <name type="place" key="Assiniboine River">Assiniboine River</name> in <name type="place" key="Canada">Canada</name>, seeking his services. <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Pryor's</name> party lost their horses within a day or two, probably to the <name type="native_nation" key="Crow Indians">Crow Indians</name>. They constructed two bullboats and headed down the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone</name> and the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, overtaking <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> on <ref n="lc.jrn.1806-08-08" type="related">August 8</ref>, in <name type="place" key="McKenzie County, N. Dak.">McKenzie County</name>, <name type="person" key="North Dakota">North Dakota</name>. See <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> account on that date.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-08-10" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-08-12" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
