<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.preface.v08">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">Volume 8 Preface</title>
            <title type="sub"/>
            <author>Gary E. Moulton</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               
               
               
               
               
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition, Volume 8</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">June 10–September 26, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1987</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">vii-viii</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Journal Editorial</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-11-01</date>
            <date/>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>
            <name/>Initial creation Transcribed</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="main">Volume 8 Preface</head>
         
         <div type="preface">
            <p>
Again, this space provides a welcome opportunity to thank the many persons who helped to bring another volume to completion. Their aid, whether friendly advice, scholarly consultation, or financial assistance, made the task less demanding and the way more pleasant. Gladys Watkins Allen (Alton, Illinois), Emilie W. Betts (New York City), Samuel H. Douglas III (Whittier, California), William P. Sherman (Portland, Oregon), Nelson S. Weller (Piedmont, California), and Lyle S. Woodcock ( St. Louis, Missouri) provided financial support to aid the editing of this volume. Finanial aid also came from the National Endowment for the Humanities, an independent federal agency, and from the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Trail Heritage Foundation, whose many members support this endeavor beyond their financial contributions.</p>
            <p>
A special friend of the project has died since publication of the last volume. Robert E. "Bob" Lange was a ceaseless laborer in the service of any cause connected with the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> expedition. He aided this project in countless ways; his unselfish assistance, ready encouragement, and great good will shall be sorely missed and never forgotten.</p>
            <p>
We again benefited from the expert service of librarians and archivists at repositories of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> journals. Beth Carroll-Horrocks, Martin L. Levitt, Martha Harrison, Roy E. Goodman, Edward C. Carter II, and Randolph S. Klein, of the American Philosophical Society, Philadelphia, and Duane R. Sneddeker and Bryan Stephen Thomas of the Missouri Historical Society, <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>, were helpful and gracious during our work at their institutions. Staff, office, and administrative help came from the Center for Great Plains Studies and the project itself at the University of Nebraska–Lincoln. John R. Wunder, Lori L. Gourama, and Linda J. Ratcliffe of the Center, and Thomas W. Dunlay and Doris VanSchooten of the project performed valuable services.</p>
            <p>
The following scholars have been generous with their advice and assistance and have aided the project substantially in the areas of their expertise.</p>
            <p>
BOTANY: Margaret R. Bolick, University of Nebraska–Lincoln; Steven J. Brunsfeld, University of Idaho; A. T. Harrison, Westminster College, Salt Lake City; and Kathleen Young, Lincoln. GEOLOGY: Robert N. Bergantino, Montana Bureau of Mines and Geology, Butta. LINGUISTICS: American Indian linguistic data in the notes were collected by Raymond J. DeMallie, Indiana University, and were provided by the followwing individuals: <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>.</hi> Haruo Aoki, University of California–Berkeley. <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name>.</hi> A. Wesley Jones, Mary College, Bismarck, North Dakota. ZOOLOGY: Frederick P. Baxendale, University of Nebraska–Lincoln, and Lewis T. Nielson, University of Utah (retired) (insects); Patricia Freeman, University of Nebraska–Lincoln (mammals, taxonomy); Anthony Joern, University of Nebraska–Lincoln (grasshoppers); and John D. Lynch, University of Nebraska–Lincoln (fish).</p>
            <p>
For the <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name> segment of the return route, especially for the portion of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> reconnaissance of the <name type="place" key="Marias River">Marias River</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> survey of the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone</name>, we again (as in volume 4) used a set of United States Geological Survey (USGS) maps (1° x 2°, 1:250,000) supplied by Robert N. Bergantino of Butte, Montana. Bergantino carefully plotted the expedition's route, camps, and points of observation on these maps. He also read and commented on our reference notes to <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name> identifications and gave us the benefit of his keen knowledge of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> trip through his state.</p>
            <p>
Of course, none of these persons deserves blame for errors or inadequacies in this volume.


</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
