<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-01-15">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">January 15, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic
        Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            6</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">November 2, 1805–March 22, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1990</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">206-211</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">267</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages"/>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jw">Joseph Whitehouse</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            11</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of Joseph Whitehouse, May 14, 1804–April 2,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1997</date>
               <biblScope type="pages"/>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journal Entries</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-08-09</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-04-12</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1806-01-15">January 15, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-01-15.01" ref="">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Thursday</hi>[
              <hi rend="italic">NB: Wednesday</hi>] 
              <hi rend="italic">January 15th 1806.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>Had a large coat completed out of the skins of the Tiger Cat and those also of a
          small animal
          <ref target="n27011501" n="1"/>about the size of a squirrel not known to me; these
          skins I procured from the Indians who had previously dressed them and formed them into
          robes; it took seven of these robes to complete the coat.    we had determined
          to send out two hunting parties today but it rained so incessantly that we posponed it.
             no occurrence worthy of relation took place today.—</p>
               <p>The implyments used by the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinnooks</name>
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsops</name>
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Cathlamet Indians">Cuth-lah-mahs</name>&amp;c in hunting
          are the gun the bow &amp; arrow, deadfalls,
          <ref target="n27011502" n="2"/>pitts, snares, and spears or gigs; their guns are
          usually of an inferior quality being oald refuse American &amp; brittish Musquits which
          have been repared for this trade. there are some very good peices among them, but they
          are invariably in bad order; they apear not to have been long enouh accustomed to fire
          arms to understand the management of them.    they have no rifles. Their guns
          and amunition they reserve for the Elk, deer and bear, of the two last however there are
          but few in their neighbourhood. they keep their powder in small japaned
          <ref target="n27011503" n="3"/>tin flasks which they obtain with their amunition from
          the traders; when they happen to have no ball or shot, they substitute gravel or peices
          of potmettal, and are insensible of the damage done thereby to their guns. The bow and
          arrow is the most common instrument among them, every man being furnished with them
          whether he has a gun or not; this instrument is imployed indiscriminately in hunting
          every species of anamal on which they subsist. Their bows are extreamly neat and very
          elastic, they are about two and a half feet in length, and two inches in width in the
          center, thence tapering graduly to the extremities where they are half an inch wide
             they are very flat and thin, formed of the heart of the arbor vita or white
          cedar, the back of the bow being thickly covered with sinews of the Elk laid on with a
          gleue which they make from the sturgeon; the string is made of sinues of the Elk also.
             the arrow is formed of two parts usually tho' sometime entire; those formed
          of two parts are unequally divided that part on which the feathers are placed occupyes
          four fifths of it's length and is formed of light white pine reather larger than a
          swan's quill, in the lower extremity of this is a circular mortice secured by sinues
          roled arround it; this mortice receives the one end of the 2nd part which is of a
          smaller size than the first and about five inches long, in the end of this the barb is
          fixed and confined with sinue, this barb is either stone, iron or copper, if metal in
          this form
          <ref target="n27011504" n="4"/>forming at it's point a greater angle than those of any
          other Indians I have observed.    the shorter part of the arrow is of hearder
          woods as are also the whole of the arrow when it is of one piece only.    as
          these people live in a country abounding in ponds lakes &amp;c and frequently hunt in
          their canoes and shoot at fowl and other anamals where the arrow missing its object
          would be lost in the water they are constructed in the manner just discribed in order to
          make them float should they fall in the water, and consequently can again be recovered
          by the hunter; the quiver is usually the skin of a young bear or that of a wolf
          invariably open at the side in stead of the end as the quivers of other Indians
          generally are; this construction appears to answer better for the canoe than if they
          were open at the end only.    maney of the Elk we have killed since we have
          been here, hae been wounded with these arrows, the short piece with the barb remaining
          in the animal and grown up in the flesh.—    the deadfalls and snares are
          employed in taking the wolf
          <ref target="n27011505" n="5"/>the raccoon
          <ref target="n27011506" n="6"/>and fox of which there are a few only.    the
          spear or gig is used to take the sea otter, the common otter, spuck, and beaver.
             their gig consists of two points or barbs and are the same in their
          construction as those discribed before as being common among the Indians on the upper
          part of this river.    their pits are employed in taking the Elk, and of
          course are large and deep, some of them a cube of 12 or 14 feet. these are usually
          placed by the side of a large fallen tree which as well as the pit lye across the roads
          frequented by the Elk.    these pitts are disguised with the slender boughs of
          trees and moss; the unwary Elk in passing the tree precipitates himself into the pitt
          which is sufficiently deep to prevent his escape, and is thus taken.—</p>
               <p>
                  <figure rend="mhs">
                     <p>Arrow, January 15, 1806, Codex J, p. 25 
              <bibl>
                           <orgName>Missouri Historical Society</orgName>
                        </bibl>
                     </p>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-01-15.02" ref="">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Friday</hi>[Wednesday] 
              <hi rend="italic">15th of January 1806</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name>had a large Coat finished
          made of the Skins of the tiger Cat, and those of the Small animal about the Size of
          Small Cat not known to me; those Skins were precured from the Indians who had previously
          dressed them and formed them into robes; it took Seven of those robes to Complete the
          Coat.    no occurrence worthey of remark took place. rained hard all day. The
          imployments used by the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinnooks</name>
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsops</name>, 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Cathlamet Indians">Cath lah mahs</name>
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Tillamook Indians">Kil a mox</name>&amp;c. in hunting
          are the gun the bow &amp; arrow, dead falls, Pitts, Snares, and Spears or gigs; their
          guns are usially of an inferior quallity being old refuse american or brittish muskets
          which have been repared for this trade there are Some verry good pieces among them, but
          they are invariably in bad order they appear not to be long enough acquainted with fire
          arms to understand the management of them.    They have no rifles.
             Their guns and amunition they reserve for the Elk, Deer, and Bear, of the
          two last however there are but fiew in their neighbourhoods.    they keep
          their powder in Small japened tin flasks which they obtain with their amunition from the
          traders; when they happen to have no Ball or Shot they Substitute Gravel and are
          insenceable of the dammage done thereby to their Guns.</p>
               <p>
                  <figure rend="aps">
                     <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">Arrow,</hi>January 15, 1806, Codex I, p. 119 
              <bibl>
                           <orgName>(American Philosophical Society library,</orgName>
                           <note place="inline">used with permission.)</note>
                        </bibl>
                     </p>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>The Bow and arrow is the most common instrement among them, every man being furnished
          with them whether he has a gun or not, this instrement is imployed indiscreminately in
          hunting every Species of animal on which they Subsist, Their bows are extreemly meet
          [neat]    and very elastic, they are about two feet Six inches long and two
          inches wide in the Center, thence tapering gradually to the extremities, where they ar ¾
          of an Inch wide, they are very flat and thin, formed of the heart of the arbor vita or
          white Cedar, the back of the Bow being thickly Covered with Sinues of the Elk laid on
          with a Gleue which they make from the Sturgeon; the String is made of the Sinues of the
          Elk also, the arrow is formed of two parts usually tho' Sometimes entire; those formed
          of 2 parts are uneaquilly devided, the part on which the feathers are placed occupie 
          <seg n="u8536">⅘</seg>of it's length and is formed of light white pine rather larger
          than a Swans quill, in the lower extremity of this is a Circular mortice Secured by
          Sinues raped around it; this mortice recives the one end of the 2d part which is of
          Smaller Size than the first and about five inches long, in the end of this the barb is
          fixed and Confined with Sinues, the berb is either Iron Copper or Stone—    in
          this form
          <ref target="n27011507" n="7"/>forming at its point a great angle than those of any
          other Indians I have observed. The Shorter part of the arrow is of harder wood, as are
          also the whole of the arrow where it is of one piece only.    as these people
          live in a Countrey abounding in Ponds lakes &amp;c. and frequently hunt in their Canoes
          and Shoot at fowls and other animals where the arrow missing its object would be lost in
          the water they are constructed in the manner just discribed in order to make them flote
          Should they fall in the water, and Consequently Can again be recovered by the hunter;
          the quiver is useally the Skin of a young bear or that of a wolf invariably open at the
          Side in Sted of the end, as the quiver of other Indians generally are, this Construction
          appears to answer better for the Canoe, than if they were open at the end only.
             maney of the Elk which our hunters have killd. Sence we have been here have
          been wounded with those arrows, the Short piece with the barbe remaining in the Animal
          and grown up in the flesh.—    the Deadfalls &amp; Snares are employd in
          takeing the Wolf, the racoon and fox of which there are a fiew. the Spear or gig is used
          to take the Sea otter, [
          <hi rend="italic">NB?: or</hi>] 
          <hi rend="italic">Spuck,</hi>[
          <hi rend="italic">NB?: Ind. name</hi>] &amp; Beaver. The gig consists of two points or
          birbs and are the Same in their Construction as those which are Common among the Indians
          on the upper part of this river and before discribed. Their pitts are employed in
          takeing the Elk, and of Course are large and Deep, Some of them a Cube of 12 or 14 feet,
          those ar commonly placed by the Side of a large fallen tree which as well as the pitt
          lie across the roads frequented by the Elk, these pitts are disguised with the Slender
          bows of trees &amp; moss: the unwarry Elk in passing the tree precipates himself into
          the pitt which is Sufficiently deep to prevent his escape.—</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-01-15.03" ref="">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>Wednesday 15th    rained hard the greater part of the day.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n27011501" n="1">Perhaps the mountain beaver, a gopherlike rodent. See
        below, 
        <ref n="1806-02-16" type="related">February 26, 1806</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n27011502" n="2">A trap constructed so that a weight falls on the animal and
        kills or disables it.</note>
            <note xml:id="n27011503" n="3">Covered with a hard, brilliant varnish.</note>
            <note xml:id="n27011504" n="4">Here a drawing of the arrow (fig. 15) in 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>Codex J, p. 25.</note>
            <note xml:id="n27011505" n="5">Gray wolf, 
        <hi rend="italic">Canis lupus.</hi>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="n27011506" n="6">Raccoon, 
        <hi rend="italic">Procyon lotor.</hi>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="n27011507" n="7">Another drawing of the arrow (fig. 16) in 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>Codex I, p. 119.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-01-14" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-01-15-16" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
