<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.introduction.v06">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">Introduction to Volume 6</title>
            <title type="sub">November 2, 1805-March 22, 1806</title>
            <author>Gary E. Moulton</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic
        Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            6</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">November 2, 1805–March 22, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1990</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">1-4</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Journal Editorial</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-07-16</date>
            <date/>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>
            <name/>Initial creation Transcribed</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-04-12</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="main">Introduction to Volume 6
      <lb/>
            <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Cascades (Great Rapids, Great Shute)">Cascades of
      Columbia River</name>, 
      <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>-
      <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>, through Winter at 
      <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name>, 
      <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>
         </head>
         <head type="sub">November 2, 1805–March 22, 1806</head>
         <div type="introduction">
            <p>Below the 
        <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Cascades (Great Rapids, Great Shute)">Cascades of
        the Columbia River</name>the Corps of Discovery passed into yet another natural region,
        the thick rain forest of the Northwest Coast. Many Indian villages dotted the banks of the
        
        <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>, some of them inhabited by people
        frightened by the coming of strangers. Fortunately the sight of 
        <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name>and her baby convinced them that the
        newcomers were not a war party. Near the mouth of the 
        <name type="place" key="Willamette (Multnomah) River">Willamette River</name>they
        reentered the world of previously known geography, for boats of 
        <name type="person" key="Vancouver, George">George Vancouver's</name>British expedition
        had penetrated this far up the 
        <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>in 1792.</p>
            <p>For November 7, 1805, 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>was able to note "Ocian in view! O!
        the joy." In fact, he was premature, for what they were seeing was only the wide estuary
        of the 
        <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>. Within a few days, however, 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and a few men pushing ahead did
        reach the coast. Their satisfaction at attaining their long-sought goal was considerably
        dampened by the weather, the characteristic rain and storms of the Northwest Coast winter.
        The party was trapped for days on the northern shore of the estuary, unable to move
        because of high winds and gigantic waves. "All wet and disagreeable" is an expression
        occurring frequently in 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>journals, and on November 22, still
        immobilized, he burst out. "O! how horriable is the day." Their discomfort was not altered
        by seeing the 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinook Indians</name>paddle their canoes
        across rough waters the explorers did not dare attempt.</p>
            <p>They had arrived where they had longed to be, and they knew that the mountain winter
        would make the return east impossible for some months. Their immediate problem was to find
        a place near the coast to wait out the winter. There seemed to be no really suitable spot
        on the north side of the 
        <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>. Considering whether to winter on
        the coast, intolerably wet but offering the possibility of contact with a ship, or to seek
        some drier inland spot up the 
        <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>, the captains took the step, rare
        in the annals of exploration, of taking a vote of the party. Even 
        <name type="person" key="York">York</name>, the slave, and 
        <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name>, the Indian woman, had their opinions
        recorded. The final decision was to cross to the south side of the Columbia to seek a
        location with adequate game and proper timber to build a stockade. After a few days of
        searching, on December 7 they picked a site on the banks of what is now called 
        <name type="place" key="Lewis and Clark (Fort, Netul) River">Lewis and Clark
        River</name>some miles from the coast. While 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>set out on the next day for the coast
        to find a site for a 
        <name type="place" key="Saltmaking Camp (Oreg.)">saltmaking camp</name>, 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and the men began felling trees
        for what they would call 
        <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name>after the local Indian
        tribe. Here would be their home for the next three and one half months, until March 23,
        1806.</p>
            <p>It was a sojourn marked not by the fierce cold and snow of the previous winter at 
        <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name>but by rain, storms, and
        gray skies. They did not starve, but food was neither plentiful nor good. The inability to
        preserve meat in the damp climate meant that they lived much of the time on spoiled elk,
        fish, and roots. Relations with the local Indians were not as satisfactory as they had
        been at 
        <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name>. The captains found many
        of the natives' customs and attitudes repugnant and thought they demanded too high a price
        for the food and other goods they furnished. Although the Indians never manifested real
        hostility, the commanders took strict security measures to insure the safety of the
        party.</p>
            <p>The quest for food kept hunting parties out constantly, elk being the chief game
        animal. Reports of a whale stranded some distance down the coast led 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>to set out on January 6 to seek this
        possible source of meat, with a party of eleven men. 
        <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name>insisted on going to see the ocean and
        the big fish, taking her baby and her husband with her. 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>found that the 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Tillamook Indians">Tillamook Indians</name>had already
        stripped the whale, but he was able to purchase a few hundred pounds of meat and a few
        gallons of oil and returned to the fort on January 10.</p>
            <p>The captains had had hopes of meeting American or British seagoing traders, from whom
        they might obtain supplies and send dispatches home, but none were in the area during the
        winter although there was abundant evidence of their contact with the local people. A
        Russian ship seeking a location for a new settlement arrived off the mouth of the 
        <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>just before the Americans left, but
        they were unable to enter the river and the two parties never met.</p>
            <p>The captains did not lack occupation. 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>resumed his journal-keeping on the
        first day of 1806, after a lapse of over three months. For the remainder of his stay at 
        <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name>he devoted himself to
        making a detailed record of the natural history and human culture of the coast and the
        region west of the 
        <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rockies</name>. 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>has occasionally received credit for
        the first descriptions of many new species, but it now appears that he simply borrowed
        material originally written by 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, while copying 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>journals. At no other time did
        they devote so much space to the description of plants and animals and the life and
        material culture of the native peoples, the record of a land little known to the outside
        world. Included with these descriptions were an unprecedented number of sketches, in the
        journals themselves, of plants, animals, and artifacts. The number of drawings other than
        maps in these 
        <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name>journals far surpasses
        those found in the rest of the captains' writings, the product of enforced leisure in a
        strange, new environment. Besides the many plant and animal species pictured, there was a
        record of the great variety of canoe types, of native clothing, implements and weapons,
        and diagrams of the local methods of deforming the heads of infants, with the results.</p>
            <p>The captains first noted the transition in the 
        <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>gorge from the dry ponderosa
        pine–white oak forest on the east to the moist Douglas fir–western hemlock–Sitka spruce
        forests on the west. Among plant species first described by 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>are the Oregon crabapple, Oregon
        grape, dull Oregon grape, and salal (all sketched in the journals and appearing in this
        volume), along with trees like Sitka spruce, grand fir, and western white pine. Among new
        animal discoveries were the greater white-fronted goose, the northern fulmar, the
        eulachon, and the sage grouse (all pictured in volume 6), and also the Columbia
        black-tailed deer, the steelhead trout, the mountain beaver (which is not a beaver), and
        the Oregon bobcat. While 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>wrote, 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>worked on his maps of the first
        transcontinental journey by Anglo-Americans.</p>
            <p>We know much less about the enlisted men, except that they were kept busy hunting and
        making moccasins for the return trip, and that the captains were sufficiently concerned
        about veneral disease that they finally asked for a pledge that none of the party would
        have anything more to do with the native women. Minor illnesses flourished because of the
        dampness and cold.</p>
            <p>Boredom, sickness, a monotonous diet, and the dreary weather all enhanced their
        impatience to start on the trip for home as soon as they reasoned that the melting snows
        of the 
        <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rockies</name>would allow their passage. The
        captains knew that the 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perces</name>, with whom they had
        left their horses on the trip west, would head east of the 
        <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rockies</name>to hunt buffalo as soon as the snow
        in the higher mountains receded. They were anxious to secure their horses, cross the
        mountains, and explore new trails the 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshones</name>had told them about—a
        more direct route from the eastern end of the Indian road across the mountains to the 
        <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">Great Falls of the
        Missouri</name>and also to carry out a separate exploration of the 
        <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone River</name>.</p>
            <p>They had planned to leave on April 1, after preparing what food and clothing they could
        obtain and leaving messages in the fort and with the Indians for any sea traders who
        arrived after their depature. If any disaster overwhelmed the Corps on the journey home,
        some record of their achievement might thus still reach the United States. Eagerness to be
        on the move prompted them to move up the date to March 20, then bad weather and the need
        to secure additional canoes held them another two days. 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>feared that the price the Indians
        wanted for another canoe would so badly deplete their small stock of trade goods as to
        cripple their ability to obtain needed supplies on the way home. The captains succumbed to
        temptation and violated their longstanding and consistently observed rule against stealing
        Indian property and sent out a party to take an unattended canoe nearby, rationalizing
        that the 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsops</name>had taken elk that the
        expedition hunters had shot and left.</p>
            <p>On March 22, 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>wrote, "we determined to set out
        tomorrow at all events."</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
