<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-01-13">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
January 13, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               
               
               
               
               
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml" n="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc" n="Clark, William">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 6</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">November 2, 1805–March 22, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1990</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">200-202</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo" n="Ordway, John">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf" n="Floyd, Charles">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">267</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg" n="Gass, Patrick">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">188</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jw" n="Whitehouse, Joseph">Joseph Whitehouse</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 11</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of Joseph Whitehouse, May 14, 1804–April 2, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1997</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">413</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Journal Entries</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-08-09</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1806-01-13">January 13, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-01-13.01" n="">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Tuesday</hi> [<hi rend="italic">NB: Monday</hi>] <hi rend="italic">January 13th 1806.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
This morning I took all the men who could be spared from the Fort and set out in quest of the flesh of the seven Elk that were killed yesterday, we found it in good order being untouched by the wolves, of which indeed there are but few in this country; at 1 P. M. we returned having gotten all the meat to the fort.    this evening we exhausted the last four candles, but fortunately had taken the precaution to bring with us moulds and wick, by means of which and some Elk's tallow in our possession we do not yet consider ourselves destitute of this necessary article; the Elk we have killed have a very small portion of tallow.</p>
               <p>
The traders usually arrive in this quarter, as has been before observed, in the month of April, and remain untill October; when here they lay at anchor in a bay within <name type="place" key="Cape Disappointment">Cape Disappointment</name>
                  <ref target="n27011301" n="1"/> on the N. side of the river; here they are visited by the natives in their canoes who run along side and barter their comodities with them, their being no houses or fortification on shore for that purpose.    the nations who repare thither are fist, those of the sea coast S. E. of the entrance of the river, who reside in the order in which their names are mentioned, begining at the entrance of the river (viz) The <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsop</name>, <name type="native_nation" key="Tillamook Indians">Killamuck</name>,<ref target="n27011302" n="2"/>
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Tillamook Indians">Ne-cost, Nat-ti, Nat-chies, Tarl-che</name>, <name type="native_nation" key="Tillamook Indians">E-slitch</name>, <name type="native_nation" key="Alsea Indians">You-cone</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Alsea Indians">So-see</name>.    secondly those inhabiting the N. W. coast begining at the entrance of the river and mentioned in the same order; the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinnook</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Chehalis Indians">Chiltch</name> the latter very numerous; and thirdly the <name type="native_nation" key="Cathlamet Indians">Cath-lâh-mah</name>, and <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skil-lutes</name>, the latter numerous and inhabiting the river from a few miles above the <name type="place" key="Marsh (Seal) Island">marshey Islands</name>, where the <name type="native_nation" key="Cathlamet Indians">Cuth-lâh-mâhs</name> cease, to the <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Cascades (Great Rapids, Great Shute)">grand rappids</name>. These last may be esteemed the principal carryers to intermediate traders between the whites and the Indians of the Sea Coast, and the <name type="native_nation" key="Tenino Indians">E-ne-shurs</name>, the <name type="native_nation" key="Wishram-Wasco Indians">E-chee-lutes</name>, and the <name type="native_nation" key="Wishram-Wasco Indians">Chil-luck-kit-te quaws</name>, who inhabit the river above, to the grand falls inclusive, and who prepare most of the pounded fish which is brought to market. The bay in which this trade is carryed on is spacious and commodious, and perfectly secure from all except the S. and S. E. winds, these however are the most prevalent and strong winds in the Winter season.<ref target="n27011303" n="3"/>    fresh water and wood are very convenient and excellent timber for refiting and reparing vessels.—
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-01-13.02" n="">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Monday 13th January 1806</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name> took all the men which Could be Speared from the Fort and Set out in quest of the flesh of the Seven Elk which were killed yesterday    they found the meat all Secure untouched by the Wolves, of which indeed there are but fiew in this Countrey; at 1 P. M. the party returned with the 2d and Last load of meat to the fort.    this evening we finished all last of our Candles, we brought with us, but fortunately had taken the precaution to bring with us moulds and wick, by means of which and Some Elk tallow in our possession we do not think our Selves distitute of this necessary article, the Elk which have been killed have a verry Small portion of tallow. The Traders usially arrive in this quarter, in the month of april, and remain until October; when here they lay at anchor in a Bay within <name type="place" key="Cape Disappointment">Cape Disapointment</name> on the N. Side of the river; here they are visited by the nativs in their Canoes who run along Side and barter their Comodities with them, their being no houses or fortification on Shore for that purpose.</p>
               <p>
The nations who repare thither ar first those of the Sea Coast S. E &amp; N W of the enterance of the river, who reside in the order in which their names are mentioned to the S E. the <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clat Sops</name>, <name type="native_nation" key="Tillamook Indians">Kil-á-mox</name>, and those to the N W. of the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chin nooks</name>, and <name type="native_nation" key="Chehalis Indians">Chiltch</name> [<hi rend="italic">NB?: Ch. on the coast to the N. W</hi>]; and Secondly the <name type="native_nation" key="Cathlamet Indians">Cath-lâh-mâh</name>, <name type="native_nation" key="Wahkiakum Indians">War-ki-a-cum</name>, and <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skil-lutes</name>, the latter noumerous and inhabiting [<hi rend="italic">NB: the river <name type="place" key="Cowlitz (Coweliskee) River">Coweliskee</name>.</hi>]<ref target="n27011304" n="4"/>    those last may be considered or intermedeate traders between the whites and nations on the Sea Coast, and the <name type="native_nation" key="Tenino Indians">E-ne-churs</name>, the <name type="native_nation" key="Wishram-Wasco Indians">E-chee-lutes</name>, and the <name type="native_nation" key="Wishram-Wasco Indians">Chil-luck-kit-te-quaws</name>, who inhabit the river up to the great falls inclusive, and who prepare most of the pounded fish which is brought to Market.</p>
               <p>
The Bay in which the trade is Carried on is Spacious and Commodious, and perfectly Secure from all except the S. &amp; S E Wings and those blow but Seldom    the most prevalent &amp; Strong winds are fromthe S W &amp; N W in the Winter Season.    fish water and wood are very Convenient and excellent timber for refitting and repareing vessels.—.

</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-01-13.03" n="">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Monday 13th Jany. 1806.    rained hard all last night and continues this morning. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name> and all the party except the guard went after the Elk meat. Six men Set jurking the meat to keep it from Spoiling.

</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-01-13.04" n="">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Monday 13th.</hi>    The weather changed and we had a cloudy wet day; and all the hands, who could spared, were engaged in bringing the meat of the elk, killed yesterday to camp.

</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-01-13.05" n="">
            <sp who="jw">
               <speaker>Whitehouse</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Monday Janry 13th    It rained during the whole of last night and continues Raining this morning.    <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Lewis</name> &amp; all our party (excepting the guard) set out in Order to bring in the Elk meat.    They brought the 7 Elk in at 2 loads, &amp; Six of the Men set at cutting up and Scaffolding the meat to day &amp;ca.—

</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n27011301" n="1">
               <name type="place" key="Baker (Haley's) Bay">Baker Bay</name>, <name type="place" key="Pacific County, Wash.">Pacific County</name>, <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>, <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 82.</note>
            <note xml:id="n27011302" n="2">In his subsequent entry for <ref n="1806-01-25" type="related">January 25</ref>, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> corrected himself to say that these groups named after the <name type="native_nation" key="Tillamook Indians">Tillamooks</name> (<name type="native_nation" key="Tillamook Indians">Killamucks</name>) were actually different bands of the <name type="native_nation" key="Tillamook Indians">Tillamook Indians</name> (see also the <ref n="1805-1806.winter.part2" type="related">Estimate of Western Indians</ref>). However, most of these names refer to villages of the <name type="native_nation" key="Alsea Indians">Alsea</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Yaquina Indians">Yaquina</name> Indians, speakers of the Alsean language, who resided below the <name type="native_nation" key="Tillamook Indians">Tillamooks</name> on the north-central <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name> coast. Dorsey (ST); Hodge, 1:665, 738–39, 2:982, 992–93; Hajda, 97–98; <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> maps 84, 93. Some of the terms may be identified linguistically. "E-slitch" is from the <name type="native_nation" key="Tillamook Indians">Tillamook</name> language, <hi rend="italic">n<seg n="u353">š</seg>l‘t<seg n="u353">š</seg>,'</hi> "Siletz (River)." "You-cone" and "So-see" are both from the Alsea language, <hi rend="italic">yaq<seg n="u243">ó</seg>·n,</hi> "Yaquina," and possibly <hi rend="italic">wusi,</hi> for "Alsea." Cf. Frachtenburg, 288, 304.</note>
            <note xml:id="n27011303" n="3">Note the discrepancy with <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> statement on the winds in his entry for this date, below.</note>
            <note xml:id="n27011304" n="4">
               <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle's</name> insertion was added to a large blank space.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-01-12" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-01-14" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
