<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-06-08">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
June 8, 1805</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               
               
               
               
               
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 4</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">April7–July 27, 1805</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1987</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">265-269</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">164-165</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">100</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jw">Joseph Whitehouse</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 11</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of Joseph Whitehouse, May 14, 1804–April 2, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1997</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">190-191</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Journal Entries</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-02-03</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1805-06-08">June 8, 1805</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-06-08.01" n="">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Saturday June 8th 1805</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
It continued to rain moderately all last night    this morning was cloudy untill about ten oClock when it cleared off and became a fine day.    we breakfasted and set out about sunrise and continued our rout down the river bottoms through the mud and water as yesterday, tho' the road was somewhat better than yesterday and we were not so often compelled to wade in the river.    we passed some dangerous and difficult bluffs. The river bottoms affording all the timber which is to be seen in the country they are filled with innumerable litle birds that resort thither either for shelter or to build their nests.    when sun began to shine today these birds appeared to be very gay and sung most inchantingly; I observed among them the brown thrush, Robbin, turtle dove, linnit goaldfinch, the large and small blackbird, wren and several other birds of less note.<ref target="n15060801" n="1"/>    some of the inhabitants of the praries also take reffuge in these woods at night or from a storm. The whole of my party to a man except myself were fully peswaided that this river was the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, but being fully of opinion that it was neither the main stream or that which it would be advisable for us to take, I determined to give it a name and in honour of <name type="person" key="Wood, Maria">Miss Maria W—d</name>. called it <name type="place" key="Marias River">Maria's</name> River.    it is true that the hue of the waters of this turbulent and troubled stream but illy comport with the pure celestial virtues and amiable qualifications of that lovely fair one; but on the other hand it is a noble river; one destined to become in my opinion an object of contention between the two great powers of America and Great Britin with rispect to the adjustment of the North westwardly boundary of the former; and that it will become one of the most interesting brances of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> in a commercial point of view, I have but little doubt, as it abounds with anamals of the fur kind, and most probably furnishes a safe and direct communication to that productive country of valuable furs exclusively enjoyed at present by the subjects of his Britanic Majesty; in adition to which it passes through a rich fertile and one of the most beatifully picteresque countries that I ever beheld, through the wide expance of which, innumerable herds of living anamals are seen, it's borders garished with one continued garden of roses, while it's lofty and open forrests, are the habitation of miriads of the feathered tribes who salute the ear of the passing traveler with their wild and simple, yet s[w]eet and cheerfull melody.—    I arrived at camp about 5 OClock in the evening much fatiegued, where I found <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name> and the ballance of the party waiting our return with some anxiety for our safety having been absent near two days longer than we had engaged to return.    on our way to camp we had killed 4 deer and two Antelopes; the skins of which as well as those we killed while on the rout we brought with us. <name type="place" key="Marias River">Maria's river</name> may be stated generally from sixty to a hundred yards wide, with a strong and steady current and possessing 5 feet water in the most sholly parts.—</p>
               <p>
As the incidents which occurred <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. C.</name> during his rout will be more fully and satisfactoryley expressed by himself <ref target="n15060802" n="2">I here insert a copy of his journal during the days we wer seperated.—</ref>
               </p>
               <p>I now gave myself this evening to rest from my labours, took a drink of grog and gave the men who had accompanyed me each a dram. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name> ploted the courses of the two rivers as far as we had ascended them. I now began more than ever to suspect the varacity of <name type="person" key="Fidler, Peter">Mr. Fidler</name> or the correctness of his instruments.    for I see that <name type="person" key="Arrowsmith, Aaron">Arrasmith</name> in his late map of N. America has laid down a remarkable mountain in the chain of the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky mountains</name> called the tooth nearly as far South as Latitude 45°, and this is said to be from the discoveries of <ref target="n15060803" n="3">
                     <name type="person" key="Fidler, Peter">Mr. Fidler</name>.</ref>    we are now within a hundred miles of the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky Mountains</name>, and I find from my observation of the 3rd Inst that the latitude of this place is 47° 24' 12.8".    the river must therefore turn much to the South, between this and the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">rocky Mountain</name> to have permitted <name type="person" key="Fidler, Peter">Mr. Fidler</name> to have passed along the Eastern border of these mountains as far S. as nearly 45° without even seeing it.    but from hence as far as <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. C.</name> had ascended the S. fork or <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> being the distance of 55 [<hi rend="italic">NB: 45 miles in Straight line</hi>] miles    it's course is S. 29° W. and it still appeared to bear considerably to the W. of South as far as he could see it. I think therefore that we shall find that the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> enters the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">rocky mountain</name>s to the North of 45°—    we did take the liberty of placing his discoveries or at least the Southern extremity of them about a degree further N. in the sketh which we sent on to the government this spring mearly from the Indian information of the bearing from <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name> of the entrance of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> into the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky Mountains</name>, and I reather suspect that actual observation will take him at least one other degree further North. The general Course of <name type="place" key="Marias River">Maria's river</name> from hence to the extremity of the last course taken by <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Sergt. pryor</name> is N 69° W. 59 mes.—</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-06-08.02" n="">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">June 8th Saturday 1805</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
rained moderately all the last night &amp; Some this morning untill 10 oClock, I am Some what uneasy for <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name> &amp; party as days has now passed the time he was to have returned, I had all the arms put in order and permited Severall men to hunt, aired and dried our Stores &amp;c. The rivers at this point has fallen 6 Inches Sinc our arrival, at 10 oClock cleared away and became fair—    the wind all the morning from the S. W. &amp; hard—    The water of the <name type="place" key="Gallatin (South, Southeast Fork) River">South fork</name> is of a redish brown colour this morning the other river of a whitish colour as usual—The mountains to the South Covered with Snow. Wind Shifted to the N E in the evening, about 5 oClock <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name> arrived with the party much fatigued, and inform'd me that he had assended the river about 60 miles by Land and that the river had a bold current of about 80 or 100 yards wide the bottoms of Gravel &amp; mud, and may be estimated at 5 feet water in Sholest parts</p>
               <p>The courses which <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name> went to examine the N. fork of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <table rows="15" cols="3">
                     <head>
                        <hi rend="right">the 4th of June 1805</hi>
                     </head>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 30° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  4 ½</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">to a hite on the Stard Side from the top of this hite    the N.<lb/>
Mountains appear to turn to the N. &amp; terminate, they bear<lb/>
N. 48° E about 30 miles, the countrey is a leavel plain—<lb/>
The <name type="place" key="Highwood (South) Mountains">South mountains</name> bear S, and appear to terminate,<lb/>
bearing S. 80° W. 35 ms    The <name type="place" key="Square Butte (Barn Mountain)">barn mountains</name> S. 38° W.<lb/>
40, the river on the left appears to be 〈about〉 turning to<lb/>
the N. W.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 70° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">12</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">to the N. E. of a high hill</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 15° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  2</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">to the river bluff</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 30° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  2</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">to the mouth of a large Creek on Lard. Side a chain of<lb/>
high hills which run parrelal to the river on the S. Side<lb/>
cease</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 20° E</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">12</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">to the river Bluffs    camped.    a Dry creek falls in at the<lb/>
end of the Course on the Stard. Side from the N E.</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <table rows="10" cols="3">
                     <head>
                        <hi rend="right">
                           <hi rend="italic">June 5th</hi>
                        </hi>
                     </head>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 50° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  4</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">up the river</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">North</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  2</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">The <name type="place" key="Tower Mountain">Tower Mountain</name> bore N. 52 W.    about 60 miles a<lb/>
high single Mtn.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 60° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  1 ½</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">allong the river</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 10° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  3</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">allong the river</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 50° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  1 ½</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">allong the river.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">West</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">10</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">to the river bluff across a Plain    river haveing a consider-<lb/>
able bend to the South.    Cntr. of bend 5 ms.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 80° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  2</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">miles on the river</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 70° W</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  6</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">to a high hill on S. S. 2½ miles N. from the river in a plain</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 80° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rend="underline" rows="1" cols="1">15</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">m. with the genl. course of the river    the Countrey leavele<lb/>
open Plain, near the river Steep reveins    the bottoms nar-<lb/>
row but well timbered, bluff ¼ to ¾ asunder. The Coun-<lb/>
trey as far as Could be Seen is a leavel plain</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rend="double underline" rows="1" cols="1">77 ½</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>Some rain in the evening.    the left hand fork rose a little.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-06-08.03" n="">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Saturday 8th June 1805</hi>. Some cloudy.    the wind blew cold from the N. W. Several men went out from Camp to hunt—    about 9 oClock A. M. cleared off pleasant.    the Indian goods &amp;.C. put out to air.    we Saw the high Mountains to the West.    our Camp covered with Snow the greater part of which has fell within a fiew days.    the <name type="place" key="Gallatin (South, Southeast Fork) River">South fork</name> of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missourie</name> is high &amp; of a yallow coulour.    the N. fork is more white than common owing as we expect to the late rain which has melted the Snow on the mountains.    about 3 oClock P. M. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name> &amp; his party returned to Camp, &amp; Informed us that they had walked through high plains for about 60 miles up the north fork.    they found that it holds its bigness, &amp; depth of water bottoms of timber which is covered with game.    they killed a nomber of buffalow, 16 Deer 6 Elk &amp; a brarow.    they Saw a range of Mountains<ref target="n15060804" n="4"/> to the South of them. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name> think that the N. fork bears too far north for our course for if we Should take the wrong fork we Should have much further to go by land &amp; more mountains to cross to git over the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name> which descends to the western ocean. So our Captains conclude to assend the <name type="place" key="Gallatin (South, Southeast Fork) River">South fork</name> and burry Some articles which we can do without &amp; leave the largest perogue.    they named <name type="place" key="Jefferson River (North, Southwest Fork)">the North fork River</name>
                  <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="place" key="Marias River">Mariah</name>
                  </hi> and the middle or little River named <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="place" key="Teton (Rose, Tansy) River">Tanzey River</name>
                  </hi>.    the water &amp; bottoms in everry respect of each resimbles the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missourie</name> below the forks.    only Smaller.    we put a brand on a tree which Stood on the point. the men generally in camp has been employed dressing Skins &amp;.C—</p>
               <p>
towards evening the hunters all came in    had killed 13 m. mule &amp; common Deer &amp; one beaver. The wind blew from the East    a light Shower of rain this evening.



</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-06-08.04" n="">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Saturday 8th.</hi>    A fine cool morning. About 10 o'clock A. M. the water of the South river, or branch, became almost of the colour of claret,<ref target="n15060805" n="5"/> and remained so all day. The water of the other branch has the appearance of milk when contrasted with the water of this branch in its present state. About 4 in the afternoon <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Lewis</name> and his party came to camp. They had been up the North branch about 60 miles, and found it navigable that distance; not so full of islands as the other branch and a greater quantity of timber near it and plenty of game, which is not the case on the South branch. Its bearing something north of west a considerable distance, and then to the south of west. The party while out killed 18 deer and some elk. From the appearance of the river where they left it to return, they supposed it might be navigable a considerable distance further. They saw no mountains ahead, but one off towards the north:<ref target="n15060806" n="6"/> it was not covered with snow like those we had seen. Both these rivers abound in fish; and we caught some of different kinds, but not large. About five o'clock in the afternoon the weather became cloudy and cold, and it began to rain. The officers concluded that the south branch was the most proper to ascend, which they think is the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>.<ref target="n15060807" n="7"/> The other they called <name type="place" key="Marias River">Maria's river</name>. At dark the rain ceased.



</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-06-08.05" n="">
            <sp who="jw">
               <speaker>Whitehouse</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Saturday 8th June 1805</hi>.    Some cloudy.    the wind blew cold from the N. W.    Several men went out to hunt.    about 9 oC. cleared off pleasant.    the Indian goods &amp;c put out to air.    we Saw the high mountain to the west of us covered with Snow.    the <name type="place" key="Gallatin (South, Southeast Fork) River">South fork</name> of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missourie</name> is high &amp; of a yallow coulour to day, &amp; <name type="place" key="Jefferson River (North, Southwest Fork)">the North fork</name> more white &amp; rile than before, owing as we expect to the rains &amp; Snow melting above, on the mountains.    about 3 oClock P. M. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name> &amp; party returned to Camp, &amp; Informed us that they had been about 60 miles distant up the north fork, had traveled through high plains the greater part of the way.    they found that the N. fork keeps its bigness, pleanty of water, considerable of timber in the bottoms &amp; an amence cite of game.    they killed a great deal of Elk Buffalow Deer &amp;c. &amp;c.    but <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name> thinks that the <name type="place" key="Jefferson River (North, Southwest Fork)">N. fork</name> bears too far North for our course to cross the Mountains, for if we Should take the wrong River, we Should have more mountains to cross &amp; further to go by land to git to the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>, which we have to descend to the west.    So the Capt. conclude to take the <name type="place" key="Gallatin (South, Southeast Fork) River">South fork</name> &amp; proceed, and named <name type="place" key="Jefferson River (North, Southwest Fork)">the North fork </name>
                  <hi rend="italic">River <name type="place" key="Marias River">Mariah</name>
                  </hi>, but it has the resemblence of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missourie</name> below the forks in everry respect, &amp; the <name type="place" key="Madison River (Middle Fork)">middle fork</name> they name <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="place" key="Teton (Rose, Tansy) River">Tanzey River</name>
                  </hi> the water &amp;c. of which resembles the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missourie</name> also.    the men in Camp generally employed Dressing Skins &amp;c—</p>
               <p>
towards evening the hunters all returned had killed Sevl. Elk 13 deer and one beaver.    the wind blew from the East, a light Shower of rain this evening.</p>
               <p>
Saturday June 8th    This morning we had Cloudy weather, and the Wind blowing from the North west; several of our Men went out to hunt, About 7 oClock A. M. the weather cleared off, and became pleasant, the Indians Goods were all put out to air, We saw on the Weather clearing away, a high mountain; lying to the West of us; which was covered with snow, The <name type="place" key="Gallatin (South, Southeast Fork) River">South fork</name> of the River <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Mesouri</name> rose to a great heighth, the Water being of a Yellowish Colour today; and <name type="place" key="Jefferson River (North, Southwest Fork)">the North fork</name> more White and riffling than it was before, the cause of which, we expect, is owing to the Rain that fell lately, and the snow melting in the Mountains.    About 3 o'Clock P. M. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Lewis</name> &amp; party returned to Camp, and inform'd us, that they had been about 60 Miles distant, up <name type="place" key="Jefferson River (North, Southwest Fork)">the North fork</name> of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Mesouri River</name>, &amp; that they had travelled, through high plains, the greater part of the way; they found that the <name type="place" key="Jefferson River (North, Southwest Fork)">North Fork</name>, kept its width, and plenty of Water, as far as they had been up it.—</p>
               <p>
The party under <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Lewis</name> found plenty of timber in the bottoms, the Land extreamly good, and game of all kinds in the greatest abundance, they had killed a great many Buffalo, Elk, deer and other game, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Lewis</name> mentioned, that <name type="place" key="Jefferson River (North, Southwest Fork)">the North fork</name> of the River, bore too far to the Northward, to be our Course to cross the Mountains; and mentioned, that if we should take the wrong river, that we should have more mountains to cross, and a farther distance to travel by land to get to the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>; which we had to descend, it lying to the Westward, Our Officers concluded on proceeding up the <name type="place" key="Gallatin (South, Southeast Fork) River">South fork</name> of the River, which they deemed as entitled to the Name of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Mesouri River</name>, it being by far the largest; and named <name type="place" key="Jefferson River (North, Southwest Fork)">the North fork</name>, <name type="place" key="Marias River">Maria's River</name>, This <name type="place" key="Marias River">River Maria</name>, has the resemblance of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Mesouri</name> below the forks, in every respect.    The <name type="place" key="Madison River (Middle Fork)">middle fork</name> they named <name type="place" key="Teton (Rose, Tansy) River">Tanzey River</name>; from the great quantity of that herb, which grows wild in its bottoms—    The <name type="place" key="Teton (Rose, Tansy) River">Tanzey River</name>, is the small River mention'd, which <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain Clarks</name> party came down, on their return to Camp; after having been to take a view, of the <name type="place" key="Gallatin (South, Southeast Fork) River">South fork</name>.—    The Water, banks, &amp;ca has also the resemblance of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Mesouri</name> River in every respect.—    The Hunters returned in the Evening and had killed 7 Elk, 3 deer, &amp; 1 Beaver, which was brought to our Camp, We had a light shower of Rain and the Wind from the Eastward towards Night.—



</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n15060801" n="1">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> "goaldfinch" is the American goldfinch, <hi rend="italic">Carduelis tristis</hi> [AOU, 529]. The wren may be the winter wren, <hi rend="italic">Troglodytes troglodytes</hi> [AOU, 722], or any of several other birds. Holmgren, 34. Burroughs questions Criswell's identification of the linnet as the
pine siskin, <hi rend="italic">Carduelis pinus</hi> [AOU, 533]. Holmgren says the term linnet was used for any
small bird with a red crown, especially the common redpoll, <hi rend="italic">C. flammea</hi> [AOU, 528], the
purple finch, <hi rend="italic">Carpodacus purpureus</hi> [AOU, 517], and the house finch, <hi rend="italic">C. mexicanus</hi> [AOU,
519]. Burroughs, 259; Criswell, 53; Holmgren, 32. It was probably <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name> who drew a red vertical line through this passage about the birds.</note>
            <note xml:id="n15060802" n="2">Here <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> copies <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> entries from Voorhis No.1 covering the period of separation, June 4–8. Having only slight differences in wording, the material is not repeated. <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name> has some emendations in red on the deleted pages, but they are of little consequence to the narrative.</note>
            <note xml:id="n15060803" n="3">
               <name type="person" key="Fidler, Peter">Peter Fidler</name>, surveyor for the Hudson's Bay Company, supplied the first information on the drainage network of the upper Missouri along the eastern front of the Rockies,
information that went into the 1802 map of the <name type="place" key="London">London</name> cartographer <name type="person" key="Arrowsmith, Aaron">
                  <name type="person" key="Arrowsmith, Aaron">Arrasmith</name>
               </name>, a copy of which <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> obtained for <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> was correct in doubting that <name type="person" key="Fidler, Peter">Fidler</name> had been as far south as 45° N. Latitude; the surveyor had been no farther south than the <name type="place" key="Oldman River">Oldman River</name> in southern <name type="place" key="Alberta">Alberta</name>, approximately 50° N. <name type="person" key="Fidler, Peter">Fidler</name> obtained his information in 1801 from a map drawn for him by <name type="person" key="Ackomokki (The Feathers)">Ackomokki</name>, a <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name> chief. <name type="person" key="Fidler, Peter">Fidler</name> placed the rivers and mountains too far south because his estimate of distance was based on Indian information, expressed in terms of days' travel, rather than
miles. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> impression that <name type="person" key="Fidler, Peter">Fidler</name> claimed to have seen these landmarks himself was apparently mistaken. MacGregor, 73–75; Moodie &amp; Kaye; Allen (PG), 79–82, 122–23, 276–77; Tooley.</note>
            <note xml:id="n15060804" n="4">Probably the <name type="place" key="Highwood (South) Mountains">Highwood Mountains</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n15060805" n="5">A reddish-brown color, according to <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n15060806" n="6">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>
               <name type="place" key="Tower Mountain">Tower Mountain</name> (see his entry of <ref n="1805-06-05" type="related">June 5, 1805</ref>); the southern end of <name type="place" key="Sweetgrass Hills">Sweetgrass Hills</name>, on the <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>-<name type="place" key="Alberta">Alberta</name> border.</note>
            <note xml:id="n15060807" n="7">For the captains' reasoning, see <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> entry of <ref n="1805-06-09" type="related">June 9, 1805</ref>.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-06-07" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-06-09" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
