<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-07-20">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
July 20, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               
               
               
               
               
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml" n="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc" n="Clark, William">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 8</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">June 10–September 26, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1987</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">118-120, 208-209</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo" n="Ordway, John">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf" n="Floyd, Charles">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">339</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg" n="Gass, Patrick">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">256</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
         <geoDecl datum="WGS" xml:id="lc.geo.1806-07-20.01">
            <placeName/>
            <geo>48.5 -111.85</geo>
            <note>Lewis camped on the north side of the Marias River, southern Toole County, MT, five miles southwest of the present town Shelby.</note>
         </geoDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Journal Entries</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-11-29</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1806-07-20">July 20, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-07-20.01" n="lc.geo.1806-07-20.01">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Sunday July 20th 1806</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
We set at sunrise and proceed through the open plain as yesterday up the North side of the river.    the plains are more broken than they were yesterday and have become more inferior in point of soil; a great quanty of small gravel is every where distributed over the surface of the earth which renders travling extreemly painfull to our bearfoot horses.    the soil is generally a white or whiteish blue clay, this where it has been trodden by the buffaloe when wet has now become as firm as a brickbat and stands in an inumerable little points quite as formidable to our horses feet as the gravel.    the mineral salts common to the plains of the missouri has been more abundant today than usual.    the bluffs of the river are about 200 feet high, steep irregular and formed of earth which readily desolves with water, slips and precipitates itself into the river as before mentioned frequentlly of the bluffs of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> below which they resemble in every particular, differing essencially from those of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> above the entrance of this river, they being composed of firm red or yellow clay which dose not yeald readily to the rains and a large quantity of rock.<ref target="n37072001" n="1"/> the soil of the river bottom is fertile and well timbered, I saw some trees today which would make small canoes.    the timber is generally low.    the underbrush the same as before mentioned.    we have seen fewer buffaloe today than usual, though more Elk and not less wolves and Antelopes also some mule deer; this speceis of deer seems most prevalent in this quarter.    saw some gees ducks and other birds common to the country.    there is much appearance of beaver on this river, but not any of otter.<ref target="n37072002" n="2"/>    from the apparent decent of the country to the North and above the broken mountains I am induced to beleive that the South branch of the <name type="place" key="Saskatchewan River">Suskashawan</name> receives a part of it's waters from the plain even to the borders of this river<ref target="n37072003" n="3"/> and from the brakes visible in the plains in a nothern direction think that a branch of that river decending from the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">rocky mountains</name> passes at no great distance from <name type="place" key="Marias River">Maria's river</name> and to the N. E. of the broken mountains.    the day has proved excessively warm and we lay by four hours during the heat of it; we traveled 28 miles and encamped as usual in the river bottom on it's N. side.<ref target="n37072004" n="4"/>    there is scarcely any water at present in the plains and what there is, lies in small pools and is so strongly impregnated with the mineral salts that it is unfit for any purpose except the uce of the buffaloe.    these animals appear to prefer this water to that of the river.    the wild liquorice<ref target="n37072005" n="5"/> and sunflower<ref target="n37072006" n="6"/> are very abundant in the plains and river bottoms, the latter is now in full blume; the silkgrass and sand rush<ref target="n37072007" n="7"/> are also common to the bottom lands. the musquetoes have not been 〈very little〉 troublesome to us since we left the <name type="place" key="White Bear Islands">whitebear islands</name>.—</p>
               <p>
                  <table rows="1" cols="3">
                     <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Courses and distances July 20th 1806.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 80° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">28</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">ms. with the river in it's course upwards to or encampment<lb/>
of this evening on it's N. side.    river 120 yds. wide and deep,<lb/>
water appears to be but little diminsed, somewhat more trans-<lb/>
parent.    passed a creek on S. side at 6 ms. also another 22 ms.<lb/>
on the N. side<ref target="n37072008" n="8"/>    this last has no water some little tim-<lb/>
ber.    bed 15 yds. wide.—    the general course of this river is<lb/>
very streight, and it meanders through a vally of about ½ a<lb/>
mile in width from side to side.</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-07-20.02" n="lc.geo.1806-07-20.01">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Sunday 20th July 1806</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
I directed <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Sergt. Pryor</name> and <name type="person" key="Shields, John">Shields</name> each of them good judges of timber to proceed on down the river Six or 8 miles and examine the bottoms if any larger trees than those near which we are encamped can be found and return before twelve oClock.    they Set out at daylight. I also Sent <name type="person" key="Labiche, François">Labech</name>
                  <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Shabono</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Hall, Hugh">hall</name> to Skin &amp; some of the flesh of the Elk <name type="person" key="Labiche, François">Labeech</name> had killed last evening    they returned with one Skin the wolves haveing eaten the most of the other four Elk. I also Sent two men in Serch of wood Soutable for ax handles.    they found some choke cherry<ref target="n37072009" n="9"/> which is the best wood which Can be precured in this Country. Saw a Bear on an Island opposit and Several Elk. <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Sergt. Pryor</name> and <name type="person" key="Shields, John">Shields</name> returned at half past 11 A M. and informed me that they had proceeded down the timbered bottoms of the rivers for about 12 miles without finding a tree better than those near my Camp. I deturmined to have two Canoes made out of the largest of those trees and lash them together which will Cause them to be Study and fully Sufficient to take my Small party &amp; Self with what little baggage we have down this river.    had handles put in the 3 Axes and after Sharpening them with a file fell the two trees which I intended for the two Canoes.    those trees appeared tolerably Sound and will make Canoes of 28 feet in length and about 16 or 18 inches deep and from 16 to 24 inches wide.    the men with the three axes Set in and worked untill dark. <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Sergt. Pryor</name> dressed Some Skins to make him Clothes. <name type="person" key="Gibson, George">Gibsons</name> wound looks very well. I dressed it. The horses being fatigued and their feet very Sore, I Shall let them rest a fiew days.    dureing which time the party intended for to take them by land to the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>
                  <ref target="n37072010" n="10"/> will dress their Skins and make themselves Clothes to bare, as they are nearly naked. Shields killed a Deer &amp; Buffalow &amp; <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name> a faun and a Buffalow &amp; <name type="person" key="York">York</name> an Elk    one of the buffalow was good meat. I had the best of him brought in and cut thin and Spread out to dry.


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-07-20.03" n="lc.geo.1806-07-20.01">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Sunday 20th July 1806.    a clear warm morning.    we conclude to lay here to day as the truck waggons are not fixed. <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Sergt. Gass</name> went at putting in the tongues to the waggons. Some of the men are engaged dressing Skins, but we are tormented by the Musquetoes and Small flys.    the men engaged dressing deer Skins &amp;c.    towards evening we got up our 4 horses tackled them in the truck waggons    found they would draw but were covred thick with Musquetoes and Small flyes &amp;C.

</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-07-20.04" n="lc.geo.1806-07-20.01">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Sunday 20th.</hi>    We had a fine day; but the musquitoes were very bad. We concluded to stay here all day, as the men, who had come with the canoes were fatigued; and, in the evening tried our horses in harness and found they would draw very well.

</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n37072001" n="1">Late Pleistocene glacial ice in this area displaced the <name type="place" key="Marias River">Marias River</name> southward from its preglacial course. The displaced <name type="place" key="Marias River">Marias River</name> then cut a new valley in older glacial till and into shale of the <name type="place" key="Colorado Group">Colorado Group</name>. This downcutting produced a more rugged topography here than it did farther to the east. The gravel is both glacial outwash and cobbles that were left behind when the finer-grained portion of the till eroded. The glacial till that overlies the <name type="place" key="Colorado Group">Colorado Group</name> was derived from this same formation farther to the north. In this area the till is composed of silt- and clay-sized particles and is highly impregnated with salts such as calcium-magnesium sulfate/bicarbonate. When the clay dries out it becomes exceedingly firm, resembling adobe. The bluffs near the river are composed mainly of goacial till. The till does not dissolve but erodes easily in contact with running water. The running water undercuts the banks and they slide or fall down into the river. The firm red or yellow clay and rock along the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> above the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Marias River">Marias</name> is part of the <name type="place" key="Kootenai Formation">Kootenai Formation</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37072002" n="2">
               <hi rend="italic">Lutra canadensis.</hi>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="n37072003" n="3">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> was still hoping that the <name type="place" key="Marias River">Marias</name> would provide Americans with access to the <name type="place" key="Saskatchewan River">Saskatchewan River</name> country and its fur trade. In fact, the entire basin of the <name type="place"
                     key="Milk (Ah-mâh-tâh ru-shush-sher, River Which Scolds at All Others) River">Milk River</name> lies between the <name type="place" key="South Saskatchewan River">South Saskatchewan</name> and any part of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> system.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37072004" n="4">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> camped on the north side of the <name type="place" key="Marias River">Marias River</name> in southern <name type="place" key="Toole County, Mont.">Toole County</name>, <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>, some five miles southwest of the present town of <name type="place" key="Shelby, Mont.">Shelby</name>, and perhaps a mile west of <name type="place" key="Interstate Highway 15">Interstate Highway 15</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37072005" n="5">Wild liquorice, <hi rend="italic">Glycyrrhiza lepidota</hi> (Nutt.) Pursh. Booth &amp; Wright, 130.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37072006" n="6">Probably the early flowering perennial, Nuttall's Sunflower, <hi rend="italic">Helianthus nuttallii</hi> T. &amp; G. ssp. <hi rend="italic">rydbergii</hi> (Britt.) Long, typically found in riverbottoms. It flowers earlier than the annual sunflowers, <hi rend="italic">H. annuus</hi> L., and <hi rend="italic">H. petiolaris</hi> Nutt. Another possibility for such an early flowering, perennial, upland sunflower is stiff sunflower, <hi rend="italic">H. rigidus</hi> (Cass.) Desf. ssp. <hi rend="italic">subrhomboideus</hi> (Rybd.) Heiser (also known as <hi rend="italic">H. laetiflorus</hi>). Booth &amp; Wright, 274; Barkley, 377–79.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37072007" n="7">Based on the bottomland habitat and association with the scouring ("sand") rush (<hi rend="italic">Equiseum</hi> sp.), the silkgrass is almost certainly hemp dogbane, <hi rend="italic">Apocynum cannabinum</hi> L., long known as a textile fiber plant commonly used by natives. See <ref n="lc.jrn.1805-08-20" type="related">August 20, 1805</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37072008" n="8">Couese (HLC), 3:1090–91 n. 43, argues that the actual order and direction of these two streams has been reversed in <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> wording. According to Coues, the first stream, from the south some eighteen miles above the previous night's camp, is the <name type="place" key="Dry Fork of Marias River">Dry Fork of Marias River</name>, in <name type="place" key="Toole County, Mont.">Toole County</name>. Coues identifies the second stream, six miles above the first on the north side of the <name type="place" key="Marias River">Marias</name>, as <name type="place" key="Medicine Rock Coulee">Medicine Rock Coulee</name>, a name perhaps present in his time but not found on current maps; it would probably be an unnamed creek occupying a glacial channel that passes through <name type="place" key="Shelby, Mont.">Shelby</name>. On the other hand, if <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> first creek did enter from the south at six miles as he has it, it could be <name type="place" key="Dead Indian Coulee">Dead Indian Coulee</name>. The second stream in <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> record almost has to be coming from the south and therefore would be <name type="place" key="Dry Fork of Marias River">Dry Fork</name> since there is no stream of any consequence coming from the north in this day's route and <name type="place" key="Dry Fork of Marias River">Dry Fork</name> most nearly fits his mileage estimates.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37072009" n="9">Choke cherry; for a previous use of the wood as axe handles, see <ref n="lc.jrn.1805-07-10" type="related">July 10, 1805</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37072010" n="10">For this party and its purpose, see <ref n="lc.jrn.1806-07-23" type="related">July 23</ref> and <ref n="lc.jrn.1806-07-24" type="related">24</ref>, 1806.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-07-19" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-07-21" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
