<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-07-27">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">July 27, 1805</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic
        Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            4</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">April7–July 27, 1805</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1987</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">433-439</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">190-191</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">118-119</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jw">Joseph Whitehouse</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume
            11</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of Joseph Whitehouse, May 14, 1804–April 2,
            1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1997</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">242-244</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
         <geoDecl datum="WGS" xml:id="lc.geo.1805-07-27.01">
            <placeName/>
            <geo>45.9249 -111.5214</geo>
            <note>Camped on what they called Barkers Island, Gallatin County, MT. About 2 miles northeast of the town of Three Forks on the Jefferson River. Stayed here until 1805-07-30</note>
         </geoDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc/>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-05-25</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-04-12</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1805-07-27">July 27, 1805</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-07-27.01"
              ref="lc.geo.1805-07-27.01">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Saturday July 27th 1805.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>We set out at an early hour and proceeded on but slowly    the current
          still so rapid that the men are in a continual state of their utmost exertion to get on,
          and they begin to weaken fast from this continual state of violent exertion.
             at the distance of 1¾ miles the river was again closely hemned in by high
          Clifts of a solid limestone rock which appear to have tumbled or sunk in the same manner
          of those discribed yesterday.    the limestone appears to be of an excellent
          quality of deep blue colour when fractured and of a light led colour where exposed to
          the weather.    it appears to be of a very fine gr[a]in the fracture like that
          of marble.
          <ref target="n17072701" n="1"/>   we saw a great number of the bighorn on
          those Clifts.    at the distance of 3¾ ms. further we arrived at 9 A. M. at
          the junction of the 
          <name type="place" key="Gallatin (South, Southeast Fork) River">S. E. fork of the
          Missouri</name>and the country opens suddonly to extensive and beatifull plains and
          meadows which appear to be surrounded in every direction with distant and lofty
          mountains; supposing this to be the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Three Forks of the">three forks of the
          Missouri</name>I halted the party on the Lard. shore for breakfast and walked up the 
          <name type="place" key="Gallatin (South, Southeast Fork) River">S. E. fork</name>about ½
          a mile and ascended the point of a high limestone clift from whence I commanded a most
          perfect view of the neighbouring country. From this point I could see the 
          <name type="place" key="Gallatin (South, Southeast Fork) River">S. E. fork</name>about 7
          miles.    it is rapid and about 70 yards wide.    throughout the
          distance I saw it, it passes through a smoth extensive green meadow of fine grass in
          it's course meandering in several streams the largest of which passes near the Lard.
          hills, of which, the one I stand on is the extremity in this direction.    a
          high wide and extensive plain succeeds the meadow and extends back several miles from
          the river on the Stard. sade and with the range of mountains up the Lard. side of the 
          <name type="place" key="Madison River (Middle Fork)">middle fork</name>.    a
          large spring arrises in this meadow about ¼ of a mile from the 
          <name type="place" key="Gallatin (South, Southeast Fork) River">S. E. fork</name>into
          which it discharges itself on the Stard. side about 400 paces above me.   
          from E to S. between the S. E. and 
          <name type="place" key="Madison River (Middle Fork)">middle forks</name>a distant range
          of lofty mountains rose their snow-clad tops
          <ref target="n17072702" n="2"/>above the irregular and broken mountains which lie
          adjacent to this beautifull spot.    the extreme point to which I could see
          the 
          <name type="place" key="Gallatin (South, Southeast Fork) River">S. E. fork</name>boar S.
          65° E. distant 7 ms. as before observed.    between the 
          <name type="place" key="Madison River (Middle Fork)">middle</name>and 
          <name type="place" key="Gallatin (South, Southeast Fork) River">S. E. forks</name>near
          their junctions with the 
          <name type="place" key="Jefferson River (North, Southwest Fork)">S. W. fork</name>there
          is a handsom site for a fortification    it consists of a limestone rock of an
          oblong form; it's sides perpendicular and about 25 ft high except at the extremity
          towards the 
          <name type="place" key="Madison River (Middle Fork)">middle fork</name>where it ascends
          gradually and like the top is covered with a fine terf of greenswoard.    the
          top is level and contains about 2 Acres.    the rock [r]ises from the level
          plain as if it had been designed for some such purpose.
          <ref target="n17072703" n="3"/>   the extream point to which I can see the
          bottom and meandering of the 
          <name type="place" key="Madison River (Middle Fork)">Middle fork</name>bears S. 15 E
          distant about 14 miles. here it turns to the right around a point of a high plain and
          disappears to my view.    it's bottoms are several miles in width and like
          that of the 
          <name type="place" key="Gallatin (South, Southeast Fork) River">S. E. fork</name>form
          one smoth and beautifull green meadow.    it is also divided into several
          streams.    between this and the 
          <name type="place" key="Jefferson River (North, Southwest Fork)">S. W. fork</name>there
          is an extensive plain which appears to extend up both those rivers many miles and back
          to the mountains.    the extreme point to which I can see the 
          <name type="place" key="Jefferson River (North, Southwest Fork)">S. W. fork</name>bears
          S. 30 W. distant about 12 miles.    this stream passes through a similar
          country with the other two and is more divided and serpentine in it's course than either
          of the others; it a[l]so possesses abundantly more timber in it's bottoms.   
          the timber here consists of the narrowleafed cottonwood almost entirely.   
          but little box alder or sweet willow the underbrush thick and as heretofore discribed in
          the quarter of the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">missouri</name>.    a range of high
          mountains at a considerable distance appear to reach from South to West and are
          partially covered with snow    the country to the right of the 
          <name type="place" key="Jefferson River (North, Southwest Fork)">S. W. fork</name>like
          that to the left of the 
          <name type="place" key="Gallatin (South, Southeast Fork) River">S. E. fork</name>is high
          broken and mountainous as is that also down the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">missouri</name>behind us, through which, these
          three rivers after assembling their united force at this point seem to have forced a
          passage    these bottom lands tho' not more than 8 or 9 feet above the water
          seem never to overflow.    after making a draught of the connection and
          meanders of these streams
          <ref target="n17072704" n="4"/>I decended the hill and returned to the party, took
          breakfast and ascended the 
          <name type="place" key="Jefferson River (North, Southwest Fork)">S. W. fork</name>1¾
          miles and encamped at a Lard. bend in a handsome level smooth plain just below a bayou,
          having passed the entrance of the 
          <name type="place" key="Madison River (Middle Fork)">middle fork</name>at ½ a mile. here
          I encamped to wait the return of 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name>and to give the men a little
          rest which seemed absolutely necessary to them.
          <ref target="n17072705" n="5"/>   at the junction of the 
          <name type="place" key="Jefferson River (North, Southwest Fork)">S. W.</name>and 
          <name type="place" key="Madison River (Middle Fork)">Middle fork</name>s I found a note
          which had been left by 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name>informing me of his intended
          rout, and that he would rejoin me at this place provided he did not fall in with any
          fresh sighn of Indians, in which case he intended to pursue untill he over took them
          calculating on my taking the 
          <name type="place" key="Jefferson River (North, Southwest Fork)">S. W. fork</name>,
          which I most certainly prefer as it's direction is much more promising than any other.
             beleiving this to be an essential point in the geography of this western
          part of the Continent I determined to remain at all events untill I obtained the
          necessary data for fixing it's latitude Longitude &amp;c.    after fixing my
          camp I had the canoes all unloaded and the baggage stoed away and securely covered on
          shore, and then permitted several men to hunt. I walked down to the 
          <name type="place" key="Madison River (Middle Fork)">middle fork</name>and examined and
          compared it with the 
          <name type="place" key="Jefferson River (North, Southwest Fork)">S. W. fork</name>but
          could not satisfy myself which was the largest stream of the two, in fact they appeared
          as if they had been cast in the same mould there being no difference in character or
          size, therefore to call either of these streams the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>would be giving it a preference
          wich it's size dose not warrant as it is not larger then the other.    they
          are each 90 yds. wide.    in these meadows I saw a number of the duckanmallad
          <ref target="n17072706" n="6"/>with their young which are now nearly grown. Currants of
          every species as well as goosberries are found her[e] in great abundance and perfection.
             a large black goosberry
          <ref target="n17072707" n="7"/>which grows to the hight of five or six feet is also
          found here.    this is the growth of the bottom lands and is found also near
          the little rivulets which make down from the hills and mountains    it puts up
          many stems from the same root, some of which are partialy branched and all reclining.
             the berry is attatched seperately by a long peduncle to the stem from which
          they hang pendant underneath.    the berry is of an ovate form smooth as large
          as the common garden goosberry when arrived at maturity and is as black as jet, tho' the
          pulp is of a cimson colour.    this fruit is extreemly asced.    the
          leaf resembles the common goosberry in form but is reather larger and somewhat
          proportioned to the superior size of it's stem when compared with the common goosberry.
             the stem is covered with very sharp thorns or bryers.    below
          the tree forks as we passed this morning I observed many collections of the mud nests of
          the small martin attatched to the smooth face of the limestone rocks sheltered by
          projections of the same rock above. Our hunters returned this evening with 6 deer 3
          Otter and a musk rat.    they informed me that they had seen great numbers of
          Antelopes, and much sign of beaver Otter deer Elk, &amp;c.    at 3 P. M. 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt clark</name>arrived very sick with a high
          fever on him and much fatiegued and exhausted.    he informed me that he was
          very sick all last night had a high fever and frequent chills &amp; constant aking pains
          in all his mustles.    this morning notwithstanding his indisposition he
          pursued his intended rout to the 
          <name type="place" key="Madison River (Middle Fork)">middle fork</name>about 8 miles and
          finding no recent sign of Indians rested about an hour and came down the 
          <name type="place" key="Madison River (Middle Fork)">middle fork</name>to this place. 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. C.</name>thought himself somewhat bilious
          and had not had a passage for several days; I prevailed on him to take a doze of Rushes
          pills, which I have always found sovereign in such cases and to bath his feet in warm
          water and rest himself. 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. C's</name>indisposition was a further
          inducement for my remaining here a couple of days; I therefore informed the men of my
          intention, and they put their deer skins in the water in order to prepare them for
          dressing tomorrow.    we begin to feel considerable anxiety with rispect to
          the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Snake</name>Indians.    if
          we do not find them or some other nation who have horses I fear the successfull issue of
          our voyage will be very doubtfull or at all events much more difficult in it's
          accomplishment.    we are now several hundred miles within the bosom of this
          wild and mountanous country, where game may rationally be expected shortly to become
          scarce and subsistence precarious without any information with rispect to the country
          not knowing how far these mountains continue, or wher to direct our course to pass them
          to advantage or intersept a navigable branch of the 
          <name type="person" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>, or even were we on such an one
          the probability is that we should not find any timber within these mountains large
          enough for canoes if we judge from the portion of them through which we have passed.
             however I still hope for the best, and intend taking a tramp myself in a
          few days to find these yellow gentlemen if possible.    my two principal
          consolations are that from our present position it is impossible that the 
          <name type="place" key="Jefferson River (North, Southwest Fork)">S. W. fork</name>can
          head with the waters of any other river but the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>, and that if any Indians can
          subsist in the form of a nation in these mountains with the means they have of acquiring
          food we can also subsist. 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. C.</name>informed me that there is a part
          of this bottom on the West side of the 
          <name type="place" key="Madison River (Middle Fork)">Middle fork</name>near the plain,
          which appears to overflow occasionally and is stony.</p>
               <p>
                  <table rows="9" cols="3">
                     <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Courses and distances of July 27th 1805.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 65° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">   ½</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">to the center of a Stard. bend passing an
                Island.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">South</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">1 ¼</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">to a clift of high rocks on the Stard.
                   here the river is again
                <lb/>confined between high and perpendicular clifts of rock.—</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 2° E.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">2 ½</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">to the center of a Lard. bend passing a small
                Island</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 45 W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">1 ¼</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">to the upper point of a high clift of rocks in
                a Stard. op-
                <lb/>posite or a little below the entrance of the 
                <name type="place" key="Gallatin (South, Southeast Fork) River">S. E.
                fork</name>of the
                <lb/>
                           <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>which we called 
                <hi rend="italic">
                              <name type="place" key="Gallatin (South, Southeast Fork) River">Gallitin's
                  river</name>
                           </hi>
                           <ref target="n17072708" n="8"/>in honor of 
                <name type="person" key="Gallatin, Albert">Albert
                <lb/>Gallitin</name>Secretary of the Treasury</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 45° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">   ½</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">to the confluence of the 
                <name type="place" key="Madison River (Middle Fork)">middle</name>and 
                <name type="place" key="Jefferson River (North, Southwest Fork)">S. W.</name>forks
                of the 
                <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Mis-
                <lb/>souri</name>each 90 yds. wide; the 
                <name type="place" key="Madison River (Middle Fork)">Middle fork</name>we called 
                <name type="place" key="Madison River (Middle Fork)">Mad-
                <lb/>dison's river</name>in honor of 
                <name type="person" key="Madison, James">James Maddison</name>the Secretary of
                <lb/>State.—
                <ref target="n17072709" n="9"/>   and the 
                <name type="place" key="Gallatin (South, Southeast Fork) River">S. W.
                fork</name>we called 
                <name type="place" key="Jefferson River (North, Southwest Fork)">Jefferson's
                River</name>in
                <lb/>honor that illustratious peronage 
                <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Thomas Jefferson</name>Presi-
                <lb/>dent of the United States.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 45° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">   ¼</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">to the entrance of a Bayou on Stard.
                side</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 30° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">   ¼</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">to a Stard. bend.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 20° E.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                           <hi rend="underline">   ¼</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">to the center of a Lard. bend where we
                encamped on Lard.
                <lb/>in Camp Island.—</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                           <hi rend="right">Miles</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                           <hi rend="double underline">7</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-07-27.02"
              ref="lc.geo.1805-07-27.01">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">July 27th Saturday 1805</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>I was verry unwell all last night with a high fever &amp; akeing in all my bones.
             my fever &amp;c. continus, deturmind to prosue my intended rout to the 
          <name type="place" key="Madison River (Middle Fork)">middle fork</name>, accordingly Set
          out in great pain across a Prarie 8 miles to the Middle    this fork is nearly
          as large as 
          <name type="place" key="Jefferson River (North, Southwest Fork)">the North
          fork</name>&amp; appears to be more rapid, we examined and found no fresh Sign of
          Indians, and after resting about an hour, proceeded down to the junction thro a wide
          bottom which appears to be overflown every year, &amp; maney parts Stoney this river has
          Several Islands and number of beaver &amp; orter, but little timber.    we
          could See no fresh Sign of Indians    just above the Point I found 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt Lewis</name>encamped haveing arrived
          about 2 oClock. Several Deer killed this evening. I continue to be verry unwell fever
          verry high; take 5 of rushes pills &amp; bathe my feet &amp; legs in hot water</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-07-27.03"
              ref="lc.geo.1805-07-27.01">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">July 27th Saturday 1805</hi>.    a clear morning.
             we Set off as usal and proceeded on.    the current Swift as
          usal.    passed clifts of rocks.    villages of little birds
          <ref target="n17072710" n="10"/>under the Shelveing rocks.    the hills not
          So high as below.    the currents abound along the Shores.    about
          9 oClock we arived at the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Three Forks of the">three forks of the
          Missourie</name>, which is in open view of the high Mountains covered in Some places
          with Snow    Saw large flocks of Mountain Sheep or Ibex and antelopes &amp;C.
          on the plain.    we passed the South &amp; west forks, and Camped at an old
          Indian Camp on the point a Short distance up 
          <name type="place" key="Jefferson River (North, Southwest Fork)">the North fork</name>.
             this is a handsom pleasant plain considerable of cotton timber about the
          points of 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Three Forks of the">the forks</name>.
             we unloaded the canoes. Several men went out in the bottoms to hunt. 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name>joined us and the men who
          were with him.    he informed us that he had been about 40 miles up the west
          fork and over to 
          <name type="place" key="Jefferson River (North, Southwest Fork)">the North
          fork</name>and came down that to 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Three Forks of the">the forks</name>.
             they had killed several deer antelopes and a cub bear. 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name>verry unwell.    he
          had Seen a large elagant horse in the plains which appeared to be verry wild.
             the hunters killed Several or 6 deer, and 3 otter and a musk rat.
             we had a Shower of rain this afternoon.    came 7 mls. to day,
          which brought us to this Camp where we intend to rest a day or two.    we
          expected to have found the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Snake</name>nation of Indians at this
          place, but as we expect they are further up the River, or perhaps they are gone over the
          mountains to the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbian River</name>
                  <ref target="n17072711" n="11"/>on the other Side to fish &amp;C.    this is
          the place where 
          <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">our Intrepters wife</name>was taken prisoner by the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Grossvauntaus</name>, about 4 years
          ago, &amp;C.
          <ref target="n17072712" n="12"/>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-07-27.04"
              ref="lc.geo.1805-07-27.01">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Saturday 27th.</hi>   We continued our voyage early, and had
          a pleasant morning; proceeded on, and at 9 o'clock got through the small mountain. At
          the entrance of the valley, a branch of the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>comes in on the south side, about
          60 yards wide; the current rapid but not very deep. Here we took breakfast, and having
          proceeded on a mile, came to another branch of the same size. There is very little
          difference in the size of the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Three Forks of the">3 branches</name>. On the
          bank of the 
          <name type="place" key="Jefferson River (North, Southwest Fork)">north branch</name>
                  <ref target="n17072713" n="13"/>we found a note 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain Clarke</name>had left informing us, he
          was ahead and had gone up that branch. We went on to the point, and, as the men were
          much fatigued, encamped in order to rest a day or two. After we halted here, it began to
          rain and continued three hours. About 12 o'clock 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clarke</name>and his men
          <ref target="n17072714" n="14"/>came to our encampment, and told us they had been up
          both branches
          <ref target="n17072715" n="15"/>a considerable distance, but could discover none of the
          natives. There is a beautiful valley at these 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Three Forks of the">forks</name>; and a good
          deal of timber on the branches, chiefly cotton-wood. Also currants, goose and service
          berries,
          <ref target="n17072716" n="16"/>and choak-cherries on the banks. The deer are plenty
          too; some of the men went out and killed several to day. 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clarke</name>was very unwell and had been
          so all last night. In the evening the weather became clear and we had a fine night.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry"
              xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-07-27.05"
              ref="lc.geo.1805-07-27.01">
            <sp who="jw">
               <speaker>Whitehouse</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Saturday 27th July</hi>1805.    a clear morning.
             we Set off at Sun rise and proceeded on.    the current as rapid
          as yesterday.    passed clifts of rocks where was villages of little birds
          under the Shelving rocks &amp;c.    the hills not So high as below.
             the currents of different kinds abound along the Shores.    about
          9 oClock we Came or arived at the 3 forks of the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missourie</name>which is in a 〈wide〉 valley in
          open view of the high Mountains which has white Spots on it which has the appearence of
          Snow.    Saw large flocks of mountain Sheep or Ibex, and goats or antelopes.
             the plain on N. Side of 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Three Forks of the">the forks</name>has lately
          been burned over by the natives.    we went on passed the 
          <name type="place" key="Gallatin (South, Southeast Fork) River">South fork</name>, and
          west fork.    went a Short distance up 
          <name type="place" key="Jefferson River (North, Southwest Fork)">the North
          fork</name>and Camped on the point which is a Smoth plain.    a large Camp of
          Indians has been encamped here Some time ago.    our Intrepters wife was taken
          prisoner at this place 3 or 4 years ago by the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Gross vauntous</name>Indians.
             their came up Showers of rain which lasted untill evening.    
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name>&amp; men returned &amp;
          Joined us.    had found no Indians, but had Seen fresh Sign of horses.
             Saw one elegant horse in the plains which appeared wild.    they
          had been about 40 miles up the 
          <name type="place" key="Madison River (Middle Fork)">middle</name>or west fork then
          Struck across the plains to 
          <name type="place" key="Jefferson River (North, Southwest Fork)">the North fork</name>,
          and was near the mountains, and informs us that their is considerable of Snow on them.
             our hunters killed in these bottoms in the forks of the Rivers, 6 Deer 3
          otter &amp; a musk rat.    
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name>&amp; party had killed
          Several Deer goats or antelopes and a young bear.    this is a verry pleasant
          handsome place, fine bottoms of timber &amp;c.    we expected to have found
          the Snake nation of Indians about this place, but as they are gone we expect they are
          gone over the mountains to the River called the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbian River</name>
                  <ref target="n17072717" n="17"/>to fish &amp;c. but perhaps we may find Some this Side
          of the mountains yet.    we Came only 7 miles to day.    at this
          Camp we unloaded all the canoes &amp; conclude to rest &amp; refresh ourselves a day or
          too &amp;c.—    
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name>taken Sick.—</p>
               <p>Saturday July 27th    A Clear morning, We set off early, and proceeded on;
          the current was as rapid as it was Yesterday, we passed some Clifts of rocks, where
          there was a quantity of small bird's nests, built under the shelving rocks.   
          The hills were not so high, as they had been some distance below.    We found
          currants of different kinds in abundance, growing along the shores of the River.—
             At 9 o'Clock A. M. we arrived at the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Three Forks of the">three forks of the Mesouri
          River</name>, which lays in a Valley, in open View of the high mountains, which have
          white spots on them, and has the appearance of being Snow.—    We saw on the
          Hills large flocks of mountain Sheep (or Ibex) and flocks of Antelopes.—   
          The plain lying on the North side of those 3 forks, had been burnt by the natives, We
          proceeded on, and passed the 
          <name type="place" key="Gallatin (South, Southeast Fork) River">South</name>and West
          forks of the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Mesouri River</name>; and went a short distance
          up 
          <name type="place" key="Jefferson River (North, Southwest Fork)">the North fork</name>,
          &amp; encamped on the Point, which is a large smooth plain—    We found here a
          large Camp, where the Indians had been encamped sometime past.—    
          <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Our Indian woman (Interpreter)</name>informed us
          that she was taken prisoner at this place between 3 &amp; 4 Years ago, by a party of the
          
          <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Gross Vaunter</name>(or 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">big Belley</name>) Indians who had
          carried her away to their Nation</p>
               <p>We had showers of rain that continued till the evening.—    
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain Clark</name>and the party that was with
          him returned; and joined us here.—    they informed us, that they had seen no
          Indians, but that they had come across fresh tracts of horses, and had seen one of the
          horses, which was elegant, they found this Horse in the plains and he appeared to them
          to be perfectly wild—    They also mentioned that they had been 40 Miles from
          the best calculation up the 
          <name type="place" key="Madison River (Middle Fork)">Middle</name>or West fork of the
          River, and then had struck across the plains to 
          <name type="place" key="Jefferson River (North, Southwest Fork)">the North fork</name>,
          and had been near the Mountains, and that there was a considerable quantity of snow on
          them.—    Our hunters killed in 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Three Forks of the">the forks</name>of these
          Rivers 6 deer, 3 Otters, and a muskrat, 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain Clarke</name>&amp; his party had killed
          several deer, Antelope, and a Young bear since they had left us.—    
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Three Forks of the">The forks</name>that we are
          present at, is a most delightful situated place, and exceeds any that we have yet seen,
          it affording a most delightfull prospect, the land extreamly rich &amp; fertile; and the
          bottoms large and well timbered, and to all appearance must be healthy,—   
          and may be called the Paradice of the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Mesouri River</name>.    We expected
          to have found the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Snake</name>Nation of Indians here,
          but they being gone, we now expect that they are gone over the Mountains, to the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>to fish.—    The
          party here are of opinion, that they may find some of those Indians, yet; on this side
          of the Mountains.    We came only 7 Miles this day; to where we are encamp'd
             We unloaded all the Canoes this day.—</p>
               <p>Our officers concluded on the party staying here, for some days; in order to refresh
          themselves.—    
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain Clark</name>was this day taken Ill,
          which was supposed to be occasioned by fataigue.—</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n17072701" n="1">The limestone belongs to the 
        <name type="place" key="Mission Canyon Limestone">Mission Canyon</name>or 
        <name type="place" key="Lodgepole Formation">Lodgepole</name>limestones of the 
        <name type="place" key="Madison Group">Madison Group</name>. The rocks in this area have
        been tilted to steep angles by faulting and folding. It was probably 
        <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>who drew a red vertical line
        through part of these geology notes.</note>
            <note xml:id="n17072702" n="2">The 
        <name type="place" key="Madison Mountains">Madison range</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n17072703" n="3">This is a monolithic outcrop of Mississippian-age limestone
        of the 
        <name type="place" key="Madison Group">Madison Group</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n17072704" n="4">Like other maps 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>may have made, this apparently has
        not survived; the information was probably incorporated into 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>map 65.</note>
            <note xml:id="n17072705" n="5">This site, where they remained until July 30, was
        apparently on later 
        <name type="place" key="Barkers Island">Barkers Island</name>(not now named), between two
        branches of 
        <name type="place" key="Jefferson River (North, Southwest Fork)">the Jefferson</name>,
        northeast of the present town of 
        <name type="place" key="Three Forks, Mont.">Three Forks</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Gallatin County, Mont.">Gallatin County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>, and two miles northeast of the present
        town of 
        <name type="place" key="Three Forks, Mont.">Three Forks</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Gallatin County, Mont.">Gallatin County</name>, 
        <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>, and two miles northeast of where 
        <name type="place" key="Interstate Highway 90">Interstate Highway 90</name>crosses the 
        <name type="place" key="Jefferson River (North, Southwest Fork)">Jefferson River</name>. 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>map 65; MRC map 83.</note>
            <note xml:id="n17072706" n="6">An old colloquial name for the mallard. Burroughs, 188–89;
        Holmgren, 30. It was probably 
        <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>who drew a red vertical line
        through the passages beginning with "duckanmallard" to "same rock above."</note>
            <note xml:id="n17072707" n="7">The swamp currant (see 
        <ref n="1805-07-17" type="related">July 17, 1805</ref>).</note>
            <note xml:id="n17072708" n="8">The 
        <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Three Forks of the">Three Forks of the
        Missouri</name>meet near the 
        <name type="place" key="Broadwater County, Mont.">Broadwater</name>-
        <name type="place" key="Gallatin County, Mont.">Gallatin</name>county line, 
        <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>, about four miles northeast of the town of
        
        <name type="place" key="Three Forks, Mont.">Three Forks</name>. The names the captains
        gave to the three forks have remained, unlike many others they bestowed. 
        <name type="person" key="Gallatin, Albert">Albert Gallatin</name>, born in 
        <name type="place" key="Geneva">Geneva</name>, came to the United States in 1780 and
        settled in southwest 
        <name type="place" key="Pennsylvania">Pennsylvania</name>. He was secretary of the
        treasury under 
        <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Madison, James">Madison</name>(1801–11), helped negotiate the
        Treaty of Ghent ending the War of 1812, was minister to 
        <name type="place" key="France">France</name>, 1816–23, and minister to 
        <name type="place" key="England">Great Britain</name>, 1826–27. He was active in
        preparations for the 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>expedition, and devoted much of his
        later life to a study of the American Indians, being recognized as having made the first
        steps toward a systematic classification of Indian languages. Walters.</note>
            <note xml:id="n17072709" n="9">
               <name type="person" key="Madison, James">James Madison</name>, one of the leading figures
        of the Constitutional Convention of 1787 and co-founder, with 
        <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, of the Democratic Republican
        Party, was 
        <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name>secretary of state and
        president from 1809 to 1817.</note>
            <note xml:id="n17072710" n="10">Bank swallow, 
        <hi rend="italic">Riparia riparia</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n17072711" n="11">
               <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>means a branch of the 
        <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>, in this case the 
        <name type="place" key="Lemhi (East Fork Lewis's) River">Lemhi River</name>. He uses the
        term "
        <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbian</name>River" very broadly in the next
        few weeks.</note>
            <note xml:id="n17072712" n="12">The best evidence is that 
        <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name>was captured by 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name>(
        <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Gros Ventres</name>
               </hi>) raiders in about 1800 near the town of 
        <name type="place" key="Three Forks, Mont.">Three Forks</name>. See 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>entries for 
        <ref n="1805-07-28" type="related">July 28</ref>and 
        <ref n="1805-07-30" type="related">30</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n17072713" n="13">The 
        <name type="place" key="Jefferson River (North, Southwest Fork)">Jefferson</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n17072714" n="14">
               <name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">Frazer</name>, 
        <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Joseph</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">Reubin Field</name>, and 
        <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n17072715" n="15">The 
        <name type="place" key="Jefferson River (North, Southwest Fork)">Jefferson</name>and the 
        <name type="place" key="Madison River (Middle Fork)">Madison</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n17072716" n="16">Serviceberry, 
        <hi rend="italic">Amerlanchier alnifolia</hi>Nutt.</note>
            <note xml:id="n17072717" n="17">Like 
        <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, 
        <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse</name>uses the term "
        <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>" broadly. Here it is the 
        <name type="place" key="Lemhi (East Fork Lewis's) River">Lemhi River</name>, a distant
        branch of the 
        <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-07-26" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-07-28" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
