<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.mult.1805-06-14kloefkorn1">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">June 14, 1805 entry by Meriwether Lewis, part 1</title>
            <title type="sub"/>
            <author>Gary E. Moulton</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic
        Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="audio">
               <ref type="x-shockwave-flash" target="n1805-06-14kloefkorn1"/>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl/>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Multimedia</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Audio</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-10-10</date>
            <name>Becky Potter</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-04-12</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="main">June 14, 1805 entry by Meriwether Lewis, part 1</head>
         <head type="sub"/>
         <div type="audio">
            <p>
               <hi rend="right"/>hearing a tremendious roaring above me I continued my rout across the
        point of a hill a few hundred yards further and was again presented by one of the most
        beatifull objects in nature, a cascade of about fifty feet perpendicular streching at
        rightangles across the river from side to side to the distance of at least a quarter of a
        mile.    here the river pitches over a shelving rock, with an edge as regular
        and as streight as if formed by art, without a nich or brake in it; the water decends in
        one even and uninterupted sheet to the bottom wher dashing against the rocky bottom rises
        into foaming billows of great hight and rappidly glides away, hising flashing and
        sparkling as it departs the sprey rises from one extremity to the other to 50 f. I now
        thought that if a skillfull painter had been asked to make a beautifull cascade that he
        would most probably have pesented the precise immage of this one; nor could I for some
        time determine on which of those two great cataracts to bestoe the palm, on this or that
        which I had discovered yesterday; at length I determined between these two great rivals
        for glory that this was 
        <hi rend="italic">pleasingly beautifull,</hi>while the other was 
        <hi rend="italic">sublimely grand.</hi>I had scarcely infixed my eyes from this pleasing
        object before I discovered another fall above at the distance of half a mile; thus invited
        I did not once think of returning but hurried thither to amuse myself with this newly
        discovered object.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
