<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.white_audio11">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Salish People and the Lewis and Clark Expedition</title>
            <title type="sub">Excerpt 11</title>
            <title type="sub"/>
            <author>Salish Pend d'Oreille Culture Committee and Elders Cultural Advisory Council,
        Confederated Salish and Kootenai Tribes</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2006</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="audio">
               <ref type="x-shockwave-flash" target="white_audio11"/>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl></bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-01-23</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-04-12</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="main">Excerpt 11</head>
         <head type="sub"/>
         <div type="audio">
            <p>In the years that followed the Lewis and Clark expedition, the world of the Salish was
        nearly obliterated but it was not wiped out. Partly because, throughout that time, the
        Salish, the Pend d'Oreille, and the Kootenai Nations—and also a number of non-Indians in
        the region—continued to work for a relationship built on mutual respect and the honoring
        of solemn obligations.</p>
            <p>And so, despite the misunderstanding, the injustice, the loss, and the tragedy
        reflected in these pages, there is also hope to be taken from this history. That hope
        depends on us continuing to work together to create a deeper understanding of our
        history.</p>
            <p>The event proved that the bicentennial of the Lewis and Clark Expedition can be about
        something other than blind celebration. The pageant, like this book, was motivated by a
        simple idea: that an unflinching reconsideration of that first encounter, and of the past
        two centuries, is essential if we are to reach for a different relationship—if our
        descendents are to look back in the year 2205, and see the next two hundred years as an
        era of greater respect, and of deeper understanding.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>