<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.mult.white_audio03">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Salish People and the Lewis and Clark Expedition</title>
            <title type="sub">Excerpt 3</title>
            <title type="sub"/>
            <author>Salish Pend d'Oreille Culture Committee and Elders Cultural Advisory Council,
        Confederated Salish and Kootenai Tribes</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2005</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="audio">
               <ref type="x-shockwave-flash" target="white_audio03"/>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl/>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Multimedia</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Audio</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-10-10</date>
            <name>Becky Potter</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-04-12</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="main">Excerpt 3</head>
         <head type="sub"/>
         <div type="audio">
            <p>
               <hi rend="right"/>Lewis and Clark now figure prominently at the beginning of nearly every
        U.S. history textbook. Even today, the word "discovery" pervades most Lewis and Clark
        materials, and it animates the tourist packages shuttling visitors to every point along
        the expedition's route. The expedition is still cast as the genesis of the United States
        as a transcontinental nation. This explains part of the powerful emotions surrounding the
        bicentennial, and the desire of many people to cast the expedition and its underlying
        purpose in the noblest light possible.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="right"/>It also explains why many native voices are being drowned out in the
        celebratory din. When our elders speak, they do not disrespect Lewis and Clark. But they
        do raise basic points that differ from the wholly positive view of the expedition. The
        elders tell us, first of all, that this was and is our land, the place prepared for us by
        Coyote, the place where we have lived for a very long time. They tell us that we were and
        are a sovereign nation. They tell us that we were kind and generous to non-Indian
        visitors. And the elders tell us that the expedition was part of a long process of
        unprovoked invasion, the taking of our resources, the stripping of our rights of
        sovereignty and self-determination, the marginalization of our cultural ways. From the
        perspective of our elders, the expedition was less an innocent "Corps of Discovery" than a
        reconnaissance for invasion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="right"/>We know this will be a difficult message for some readers to hear. It
        cannot be squared with a blind celebration of Lewis and Clark. But we know that many
        people are more interested in understanding the expedition than in simply glorifying it.
        Many are concerned about the damage the continuing distortion of our past does to all of
        us, and especially the countless native children who are every day exposed to a false
        depiction of their own cultures and histories. Many people are interested in a more
        realistic assessment of American history, even if it is a less comfortable assessment. To
        reach that point, we must begin by listening to the voices that have until now been left
        out.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="right"/>By looking at Lewis and Clark within this larger context, we hope this
        book will help open the national conversation on Lewis and Clark, and that it will provide
        some small contribution in helping other tribes have the opportunity to put their own
        voices forward. We would all benefit by learning from the unique perspective of each
        native nation, embedded in their own cultural and historical contexts. A larger collection
        of native narratives on Lewis and Clark would help bring us all to a deeper and richer
        understanding of the entirety of the expedition.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
