<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.mult.videot3">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">Texts</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2005</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic
        Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note/>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl/>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Multimedia</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Video</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-11-30</date>
            <name>Becky Potter</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-04-12</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="main">Moulton discusses the enlisted men's journals</head>
         <div type="additional">
            <p>We have journals from four other enlisted men: Charles Floyd, who was a sergeant on the
        expedition; his journal is very short. He died. He was the only member of the party to die
        on the expedition; his journal starts like everyone else's, on May 14, 1804, when they set
        out on the Missouri River, it only lasts until mid-August when he became ill and died; he
        was buried near Sioux city, Iowa; two sergeants John Ordway and Patrick Gass; Ordway is
        the most complete. He wrote an entry for each of the 863 days they were out, so he is the
        most faithful journal-keeper. Patrick Gass isn't altogether satisfying because we don't
        have the original journal, all we have is a copy that was published and has been reprinted
        over the years. The original has been lost over the years, so we have to deal with a
        heavily-reprinted copy from 1807. Joseph Whitehouse is the only private whose journal has
        come down to us, and it isn't complete so we only have incomplete versions of it. The
        enlisted men's journals, although they vary in completeness, are still an important link
        to the writing as a whole because they provide not necessarily additional information but
        different kinds of information. There may have been other people keeping journals. Lewis
        and Clark are ambiguous about how many people were keeping journals, so people are always
        looking for the "lost journals" of Lewis and Clark.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
