<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.sup.lavender.01.05">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Way to the Western Sea</title>
            <title type="sub">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> across the Continent</title>
            <title type="sub" level="a">Chapter 5</title>
            <author>David Lavender</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2005</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               
               
               
               
               
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Way to the Western Sea</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">Chapter 5</title>
               <author>David Lavender</author>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>2001</date>
               <idno type="ISBN">0-8032-8003-3</idno>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
              <term>Texts</term>
            </keywords>
           <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Books</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-11-09</date>
            <date>2005-04-20</date>
            <name>Becky Potter</name>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Split into chapters Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="five" type="chapter">
            <head rend="center">FIVE. Facing Reality</head>
            <div type="section">
               <p>
His first stop on the way north was <name type="place" key="Fort Kaskaskia (Ill.)">Fort Kaskaskia</name>, <name type="place" key="Illinois">Illinois</name>. Two companies of infantry were stationed there, one under <name type="person" key="Bissell, Richard">Captain Richard Bissell</name>, brother of <name type="person" key="Bissell, Daniel">Daniel Bissell</name> of <name type="place" key="Fort Massac (Ill.)">Fort Massac</name>, and the other under <name type="person" key="Stoddard, Amos">Captain Amos Stoddard</name>. Though the latter was twelve years older than <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name>, they were either already fast friends or soon would be.</p>
               <p>
Times had been dull for <name type="person" key="Stoddard, Amos">Stoddard</name>. When the <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> administration had been preparing for war in 1802, he had been ordered to take his company to the ancient French town of <name type="place" key="Cahokia, Ill.">Cahokia</name>, across the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name> and four miles downstream from <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>, and build a fort there. Before he could start work another message had been rushed to him: <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name> now belonged to the United States and the fort was no longer needed. Instead he should sit tight at 
<name type="place" key="Kaskaskia, Ill.">Kaskaskia</name>, ready to receive, as America's representative, Upper <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name> from the lieutenant governor in <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>. Both <name type="person" key="Stoddard, Amos">Stoddard</name> and <name type="person" key="Bissell, Richard">Bissell</name> welcomed <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> expansively, hoping he had more recent news than they did. But he had been hoping the same of them.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Bissell, Richard">Bissell</name>, heedful of his orders from the War Department, made no trouble about lending a supply boat, a corporal, and six privates to help the expedition partway up the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> during the ensuing summer. The men would report for duty as soon as <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> knew where his winter quarters would be, a determination that depended on whether or not <name type="person" key="Delassus, Carlos Dehault">Lieutenant Governor Delassus</name> would let the Americans enter the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>. In any event, <name type="person" key="Bissell, Richard">Bissell</name> wanted his soldiers back before Christmas, 1804.</p>
               <p>
How many hands, he may well have asked, did <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> have for continuing from the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri's</name> headwaters to the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>? <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether</name> counted them out—the two he had picked up at the start of his trip, the seven <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had recruited at <name type="place" key="Louisville, Ky.">Louisville</name>, two more from <name type="place" key="Fort Massac (Ill.)">Fort Massac</name>, and eight from <name type="place" key="South West Point, Tenn.">South West Point</name>, assuming <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name> returned with that many acceptable volunteers. Nineteen all told, more than the twelve authorized by Secretary 
of War <name type="person" key="Dearborn, Henry">Dearborn</name>, more than the fifteen <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> had bought guns and shirts for at <name type="place" key="Harpers Ferry, W. Va.">Harpers Ferry</name>. Evidently he had some unrecorded understanding with his superiors about signing on as many permanent recruits as he felt he needed. Or maybe, though it seems reckless even for him, he had the understanding with himself. Anyway, the count at the moment was nineteen, plus himself, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, the slave <name type="person" key="York">York</name>, and <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name>, if the interpreter consented to continue with the party. Hardened men all—enough, he thought, to turn back possible Indian attacks, yet not too many to find food for during the final push. And speaking of food, he had his winter camp to consider. Would <name type="person" key="Bissell, Richard">Captain Bissell</name> be so kind as to introduce him to the contractor who was already supplying <name type="place" key="Fort Kaskaskia (Ill.)">Fort Kaskaskia</name> with staples?<ref target="n0501" n="1"/>
               </p>
               <p>
He also asked about an interpreter, for he spoke no French and he had learned <name type="person" key="Delassus, Carlos Dehault">Delassus</name> understood no English. The man recommended to him, <name type="person" key="Hay, John">John Hay</name>, was postmaster of <name type="place" key="Cahokia, Ill.">Cahokia</name> and part-owner of a prosperous American trading firm doing business along the upper <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name>. He turned out to be a jewel—thirty-four years old, nimble, loyal, intelligent, and well acquainted in <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>. He had entered the North West Company of <name type="place" key="Canada">Canada</name> at the age of fourteen and had traded extensively for furs on the <name type="place" key="Assiniboine (Ossiniboine) River">Assiniboine</name> and <name type="place" key="Red River of the North">Red</name> rivers, west and northwest of the headwaters of the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name>.<ref target="n0502" n="2"/> He had listened intently to the tales of men who had risked the upper <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri's</name> snag-filled currents and collapsing banks, and had obtained sketch maps from some of them. He had a broad knowledge of Indian ways and of such unsung but essential arts as the proper loading of keelboats and pirogues.</p>
               <p>
Accompanied by this redoubtable volunteer and a fellow trader named <name type="person" key="Jarrot, Nicholas">Nicholas Jarrot</name>, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name> crossed the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name> on December 8 to call on <name type="person" key="Delassus, Carlos Dehault">Carlos Delassus</name>. From the water the city presented a deceptively fine appearance. Three streets, each about a mile long, ran parallel to the river along the top of a low bluff of yellowish limestone—an important bluff since it resisted erosion by the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name> and collected at its base a sandbar on which keelboats could be loaded and unloaded. About two hundred houses, together with their outbuildings, were scattered along the streets. Most were constructed of squared logs eight feet tall set on 
end and chinked with mud, French fashion, rather than laid horizontally as American log cabins were. The larger dwellings, often built of stone and two stories high, were shaded on two or more sides by wide galleries; kitchen gardens and fruit trees occupied the cluttered areas in the rear. Nearly all buildings, large or small, gleamed with whitewash.</p>
               <p>
Long years since, the inhabitants had hewn steep troughs into the bluff so that carts and wagons could reach the sandbar. One of the streets, called Tour, continued across the parallel thoroughfares to the top of a second bluff, on which stood a round stone fort built in 1780 to repel a British attack that never came. In 1803 it housed <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis's</name> small contingent of troops. The other street, called Bonhomme, led <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and his companions up to the Rue 
Principale, later called Main Street. The government house, where <name type="person" key="Delassus, Carlos Dehault">Delassus</name> lived and worked, stood there.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Delassus, Carlos Dehault">Delassus's</name> round, balding pate was fringed with curly white hair. He had a wide mouth in a round face. Behind his small, wire-rimmed spectacles his eyes, too, looked round. He wore a starched, stand-up collar decorated with a bow tie. Beneath the cherubic appearance lurked a quick temper. According to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, writing <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> on December 28, 1803, the lieutenant governor frequently popped some of the wealthiest of his citizens into the "Carrabose" for the slightest of offenses. "This has produced a general dread of him among all classes of people."<ref target="n0503" n="3"/>
               </p>
               <p>
After looking at the identifications <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> offered, the governor asked testily, through the interpreters, why the American did not have a passport from the Spanish minister in <name type="place" key="Washington D. C.">Washington</name>. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> was prepared for that. Inasmuch as <name type="place" key="Spain">Spain</name> had sold <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name> to <name type="place" key="France">France</name> some time since, he said suavely, he had expected to find French officials installed in <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>; therefore he had supposed his French passport would suffice. Moreover, he added, he had 
been informed while on his way West that the United States had purchased the territory from <name type="person" key="Bonaparte, Napoleon">Napoleon</name>.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Delassus, Carlos Dehault">Delassus</name> granted that those things might be so. (Word of the Louisiana Purchase had, in fact, reached <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> the preceding August.) But since no instructions had come to him from Spanish sources, he could not allow undocumented foreigners to enter the interior provinces. He promised, however, to write his superiors in <name type="place" key="New Orleans, La.">New Orleans</name>. Meanwhile, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> should return to <name type="place" key="Cahokia, Ill.">Cahokia</name> and wait there (if he persisted in going ahead) until a reply arrived.<ref target="n0504" n="4"/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> would rather have pressed a short distance up the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, but this was not a time to stand on his rights, especially since he hoped to spend much of the winter interviewing knowledgeable sources in <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>. Amiably he said that of course his party would stay east of the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name>—not at <name type="place" key="Cahokia, Ill.">Cahokia</name>, though he might make his own headquarters there, but at a place already recommended by <name type="person" key="Hay, John">Mr. Hay</name>. This was the mouth of the small <name type="place" key="Dubois River">Riviêre du Bois</name> (Americanized to <name type="place" key="Dubois River">Wood River</name>) which ran into the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name> directly across from the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>. The site lay eighteen miles above <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>, far enough so that his recruits would not be distracted by the temptations of the town. There they could be drilled and disciplined for what lay ahead.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Delassus, Carlos Dehault">Delassus</name>, who was interested in protecting his own flanks from attack when administrations changed, agreed to the quid pro quo and even invited the visitors to spend the evening at his home. The next day the trio returned to <name type="place" key="Cahokia, Ill.">Cahokia</name>. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> was waiting there, the keelboat and the two pirogues showing signs of the violent wind and rains they had encountered on the way upstream.<ref target="n0505" n="5"/> The captains swapped accounts of their experiences and talked late into the night, reviewing plans.</p>
               <p>
The division of responsibilities they worked out was all but preordained by their natures. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, the frontiersman, would build the winter camp at <name type="place" key="Dubois River">Wood River</name>, collect and pack the supplies that came in, train the men, and ready the boats for a spring start. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, the more socially and politically trained of the two, would seek out men who could give him the kinds of information about Upper <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name> that <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> needed for executing his Indian removal plan and that the expedition would require for carrying out its multitude of assignments. The pattern was not rigid, however. Now and then during the coming months the captains would exchange places, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> going to the camp and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> to <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>, so that each could become familiar with the entire scene.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Delassus, Carlos Dehault">Delassus</name> kept his part of the bargain. When <name type="person" key="Soulard, Antoine">Antoine Soulard</name>, the surveyor general of Upper <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name>, declined, out of fear of the governor, to let <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> copy the maps and census figures in his office, <name type="person" key="Delassus, Carlos Dehault">Delassus</name> cleared the way with a note of permission.<ref target="n0506" n="6"/> Later, after <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> had won the cooperation of the town's leading merchants and traders, <name type="person" key="Chouteau, René Auguste">René Auguste Chouteau</name> and his younger half-brother, <name type="person" key="Chouteau, Jean Pierre">Jean Pierre Chouteau</name>, the influx of material swelled to a flood.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> sifted it first for information relevant to <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name> plan of resettling Upper <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana's</name> non-Indian residents somewhere in the East, in order to turn the West into a vast Indian reservation. To this end he collected statistics about the region's handful of Spanish, the deeply entrenched French, the inpouring Americans, and the numerous blacks, both free and enslaved. He sent questionnaires to leading residents about land holding and land use patterns, about the underpinnings of the economy, and about exploitable natural resources.</p>
               <p>
Did he really believe that a population he estimated at 10,000 including 2,000 slaves and 5,500 American frontiersmen could be shuffled around at will—to say nothing of the Indians? He assured <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> that he did. Yet he also seemed to think the process would take a long time, for he suggested that during the radical change-over Upper <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name> should be divided into three counties and attached to <name type="place" key="Indiana Territory">Indiana Territory</name> for the sake of orderly government.</p>
               <p>
(In the end neither plan was adopted. What eventually happened was the herding, against their will, of Eastern and Southern Indians far enough west not to be a burden, at least for a while, to white settlers. Very few whites were ever relocated during this cruel offspring of <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name> original plan.)</p>
               <p>
While gathering these statistics, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> stayed alert to his own needs. The moment the whites took over the territory, it would become his and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> duty to impress awareness of the change on as many Indian and foreign traders as they could reach during their ascent of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri River</name>. They had to know what to expect. Exactly where and how did the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> turn and twist on its way from the mountains? What sequence of tribes lived along 
its banks? What alliances existed among them? What enmities? By what routes did traders bring merchandise to them, and how did the Indians respond to those traders? Could they develop a program for turning the Indians away from their old purveyors toward the traders of the United States?</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> probings brought him maps, journals, and gossip from many sources—from <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">President Jefferson</name> and <name type="person" key="Harrison, William Henry">Governor Harrison</name> of <name type="place" key="Indiana Territory">Indiana Territory</name>, who mailed him material they had picked up from sources of their own; from Surveyor <name type="person" key="Soulard, Antoine">General Antoine Soulard</name>; from <name type="person" key="Hay, John">John Hay</name> and the Chouteau brothers; from the dean of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri River</name> traders, <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">James Mackay</name>; and from no one knows how many now-anonymous, semiliterate but shrewdly informed rivermen.<ref target="n0507" n="7"/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">James Mackay</name> soon came to embody, in their minds, the essence of these diffuse sources. The trader visited the <name type="place" key="Dubois River">Wood River</name> camp on January 10, 1804, and personally handed <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> a packet of documents the captains later carried up the river. Almost as valuable as the papers was a flood of oral data that <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> did not record in his journal, but that he certainly recorded in his orderly mind. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, too, might have met <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">Mackay</name>. An opportunity to do so came late in February or early in March when <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> and he rode with <name type="person" key="Chouteau, Pierre">Pierre Chouteau</name> and other influential residents of <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> to the <name type="place" key="Saint Charles, Mo.">St. Charles</name> district beside the lower <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, where <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">Mackay</name> lived. There the visitors halted a <name type="native_nation" key="Kickapoo Indians">Kickapoo</name> war party bent on attacking an <name type="native_nation" key="Osage Indians">Osage</name> village farther upstream.<ref target="n0508" n="8"/> From this experience in wilderness diplomacy and from stories of other adventures <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">Mackay</name> may well have told both at <name type="place" key="Dubois River">Wood River</name> and <name type="place" key="Saint Charles, Mo.">St. Charles</name>, the captains learned much about the sort of problems they were likely to face along the river—a river not nearly as unknown in the West as they had supposed.<ref target="n0509" n="9"/>
               </p>
               <p>
The difficulties of which their informants made much had begun in the fall of 1792, eleven years before, when a naturalized Spanish subject, <anchor/>
                  <name type="person" key="D'Église, Jacques">Jacques D'Église</name> (the Spaniards called him <name type="person" key="D'Église, Jacques">Santiago Leglise</name>), arrived in town with a small, gaunt crew, a meager invoice of pelts, and a cargo of tales that astounded and alarmed <name type="person" key="Delassus, Carlos Dehault">Delassus's</name> predecessor, <name type="person" key="Trudeau, Zenon">Lieutenant Governor Zenon Trudeau</name>. The trader said he had discovered, far up the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, two related tribes of Indians hitherto unknown to the Spanish. They were the <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name> and the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>. About five thousand of them, by his estimate, lived in eight or so villages of dome-shaped, earth-covered houses scattered for nearly a dozen miles along the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, both above and below the point where the <name type="place" key="Knife River">Knife River</name> flooded into it, in what is now the west-central part of <name type="place" key="North Dakota">North Dakota</name>.</p>
               <p>
This was Spanish territory. Nevertheless, an old Canadian, <name type="person" key="Ménard, Pierre">Pierre Ménard</name>, lived in one of the earthen towns, as thoroughgoing an Indian in his ways as the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>. Other Canadians on occasion came south from their posts beside the <name type="place" key="Assiniboine (Ossiniboine) River">Assiniboine</name> and <name type="place" key="Red River of the North">Red</name> rivers (in today's <name type="place" key="Manitoba">Manitoba</name>) to trade for horses, corn, buffalo robes, wolf skins, and beaver pelts. Moreover, D'Église added, many of the horses in the Indian villages bore Spanish brands, and 
he had seen Spanish bridles in some of the lodges. Clearly they had come from <name type="place" key="New Mexico">New Mexico</name>. What then was to prevent English soldiers from following British-Canadian traders to the earthen villages and afterwards continuing along the trail of the Spanish traders to the silver mines of <name type="place" key="Mexico">Mexico</name>?</p>
               <p>
Actually, <name type="person" key="D'Église, Jacques">D'Église</name> had touched on a more complex system of barter than he or <name type="person" key="Trudeau, Zenon">Trudeau</name> realized. The <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>-<name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> contact with distant <name type="place" key="New Mexico">New Mexico</name> was not direct but through a chain of tribes that ranged across the central and southern section of the <name type="place" key="Great Plains">Great Plains</name>. Those tribes acquired many horses but little armament from the New Mexicans, who did not want European weapons in the hands of the Indians. By contrast, the tribes of the northern plains were fairly well equipped with armament brought them in canoes by British-Canadian traders, who seldom used 
horses. Northern guns for southern horses and vice versa: it was a trade flow that the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name> were well fitted by geography for expediting as middlemen. This far-flung exchange was what <name type="person" key="D'Église, Jacques">D'Église</name> had glimpsed without comprehending it.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="D'Église, Jacques">D'Église</name> asked for a trading monopoly among the Indians he had "discovered." When it was refused, he found a partner with a little capital, <name type="person" key="Garreau, Joseph">Joseph Garreau</name>, filled two pirogues with goods, and toiled dreadfully back upstream. This time he was blocked by <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> (or perhaps <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>; records are not clear) in what is now the north-central part of <name type="place" key="South Dakota">South Dakota</name>. They roughed him up a bit, took some of his goods, and paid miserly amounts for more to 
use in their own dealings. What little was left, <name type="person" key="Garreau, Joseph">Garreau</name>, "inspired by a troublesome and wanton spirit, used . . . for other purposes than those for which they were intended." That is, he had found one or more young women with whom he wished to exchange pleasures. Or so his senior partner reported when he returned to <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> in quest of more merchandise and, he hoped, favorable reconsideration of his request for a monopoly.</p>
               <p>
He simply did not pack enough weight. <name type="person" key="Trudeau, Zenon">Lieutenant Governor Trudeau</name> had already written his superior in <name type="place" key="New Orleans, La.">New Orleans</name>, <name type="person" key="Carondolet, Francisco">Baron Francisco Carondolet</name>, that the best hope of keeping the British away from <name type="place" key="Mexico">Mexico</name> was to grant the monopoly to a trading company capable of stringing a series of forts along the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> and on to the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>. The forts would not be primarily for garrisoning soldiers but for housing traders whose goods and good will would wean the Indians from the British merchants and thus cool their desire to move on south. <name type="person" key="Carondolet, Francisco">Governor Carondolet</name> not only approved 
the plan but in addition promised a prize of two thousand pesos to whoever brought back from one of the Russian posts on the distant coast a letter, written in Russian, that said the crossing had been completed. Later he raised the prize to three thousand pesos, which apparently was all the public money <name type="place" key="Spain">Spain</name> was able to afford for a wilderness riposte against the hated British.</p>
               <p>
The monopoly that resulted was called La Compagne de Commerce pour la Decouverte des Nations du haut du Missouri, generally clipped in everyday usage to the Missouri Company. As field manager the investors hired <name type="person" key="Truteau, Jean Baptiste">Jean Baptiste Truteau</name>. He may have been a relative of <name type="person" key="Trudeau, Zenon">Governor Trudeau</name> who, for some reason, spelled the last part of his surname with a t instead of a d. For the time and place he was well educated. He had been <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis's</name> first schoolteacher, and he had also traded with the Indians along the <name type="place" key="Des Moines River">Des Moines River</name> in <name type="place" key="Iowa">Iowa</name>.</p>
               <p>
In June 1794, <name type="person" key="Truteau, Jean Baptiste">Truteau</name> started up the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> in two pirogues loaded with goods that cost the company 46,747 pesos. His instructions were explicit. If necessary, he could use half his merchandise to bribe his way past any piratical tribe that tried to stop him; this would be "onerous, but it is proper to make some sacrifice to attain success." On reaching <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> territory, he was to build, as his headquarters, an English-style log cabin (horizontal logs rather than upright ones) and try to learn, while conducting his trade, the geographic truths about the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky Mountains</name>, the Indians that lived on their far side, and the rivers that flowed westward. Above all he should dilute British influence among the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name> by telling them about the great chief of the Spaniards, "the protector and friend of all red men, who loves the beautiful land, free roads [that is, an open river], and the serene sky."<ref target="n0510" n="10"/> Reinforcements whose duty would be to push on to the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name> would follow him upstream the next year, 1795.</p>
               <p>
Alas for plans. The <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name> delayed <name type="person" key="Truteau, Jean Baptiste">Truteau</name> so long he could not possibly reach the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name> before the river froze. To escape his tormentors, he slipped back downstream to an uninhabited stretch of the river valley, where he built a crude winter hut. The <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Mahas</name>, or <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Omahas</name>, led by their villainous chief, <name type="person" key="Blackbird">Parajo Negro (Blackbird)</name>, discovered him there and heaped on more indignities. He survived and spent another year roaming the edges of the plains without 
ever reaching the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>. During those wanderings he kept a journal describing the country and people he saw. He bewailed the second-rate goods that had been given him, the high prices he was supposed to charge, and the low esteem in which Spaniards were held because of the violence and licentiousness of their voyageurs, most of whom were French-Canadians. He declared wisely that exploration and commerce did not fit well together, a point that 
must have interested <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> when his journal fell into their hands at about the time <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">Mackay</name> was telling these stories.</p>
               <p>
In May 1795, while <name type="person" key="Truteau, Jean Baptiste">Truteau</name> was still being bullied by <name type="person" key="Blackbird">Blackbird</name>, his first reinforcement party started up the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> with goods worth 96,779 pesos. Their leader is known now simply as <name type="person" key="Lécuyer">Lécuyer</name>. His orders were to join <name type="person" key="Truteau, Jean Baptiste">Truteau</name> at the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> villages and then continue to the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>. In the event, he bogged down among the <name type="native_nation" key="Ponca Indians">Poncas</name> in northeastern <name type="place" key="Nebraska">Nebraska</name>—a total fiasco. The <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> and its Indians, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> were soberly realizing, were an enormous obstacle.</p>
               <p>
Before word of <name type="person" key="Lécuyer">Lécuyer's</name> collapse reached <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>, the stockholders in the Missouri Company prepared, for launching in August 1795, what was to be the culminating thrust of their westward drive. They loaded four pirogues with a reputed two hundred thousand pesos' worth of merchandise. One pirogue carried placating gifts for the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>, "whom it is necessary to flatter in order not to risk being beheaded," one for the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name>, one for the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>, and the fourth for the still unknown tribes of the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rockies</name> and on beyond to the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>.</p>
               <p>
The commander of the expedition, <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">James Mackay</name>, was carefully chosen. He had emigrated from <name type="place" key="Scotland">Scotland</name> to <name type="place" key="Canada">Canada</name> at about the time of the American Revolution and had found employment with the North West Company. For a time he was stationed at <name type="place" key="Fort Espérance (Canada)">Fort Espérance</name> near the junction, in today's <name type="place" key="Saskatchewan">Saskatchewan</name>, of the <name type="place" key="Qu'Appelle (Catapie, Cappell) River">Qu'Appelle</name> and <name type="place" key="Assiniboine (Ossiniboine) River">Assiniboine</name> rivers. In 1787 he took a few men and a dab of merchandise due south to the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> towns. The arrival of white men was still a novelty then, and the Indians, in their excitement, hoisted the visitors onto buffalo robes and paraded 
them into the village. They stayed ten days. What <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">Mackay</name> collected other than bits of information is unknown.</p>
               <p>
It is not known, either, why he left <name type="place" key="Canada">Canada</name> for <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> and became a naturalized subject of <name type="place" key="Spain">Spain</name>. The reputation he achieved there as a trader was such that the Missouri Company not only agreed to pay him four hundred pesos a year to lead this climactic expedition, but also granted him a share of the profits.</p>
               <p>
The man <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">Mackay</name> employed as his second-in-command is next to unbelievable. He was <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">John Thomas Evans</name>, aged twenty-five, recently arrived in <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> from <name type="place" key="Wales">Wales</name> in quest of a lost group of Welshmen. Pure fable. A standard item of Welsh lore declared that a certain Prince Madoc had led ten shiploads of colonists to America in 1170. They had vanished into the interior. Perhaps they had maintained themselves through the centuries as Christians, or they
had lapsed into savagery, though still white of skin. Whatever the truth, they clearly needed redeeming. Given a pittance of seed money by a group of true believers in Wales, Evans made his way west, supporting himself with such jobs as turned up. In <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> his hopes leaped when he heard that the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name> were unusually light-skinned. The lost <name type="native_nation" key="Welsh Indians">Welsh</name>men! He also learned that a band of traders under <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">James Mackay</name> was preparing to visit them. <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name> promptly asked to go along as one of the thirty-three hands.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">Mackay</name> was reasonably sure that no Welsh blood flowed in the veins of any <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> he had seen, but <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name> was husky and, of greater importance, powerfully motivated. He signed him on not as an ordinary voyageur, but as a first mate of sorts. Inasmuch as there was no possibility of reaching the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> towns ahead of winter—not with an August start—<name type="person" key="Mackay, James">Mackay</name> halted in northeastern <name type="place" key="Nebraska">Nebraska</name>, several miles above the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Platte River (Nebr.)">Platte</name>, close to 
<name type="person" key="Blackbird">Blackbird's</name>
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Omahas</name>; there he built a post he named <name type="place" key="Fort Charles (Nebr.)">Fort Charles</name>, after <name type="person" key="Carlos IV">King Carlos IV</name> of <name type="place" key="Spain">Spain</name>.</p>
               <p>
It was a strategic spot. So that those who followed him could make the most of it he set about establishing sound working relations with the local tribes, which meant outfacing <name type="person" key="Blackbird">Blackbird</name>. He also wanted reports on the land ahead. To that end he sent young <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">John Evans</name> up the frozen river with a small group of chosen hands. The explorers departed in February 1796. If they were lucky, they were mounted on horses obtained from either the <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Omahas</name> or the <name type="native_nation" key="Oto Indians">Otos</name>, who resided a little farther south. Horses were expensive, however, and they may well have walked, with only a packhorse or two along for carrying their gear. Whatever the means, they covered some eighty leagues and had reached the mouth of the <name type="place" key="White River">White River</name>, near today's <name type="place" key="Chamberlain, S. Dak.">Chamberlain</name>, <name type="place" key="South Dakota">South Dakota</name>, when a party of <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux Indians</name> discovered them. Cat-and-mouse for four days. Then a blizzard whooped across the plains. The whites escaped under its cover and hurried back to <name type="place" key="Fort Charles (Nebr.)">Fort Charles</name>. Those <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name> had made it clear that they did not want <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> traders 
cutting in on the commerce they had developed with British interests to the northeast. If <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">Mackay's</name> group hoped to navigate the upper river, they'd better start smoothing the way now—one more item for <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> to remember.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">Mackay</name> had not yet completed all he wanted to do in the <name type="place" key="Fort Charles (Nebr.)">Fort Charles</name> area. Moreover, according to <name type="person" key="Blackbird">Blackbird</name>, British goods were reaching the river not only through Indian middlemen but directly. British traders with packhorses, so the chief said, had gone up the <name type="place" key="Platte River (Nebr.)">Platte</name> the year before, and more merchants were gathering on the <name type="place" key="Minnesota River">St. Peters (Minnesota) River</name> for a push southwestward toward the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name>. If true, and <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans's</name> experience made it seem so, this was a serious trespass on Spanish territory. For the sake of the company's trade <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">Mackay</name> wanted to turn it back. This meant that <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name>, for whom <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">Mackay</name> had developed considerable respect, would have to press on upriver with a few men, get in touch with <name type="person" key="Truteau, Jean Baptiste">Truteau</name> at the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> towns, and work out means of continuing to the Western ocean.</p>
               <p>
Indian messengers invited the principal <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name> chiefs to the <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Omaha</name> villages for a conference. <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">Mackay</name> greased palms, swore undying brotherhood, and argued that in due time his company would be better able than the British to send them whatever items they most desired. They thought it over. <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">Mackay</name> had an impressive assortment of merchandise on display in <name type="place" key="Fort Charles (Nebr.)">Fort Charles</name> and he himself was clearly a cut above the other <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> traders they had seen. Very well. They would let a small party carrying a few bundles of goods go through. With that <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name> loaded a pirogue and 
on June 8 started upstream. Quite probably some of his men, including his interpreter, had visited the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name> with <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">James Mackay</name> in 1787 and then, like him, had chosen to leave <name type="place" key="Canada">Canada</name> for <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name>.<ref target="n0511" n="11"/>
               </p>
               <p>
The party spent two months covering the seven hundred miles to the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> villages.<ref target="n0512" n="12"/> They had to live off the country as they went, and undoubtedly they stopped to give a sales talk to every Indian band that showed the least signs of friendliness. <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name>, moreover, was making a detailed map of the river that he anticipated would be useful not only for the Missouri Company but also for his countrymen when they followed him West to rescue the <name type="native_nation" key="Welsh Indians">Welsh Indians</name>. The <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> delayed him for six weeks, but after that progress quickened, and he reached the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> towns on September 23, 1796. By that time his map covered seven separate, long sheets. There is no evidence that he ever saw <name type="person" key="Truteau, Jean Baptiste">Jean Baptiste Truteau</name>, who may have dropped in on the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> earlier that summer but who had then grown discouraged and returned to <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>.</p>
               <p>
What <name type="native_nation" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name> did find, between a <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> and a <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> village and about three miles below the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Knife River">Knife River</name>, was a "small fort and a hut." Unoccupied at the time, the buildings had been erected two years earlier by a party led to the site by <name type="person" key="Jusseaume, René">René Jessaume</name>, a rascally trader associated with the North West Company. Appropriating the habitation, <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name> ran up a Spanish flag. The act of defiance helped soothe his bitter disappointment: there was nothing about the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> Indians to make him suppose they had ever been related to Prince Madoc's legendary Welsh colonists.<ref target="n0513" n="13"/>
               </p>
               <p>
No <name type="person" key="Truteau, Jean Baptiste">Truteau</name> was around to help point him toward the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>. Working on his own, he found the width of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> to be a hefty thirty-two hundred feet and decided its source must be much farther west than had hitherto been imagined. He heard, possibly from old <name type="person" key="Ménard, Pierre">Pierre Ménard</name>, a far wanderer, of the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone River</name> and of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">Missouri's Great Falls</name>, a little west of the central part of today's <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>. Most surprising was the glimmer that came to him about the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rockies</name>. Apparently they were made up not of one ridge, as shown on <name type="person" key="Arrowsmith, Aaron">Arrowsmith's</name> map, but of four or five parallel chains. The <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, his informant indicated, headed among them far to the south and then ran north between two of the ridges before breaking out of the mountains, perhaps at the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">Great Falls</name>.<ref target="n0514" n="14"/> There is no indication that he pictured those ridges as being anything more than normal hills such as he had seen when traveling through <name type="place" key="Pennsylvania">Pennsylvania</name> on his way to <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>.</p>
               <p>
He estimated by dead reckoning how far west he had come from the <name type="place" key="Missouri">Missouri</name> city, whose longitude he knew. From this he deduced that the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> villages were located at 107°48' west of Greenwich, <name type="place" key="England">England</name>. (<name type="person" key="Mackay, James">Mackay</name>, basing his estimates on his 1787 trip, had come up with 110°–111°.) Actually the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> villages lay at 
101°27'. Since degrees of longitude are separated, at that latitude, by about 41 miles, Evans placed the towns roughly 260 miles (and <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">Mackay</name> 370 miles) too far west. These figures led <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name> to believe he was closer to the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name> than was actually the case.</p>
               <p>
He was never able to test the theory. <name type="person" key="Jusseaume, René">René Jessaume</name>, the fort builder, showed up with a party of Canadian traders. Evans brusquely ordered them off: this was Spanish land. Angered but not wishing to embroil their principals in an international incident, they withdrew. After a few stiffly polite letters had been carried back and forth by Indian messengers, <name type="person" key="Jusseaume, René">Jessaume</name> reappeared. According to <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name>, the Canadian tried to hire a few <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name> to violate the tribe's deeply felt laws of hospitality by killing their guest. The chiefs, discovering the plot, "shuddered at the thought of such a horrid Design and came and informed me of the whole." <name type="person" key="Jusseaume, René">Jessaume</name> then decided to do the work himself and "came to my house with a number of his Men, and seizing the moment that my Back was turned to him, tried to discharge a Pistol at my head loaded with Deer Shot but my interpreter having perceived his design hindered the Execution—the Indians immediately dragged him out of my house and would have killed him, had not I prevented them."<ref target="n0515" n="15"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Pyrrhic victory. The Canadian companies decided that no one really knew which side of the international boundary the villages were on and that they could drive <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name> away with a flood of cheap goods. This they proceeded to do. Later that year, the North West Company sent its great astronomer, <name type="person" key="Thompson, David">David Thompson</name>, to the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> to determine the exact location of the towns. They were indeed in Spanish territory, but by then the point was moot. <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name> had given up and had gone back down the river. At <name type="place" key="Fort Charles (Nebr.)">Fort Charles</name> he discovered that <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">Mackay</name> too had decided that carrying out the Missouri Company's plans was not worth the risk and labor involved, and had gone to <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> to tell the investors so. He had arrived there in May 1797; <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name> followed in July.</p>
               <p>
Thus <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> learned, with more than a little somberness, that <name type="place" key="Spain">Spain's</name> only determined effort to reach the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>, with an expedition larger than and as well financed as theirs, had ended in failure. Could they do any better?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>
When collated, the maps, journals, and oral accounts obtained in <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> and at <name type="place" key="Camp Dubois (Camp Wood, River Dubois) (Ill.)">Camp Wood</name> gave the trail blazers a remarkably full directory of the many tribes that inhabited the banks of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> as far north as the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> towns.<ref target="n0516" n="16"/> They knew which groups were powerful enough to require special attention, which might be helpful, and which dangerous. From this emerged a more comprehensive understanding of the preparations that would have to be completed before the corps's departure in the spring. The physical side of the task fell to <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark</name> under circumstances that were, to state it mildly, taxing.</p>
               <p>
Immediately after reaching the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Dubois River">Wood River</name> on December 12, 1803, he had put his men to work clearing a site for the camp on the south bank of the little stream.<ref target="n0517" n="17"/> That done, they had chopped down trees and cut them into logs for eight or nine cabins, including one for <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>. The men also hauled the unwieldy keelboat partway up the bank and stabilized it with wedges against the fluctuations of the rivers. More heavy ax work was required to break a road about a mile and a half long through the timbered bottomland to an adjacent prairie so that supplies could be brought in by wagon from nearby farms and from <name type="place" key="Cahokia, Ill.">Cahokia</name>, for floating ice in the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name> would make the river route unusable much of the time. Fat turkeys, grouse, opossums, rabbits, and occasional deer furnished the basis of the meals turned out by soldiers assigned to do the camp cooking.</p>
               <p>
Though formal drilling is almost never mentioned in the records, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, as a seasoned professional, may well have believed that routine parade-ground maneuvers were necessary for knitting the group into a team. Periodic breaches of discipline—drunkenness, insubordination, absence without leave, and fighting whether for sheer joy or for proving one's manhood—were often followed by courts-martial, their members chosen from the ranks by <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, 
that at times decreed floggings for the culprits. At other times <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> was more ingenious: when privates <name type="person" key="Potts, John">John Potts</name> and <name type="person" key="Werner, William">William Werner</name> got into a bloody fistfight, he had them work off their excess energy by building a cabin for a local woman who had offered to serve as the camp laundress.<ref target="n0518" n="18"/> On the positive side he rewarded good shooting and commendable actions during duty with extra rations of grog. He also put up prize money, generally a dollar, for the winners of shooting matches with local "countrymen," as he called their civilian neighbors. The troopers generally 
won.</p>
               <p>
On December 16 <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">George Drouillard</name> arrived with the eight men he had been directed to bring in from <name type="place" key="South West Point, Tenn.">South West Point</name>, <name type="place" key="Tennessee">Tennessee</name>. It had been a fast trip and since he was not an army man he had controlled his charges with the strength of his character and, on occasion perhaps, with his bare knuckles. They were not a choice bunch. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, disappointed that none was a hunter, interviewed them carefully, found only four suitable, and asked <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> 
to check the decisions. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> concurred entirely. Meanwhile they again urged <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name>, who had been on temporary assignment while shepherding the men, to join the expedition as hunter and interpreter for the standard pay of twenty-five dollars a month. After wavering for a time he agreed, provided he was given time to straighten out his personal affairs. The request granted, he disappeared from the records until the following May. He and <name type="person" key="York">York</name> 
were the only nonmilitary persons to travel the entire distance from <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> to the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name> and back.</p>
               <p>
On January 9, while hiking through snow squalls to examine a nearby Indian mound, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> broke through the ice of a slough. On returning to camp he found his feet frozen into his shoes, "which rendered precautions necessary to prevent frost bite." By the next day—the day he welcomed <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">James Mackay</name> to the camp—he was very ill. He blamed the indisposition on his wetting and the "excessive cold." Probably, though, it was a flare-up of his familiar digestive disorders, for he kept complaining about being sick for a month and eventually tried to cure himself with pills made from walnut bark, an ancient folk remedy. Throughout much of this time the thermometer never rose above freezing. Yet <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> could write on January 25 in his field notes, "a verry Clear mone Shiney 
night . . . Trees and small groth ar Gilded with ice from the frost of last night, which affords one of the most magnificent appearances in nature, the river began smoking at 8 o'Clock and the thermometer stood at 2° below 0."<ref target="n0519" n="19"/>
               </p>
               <p>
He kept himself busy practicing with the astronomical instruments <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> had left with him, and recording meteorological data—wind, snowfall, ice conditions in the river, temperatures, and so on. He also worked hard at things he could do inside his cabin. He drew plans for reconstructing the keelboat and began making a map of the lower <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, using material gleaned from <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">Mackay</name> and, presumably, from notes sent him by <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>. He also tried to 
read the future. How much time would reaching the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name> require? How many men; how many boats?</p>
               <p>
On January 20 he began estimating distances. Using <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans's</name> and <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">Mackay's</name> charts and perhaps their notes as well, he came within six percent of accuracy in gauging the miles from <name type="place" key="Camp Dubois (Camp Wood, River Dubois) (Ill.)">Camp Wood</name> to the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> villages—fifteen hundred miles instead of the correct sixteen hundred. But as a guideline for the stretch from the villages to the ocean he used the <name type="person" key="King, Nicholas">King</name> and <name type="person" key="Arrowsmith, Aaron">Arrowsmith</name> maps he and <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> had brought with them. One reason for the choice may be that he felt sure <name type="person" key="Thompson, David">David Thompson's</name> instrument readings for the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans'</name> location, as shown on the <name type="person" key="Arrowsmith, Aaron">Arrowsmith</name>-<name type="person" key="King, Nicholas">King</name> charts, were reliable, whereas the <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name> dead-reckoning estimates contained too much room for error. On top of that was the force of tradition. The <name type="person" key="King, Nicholas">King</name> map showed the main branch of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> running almost due west from the villages; <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans's</name> map, by contrast, showed a long dip to the south, and theoretical geography allowed for no such aberration. The <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, as shown by <name type="person" key="King, Nicholas">King</name>, also allowed for a direct, short portage to a presumed south fork of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>. That <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> was thinking, in his estimates, of a very short, traditional portage across the "<name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rock Mountains</name>," as he called them, is indicated by his failure to allow extra time for surmounting the divide.<ref target="n0520" n="20"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Using a distance of 41 miles between parallels of longitude and allowing generously for windings in the rivers, he came up with 1,550 miles from the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> towns to the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>. (The actual distance the expedition traveled turned out to be, for that stretch, 2,550 miles.) On the basis of these estimates, he figured that if the party left <name type="place" key="Camp Dubois (Camp Wood, River Dubois) (Ill.)">Camp Wood</name> on May 1 and traveled 12 miles a day, it would reach the foot of the mountains about September 5. A rate 
of 10 miles a day, which took into consideration pauses for Indian councils, would bring the expedition to the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rockies</name> late in September. In either event, the explorers would camp at the headwaters of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> throughout the winter. Then they would cross the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rock Mountains</name> on Indian horses if possible, make new dugouts, and triumphantly gain the ocean by early summer, 1805.</p>
               <p>
His concept of the party's size wavered between twenty-five and fifty men. "Those numbers will Depend on the probabillity of an oppisition from roving parties of Bad Indians, which it is probable may be in the [name blotted] R." One suspects the "R" he was thinking of was the <name type="place" key="Bad (Teton) River (S. Dak.)">Bad River</name> in central <name type="place" key="South Dakota">South Dakota</name>, where the most belligerent band of the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name> tribe often sought to assert their dominance over any trade moving along the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>. If the number of men needed to challenge them rose, so would the number of craft needed for transportation—perhaps as many as three: the keelboat and two pirogues. Clearly the idea of a dozen men skimping along on the twenty-five hundred dollars authorized by Congress had long since been abandoned.</p>
               <p>
Dissatisfied with the keelboat, he planned to reconstruct it, beginning with a single new mast thirty-two feet tall and jointed at the bottom so it could be lowered. He decided on twenty oars, ten to a side.<ref target="n0521" n="21"/> The rowers would occupy cramped quarters, each pair sitting elbow to elbow on benches three feet wide. Between them and the sides of the boats he would construct lockers 2 feet wide and 1½ feet deep. Their hinged tops could be raised in case of attack by Bad Indians. When the lids were lowered, they would form <hi rend="italic">passe-avants</hi> from which the men could set their poles when propelling the craft by thrusting hard against the river bottom. About ten feet of the bow would be decked over to protect goods and perhaps a few beds from the weather. The high cabin in the stern, clearly shown in his working sketches, contained more lockers and was an inheritance from the original builder in <name type="place" key="Pittsburgh, Pa.">Pittsburgh</name>. A final bit of ingenuity was pure <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>: an awning held by three removable, fork-topped poles to protect the rowers from the sun.</p>
               <p>
The support boats were pirogues. One had six oars and was called the white; the other, of seven oars, was called the red. Whoever sat in the stern of the red pirogue would manipulate the seventh oar as a rudder. The boats may have been the ones <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> had purchased in <name type="place" key="Pittsburgh, Pa.">Pittsburgh</name> and <name type="place" key="Wheeling, W. Va.">Wheeling</name> to lighten his load while descending the <name type="place" key="Ohio River">Ohio</name>. Or one may have come from <name type="place" key="Fort Kaskaskia (Ill.)">Fort Kaskaskia</name>. Or both may have been purchased in <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>. There is no way of telling, though several people have tried.</p>
               <p>
At the end of January 1804, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> put in his first appearance at the camp, accompanied by <name type="person" key="Hay, John">John Hay</name> and one of <name type="person" key="Hay, John">Hay's</name> employees, to talk over developments. Realizing quickly that <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> needed a rest, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> suggested they change places for a few weeks, and on February 9 or thereabouts, the older of the two leaders went downriver to <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>. He walked into a highly pleasant situation created by <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> with the adroit cooperation of the town's social leaders <name type="person" key="Chouteau, René Auguste">René Auguste Chouteau</name>, then fifty-five, and his half-brother, <name type="person" key="Chouteau, Jean Pierre">Jean Pierre Chouteau</name>, nine years younger.</p>
               <p>
Though <name type="person" key="Chouteau, René Auguste">René Auguste</name> had helped found the city in 1764, when he was fourteen, and <name type="person" key="Chouteau, Pierre">Pierre</name> had begun trading with the <name type="native_nation" key="Osage Indians">Osage Indians</name> in the 1780s, they were not pioneers in the American sense, but were urban gentlemen of grace and polish. Like the other prominent French inhabitants of the town, they lived in imposing stone houses with polished wooden floors, elegantly crafted furniture, fine china and silverware. They sent their children to <name type="place" key="Montreal">Montreal</name> or <name type="place" key="Quebec">Quebec</name> or sometimes to <name type="place" key="France">France</name> for a few years of schooling. Their dinners, <name type="person" key="Stoddard, Amos">Captain Amos Stoddard</name> wrote, were 
"sumptuous . . . almost every sort of food dressed in all manner of ways . . . the best wines and other liquors." The women were pretty and danced well, although, in <name type="person" key="Stoddard, Amos">Stoddard's</name> opinion, somewhat theatrically.<ref target="n0522" n="22"/>
               </p>
               <p>
As handlers of most of the furs brought out of the interior and as owners of prosperous farms, a gristmill, and a distillery, the Chouteaus were the dominant economic, political, and social figures of <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>. Wary even before the Louisiana Purchase of the bumptious Americans who were elbowing across the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name>, they were profoundly shocked when word arrived from <name type="person" key="Harrison, William Henry">Governor Harrison</name> of <name type="place" key="Indiana Territory">Indiana Territory</name> that the United States had acquired the trans-<name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name> region. But they, and most of the other leading traders of the city, were too intelligent simply to withdraw and sulk. Eager to maintain their positions under the new government, they had welcomed <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> effusively and they were equally considerate of <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>. Quite naturally but not very diplomatically, the American officers responded with a favoritism for the Chouteaus that created cankering jealousies among their rival traders.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> stayed busy while his health mended. With <name type="person" key="Chouteau, Pierre">Chouteau's</name> help, he distributed a long questionnaire designed to elicit detailed information about the characteristics of the Western Indians: their traditions, warfare, hunting and farming practices, medicines, morals, amusements, and so on—a list originally drawn up the year before for <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> by <name type="person" key="Rush, Benjamin">Dr. Benjamin Rush</name> and his other tutors, in <name type="place" key="Philadelphia, Pa.">Philadelphia</name>.<ref target="n0523" n="23"/> And <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, apparently, was the one who opened negotiations with <name type="person" key="Chouteau, Pierre">Pierre Chouteau</name> about escorting a delegation of <name type="native_nation" key="Osage Indians">Osage</name> chiefs to <name type="place" key="Washington D. C.">Washington</name> to visit the president.</p>
               <p>
Punctilious about outward forms, however much he might contrive in private, <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> had refrained from meddling with the Indians of <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name> until the physical transfer of the territories was completed in both <name type="place" key="New Orleans, La.">New Orleans</name> and <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>. As soon as he learned by special courier that the <name type="place" key="New Orleans, La.">New Orleans</name> formalities were ended and that those in <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> would soon begin, he rushed word to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> to start advising the Western Indians of the change of sovereignty and to discuss with them the establishment of government trading posts in their country. Implicit in the letter was a charge given <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> in the first set of instructions handed him shortly before his departure from <name type="place" key="Washington D. C.">Washington</name>: "If a few of their influential chiefs, within practicable distance, wish to visit us, arrange such a visit . . . at the public expense. . . . If any of them should wish to have some of their young people brought up with us, &amp; taught such arts as may be useful to them, we will receive, instruct, and take care of them."<ref target="n0524" n="24"/>
               </p>
               <p>
The practice of taking Indians to the seat of government so they would be impressed with the might of the whites was almost as old as the New World. In 1804 the long-tested strategy seemed particularly important in dealing with the Indians of <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name>. Most of them had scarcely heard of the United States. Many a chief considered himself more powerful than the cowering Spaniards who came to his people begging for trade; the only rivals they worried 
about were other natives desirous of contending with them for control of the commerce that trickled up the rivers and across the plains. <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> mentioned the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name> as a nation on which he hoped the explorers would make an especially strong and friendly impression, a directive that would have, as we shall see, almost fatal consequences.</p>
               <p>
For the time being, however, the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name> were out of reach. Closer by were the <name type="native_nation" key="Osage Indians">Osages</name>, about five thousand of them, most of them living in what is now southwestern <name type="place" key="Missouri">Missouri</name> and northeastern <name type="place" key="Oklahoma">Oklahoma</name>. The Chouteaus exerted a persuasive influence over the tribe, and when the American captains suggested that certain chiefs be selected for a pilgrimage to <name type="place" key="Washington D. C.">Washington</name>, <name type="person" key="Chouteau, Pierre">Pierre</name> jumped at the chance—provided his role was kept secret lest this new evidence of partiality make his <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> rivals more jealous than they already were.<ref target="n0525" n="25"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Before the <name type="place" key="Washington D. C.">Washington</name> visit could be arranged, a new excitement arose—the ceremonies transferring Upper <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name> to the United States. By means of a letter dated <name type="place" key="New Orleans, La.">New Orleans</name>, January 12, 1804, <name type="person" key="Bonaparte, Napoleon">Napoleon's</name> representative in charge of the transfers, <name type="person" key="Laussat, Pierre Clement de">Pierre Clement de Laussat</name>, had written <name type="person" key="Stoddard, Amos">Captain Amos Stoddard</name> at <name type="place" key="Fort Kaskaskia (Ill.)">Fort Kaskaskia</name>, appointing him the French representative to receive the territory from <name type="person" key="Delassus, Carlos Dehault">Governor Delassus</name>. <name type="person" key="Laussat, Pierre Clement de">Laussat</name> also named 
<name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name>, <name type="person" key="Soulard, Antoine">Antoine Soulard</name>, the surveyor general, and the trader <name type="person" key="Gratiot, Charles">Charles Gratiot</name>, a brother-in-law of the Chouteaus, to witness the correctness of the ceremonies. <name type="person" key="Stoddard, Amos">Stoddard</name> in turn wrote both <name type="person" key="Delassus, Carlos Dehault">Delassus</name> and <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> from <name type="place" key="Fort Kaskaskia (Ill.)">Fort Kaskaskia</name> on February 18, saying he would shortly dispatch a contingent of troops under <name type="person" key="Worrell, Stephen">Lieutenant Stephen Worrell</name> upstream to <name type="place" key="Cahokia, Ill.">Cahokia</name> by boat and that he would cross the river on or about the 24th to confer with <name type="person" key="Delassus, Carlos Dehault">Delassus</name> about details.</p>
               <p>
The letter prompted <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> to make arrangements for leaving <name type="place" key="Camp Dubois (Camp Wood, River Dubois) (Ill.)">Camp Wood</name>. He placed command in the hands of <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">John Ordway</name>, who had been a sergeant at the time he volunteered to join the expedition. He named twenty-year-old <name type="person" key="Floyd, Charles">Charles Floyd</name>, son of a friend of the <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> family and, in <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> words, "a young man of merit," to be <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway's</name> assistant. To give <name type="person" key="Floyd, Charles">Floyd</name> weight in the eyes of the somewhat older and considerably more obstreperous troopers, he raised the young man to a sergeant's rank.</p>
               <p>
By the 24th of February, both <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Stoddard, Amos">Stoddard</name> were in <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>. <name type="person" key="Delassus, Carlos Dehault">Delassus</name>, completely gracious now, entertained them, along with <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> and many of the town's leading socialites, at a regal banquet in Government House. On the 29th, the American troops necessary for lending stature to the occasion landed at <name type="place" key="Cahokia, Ill.">Cahokia</name>. And there they stayed, immobilized by clots of ice along the <name type="place" key="Illinois">Illinois</name> shore.</p>
               <p>
Nervous about affairs at <name type="place" key="Camp Dubois (Camp Wood, River Dubois) (Ill.)">Camp Wood</name>, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> hurried back. (How he crossed the river that chained <name type="person" key="Stoddard, Amos">Stoddard's</name> troops does not appear.) He found his sergeants frantic with frustration. <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">Reuben Field</name> had refused to stand guard when his turn came, and <name type="person" key="Shields, John">John Shields</name> had backed the insubordination. <name type="person" key="Colter, John">John Colter</name>, <name type="person" key="Boley, John">John Boley</name>, <name type="person" key="Robertson, John">John Robertson</name>, and <name type="person" key="Weiser, Peter">Peter Wiser</name> had visited a local grogshop in defiance of orders.</p>
               <p>
A grim <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> ordered the entire contingent to attention in the camp compound while he excoriated the delinquents for failing to measure up to the opportunity that was being presented to them. He outlined the importance of the expedition, said that there would be times when neither <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> nor he could be in camp, and warned that on such occasions the directives of duly appointed sergeants had the same authority as the captains'. He then confined 
the offenders to the camp area for the next ten days.<ref target="n0526" n="26"/> On March 3, after keeping the kind of eye on affairs that made the troopers squirm, he returned to <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> to attend to his duties there.</p>
               <p>
Gradually the ice that had immobilized the soldiers at <name type="place" key="Cahokia, Ill.">Cahokia</name> began to thin. Allowing a safe margin of time for further improvement, the men in charge of the two-day ceremony scheduled the first event, the transfer of the territory from <name type="place" key="Spain">Spain</name> to <name type="place" key="France">France</name>, for noon, March 9, 1804. On the dot of the hour, the dignitaries who had taken position in Government House stepped outside, resplendent in dress uniforms or impeccable black civilian garb—<name type="person" key="Delassus, Carlos Dehault">Delassus</name>, <name type="person" key="Soulard, Antoine">Soulard</name>, <name type="person" key="Gratiot, Charles">Gratiot</name>; <name type="person" key="Stoddard, Amos">Stoddard</name>, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, and <name type="person" key="Worrell, Stephen">Lieutenant Stephen Worrell</name>. If <name type="person" key="Worrell, Stephen">Worrell's</name> soldiers were in <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> at all, they kept a low profile; tomorrow would be their day. And nothing is said anywhere about <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, though he was certainly in attendance.</p>
               <p>
A Spanish soldier stationed on the Government House second-floor veranda leaned out and waved his hat as a signal to a sentry watching from the tower-fort at the top end of Rue Tour. Orders rang out, drums rolled, and Spanish infantrymen in parade dress with knapsacks on their backs marched double time down the street. Silence fell on the close-pressed crowd of French Creoles, many in tears, on lounging American newcomers, on staring Indians, on roughly clad rivermen and field hands, and on the numerous blacks, who, being slaves, were the lowliest of all. The Spanish sergeant barked his men into line and snapped for shoulder arms. The officers drew their swords. Drums rolled again, then stopped. The governor made a farewell speech in French and Spanish. <name type="person" key="Gratiot, Charles">Gratiot</name> translated it into English. <name type="person" key="Stoddard, Amos">Stoddard</name>, acting for the moment as an agent for Napoleonic France, answered formally, and again <name type="person" key="Gratiot, Charles">Gratiot</name> interpreted. Papers changed hands; the Spanish flag slowly sank from the staff in front of Government House. As <name type="person" key="Stoddard, Amos">Stoddard</name> received it, the battery in the stone fort on the hill fired eleven salutes. The dignitaries vanished inside the house, and the crowd slowly dispersed, uncertain of their own emotions.<ref target="n0527" n="27"/>
               </p>
               <p>
That night <name type="person" key="Delassus, Carlos Dehault">Delassus</name> was host at a lavish public dinner and ball in Government House. The next morning, March 10, the same crowd gathered for the symbolic ceremony transferring French Louisiana to the United States. <name type="person" key="Worrell, Stephen">Worrell's</name> troops landed below the bluff and marched up Bonhomme Street (now Walnut) to stand at attention where the Spanish soldiers had stood the day before. At 10:00 <hi rend="smallcaps">A.M</hi>. the same officials, with <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> added this time, stepped outside, <name type="person" key="Stoddard, Amos">Stoddard</name> carrying the Stars and Stripes. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name> and his fellow witnesses stepped forward to testify to the actuality of the transfer, and the little cannon up on the hill boomed out another series of salutes.</p>
               <p>
Upper <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name> was now legally American. As soon as travel was possible, the Corps of Discovery, its status long anomalous, could openly enter the lands of the West. Both <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, who was sometimes a prey to his emotions, and the more placid <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> must have keenly felt the impact of the moment. From now on every move they made would be imbued with the full majesty of their nation. With that must have come a new sense of dignity and a heightened determination not to fail. Yet neither of them, as far as is known, ever left a written word about their reactions to that magic moment.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         
      </body>
      <back>
        <div xml:id="notes" type="notes">
          <head rend="center">Notes</head>
          <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n0501" n="1">On December 19, 1803, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> wrote <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> that during his pause at <name type="place" key="Kaskaskia, Ill.">Kaskaskia</name> he had filled the expedition's roster. He was including the seven-man crew of the supply boat when he said that. (Actually, the boat crew lifted the count to twenty-six.) Jackson, <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, 142, 145.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0502" n="2">Ibid., 155. Innis, 254–55, outlines the travels of a trader named <name type="person" key="Hay, John">John Hay</name> through the borderlands between central <name type="place" key="Canada">Canada</name> and the United States in 1794–95. I suspect this is the same <name type="person" key="Hay, John">John Hay</name>
              <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> met in <name type="place" key="Cahokia, Ill.">Cahokia</name>. In any event, the <name type="person" key="Hay, John">Hay</name> of <name type="place" key="Cahokia, Ill.">Cahokia</name> was able to make valuable corrections to that part of <name type="person" key="King, Nicholas">King's</name> map depicting the regions west and northwest of the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi's</name> headwaters.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0503" n="3">Jackson, <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, 151.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0504" n="4">Ibid., 142–43, 145–47.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0505" n="5">Ibid., 147. Quaife, 63.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0506" n="6">Jackson, <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, 150–51.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0507" n="7">Ibid., 148–55.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0508" n="8">Osgood, <hi rend="italic">Field Notes</hi>, 28.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0509" n="9">My summary of events on the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri River</name> preceding the arrival of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> in <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> rests on four works by the indefatigable Abraham P. Nasatir, two by Abel, and one each by Houck (vol. II) and
              Williams. See bibliography for titles. See also Quaife, 186ff.: Ewers, "Indian Trade"; scattered references in Wood and Thiessen (consult index under "<name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name>," "<name type="person" key="Mackay, James">Mackay</name>," "<name type="person" key="Ménard, Pierre">Menard</name>," "<name type="person" key="Jusseaume, René">Jessaume</name>," "Truteau," "<name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>"); and DeVoto, <hi rend="italic">Course</hi>, 355–79.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0510" n="10">Houck, II, 171.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0511" n="11">Wood and Thiessen, 50.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0512" n="12">DeVoto, <hi rend="italic">Course,</hi> calls this "a lot of time." <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, however, spent about ten days more on the same stretch.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0513" n="13">For <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> on <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans's</name> sad realization: Jackson, <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, II, 515.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0514" n="14">For <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans's</name> map: Allen, 143. For <name type="person" key="Ménard, Pierre">Ménard's</name> wanderings: Wood and Thiessen, 30, 44–45.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0515" n="15">Quaife, 197.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0516" n="16">Scholars have spent years trying to determine just what maps <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> drew on in <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>—a subject too complex to detail in my narrative. To pursue the matter further, start with Diller, Friis, and Allen, 68, 73—180. <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name> died before <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> reached <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>, but much of his material may have fallen into <name type="person" key="Hay, John">Hay's</name> hands and have been passed on by him. (Osgood, <hi rend="italic">Field Notes</hi>, 16; Jackson, <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, 156–57.) For a fine summary incorporating the latest speculation, Moulton, <hi rend="italic">Journals</hi>, I, 6–7.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0517" n="17">"Because of subsequent changes in the channel of the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name>, this site is now on its west side.... The mouth of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> has also shifted and is presently some [four miles] farther to the south." 
              Appleman, 287–90, 366 n. 2.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0518" n="18">Osgood, <hi rend="italic">Field Notes</hi>, under date January 3, 1804.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0519" n="19">Ibid., 16–27. Although <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> hardly sounds well in his field notes, he kept a stiff upper lip when writing his brother-in-law, <name type="person" key="Grogan, William">William Grogan</name>, on January 15. "I am in tolerable health.... My situation is as could be expected in the woods and on the frontier." (Jackson, <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, 164.)</note>
            <note xml:id="n0520" n="20">Osgood, Field Notes, 21. Allen, 160–67.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0521" n="21">
              <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>, 2, flatly states the keelboat had twenty-two oars. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> sketch of the boat clearly shows twenty. (Osgood, <hi rend="italic">Field Notes</hi>, 37, 41.) Completely conclusive, it seems to me, is a mention of twenty oars by a Canadian trader, <name type="person" key="McKenzie, Charles">Charles McKenzie</name>, who saw the keelboat at <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name>. (Wood and Thiessen, 238.)</note>
            <note xml:id="n0522" n="22">For early <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>, the Chouteaus, and the transfer of flags see McDermott, Scharf, and Foley and Rice.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0523" n="23">Jackson, <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, 157–61.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0524" n="24">Ibid., 64, 165–66.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0525" n="25">Ibid., 167–68.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0526" n="26">Dillon, 93–94.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0527" n="27">Details of this and the following transfer come from Scharf, 250ff., and articles by Shoemaker and McDermott. Legend attests that after the Spanish flag was lowered in <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>, the French tricolor replaced it briefly, as had happened in <name type="place" key="New Orleans, La.">New Orleans</name>. However, the tale did not pop up until 1876 and is open to doubt.</note>
          </div>
        </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.sup.lavender.01.04" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.sup.lavender.01.00" type="contents"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.sup.lavender.01.06" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
