<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.sup.allen.02">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">Montana [The Magazine of Western History] 21.3 (1971): 2–17.</title>
            <title type="sub">New World Encounters</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="Allen, John L.">John L. Allen</name>
            </author>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic
        Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
              <bibl/>
          </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Supplements</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Texts</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-11-28</date>
            <name>Beth Burke</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-04-12</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="additional">
            <head type="main">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>&amp; 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>on the Upper Missouri: Decision at
        the Mamas</head>
            <p>by 
        <name type="person" key="Allen, John L.">John L. Allen</name>
            </p>
            <p>(This article first appeared in 
        <hi rend="italic">
                  <ref target="http://www.his.state.mt.us/pub/magazine/default.asp">Montana [The Magazine of
          Western History]</ref>
               </hi>21.3 [1971]: 2–17.)</p>
            <p>On April 7, 1805, The Corps of Western Discovery under the command of 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark</name>left winter quarters near the
        fortified villages of the 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indian">Mandan</name>nation in present-day North
        Dakota and, in six canoes and two pirogues, headed up the Missouri River into the
        unknown—"a country at least two thousand miles in width, on which the foot of civilized
        man had never trodden."
        <ref target="n01" n="1"/>
            </p>
            <p>Like virtually all exploring expeditions, this one had a goal—a goal as old as Europe's
        realization that the New World was a barrier lying athwart the all-water route to the
        Orient. For three centuries, the conjectural Northwest Passage or Passage to India had
        conditioned North American exploration. The experiences of explorers during those
        centuries had altered the nature of the dream passage and the earliest conceptions of a
        sea-level strait across the continent gave way to views of inland seas connected to the
        eastern and western oceans by mighty rivers.</p>
            <p>These rivers retreated, in turn, before ideas of great navigable waterways which
        mingled their waters somewhere in the interior of the continent and provided
        interconnected water travel from east to west.</p>
            <p>But although exploration had changed the nature of the conceptual Passage, it had not
        changed the dream itself. By the time of 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, the Passage to India had been
        articulated in its final and most realistic form—it was a simple and very short portage
        between the headwaters of a navigable river which flowed to the Atlantic and the sources
        of a great river draining toward the setting sun. Guided by 
        <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Thomas Jefferson</name>'s specific
        instructions to locate the portage between the heads of the Missouri and Columbia rivers
        and establish thereby the "most direct and practicable water communication across this
        continent for the purposes of commerce,"
        <ref target="n02" n="2"/>the men of the 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>Expedition turned their faces toward
        the West and toward the final solution to the centuries–old riddle of the water route
        across North America.</p>
            <p>Preparation for this attempt on the Northwest Passage had been lengthy and careful;
        among all the planning efforts, none were more painstaking or more important than the
        accumulation of the then-available geographical knowledge about the western parts of North
        America. 
        <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Thomas Jefferson</name>, conceiver and sponsor
        of the Expedition, had spent years gathering and analyzing geographical and cartographic
        information on the possible connections between the Missouri and the
        first-mythical-then-actual Great River of the West or Columbia.
        <ref target="n03" n="3"/>
            </p>
            <p>Much of this information had been imparted to 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name>, 
        <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>'s personal secretary, prior
        to the Expedition. Before the party left Fort Mandan in the spring of 1805, considerably
        more lore on western geography had been added.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and his co-commander, 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark</name>, had, during the encampment
        at Wood River near St. Louis in the winter of 1803–04, studied the maps and journals
        brought from Washington by 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>or forwarded by 
        <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>and others. This material was
        combined with data obtained from merchants, fur traders, and government officials in the
        St. Louis area. When the captains started their journey to the Pacific in the spring of
        1804, they took with them a set of definite geographical conceptions about the West,
        gleaned from the materials they had spent months in studying.</p>
            <p>Although neither captain wrote a description or drew a map to illustrate their image of
        the West before leaving Wood River, it is possible to understand the nature of their views
        on western geography by examining those geographical materials which they considered to be
        the most important. Among all the items upon which 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>relied most heavily in making their
        plans, none was more representative of the extent and character of their geographical
        knowledge than the 1802 edition of 
        <name type="person" key="Arrowsmith, Aaron">Aaron Arrowsmith</name>'s map of North
        America.</p>
            <p>This map, drawn by a British cartographer and based on the late Eighteenth Century
        surveys of 
        <name type="person" key="Fidler, Peter">Peter Fidler</name>, a Hudson's Bay Company
        employee, was widely considered by the finest geographical minds of the time to be the
        best and most accurate representation of the West. As such, it is symbolic of the nature
        of the image held by 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>. From it, and from other materials
        which supplemented it, the captains derived those elements of their image which bore
        directly on their central objective of locating the shortest water route across the
        continent.
        <ref target="n04" n="4"/>
            </p>
            <p>In the explorers' mind's-eye view of the country through which they were to pass, the
        significant features were the drainage systems of the Missouri and Columbia rivers, the
        courses and navigability of those streams, and the Rocky Mountain source region from which
        they flowed. And in the image held by 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>in the spring of 1804 these elements
        held the promise of the Passage to India.</p>
            <p>The drainage system of the Missouri was seen as triangular or fanlike in shape. The
        base of the triangle lay along the eastern side of a range of mountains where, between the
        45th and 50th parallels of latitude, a number of small but navigable rivers had their
        sources. These rivers flowed toward the east and converged to form two major streams which
        joined at the apex of the triangle near the 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>villages, recognized by 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>as the furthest penetration of
        explorers and traders into the western interior of the Louisiana Territory. From the
        villages, the river that was now called the Missouri turned toward the southeast to enter
        the Mississippi at St. Louis.</p>
            <p>Of the two main rivers that joined near the 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>villages, the southern was
        the true Missouri. It had its source in the mountains near the headwaters of streams which
        flowed toward the Pacific. From this source it ran a course that was nearly due
        west-to-east and was navigable throughout. This was the proper route to the Pacific.
        <ref target="n05" n="5"/>
            </p>
            <p>The mountain range in which the Missouri had its source appeared in the captains' image
        as a narrow, single-ridge structure, extending from south to north and being extensive in
        neither height nor breadth.
        <ref target="n06" n="6"/>On the western slope of this range, opposite the heads of the
        Missouri and the streams which fed it, were the source waters of the Columbia system.
        Although the Columbia was more of a geographical unknown than the Missouri, it was assumed
        that its source rivers were also navigable to their heads.</p>
            <p>The assumed navigability of the upper reaches of both the Missouri and the Columbia
        combined with the captains' notions on the size of the mountain range they knew as the
        Rocky or Stony Mountains to create the core of misconception upon which their mission was
        based. The Missouri was navigable to its source in a range of low mountains and only a
        short and easy portage across that range would be necessary to link the waters of the
        Atlantic with some navigable branch of the Columbia. With this linking the ancient dream
        of the Passage to India could become a reality.</p>
            <p>The image of western geography that 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>carried up the Missouri in the spring
        of 1801 underwent significant changes during the first summer of exploration and the
        winter hibernation at Fort Mandan. Acquisition of geographical knowledge did not cease
        with the Expedition's departure from the Wood River camp and inputs of new knowledge from
        documents and maps, fur traders, and Indians served to restructure the captains'
        geographical understanding of the West.</p>
            <p>Even before leaving Wood River, 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>acquired documents from the
        explorations of 
        <name type="person" key="Evans, John">John Evans</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">James Mackay</name>, Spanish-sponsored explorers
        in the Missouri Valley during the late Eighteenth Century.
        <ref target="n07" n="7"/>A journal written by 
        <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">Mackay</name>and a map of the country west of the 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>villages, drawn by 
        <name type="person" key="Evans, John">Evans</name>, provided the captains with the most
        current knowledge available on the West. Although this data was received too late to
        become assimilated into their image before their departure, 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>would find it vital for later
        modifications of that image.</p>
            <p>Even more important was information received during the winter at Fort Mandan.
        Throughout the long winter there, from November of 1801 to April of 1805, 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>were visited in their winter quarters
        by 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>and Minitaree Indians and by
        traders in the employ of the British Northwest Company. From these visitors the captains
        obtained sketches and oral information on the country to the west.
        <ref target="n08" n="8"/>This data, in conjunction with the 
        <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">Mackay</name>–
        <name type="person" key="Evans, John">Evans</name>material, was responsible for changes in
        the earlier image. New information had given old ideas new expression and although the
        central theme in the explorers' image of the West was still the Passage to India, many of
        the elements within that image had undergone change by the end of the winter at Fort
        Mandan.</p>
            <p>The nature of these changes and the character of the new image can be seen quite
        clearly in what is, quite possibly, the most important documentary material of the entire
        Expedition. This material, compiled by the captains during the Fort Mandan winter,
        includes 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>'s lengthy and detailed
        geographical description of the West and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>'s large map of the country from St.
        Louis to the Pacific.
        <ref target="n09" n="9"/>
            </p>
            <p>One of the major components of the new image was the recognition that neither the
        straight-line course of the Missouri from the mountains to the 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>villages nor the fanlike
        drainage pattern of the Missouri system as shown on the 
        <name type="person" key="Arrowsmith, Aaron">Arrowsmith</name>map were accurate.</p>
            <p>From the 
        <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">Mackay</name>–
        <name type="person" key="Evans, John">Evans</name>material and from the Indian
        information, 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>had learned that the Missouri did not
        divide into two major branches above the 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>villages. Instead, the
        Missouri proper was the only major river west of the 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>s. It did, it is true, flow a
        fairly straight course from the mountains. But its sources were far to the south and it
        flowed northward between several mountain ranges before bending toward the east and
        passing out of the mountains.</p>
            <p>This was a critical restructuring of the view of the West. 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>had learned of the long
        south-to-north passage of the Missouri through the mountains. They had also learned that
        the Rockies were not a single ridge but were composed of several ranges. And, finally,
        they had learned of a critical landmark of the Upper Missouri. At the point where the
        Missouri left the mountains and flowed into the plains there was a great cataract. This
        was the Missouri's Great Falls and both the 
        <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">Mackay</name>–
        <name type="person" key="Evans, John">Evans</name>data and the Indian information agreed
        on its location near the Missouri's emergence from the Rockies.</p>
            <p>Since their sources of data placed the Falls near the 47th parallel of latitude, 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>concluded that the fanlike drainage
        system shown on the 
        <name type="person" key="Arrowsmith, Aaron">Arrowsmith</name>map between the 4th and 50th
        parallels was a misrepresentation. 
        <name type="person" key="Arrowsmith, Aaron">Arrowsmith</name>'s data provider, 
        <name type="person" key="Fidler, Peter">Peter Fidler</name>, could not have gone as far
        south as the 45th parallel without seeing the Missouri or its Great Falls. Therefore, his
        surveys must have all been made north of the Missouri and the mountains he saw with small
        streams issuing from them must lie above the 47th parallel.
        <ref target="n10" n="10"/>
            </p>
            <p>These corrections in the 
        <name type="person" key="Arrowsmith, Aaron">Arrowsmith</name>map were not the only changes
        made in the captains' image of the West. Another feature of the new image was an absolute
        increase in the quantity and quality of knowledge of the country between the 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>villages and the Pacific.
        This new knowledge included vital descriptions of the Missouri itself, of the streams
        tributary to it, of its passage through the Rockies, of the portage between its source and
        the waters of the Columbia, and, finally, of the course of the Columbia to the
        Pacific.</p>
            <p>Above the 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>villages, the Missouri ran a
        direct course to the Great Falls, located near the first or easternmost range of the
        Rockies. Between the villages and the mountains the Missouri was joined by the Knife, the
        Little Missouri, the Yellowstone, and the Musselshell, all coming from the south. From the
        north came the White Earth River and the Missouri's most important northern tributary, a
        river that the Indians had called "the river which scolds at all others."</p>
            <p>From the Falls, the Missouri turned to the southwest and was joined from the west by
        the Medicine River. The southwesterly direction continued through a second and third range
        of mountains to a point above the third range of mountains where three rivers of nearly
        equal size joined to form the Missouri proper. Here was knowledge of another critical
        landmark—the Three Forks.</p>
            <p>The westernmost fork of the Missouri above Three Forks was navigable to the foot of the
        fourth and final range of the Rockies. Across this range to the west, at a distance of a
        half-day's journey, the waters of a mighty southern branch of the Columbia ran in a
        south-to-north direction and then, bending westward, flowed through plains to the Columbia
        proper and thence to the Pacific.
        <ref target="n11" n="11"/>
            </p>
            <p>Here was the short portage, the Passage to India. It did exist and therefore it could
        be located and negotiated and all the commerce of the Orient could be brought to American
        shores. Full of the hope and expectation and optimism that this image created, the
        Expedition left its winter camp.</p>
            <p>The upriver voyage from Fort Mandan, begun on April 7, 1805, proceeded past the mouths
        of the Little Missouri, White Earth and Yellowstone rivers, each located approximately
        where it should have been, according to the available knowledge. This part of the journey
        was pleasant and without major incident. Although the wind blew violently from the west
        and northwest, stinging the faces of the men and sometimes obscuring the far shores of the
        Missouri with clouds of dust and sand, the countryside was rich and beautiful,
        grass-cloaked and teeming with immense herds of buffalo, deer, elk, and antelope. It was a
        beautiful spring and if the winds continued to blow and ice formed on the cooking pots
        during the nights, the days were warm. By May 4, the snow had all but disappeared and the
        open grasslands and trees along the river were showing the light green of spring in the
        Great Plains.</p>
            <p>On May 8, the Expedition reached the mouth of the river that they named the Milk, after
        the color of its waters. The captains concluded that this river was the one the Indians
        who had visited Fort Mandan during the winter had called "the river which scolds at all
        others." The Milk River was the only major tributary entering the Missouri from the north,
        according to their Indian informants. As such, it was an important landmark and to find it
        about where they had anticipated meant that the conceptions with which they left Fort
        Mandan were holding true.
        <ref target="n12" n="12"/>Above it lay the Great Falls, the Three Forks, and the short
        portage to Columbian waters.</p>
            <p>For the next ten days the small fleet sailed through the fantastic country of the
        Missouri Breaks. Although 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>believed that the Great Falls were at
        least two hundred miles from the mouth of the Milk Rivera,
        <ref target="n13" n="13"/>both they and the men became extremely anxious to come in sight
        of the first ranges of the Rockies that their information had represented to them as
        beginning near the cataracts of the Missouri.</p>
            <p>They were temporarily elated when, on May 19, 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>climbed a hill on the northern side
        of the Missouri and saw to the west and north the first outlying ranges east of the Rocky
        Mountains. These mountains remained in sight on both sides of the river for several days.
        They did not match the descriptions given them by the natives, however, and the captains
        soon realized that they were not viewing the ranges near the Falls.
        <ref target="n14" n="14"/>
            </p>
            <p>From the first sighting of the scattered ranges east of the Rockies, the progress of
        the Expedition up the Missouri became more tedious. For hours at a time the party was
        compelled to beach their craft, waiting for the wind to abate. The river became more and
        more choked with shoals and sandbars and the captains must have begun to wonder about the
        validity of their assumptions about the navigability of the Missouri. In most places the
        boats had to be towed by lines from the shore. The rocks of the bluffs, broken here and
        there by the numerous dry channels through which water from the plains above the Missouri
        enters the river, closed in on either side and made towing a hazardous and difficult
        operation.</p>
            <p>Mountainous country continued to be visible north and south of the river and when, on
        May 26, the very tips of the Highwood Mountains came into view just above the western
        horizon, the captains were convinced that they were nearing the first range of the Rockies
        and, therefore, the Great Falls.
        <ref target="n15" n="15"/>Traveling became easier above the unexpected Judith River and
        the distant mountains remained in sight. Anticipation now ran high. 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>knew, from their distance
        calculations and the proximity of the mountains, that they were close to the Falls and to
        the portage of hope and desire which lay beyond.</p>
            <p>But before reaching the Great Falls, the 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>Expedition encountered one of the
        greatest obstacles in the course of their two-year journey, a problem that they would
        spend more than a week in solving completely. In the late afternoon of June 2, the party
        came to and camped in a grove of small cottonwoods on the Missouri's left bank, opposite
        the mouth of a "very considerable river" which entered the Missouri from the north and
        almost equalled it in size.</p>
            <p>This river was the Marias and its presence was puzzling. In the explorers' store of
        geographical information there was agreement that the Missouri had only one major northern
        tributary. That was "the river which scolds at all others" and they had passed the river
        fitting that description more than three weeks before.</p>
            <p>What, then, was to be made of this second northern river? Or, if the northern branch
        were the true Missouri, what was to be made of the southern branch? Their information
        contained no account of a large southern tributary stream above the mouth of the
        Yellowstone.
        <ref target="n16" n="16"/>
            </p>
            <p>The true Missouri was the river, according to their conceptions of western geography,
        that had its sources within portaging distance of the navigable waters of the Columbia
        River. It was, therefore, the river that must be followed to its uppermost reaches if the
        Passage to India were to be found. But the unexpected division of the Missouri into two
        streams of near-equal size necessitated a major decision: "which of these rivers was the
        Missouri, or that river which the Minetares call Amahte Arz-zha or Missouri, and which
        they had described to us as approaching very near to the Columbia River?" 
        <ref target="n17" n="17"/>
            </p>
            <p>For the purpose of answering this question, the party crossed the Missouri below the
        junction early on the morning of June 3 and "formed a camp on the point formed by the
        junction of the two large rivers."
        <ref target="n18" n="18"/>Here the decision that would determine the success or failure
        of the entire enterprise would be made:</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">to mistake the stream at this period of the season, two months of the
          traveling season having now elapsed, and to ascend such stream to the rocky Mountain or
          perhaps much further before we could inform ourselves whether it did approach the
          Columbia or not, and then be obliged to return and take the other stream would not only
          loose us the whole of this season but would probably so dishearten the party that it
          might defeat the expedition altogether. convinced we were that the utmost circumspection
          and caution was necessary in deciding on the stream to be taken.</hi>
               <ref target="n19" n="19"/>
            </p>
            <p>The process of making this critical decision was not, as it has often been supposed, a
        simple one based on field observation alone. Nor was the decision itself just a lucky
        guess. Instead, the decision-making procedure was a complex and well–calculated series of
        operations lasting more than a week.</p>
            <p>On the first day at the junction, the captains decided to make a preliminary
        investigation of the width, depth, and speed of flow of the two rivers in order to
        determine which was the major stream. To this end they sent a light canoe manned by three
        men up each branch. In an attempt to get some kind of long-range bearing on the direction
        from which the two forks came, they also sent several small parties by land to travel as
        far as possible and still return by nightfall.</p>
            <p>Meanwhile, 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>remained at the camp between the two
        rivers and made observations in the immediate area. During the morning they strolled to
        the highest ground between the Missouri and Marias and from this observation point had
        what 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>termed an "inchanting view:"</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">to the South we saw a range of lofty mountains which we supposed to be
          a continuation of the S. Mountains. stretching themselves from S.E. to N.W. terminating
          abbruptly about S.West from us; these were partially covered with snow; behind these
          Mountains and at a great distance, a second and more lofty range of mountains appeared
          to stretch across the country in the same direction with the others, reaching from West,
          to the N. of N.W., where their snowey tops lost themselves beneath the horizon. This
          last range was perfectly covered with snow.</hi>
               <ref target="n20" n="20"/>
            </p>
            <p>But although the view was sublime, it was inconclusive. Little could be learned about
        the courses of the rivers, their channels being obscured by the convolutions of the
        countryside.</p>
            <p>From the high ground the captains wandered down into the lovely little valley of the
        Teton River, through chokecherry and gooseberry and wild rose, thence back to the junction
        of the Missouri and Marias. Here they examined the nature of the two main rivers more
        closely:</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">we took the width of the two rivers, found the left hand or S. fork
          372 yards and the N. fork 200. The no[r]th fork is deeper than the other but it's
          currant not so swift; it's waters run in the same boiling and roling manner which has
          uniformly characterized the Missouri throughout it's whole course so far; it's graters
          are of a whitish brown colour very thick and terbid, also characteristic of the
          Missouri; while the South fork is perfectly transparent runds very rappid but with a
          smoth unriffled surface it's bottom composed of round and flat smooth stones like most
          rivers issuing from a mountainous country. the bed of the N. fork composed of some
          gravel but principally mud.</hi>
               <ref target="n21" n="21"/>
            </p>
            <p>“In short,” wrote 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, "the air and character of this
        river [the Marias] is so precisely that of the Missouri below that the party with very few
        exceptions have already pronounced the N. fork to be the Missouri."</p>
            <p>But at this point, sometime in the afternoon of June 3, 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>showed their competence as field
        observers and analyzers of geographical information and made the initial assessment that
        further study would prove to be correct.</p>
            <p>“If we were to give our opinions I believe we should be in the minority," noted 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>. It is quite apparent that, in
        their considered opinion, the southern river was the one the Indians had described to them
        as approaching the waters of the Columbia. The limited and brief reconnaissance undertaken
        that morning was responsible for this tentative conclusion. But the conclusion was
        possible only because the things observed during the mornings' field work were analyzed in
        the light of what were, to 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, the "known" graphical facts.</p>
            <p>When the captains returned from their reconnaissance of the morning of June 3, they
        returned with a perspective that was crucial for their decision. From the height-of-land
        separating the Missouri and Marias they had not been able to see the course of either
        river beyond the junction—but they had seen mountain ranges to the south and southwest.
        The nearest range of mountains had been in view for over a week and were not, by this
        time, considered to be the first range of the Rockies that was believed to begin near the
        Great Falls.</p>
            <p>But behind these ranges, to the south and southwest and at a great distance, lofty,
        snow-covered peaks were visible and these might well have seemed to be the range near the
        Falls. If so, and if the southern branch continued its southwesterly trend above the
        junction, then it was the river which lay in the proper geographic relationship with the
        mountains and was, consequently, the river leading to Columbian waters.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, their examination of the characteristics of the rivers upon their return
        to the base camp at the junction had shown the waters of the southern fork to be
        transparent, running over a bottom of round and flat smooth stones. It was "like most
        rivers issuing from a mountainous country" and the true Missouri, according to the
        captains' image, ran through mountains for a considerable distance from its source, all
        the way to its entrance into the plains at the Great Falls. The northern fork, their
        examination showed, was a muddy and silty river and although it was very similar to the
        Missouri below the junction, 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>were inclined to view it only as a
        tributary stream. It might well have been part of the drainage system indicated in their
        re-evaluation of the 
        <name type="person" key="Arrowsmith, Aaron">Arrowsmith</name>map and probably passed
        through the plains north of the Missouri without penetrating the mountains far enough to
        interlock with the Columbia.</p>
            <p>On the evening of June 3, 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>wrote:</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">I am confident that this river rises in and passes a great distance
          through an open plain country ... convinced I am that if it penetrated the Rocky
          Mountains to any great distance it's waters would be clearer unless it should run an
          immence distance indeed after leaving those mountains through these level plains in
          order to acquire it's turbid hue.</hi>
               <ref target="n22" n="22"/>
            </p>
            <p>The river whose transparent waters flowed from the southwest, from the mountains, was
        probably the Missouri and, therefore, the proper route to the Pacific.</p>
            <p>But this assumption was only tentative. The parties that had been sent by land and
        water up both branches had returned with no conclusive information and the captains were
        still puzzled by the failure of their Indian informants to mention the junction of the
        Missouri and a large tributary stream.
        <ref target="n23" n="23"/>Furthermore, it is apparent from the tone of the captains'
        journal for June 3, that they were the only members of the party who did not adhere to the
        belief that the northern fork, because of its similarities with the Missouri below, was
        the proper river to follow.</p>
            <p>Two factors played a role in shaping the events of the week to follow. First. 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>were good enough officers to realize
        the potential deterioration of their command situation should they go against the opinions
        of their men—some of whom were trained rivermen and wilderness experts—and then be proved
        wrong. And second, although the captains might have been firm in the belief that the
        left-hand fork was the Missouri and had the geographical evidence to support this view,
        they were too competent not to recognize the tactical dangers of a hasty decision without
        more definite proof of their preliminary assessment. Accordingly, it was concluded that
        each officer should take a small party and "ascend these rivers untill we could perfectly
        satisfy ourselves of the one, which it would be most expedient for us to take on our main
        journey to the Pacific."
        <ref target="n24" n="24"/>
            </p>
            <p>On the cool and cloudy morning of June 4, Captains 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>departed from the camp at the
        junction of the Missouri and Marias rivers. 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>and a party of five men set out up
        the right-hand side of the Missouri, keeping to the higher lands well back from the river
        in an attempt to get the best views possible. By the end of a rainy afternoon they had
        traveled nearly 30 miles and made camp in an abandoned Indian shelter somewhere near the
        later site of Fort Benton. Except for an encounter with a couple of grizzlies, the small
        party spent an uneventful night alongside the Missouri, the waters of which continued to
        run rapidly over a gravelly bed.</p>
            <p>It rained and snowed intermittently throughout the night and when the party prepared to
        break camp the morning of the 5th, they noted considerable amounts of snow on the
        mountains (the Highwood Mountains) southeast of their campsite. By around noon they had
        come in sight of other snow-covered mountains (the Little Belt and Big Belt ranges) to the
        southwest and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>had seen enough to convince him that
        the river they were following was the true Missouri. From a ridge high above the river 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>could see the waters of the Missouri,
        still running deep and swift and trending toward the southwest, toward the mountains that
        he assumed to be those near the Falls.</p>
            <p>To proceed any further would be useless and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>and his men struck out overland for
        the main camp at the junction, reaching the Teton River in the late afternoon and making
        camp in its valley. At five o'clock on the next afternoon, June 6, the party led by 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>arrived at the junction of the
        Missouri and Marias where they expected to find 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>waiting for them.</p>
            <p>But 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>was taking a little bit longer to
        reach a firm conclusion. He and his party of six men had crossed the Marias from the camp
        at the junction on the morning of the 4th and had proceeded on foot up that river along
        its right bank. At a distance of about five miles from the main camp, 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>climbed a hill from which he
        viewed the "North Mountains" (the Bearpaws) lying toward the northeast and saw the
        northwesterly trend of the Marias. To the northwest, along the course of the river he was
        following, he could see nothing but a range of hills and since this view was inconclusive,
        he determined to proceed further.</p>
            <p>The river continued its course to the north and west and for the remainder of the day, 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and his party traveled through the
        plains behind the river bluffs and, when the ravines grew too steep and numerous, along
        the bottomlands of the Marias. The evening encampment was made amidst clumps of willows
        which provided protection against the wind but did little to keep out the rain which
        continued to fall most of the night.</p>
            <p>The men awoke cold and wet on the morning of the 5th and broke camp early, hoping to
        keep warmer by walking. The river kept to its north by west direction and before noon had
        led the party to a site from which they could see a high mountain (the main peak of the
        Sweetgrass Hills) toward the northwest and at a great distance. Late afternoon brought
        them in sight of still more mountains (the other peaks of the Sweetgrass Hills) in the
        northwest and here they made camp in a grove of cottonwoods and the ever-inquisitive 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>experimented by roasting some
        prairie dogs for supper and found them "well flavored and tender.
        <ref target="n25" n="25"/>
            </p>
            <p>Had it not been for his systematic method of observation and analysis, the view of the
        mountains to the northwest could have led 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>to the conclusion that this range
        was the one represented as starting near the Great Falls and that this northern river,
        therefore. was the Missouri. But the mountains were, 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>believed, at least 80 or 100 miles
        away. This was too distant to have been the ranges near the Falls, according to the
        captains' mileage calculations not a very great distance above the junction on whichever
        river was the true Missouri. Moreover, the course of the river that 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>was following ran so far north
        that it, in his thinking, must have drained a vast plains area and be part of the northern
        waters of the Missouri as shown on his and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>'s reinterpretations of the data from
        the 
        <name type="person" key="Arrowsmith, Aaron">Arrowsmith</name>map. By the morning of the
        6th 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>had become "well convinced that
        this branch of the Missouri had its direction too much to the North for our rout to the
        Pacific"
        <ref target="n26" n="26"/>and decided to return to the main camp.</p>
            <p>While 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and four of his men engaged
        themselves in constructing rafts to descend the Marias, two others traveled farther up the
        river in order to get a more precise bearing on its course. They returned around noon with
        the report that the river did continue its northerly course as far as they could see and,
        after lunching on elk killed the night before, the small force embarked on their two
        hastily-constructed rafts to the mouth of the Marias. But attempted navigation of the
        Marias was unsuccessful and the rafts were soon abandoned for a less comfortable but more
        secure land route. This took them along the river bottoms where possible and across the
        exposed plains that offered little protection from the wind and rain which began soon
        after they left the rafts and continued through the afternoon and evening.</p>
            <p>After a night spent in an unsheltered spot, 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and his cold, exhausted men broke
        camp early and resumed their trek across plains grown slippery and treacherous from the
        prolonged rains. On the evening of the 7th they bivouaced comfortably in an old Indian
        shelter. They resumed the return journey to the main camp on the cloudy and cool morning
        of June 8. By ten o'clock that morning the clouds had broken under a warming spring sun.
        As the weather improved so did 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>'s spirits as the party passed
        through "one of the most beautifully picturesque countries I ever beheld."
        <ref target="n27" n="27"/>
            </p>
            <p>But the captain had little else to be enthusiastic about. For although he had fully
        concluded that this river was "neither the main stream, nor that which it would be
        advisable for us to take" and gave it the name "Maria's River," the whole of his party was
        "fully persuaded that this river was the Missouri."
        <ref target="n28" n="28"/>This was a potentially serious problem and one that he and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>would have to work out when, at five
        o'clock on the afternoon of the 8th, the two captains were reunited at the junction of the
        Missouri and the river that was now officially the Marias.</p>
            <p>While 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and his men relaxed with a "drink
        of grog" during the evening of the 8th, 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>began plotting the courses of the two
        rivers as far as he and 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>had ascended them. Looking at the
        crude charts, both captains were more convinced than ever that their initial supposition
        about which stream was the Missouri was correct. They also came to the conclusion that
        they had been justified in making corrections in the 
        <name type="person" key="Arrowsmith, Aaron">Arrowsmith</name>map during the winter at Fort
        Mandan. In his journal for June 8, 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>wrote:</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">I now began more than ever to suspect the varacity of Mr. 
          <name type="person" key="Fidler, Peter">Fidler</name>or the correctness of his
          instruments ... we are now within a hundred miles of the Rocky Mountains, and I find
          from my observations of the 3rd. Inst [June 3] that the latitude of this place is
          47°.24'12".8. the river must therefore turn much to the South between this place and the
          rocky Mountains to have permitted Mr. 
          <name type="person" key="Fidler, Peter">Fidler</name>to have passed along the Eastern
          border of these mountains as far S. as nearly 45° with-out even seeing it. but from
          hence as far as Capt. C. had ascended the S. fork or Missouri being the distance of 55
          (45 miles in straight line) Miles it's course is S. 29° W. and it still appeared to bear
          considerably to the W. of South as for as he could see it. I think therefore that we
          shall find that the Missouri enters the rocky mountains to the North of 45°.</hi>
               <ref target="n29" n="29"/>
            </p>
            <p>Analysis of the geographical data derived from all sources, including the captains' own
        separate field reconnaissances, continued on the 9th and further settled in the minds of 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>"the propryety of addopting the South
        fork for the Missouri, as that which it would be expedient for us to take."
        <ref target="n30" n="30"/>The captains determined that the 
        <name type="person" key="Arrowsmith, Aaron">Arrowsmith</name>map, incorrect as it was,
        provided a strong argument against the north branch or Marias as the true Missouri. Even
        if 
        <name type="person" key="Arrowsmith, Aaron">Arrowsmith</name>'s informant, 
        <name type="person" key="Fidler, Peter">Fidler</name>, had penetrated as far south as 47'
        and had seen only small streams running east, then the presumption was that "those little
        streams do not penetrate the rocky mountains to such distance as would afford rational
        grownds for a conjecture that they had their sources near any navigable branch of the
        Columbia."
        <ref target="n31" n="31"/>This eliminated the Marias from consideration as the true
        Missouri or route to the Pacific.</p>
            <p>On the other hand, the Indian information obtained during the previous winter, combined
        with the 
        <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">Mackay</name>journal and 
        <name type="person" key="Evans, John">Evans</name>map, argued strongly in favor of the
        southern branch:</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">they [the Indians] informed us that the water of the Missouri was
          nearly transparent at the great falls, this is the case with the water of the South
          fork; that the falls lay a little to the South of sunset from them; this is also
          probable as we are only a few minutes [of latitude] North of Fort Mandan and the South
          fork bears considerably South from hence to the Mountains; that the falls are below the
          rocky mountains and near the No[r]thern termination of one range of those Mountains, a
          range of mountains [the Little Belts] which apear behind the S. mountains [the
          Highwoods] which appear to terminate S.W. from this place and on this side of the
          unbroken chain of the Rocky Mountains [the Big Belts] gives us hope that this part of
          their information is also correct. and there is sufficient distance between this and the
          mountains for many and I fear for its much too many falls. another impression on my mind
          is that if the Indians had passed any stream as lame as the South fork on their way to
          the Missouri that they would not have omitted mentioning it; and the South fork from
          it's size and complexion of it's waters must enter the Ry. Mountains and in my opinion
          penetrates them to a great distance, or els whence such an immence body of water as it
          discharges: it cannot proceed from the dry plains to the N. W. of the Yellow Stone river
          on the East side of the Rocky Mountains for those numerous large dry channels which Ice
          witnessed on that side as we ascended the Missouri forbid such a conjecture: and that it
          should take it's sources to the N. W. under those mountains and travels of Mr. 
          <name type="person" key="Fidler, Peter">Fidler</name>fo[r]bid us to belive.</hi>
               <ref target="n32" n="32"/>
            </p>
            <p>This was a brilliant piece of deduction from a fuzzy set of facts and illustrates, as
        well as any other event during the course of the Expedition, the competence and
        intelligence of the two officers.</p>
            <p>Investigation had borne out the tentative conclusion made by 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>on the very first day at the
        junction. But as before, the men remained obdurate in their belief that the northern
        branch was the true Missouri. The captains tried to impress their geographical concepts
        and reasoning on the men but Peter Cruzatte, an old Missouri hand and the party's most
        expert riverman, "had acquired the confidence of every individual of the party [and]
        declared it as his opinion that the N. fork was the true genuine Missouri and could be no
        other."
        <ref target="n33" n="33"/>
            </p>
            <p>Discipline had been remarkably good on the trek from the 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>villages to the
        Missouri–Marias junction. Nevertheless, this was a delicate situation. Although 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>noted that the men were ready to
        follow us any wher we thought proper to direct,”
        <ref target="n34" n="34"/>the seeds of a possible breakdown must have existed. "Finding
        them so determined in this belief," wrote 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>:</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">and wishing that if we were in an error to be able to detect it and
          rectify it as soon as possible it was agreed between Capt. C. and myself that one of us
          should set out with a small party by land up the South fork and continue our rout up it
          untill we found the falls or reached the snowy Mountains by which means ice should be
          enabled to determine this question prety accurately.</hi>
               <ref target="n35" n="35"/>
            </p>
            <p>This decision to split the party again does not indicate the captains' lack of
        assurance in their conclusions nearly as much as it indicates the necessity to maintain
        the confidence of their men.</p>
            <p>The afternoon of the 9th was spent in making preparations for caching equipment prior
        to a departure from the junction and, in the evening, the party enjoyed a ration of grog
        distributed by the officers and danced and sang to the rhythms of Cruzatte's fiddle. June
        10 was a fair, dry day and work on the cache continued.</p>
            <p>Although 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>was down with dysentery, it was
        decided that he and four men would depart the camp early the following morning, leaving 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>and the remainder of the party to
        complete the cache and the repair of the canoes and then to follow 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>by water up the left-hand fork.
        Hopefully, before 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>and the main body could proceed too
        far up the south fork, 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>would have found the proof they
        all desired.</p>
            <p>At 8:00 a.m. on the morning of June 11, 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and his men swung their packs onto
        their shoulders and proceeded along the right bank of the Missouri, following 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>'s earlier route. The march of the
        11th was a short one and camp was made early as 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>'s illness grew more severe and he
        was unable to proceed. But he healed himself with a concoction made from the bark of
        chokecherry bushes and by morning, feeling quite revived, resumed the ascent of the
        Missouri.</p>
            <p>Their route on the 12th carried them through level and open plains above the river and,
        after a side trip to the river for rest and refreshment during the morning, the party
        reached a ridge of land considerably higher than the rest of the plains. From here they
        saw the "august spectacle" of the Little Belt and Big Belt ranges to the south and
        southwest and 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>'s suspicions that they were
        nearing the Great Falls were confirmed. They did not reach that vital landmark on the
        12th, however, and camp was made before sunset in a clump of cottonwoods along the
        Missouri.</p>
            <p>After breakfasting on venison and fish, 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and his small band again ascended
        the hills beyond the river and continued their travel across the open plains. The river
        took a sharp bend to the south and, fearing that he would miss the Falls if he continued
        through the plains, 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>altered his southwesterly course
        near Square and Crown Buttes and headed directly for the river.</p>
            <p>About noon on June 13, Captain Meriwether 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>found the proof he sought. After
        moving through a beautiful meadow above the river, his ears were met with the sound of
        falling water and his eyes with a column of spray that rose like smoke above the plains.
        The roaring noise increased and became too great "to be mistaken for any cause short of
        the great falls of the Missouri." 
        <ref target="n36" n="36"/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>hurried down the hills "to gaze on
        this sublimely grand specticle" and, from a position atop some rocks, he came in sight of
        one of the great unknowns of the West.</p>
            <p>Here at the Great Falls of the Missouri all the information he and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>had collected, all the assumptions
        they had they had made, must have seemed correct. The presence of the Falls fulfilled 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>'s dreams and ambitions and,
        unwilling to leave before having a look at what lay beyond the cataracts, he determined to
        make camp in the vicinity for the remainder of the afternoon and evening. His hunters
        killed buffalo during the afternoon while one of the men fished in the Missouri and that
        evening they feasted sumptuously on buffalo hump and fine trout.</p>
            <p>The next morning 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>dispatched a courier to 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>with a message dated "from the Great
        falls of the Missouri," and set out himself up the river to find the extent of the break
        in navigation created by the Falls. Cascade after cascade met his eyes and, apparently not
        worrying about the difficulties the long and extensive rapids would place in the way of
        their navigation toward the Passage to India, 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>wrote glowingly of the views that
        presented themselves. He passed an eagle's nest which the Indians had told him lay near
        the upper end of the Falls and once beyond he climbed to the top of a hill and toward the
        south saw the Missouri running a meandering course toward the southwest.</p>
            <p>From the west came the Medicine River (now the Sun River) the Indians had described to
        him and, on the horizon, was the second snowclad range of the Rockies. All the components
        of the image and the Passage to India were there and 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>turned back to rejoin 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>and prepare for the glory that must
        be beyond.</p>
            <p>The great falls, the mountains, the Medicine River—all were as the captains had
        expected to find them. And when, on June 16, 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>met at the camp 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>had made at the base of the Falls in
        preparation for the portage around them, they must have been convinced that the easy
        Passage to India would also be fulfilled. Their geographical knowledge had proved accurate
        thus far. It should prove accurate in the future and they could expect to reach the Three
        Forks, the half-day portage across the final range of mountains, and then the Columbia and
        the Pacific—the ultimate goal of American exploration.</p>
            <p>But disappointment and failure lay ahead. The Pacific would be reached—but not via the
        short portage. The Passage to India was not there. All their seeking would not reveal it
        and, with very few exceptions, they were the last that looked.</p>
            <p>The dream of the Passage would end above Great Falls and the quality of the explorers'
        information and the accuracy of their images would begin to fade. They would learn these
        things in the months ahead and after their hungry and tortuous struggle through mountains
        that were supposed to be easy and through mountains that were not supposed to be there at
        all, after the constant drought and bad food of the dusty Columbian plains, after their
        sodden and dreary winter on the Oregon coast, they would turn their backs on the dream—on
        the promise of the Golden Chersonese and the breezes from the Spice Islands and the golden
        sands of Cathay.</p>
            <p>But when these intrepid men turned their backs on the dream and on the Pacific, they
        would begin to fill in the map of the West. The Passage to India would be no more—for when
        man fills his maps there is little room left for his dreams.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="additional">
            <p>About the Author</p>
            <p>A native of Laramie, Wyoming, 
        <name type="person" key="Allen, John L.">John Logan Allen</name>reflects his professional
        interest in the geographical history of the American West in the present article. Now
        assistant Professor of Historical Geography at the University of Connecticut, Storrs, he
        spent the 1970–71 academic year at the Clark University Graduate School of Geography,
        Worcester, Mass., on a post-doctoral fellowship endowed by the National Science
        Foundation. He offered a seminar in American attitudes toward the West during the 19th
        century and took time out as well to revise his doctoral dissertation for book
        publication. The dissertation, written for Clark University in 1969, deals with the
        formation of geographical images of the West front 1673 to 1804 and the impact of these
        images on the course and objectives of the 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>Expedition. Before going to Clark for
        his doctoral work, Allen took both B.A. and M.A. degrees (with honors) from the University
        of Wyoming at Laramie.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="additional">
            <note xml:id="n01" n="1">
               <hi rend="italic">Original Journals of the 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>Expedition, 1804–1806</hi>, 
        <name type="person" key="Thwaites, Reuben Gold">Reuben Gold Thwaites</name>, ed. (8 vols.,
        New York, 1904), vol. I, p. 284. Hereafter cited as RGT:OJ:vol:page.</note>
            <note xml:id="n02" n="2">
               <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>'s instructions to 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, June 19, 1803; 
        <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>Papers, Manuscript Division,
        Library of Congress, vol. CXXXII, folios 22884–22887.</note>
            <note xml:id="n03" n="3">A full treatment of the efforts of 
        <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>and others in gathering
        geographical data on the West prior to the Expedition may be found in the author's
        doctoral dissertation: 
        <name type="person" key="Allen, John L.">J. L. Allen</name>, "Geographical Images of the
        American Northwest, 1673 to 1806" (unpublished mss., Clark University, 1969), particularly
        pp. 273–416.</note>
            <note xml:id="n04" n="4">The 
        <name type="person" key="Arrowsmith, Aaron">Arrowsmith</name>map compiled nearly all of
        the available information on the West. But as supplementary material, the captains
        possessed a detailed map of the vicinity of the 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>villages, several maps of the
        Missouri River between St. Louis and the 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>s, charts of the Pacific
        coastal area near the mouth of the Columbia, journals of several British and French
        explorers in the West, and a considerable volume of less formal data in the form of
        letters, reports, and governmental documents. None of this material was in substantial
        disagreement with the view of the West presented on the 
        <name type="person" key="Arrowsmith, Aaron">Arrowsmith</name>map.</note>
            <note xml:id="n05" n="5">The northern branch of the Missouri above the villages was not
        given a name and was of little importance to the Expedition's objective. It supposedly
        headed near the Saskatchewan River in what is now southern Alberta. 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>had already been warned away from
        this northern branch by 
        <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>who wrote: "These northern
        waters have been ascertained to a considerable degree, and are still in a course of
        ascertainment by English traders and travellers" (
        <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>'s instructions to 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, op.cit.).</note>
            <note xml:id="n06" n="6">This was the common American view of the Rockies during the
        opening years of the nineteenth century. See 
        <name type="person" key="Allen, John L.">J. L. Allen</name>, "Geographical Knowledge and
        American Images of the Louisiana Territory at the Time of the Purchase" 
        <hi rend="italic">Western Historical Quarterly</hi>II: 2 (1971): 151–170.</note>
            <note xml:id="n07" n="7">The best source of information on the 
        <name type="person" key="Evans, John">Evans</name>–
        <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">Mackay</name>travels (including a large number of
        pertinent documents) is in: 
        <name type="person" key="Nasatir, A. P.">A. P. Nasatir</name>, 
        <hi rend="italic">Before 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>
               </hi>(2 vols., St. Louis:
        1952).</note>
            <note xml:id="n08" n="8">Cf. the captains' entries in their daily journals for December
        1719 (
        <name type="person" key="Thwaites, Reuben Gold">RGT</name>:OJ:I:238–239), January 5 (
        <name type="person" key="Thwaites, Reuben Gold">RGT</name>:OJ:I:244–245), January 7 (
        <name type="person" key="Thwaites, Reuben Gold">RGT</name>:OJ:I:245–246), January 16 (
        <name type="person" key="Thwaites, Reuben Gold">RGT</name>:OJ:I:249), February 18 (
        <name type="person" key="Thwaites, Reuben Gold">RGT</name>:OJ:I:263), and February 27 (
        <name type="person" key="Thwaites, Reuben Gold">RGT</name>:OJ:I:266).</note>
            <note xml:id="n09" n="9">These documents were sent down the Missouri in the spring of
        1805, along with many other materials gathered during the first summer and winter of the
        Expedition. 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>'s description of western
        geography is reproduced in the 
        <name type="person" key="Thwaites, Ruben Gold">Thwaites</name>edition of the 
        <hi rend="italic">Original Journals</hi>VI, 29–55.</note>
            <note xml:id="n10" n="10">The northern tributaries of the Missouri, wrote 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>in his description, were the
        channels "through which, those small streams. on the E side of the Rocky mountains laid
        down by Mr. 
        <name type="person" key="Fidler, Peter">Fidler</name>, pas to the Missouri" (
        <name type="person" key="Thwaites, Reuben Gold">RGT</name>:OJ:VI:53).</note>
            <note xml:id="n11" n="11">See 
        <name type="person" key="Thwaites, Reuben Gold">RGT</name>:OJ:VI:55. The western fork of
        the Missouri, was, of course, the 
        <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>. The southern branch of the
        Columbia probably represented misinterpreted information about the Lemhi–Sahnon system and
        the Bitterroot–Clark's Fork drainage.</note>
            <note xml:id="n12" n="12">A set of distance estimates between key points along the
        Missouri made by 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>during the winter at Fort Mandan gave
        the distance from the 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>villages to the "river which
        scolds . . ." as 370 miles in a straight line. The captains' mileage figures taken during
        the Expedition, with corrections for the Missouri's meandering course, corresponded
        closely with this estimate (
        <name type="person" key="Thwaites, Reuben Gold">RGT</name>:OJ:VI:60–61).</note>
            <note xml:id="n13" n="13">
               <name type="person" key="Thwaites, Reuben Gold">RGT</name>:OJ:VI:60.</note>
            <note xml:id="n14" n="14">"Those mountains [the Little Rocky Mountains to the north and
        the Moccasin and Judith ranges on the south] appear to be detached, and not ranges as laid
        down by the Minetarrees" (
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, May 25; 
        <name type="person" key="Thwaites, Reuben Gold">RGT</name>:OJ:II:77).</note>
            <note xml:id="n15" n="15">in his magnificently–edited condensation of the journals,
        Bernard DeVoto (
        <hi rend="italic">The Journals of 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>
               </hi>, Boston: Houghton Mifflin,
        1953), identifies the range seen on May 26 as the Little Rocky Mountains. This is a rare
        error in 
        <name type="person" key="Devoto, Bernard">DeVoto</name>'s identifications and results from
        a misinterpretation of the compass readings given by 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>. 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, the first to see the range, clearly
        indicates they lay to the south and west. But 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>(from whose journal DeVoto made
        his identification) noted that they bore 65 degrees west of north. This does not mean that
        the mountains were northwest of the observer but that their direction of alignment was
        from southeast to northwest. 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>frequently gave compass readings
        like this, a fact that has resulted in considerable confusion in trying to identify
        landmarks along the Expedition's course. Furthermore, the Little Rocky Mountains are
        northeast of the point of observation on May 26 and therefore could not have been the
        mountains whose peaks were visible to the west.</note>
            <note xml:id="n16" n="16">
               <name type="person" key="Thwaites, Reuben Gold">RGT</name>:OJ:II:109. The Marias is, of
        course, nowhere near as big a river as the Missouri under normal conditions. But 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>had the misfortune of viewing it
        during peak runoff conditions and considered it to be a greater and more important river
        than it actually is. Had they seen the Marias later in the season, the probability of
        confusion would have been greatly reduced.</note>
            <note xml:id="n17" n="17">
               <name type="person" key="Thwaites, Reuben Gold">RGT</name>:OJ:II:112–113.</note>
            <note xml:id="n18" n="18">
               <name type="person" key="Thwaites, Reuben Gold">RGT</name>:OJ:II:112.</note>
            <note xml:id="n19" n="19">
               <name type="person" key="Thwaites, Reuben Gold">RGT</name>:OJ:II:113.</note>
            <note xml:id="n20" n="20">
               <name type="person" key="Thwaites, Reuben Gold">RGT</name>:OJ:II:113–114. The first range
        of mountains mentioned by 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>was the Highwood range. The rugged
        country behind this first range included the Little Belt and Big Belt ranges. Note that 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>is giving compass directions
        according to the directional alignment the mountains rather than the bearing from the
        observer to the ranges.</note>
            <note xml:id="n21" n="21">
               <name type="person" key="Thwaites, Reuben Gold">RGT</name>:OJ:II:114.</note>
            <note xml:id="n22" n="22">
               <name type="person" key="Thwaites, Reuben Gold">RGT</name>:OJ:II:114–115.</note>
            <note xml:id="n23" n="23">"What astonishes us a little is that the Indians who appeared to
        be so well acquainted with the geography of this country should not have mentioned this
        river on [the] wright hand" (
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, June 3, 
        <name type="person" key="Thwaites, Reuben Gold">RGT</name>:OJ:II:115).</note>
            <note xml:id="n24" n="24">
               <name type="person" key="Thwaites, Reuben Gold">RGT</name>:OJ:II:116.</note>
            <note xml:id="n25" n="25">
               <name type="person" key="Thwaites, Reuben Gold">RGT</name>:OJ:II:124.</note>
            <note xml:id="n26" n="26">
               <name type="person" key="Thwaites, Reuben Gold">RGT</name>:OJ:II:125.</note>
            <note xml:id="n27" n="27">
               <name type="person" key="Thwaites, Reuben Gold">RGT</name>:OJ:II:131.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28" n="28">
               <name type="person" key="Thwaites, Reuben Gold">RGT</name>:01:II:130.</note>
            <note xml:id="n29" n="29">
               <name type="person" key="Thwaites, Reuben Gold">RGT</name>:OJ:II:131–132.</note>
            <note xml:id="n30" n="30">
               <name type="person" key="Thwaites, Reuben Gold">RGT</name>:OJ:II:134.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31" n="31">
               <name type="person" key="Thwaites, Reuben Gold">RGT</name>:OJ:II:134.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32" n="32">
               <name type="person" key="Thwaites, Reuben Gold">RGT</name>:OJ:II:136.</note>
            <note xml:id="n33" n="33">
               <name type="person" key="Thwaites, Reuben Gold">RGT</name>:OJ:II:136.</note>
            <note xml:id="n34" n="34">
               <name type="person" key="Thwaites, Reuben Gold">RGT</name>:OJ:II:136.</note>
            <note xml:id="n35" n="35">
               <name type="person" key="Thwaites, Reuben Gold">RGT</name>:OJ:II:135.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36" n="36">
               <name type="person" key="Thwaites, Reuben Gold">RGT</name>:OJ:II:147.</note>
            <p>This article is reprinted with the courtesy of John Logan Allen.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
