<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.lc.ronda.01.intro">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>&amp; 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>among the Indians</title>
            <title type="sub" level="a">Introduction to the Bicentennial Edition</title>
            <title type="sub"/>
            <author>James P. Ronda</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2005</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic
        Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title level="m" type="main">
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>&amp; 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>among the Indians</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">Introduction to the Bicentennial Edition</title>
               <author>James P. Ronda</author>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1984</date>
               <idno type="ISBN">0-8032-8990-1</idno>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-11-01</date>
            <date>2005-02-01</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>File splitting Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-04-12</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="intro" type="intro">
            <p>Henry David Thoreau once asked, "how many a man has dated a new era in his life from
        the reading of a book?" Thoreau's question was his way of acknowleding the power of print
        to transform and redirect lives. 
        <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Thomas Jefferson</name>would have agreed. The
        idea for the 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>expedition was born in the summer of
        1802 when he read 
        <name type="person" key="Mackenzie, Alexander">Alexander Mackenzie's</name>
               <hi rend="italic">Voyages from 
        <name type="place" key="Montreal">Montreal</name>
               </hi>and realized that John Bull might
        claim the West before Uncle Sam made it over the mountains. For me the book that changed
        everything was 
        <name type="person" key="Allen, John L.">John L. Allen's</name>
               <hi rend="italic">Passage through the Garden: 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>and the Image of the American
        Northwest,</hi>first published by the University of Illinois Press in 1975. Reading it set
        me to studying western exploration in general and the 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>expedition in particular. It was 
        <hi rend="italic">Passage through the Garden</hi>that prompted me to ask if anyone had
        written about 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>and native people. The topic seemed
        an obvious one to me, and I was sure that many books must explore so rich and compelling a
        subject. When I learned there were none, I impetuously decided to try my hand at the
        topic. 
        <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>among the Indians</hi>would not have
        come into existence without 
        <hi rend="italic">Passage through the Garden.</hi>Books make a difference; reading changes
        lives.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>among the Indians</hi>was sparked by
        reading what 
        <name type="person" key="Allen, John L.">John Allen</name>wrote about geographic
        exploration, but the book also developed at a unique time in the writing of American
        history. Beginning in the 1960s many historians and other scholars were deeply involved in
        a comprehensive reevaluation of race in the American experience. While some scholars
        centered their attention on African Americans and Asian Americans, others probed the
        complexities of Native American cultures and communities. Until that time much Native
        American history centered on federal Indian policy and formal tribal histories. The story
        was most often told from 
        <name type="place" key="Washington D.C.">Washington, D.C.</name>, and the principal actors
        were bureaucrats, soldiers, missionaries, and white settlers. But a different
        approach—something called ethnohistory—offered a new way to tell old stories. Inspired by
        the shared perspectives of history and anthropology, ethnohistorians expanded the field of
        inquiry, asked fresh questions, paid attention to often-neglected native sources, and
        listened carefully to Indian voices. Throughout the 1970s the ethnohistory I wrote
        described native people, Christian missionaries, and the changes sweeping throughout the
        colonial Northeast. In retrospect that work—so far from the Native American West of 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>—prepared me to ask new questions
        about the larger western exploration story. As I wrote in the preface to this book, what
        captured my imagination was the possibility of writing "exploration ethnohistory."</p>
            <p>At the very time Native American history experienced both transformation and renewal,
        the field of western American history underwent profound changes. While 
        <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>among the Indians</hi>was never
        identified with what became known as the "New Western History," the book was undoubtedly
        influenced by reading and listening to Patricia Nelson Limerick, Bill Cronon, Richard
        White, and Donald Worster. Their struggles to redefine western history and escape the
        intellectual straitjacket of the Turner Thesis impressed me and encouraged me. At the same
        time I did not want to abandon the narrative power and broad appeal I admired in the
        writing of Francis Parkman and Bernard DeVoto. Like them, I also wanted to engage a wider
        audience that included readers beyond the academic ranks. Quite simply, I hoped to write
        narrative history informed by a reinvigorated Indian history and a renewed western
        history. Exploration history—with its journey structure and memorable cast of
        characters—seemed to offer that possibility.</p>
            <p>Because I was not trained as a western historian, I knew I needed a mentor, someone to
        guide me up the trails and over the mountains. In January 1980 I wrote to Donald
        Jackson—the dean of 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>scholars—asking his help with my
        project. Don's answer was quick and gracious. As the senior editor at the University of
        Illinois Press and later as founding editor of the George Washington Papers at the
        University of Virginia, he never had students. Now Don became a professor. I was his sole
        student and our often-weekly letters were a seminar in the writing of western exploration
        history. Those letters continued until his death in December 1987. Rereading them now I
        can see Don cajoling and correcting me, keeping me on the trail, and reminding me not to
        lose track of the narrative line. If the dedication page had not been promised to someone
        else, it surely would have gone to Don.</p>
            <p>When 
        <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Thomas Jefferson</name>prepared exploration
        instructions for 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name>in June 1803 he
        repeated one phrase—"the object of your journey"—again and again. The president used the
        word "object" to mean "objective." 
        <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>among the Indians</hi>also has its
        objects. Perhaps the most important of those objects is to tell a familiar western journey
        story in a new way. I wanted to give readers a different angle of vision, another way to
        appreciate a story that had grown too familiar and perhaps a bit stale. Simply put, 
        <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>among the Indians</hi>asks readers to
        get off the expedition's boats and get on the bank. What had always been seen through the
        eyes of 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>needed to be experienced through the
        eyes of native people. By shifting points of view and introducing new speakers I hoped to
        tell a richer and more compelling story, one that would reflect the diversity of the West
        itself.</p>
            <p>That was my intention. I soon found that the telling involved a research task of
        considerable size and complexity. The task was more than thinking out a new research
        design. It involved enlarging the 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>story in particular and the western
        exploration story in general. Writing history is always an act of the imagination. What I
        needed to do was reimagine the expedition and the western worlds through which it moved.
        In the popular mind 
        <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name>Corps of Discovery had only
        three members—
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, and 
        <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name>. Donald Jackson's magisterial 
        <hi rend="italic">Letters of the 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>Expedition</hi>changed all that for
        those who were paying attention. Jackson put it with characteristic bluntness: "It is no
        longer useful to think of the 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>Expedition as the personal story of
        two men. Their journey . . . was an enterprise of many aims and a product of many minds."
        Jackson's cast of characters ranged from the attorney general of the United States to
        obscure craftspeople in 
        <name type="place" key="Philadelphia, Pa.">Philadelphia</name>and 
        <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>. Challenged by Jackson's words
        and our correspondence, I went in search of an even larger cast, one that acted on a stage
        that stretched up the 
        <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, across the mountains, down the 
        <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>, and on to the shores of the 
        <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>. If this journey story was to have
        any cultural meanings within the larger American experience, it needed a telling that paid
        attention to native aims and minds.</p>
            <p>Enlarging the expedition story called for more actors on a wider stage; it also meant
        broadening the range of sources and methodologies from those typically used in writing
        history. 
        <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>among the Indians</hi>drew heavily on
        the available anthropological and archaeological literature, especially the site reports
        from digs along the 
        <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>and 
        <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>Rivers. Here I had the good fortune
        to meet W. Raymond Wood, one of the foremost northern 
        <name type="place" key="Great Plains">Great Plains</name>archaeologists. He introduced me
        to unpublished materials, including specialized studies done for the National Park
        Service. From there the research spread out to formal, academic tribal histories and the
        invaluable oral traditions preserved in many different ways. But in all of this I
        repeatedly came back to the expedition's journals. Don Jackson once called the
        expedition's journal keepers "the writingest explorers" in American history. What I found
        in a close and critical reading of 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, 
        <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">John Ordway</name>, 
        <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Patrick Gass</name>, 
        <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Joseph Whitehouse</name>, and 
        <name type="person" key="Floyd, Charles">Charles Floyd</name>was a wealth of material
        about expedition-Indian relations. The biases and prejudices are surely there; but so are
        the native voices. The journals name the names and mark out the places. And it is more
        than simply names and places. At a certain level writing history is an act of rescue.
        Historians rescue and restore lost voices. The 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>journals make that kind of rescue and
        restoration possible. Again and again Corps of Discovery journal keepers recorded what
        native people told them about everything from plants and animals to geography and
        relations with tribal neighbors. Despite what were surely inadequate translations we can
        still hear the voices of 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>chief 
        <name type="person" key="Black Cat (Posecopsahe)">Black Cat</name>, 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsop</name>headman 
        <name type="person" key="Coboway">Coboway</name>, and 
        <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html" rend="box">
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
               </ref>chief 
        <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">Twisted Hair</name>. It is those
        voices that give depth and richness to the 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>story.</p>
            <p>In the nearly twenty years since the publication of 
        <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>among the Indians</hi>interest has
        only grown in the expedition and its place in the history of the American West. That
        fascination has been fueled by a tidal wave of books, television documentaries, guided
        tours, and museum exhibitions. The shared bicentennials of the 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>expedition and the Louisiana Purchase
        add that much more to a widespread enthusiasm for the Corps of Discovery and its journey.
        While many in the general public still cling to the notion of 
        <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name>explorers as "captains
        courageous," historians have come to appreciate the expedition story as an emblematic
        moment in the larger history of the continent. The central argument in 
        <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>among the Indians</hi>has gained
        considerable acceptance. Most who write about the expedition now acknowledge that native
        people were at the heart of the enterprise. Without those Indian voices and views the
        story is at best only half told.</p>
            <p>Some two decades later I would have said some things more forcefully. One of those
        would be the importance of Indians as explorers. Just as 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>explored the lives and cultures of
        native people, so too did Indians explore 
        <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name>travelers and the things
        they carried with them. What happened from the 
        <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>to the 
        <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>was mutual discovery, shared
        moments of exploration encounter. Much of that discovery was done through the fog of
        confusion, misunderstanding, and ambiguity. But when 
        <name type="person" key="Black Cat (Posecopsahe)">Black Cat</name>went to 
        <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name>inquiring about the
        expedition's "fashions," he was part of a Corps of Discovery far larger than 
        <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Thomas Jefferson</name>ever imagined.</p>
            <p>Perhaps nothing has contributed more to 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>scholarship over the past twenty
        years than the appearance of Gary E. Moulton's magnificent 
        <hi rend="italic">Journals of the 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>Expedition,</hi>published by the
        University of Nebraska Press. When I wrote 
        <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>among the Indians</hi>in the early
        1980s, only the atlas volume of the Moulton edition was available. My research was in the
        Reuben Gold Thwaites edition, with its reasonably reliable text but woefully inadequate
        annotations. Had I started a bit later, my book would have benefited substantially from
        the comprehensive ethnographic and linguistic scholarship that informs the entire Moulton
        edition. Examples abound. I would have spelled and translated names like 
        <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Untongarabar (Black Buffalo
        Bull)</name>or 
        <name type="person" key="Stabber (War-cha-pa)">War-cha-pa (The Stabber)</name>differently.
        I would have more precisely located important 
        <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html" rend="box">
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
               </ref>and 
        <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>villages and fishing camps. I
        would have had much more to say about the native use of medicinal plants and medical
        practices. Perhaps most important, I could have made use of the superb linguistic
        scholarship present in every Moulton volume.</p>
            <p>On May 13, 1804—the day the Corps of Discovery left its camp at 
        <name type="place" key="Dubois River">Wood River</name>—
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark</name>wrote that the expedition's
        "road across the continent" would take it through a "multitude of Indians." Almost a year
        later, as the company prepared to head out from 
        <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name>on its way to the 
        <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>, 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name>declared that he and
        his fellow travelers were "about to penetrate a country . . . on which the foot of
        civillized man had never trodden." In that contest of images—a West filled with native
        people and an empty, savage land—
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>had it right. He recognized something
        fundamental about his own journey and the larger American journey. The expedition was a
        diverse human community moving through the lands and lives of other communities. This was
        no "tour of discovery" through an empty West. 
        <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>among the Indians</hi>is an attempt
        to tell that story. What has so often been recounted in terms of high adventure, national
        triumph, and male courage needs to be told again as a complex human story. 
        <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>among the Indians</hi>aims at
        overturning the old narrative and replacing it with one more subtle, more nuanced, and, I
        hope, more compelling. I remain persuaded that this story and its many voices has much to
        offer as we struggle to understand our troubled past and often-uncertain present. This
        larger Corps of Discovery is a reminder that we are all pilgrims on the way, making our
        way by the kindness of strangers.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.ronda.01.00" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.ronda.01.00" type="contents"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.ronda.01.preface" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>