<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.sup.oconnor.01">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">Oregon Historical Quarterly 105:3 (2004): 390–421.</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="O'Connor, Jim E.">Jim E. O'Connor</name>
            </author>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               
               
               
               
               
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Texts</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Articles</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-06-22</date>
            <name>Beth Burke</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="main">The Evolving Landscape of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River Gorge">Columbia River Gorge</name>: <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> and Cataclysms on the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>
         </head>
         <p>by Jim E. O'Connor</p>
         <p>(This article first appeared in <hi rend="italic">
               <!--<ref target="http://www.ohs.org/publications/about_ohq.cfm">-->Oregon Historical Quarterly<!--</ref>-->
            </hi> 105:3 [2004]: 390–421.)</p>
        <div type="section">
         <p>Travelers retracing <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>’s journey to the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name> over the past two hundred years have witnessed tremendous change to the <name type="place" key="Columbia River Gorge">Columbia River Gorge</name> and its primary feature, the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>. Dams, reservoirs, timber harvest, altered fisheries, transportation infrastructure, and growth and shrinkage of communities have transformed the river and valley.<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0101" n="1"/> This radically different geography of human use and habitation is commonly contrasted with the sometimes romantic view of a prior time provided both by early nineteenth-century chroniclers and present-day critics of the modern condition—an ecotopia of plentiful and perpetual resources sustaining a stable culture from time immemorial. Reality is more complicated. Certainly the human-caused changes to the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name> and the gorge since <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> have been profound; but the geologic history of immense floods, landslides, and volcanic eruptions that occurred before their journey had equally, if not more, acute effects on landscapes and societies of the gorge. In many ways, the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition can be viewed as a hinge point for the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>, the changes engineered to the river and its valley in the two hundred years since their visit mirrored by tremendous changes geologically engendered in the thousands of years before.</p>
         <p>In their landscape and hydrographic descriptions, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> recorded effects of several different "cataclysms on the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>," a phrase <name type="person" key="Allen, John">John Allen</name> used for the title of his 1986 book on the ice-age Missoula floods.<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0102" n="2"/> Geologic cataclysms affecting the <name type="place" key="Columbia River Gorge">Columbia River Gorge</name>, however, include more than the gigantic floods of fifteen to seventeen thousand years ago. Others involve more human timescales. In addition to shooting through the narrows at <name type="place" key="The Dalles of the Columbia">The Dalles of the Columbia</name>, perhaps a remnant of the great ice-age floods, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> drifted past a submerged forest and portaged <name type="place" key="Cascade Rapids">Cascade Rapids</name>, the result of a huge landslide only three hundred and fifty years before their exploration. At the downstream end of the gorge, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> walked on rich bottomlands partly formed by <name type="place" key="Mount Hood">Mount Hood</name> volcanism fewer than twenty-five years earlier. This essay aims to weave <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>'s first maps and observations of these three areas into a narrative of modern geologic thinking about landscape formation, particularly for the <name type="place" key="Columbia River Gorge">Columbia River Gorge</name>.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
         <head>
            <hi rend="italic">"Other objects worthy of notice will be the soil &amp; face of the country ..."</hi>
         </head>
         <p>While not trained as geologists, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, true to <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>'s instructions, were careful observers of the landscape.<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0103" n="3"/> They provided volumes of rich observations and findings that established both geographic knowledge and methodological precedent for future explorations and surveys of the West. In the spring of 1804, however, when <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> headed west, geology was hardly an established science. The first widely distributed scientific treatment of earth history had been published in 1802, John Playfair's <hi rend="italic">Illustrations of the Huttorlian Theory of the Earth</hi>. This treatise advanced the emerging British idea that the earth's features were formed by slow, continuous processes, not by radical upheavals such as biblical floods. This concept of uniformantarianism and the effectiveness of slow gradual erosion by rivers were advanced more fully by <name type="person" key="Lyell, Charles">Charles Lyell</name> in his 1830–1833 <hi rend="italic">Principles of Geology</hi>.<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0104" n="4"/>
         </p>
         <p>Many surveys of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name> region after <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> would include geologists: <name type="person" key="Dana, James D.">James D. Dana</name> of the U.S. Exploring Expedition of 1838–1842; <name type="person" key="Newberry, John S.">John S. Newberry</name> of the Pacific Railroad Surveys of 1854–1855; <name type="person" key="Emmons, Samuel F.">Samuel F. Emmons</name> of the King Survey of 1867–1873. In 1879, <name type="person" key="King, Clarence">Clarence King</name>'s survey of the fortieth parallel and three other western geological and topographical surveys merged into the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS), with King as director. Within the newly formed USGS were <name type="person" key="Emmons, Samuel F.">Emmons</name>, <name type="person" key="Powell, John Wesley">John Wesley Powell</name>, <name type="person" key="Dutton, Clarence E.">Clarence E. Dutton</name>, and protégés of <name type="person" key="Newberry, John S.">Newberry</name> such as <name type="person" key="Gilbert, G.K.">G.K. Gilbert</name>.<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0105" n="5"/> Building on observations and measurements from all over the West, these geologists and many others established a basic understanding of the geologic history of western North America by the early twentieth century. This included evidence of extensive continental and alpine glaciation, growth and shrinkage of huge ice-age lakes, and episodes of volcanism, mountain building, and canyon cutting.<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0106" n="6"/>
         </p>
         <p>More than just documenting the geologic history of the West, these geologists and geographers also developed key concepts of landscape formation. Some of these principles, which still steer landform analysis, are traceable back to <name type="person" key="Dana, James D.">Dana</name>'s and <name type="person" key="Newberry, John S.">Newberry</name>'s reports on the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name> region. This was especially the case for the <name type="place" key="Columbia River Gorge">Columbia River Gorge</name>, where the landscape reflects an ever-changing and wildly swinging balance between the power of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>, concentrating runoff from 240,000 square miles, and the rock and debris that the river must cut through in maintaining its way to the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name> through the <name type="place" key="Cascade Range">Cascade Range.</name>
         </p>
         <p>
            <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> reached the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name> at the <name type="place" key="Snake River">Snake River</name> confluence on October 16, 1805.<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0107" n="7"/> They proceeded quickly downstream, reaching the site of <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>'s proclamation "in <hi rend="italic">View</hi> of the <hi rend="italic">Ocian</hi>" only twenty-two days later, on November 7. Departing <name type="person" key="Fort Clatsop">Fort Clatsop</name> on March 23, 1806, they lingered a bit more on their return, following the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> valley upriver as far as the <name type="place" key="Walla Walla River">Walla Walla River</name> confluence. There they diverged east from the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> on April 30. Their time in the <name type="place" key="Columbia River Gorge">Columbia River Gorge</name>—the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name> valley through the Cascade Range between the <name type="place" key="Deschutes River">Deschutes</name> and <name type="place" key="Sandy River">Sandy</name> rivers—totaled thirty-seven days, from October 21 to November 3, 1805, outbound and from March 31 to April 22, 1806, on their return. Most—and most valuable—of their observations in the gorge were ethnographic and botanic, but they also described the spectacular and formidable landscape: <name type="place" key="Celilo Falls">Celilo Falls</name>, <name type="place" key="The Dalles of the Columbia">The Dalles of the Columbia</name>, a submerged forest, <name type="place" key="Cascade Rapids">Cascade Rapids</name>, waterfalls misting the gorge walls, and the sand-laden <name type="place" key="Hood River">Hood</name> and <name type="place" key="Sandy River">Sandy rivers</name>. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> were alternately amazed and dismayed by the changes in climate, physiography, and flora and fauna they encountered.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
         <head>
            <hi rend="italic">"I heard a great roreing" "<name type="place" key="The Dalles of the Columbia">The Dalles of the Columbia</name> Type of River Channel"</hi>
         </head>
         <p>The noisy falls and rapids at <name type="place" key="The Dalles of the Columbia">"The Dalles of the Columbia"</name> audibly impressed <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark</name> as the expedition approached the <name type="place" key="Cascade Range">Cascade Range</name> in late October 1805.<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0108" n="8"/> In this reach of river, prior to its inundation behind <name type="place" key="The Dalles of the Columbia">The Dalles of the Columbia</name> Dam in 1957, the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> descended eighty feet in twelve miles as it flowed over the twenty-foot-high <name type="place" key="Celilo Falls">Celilo Falls</name> and then through a series of constrictions and expansions before emerging, presumably quieter, as a "butifull jentle Stream of about half a mile wide" near present-day <name type="place" key="The Dalles of the Columbia">Dalles of the Columbia</name>. These falls and constrictions were not just noisy; they also impeded upstream fish passage and human navigation, factors that had already made <name type="place" key="The Dalles of the Columbia">The Dalles of the Columbia</name> area one of the premier cultural centers in the Pacific Northwest, famously described by <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> as "the Great Mart of all this Country." <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>'s immediate concerns were navigation and relations with the Natives, but later this area of "rugid black rock" and others like it in the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name> Basin became the intellectual battleground of a great debate in twentieth-century geology–the Spokane Flood controversy.<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0109" n="9"/>
         </p>
         <p>The outstanding physical and cultural characteristics of <name type="place" key="The Dalles of the Columbia">The Dalles of the Columbia</name> inspired William <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Patrick Gass</name>, and Meriwether <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> (during the return trip) to devote several journal pages to describing and mapping this reach of river. They measured river fall, flood heights, lengths of portages, numbers of Indian dwellings, and stacks of drying fish. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>'s descriptions of the black rocks, perpendicular cliffs flanking the valley bottom, and windblown sand collected in hollows make his resulting maps, such as the one of <name type="place" key="Celilo Falls">Celilo Falls</name>, the first geologic maps made in the Pacific Northwest.<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0110" n="10"/>
         </p>
         <p>Their hydrologic observations, too, are vivid, sharpened by a wild ride through the chutes. Before entering the fifty-yard-wide Short Narrows, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> wrote: "... I deturmined to pass through this place notwithstanding the horrid appearance of this agitated gut Swelling, boiling &amp; whorling in every direction (which from the top of the rock did not appear as bad as when I was in it[)]."<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0111" n="11"/> Before even seeing the entrance to the Short Narrows, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> anticipated the constriction and resulting backwater from three miles upstream at Celilo Falls:</p>
         <p>... that from Some obstruction below, the cause of which we have not yet learned, the water in high fluds (which are in the Spring) rise 〈nearly〉 below these falls nearly to a leavel with the water above the falls; the marks of which can be plainly trac'd around the falls. at that Stage of the water the Salmon must pass up which abounds in Such great numbers above.<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0112" n="12"/>
         </p>
         <p>This observation neatly links the geology, hydrology, and ecology by which <name type="place" key="The Dalles of the Columbia">The Dalles of the Columbia</name> of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> merits its spotlight in regional history.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
         <head>
            <hi rend="italic">"<name type="place" key="The Dalles of the Columbia">Dalles of the Columbia</name> is one of the most remarkable places upon the Columbia"</hi>
         </head>
         <p>Later explorers, surveryors, engineers, and scientists who passed through the <name type="place" key="Columbia River Gorge">Columbia River Gorge</name> were motivated first by establishing U.S. ownership, then by the practical issue of navigation, and finally by the river's vast hydropower. Explorers, missionaries, and fur traders during the three decades after <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>—such as Wilson Hunt, David Thompson, Peter Skeen Ogden, Nathaniel Wyeth, and Samuel Parker—reiterated <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>'s observations of flow through multiple rock-bound channels, in particular noting the branching channels, the strong currents, and the intense whirlpools and boils. Government surveys during the 1840s and 1850s provided more hydrologic and geologic observations. A contingent of the U.S. Exploring Expedition under the command of the U.S. Navy's Charles Wilkes explored the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name> in the summer of 1841. This group, led by expedition artist Joseph Drayton and in the company of Ogden, described <name type="place" key="The Dalles of the Columbia">The Dalles of the Columbia</name> while ascending the river in flood in early July. Wilkes summarized:</p>
         <p>
            <name type="place" key="The Dalles of the Columbia">The Dalles of the Columbia</name> is one of the most remarkable places upon the Columbia. The river is here compressed into a narrow channel, three hundred feet wide, and half a mile long; the walls are perpendicular, flat on the top, and composed of basalt.... The tremendous roar arising from the rushing of the river through this outlet, with the many whirlpools and eddies which it causes, may be more readily imagined than described.<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0113" n="13"/>
         </p>
         <p>The Wilkes Expedition included geologist <name type="person" key="Dana, James Dwight">James Dwight Dana</name>, who did not actually visit <name type="place" key="The Dalles of the Columbia">The Dalles of the Columbia</name> but who recognized from Drayton's observations and samples that the basaltic rocks forming <name type="place" key="The Dalles of the Columbia">The Dalles of the Columbia</name> were part of the regionally extensive lavas that covered the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> plains of eastern <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name> and flanked the lower <name type="place" key="Snake River">Snake</name> and <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>s.<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0114" n="14"/>
         </p>
         <p>About two years later, in November 1843 (and in much lower water), <name type="person" key="Frémont, John Charles">John Charles Frémont</name>'s exploring party descended the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>, passing quickly by "the roar of the <hi rend="italic">Falls of the Columbia</hi>" and then to the Long Narrows, where</p>
         <p>the whole volume of the river at this place passed between the walls of a chasm, which has the appearance of having been rent through the basaltic strata which form the valley-rock of the region. At the narrowest place we found the breadth, by measurement, 58 yards, and the average height of the walls above the water 25 feet; forming a trough between the rocks.... The rock, for a considerable distance from the river, was worn over a large portion of its surface into circular holes and well-like cavities, by the abrasion of the river, which, at the season of high waters, is spread out over the adjoining bottoms.<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0115" n="15"/>
         </p>
         <p>In early September 1855, <name type="person" key="Abbot, Henry">Henry Abbot</name> of the U.S. Corps of Topographical 
Engineers explored railroad routes between California and the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>. Like <name type="person" key="Frémont, John Charles">Frémont</name>, he described the Long Narrows at low water:</p>
         <p>the river rushes through a chasm only about 200 feet wide, with vertical basaltic sides rising from 20 to 30 feet above the water. .. . There are many fine specimens of columnar basalt in this vicinity, and the banks rise in low basaltic terraces, which, on the northern side opposite the town <name type="place" key="The Dalles of the Columbia">The Dalles of the Columbia</name>], are very rough and broken.<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0116" n="16"/>
         </p>
         <p>Accompanying Abbot was a young geologist, <name type="person" key="Newberry, John S.">John Strong Newberry</name>, whose career, like <name type="person" key="Dana, James D.">Dana</name>'s, would culminate in steering the study of U.S. geology in government and academia. <name type="person" key="Newberry, John S.">Newberry</name> reported: "<name type="place" key="The Dalles of the Columbia">The Dalles of the Columbia</name> are formed by one of those beds of trap [basalt], through which the stream cuts in deep and narrow channels...”<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0117" n="17"/>
         </p>
         <p>These observations from government exploratory parties were the first after William <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>'s to provide geologic context for <name type="place" key="The Dalles of the Columbia">The Dalles of the Columbia</name>. <name type="person" key="Newberry, John S.">Newberry</name>'s descriptions of the basaltic rocks, the ragged rocky surfaces, and the inferences of fluvial-erosion are among the first such writings in the Pacific Northwest. <name type="person" key="Dana, James D.">Dana</name> and especially <name type="person" key="Newberry, John S.">Newberry</name> leveraged observations along the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name> and elsewhere in the Pacific Northwest into broad and still-held conclusions regarding processes and regional landscape evolution. The erosion required to form <name type="place" key="The Dalles of the Columbia">The Dalles of the Columbia</name> seemed consistent with evidence elsewhere in the region of the great erosional capacity of large rivers. <name type="person" key="Newberry, John S.">Newberry</name> argued that this allowed the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name> to maintain a near sea-level route through a rising Cascade Range and thus anticipated by twenty years the concept of an "antecedent river," promoted by John Wesley Powell in his description of the Colorado River and the formation of the Grand Canyon.<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0118" n="18"/>
         </p>
         <p>The press for navigational improvements and hydropower structures resulted in the first detailed surveys of <name type="place" key="The Dalles of the Columbia">The Dalles of the Columbia</name> by the U.S. Engineers in October 1874, followed by additional surveys during the next few decades. These maps quantitatively show the rugged above-water topography and the marked widening and narrowing of the river, and they provide the first measurements of the great depths of the channels; some rock-bound holes in Long Narrows sounded at 170 feet below the low-water surface, more than 170 feet below sea level.<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0119" n="19"/>
         </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
         <head>
            <hi rend="italic">"All other hypotheses meet fatal objections"</hi>
         </head>
         <p>The 1874 topographic mapping by the U.S. Engineers and early twentieth-century U.S. Geological Survey topographic quadrangles showed the bizarre landscape of The Dalles and other places along the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>. These were the maps that inspired Harlan Bretz to hypothesize that a cataclysmic ice-age flood had carved what he called the "Channeled Scabland" of eastern Washington and the <name type="place" key="Columbia River Gorge">Columbia River Gorge</name>.<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0120" n="20"/> Bretz's first experience in the gorge was in the summer of 1915, when he assisted geologist Ira Williams in describing the geology along the new highway linking Portland and <name type="place" key="The Dalles of the Columbia">The Dalles of the Columbia</name>. In 1922, as a new faculty member in the geology department at the University of Chicago, Bretz returned to the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name> Basin with students to explore the landscape shown by the maps.<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0121" n="21"/> Like earlier explorers at <name type="place" key="The Dalles of the Columbia">The Dalles of the Columbia</name>, he found flat, barren basalt flows with rugged and rocky surfaces, in some places gouged by huge holes and deep vertical slots. These features were episodically flooded by the raging <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> during peak snowmelt; but in many other places in eastern Washington, such as Grand Coulee, similar landscapes were waterless. As he mapped the fluted, channeled, and potholed surfaces, he saw that they formed long anastomosing tracts of scabland separated by islands of softly rounded hills of windblown sand and silt cultivated by dryland wheat farmers.</p>
         <p>In more than a dozen geological reports published between 1923 and 1932, Bretz built a case that these scablands had been eroded by a truly cataclysmic flood from a then-unknown source. He deduced that the flood had spilled out of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> and Spokane river valleys in northern and eastern Washington, cutting rocky coulees hundreds of feet deep and miles wide southwest across eastern Washington, before regathering in Pasco Basin and following the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> valley westward through the gorge. Bretz asserted that the eroded scabland topography and nearby deposits of sand and gravel resulted from river channel processes, but at a valley scale. The streamlined mounds of gravel hundreds of feet high that flanked the coulees were not terraces left by rivers in earlier ages but immense flood bars deposited almost instantaneously in reaches of slacker current. The basalt benches resulted from plucking and erosion at the bottom of deep and fast currents that covered entire valley bottoms to depths of hundreds of feet. Finding that "all other hypotheses meet fatal objections," Bretz wrote: "These remarkable records of running water on the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> Plateau and in the valleys of the Snake and <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>s cannot be interpreted in terms of ordinary river action and ordinary valley development.... Enormous volume, existing for a very short time, alone will account for their existence."<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0122" n="22"/> In short, Bretz concluded that this landscape was formed in days, not eons.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
         <head>
            <hi rend="italic">"We are all now catastrophists"</hi>
         </head>
         <p>Named the “Spokane Flood” by Bretz in 1925—but now more commonly called the Missoula Floods for their more recently discovered source in ice-dammed Lake Missoula the "outrageous hypothesis" spurred three decades of sometimes acrimonious debate.<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0123" n="23"/> The issue was not just the genesis of peculiar scabland landscapes in the Pacific Northwest. It dove at the heart of accepted geological thinking. In the early 1900s, European and North American geology was less than a century past overcoming the doctrine that landscapes were formed from the Noachian flood. By the 1870s, science had embraced wholesale Charles Lyell's uniformitarianism—that landscapes form from slow, gradual, everyday processes operating over millions and millions of years. Bretz's cataclysmic flood explanation was a heretical return to catastrophism, "flaunting catastrophe too vividly in the face of the uniformity that had lent scientific dignity to interpretation of the history of the earth."<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0124" n="24"/> Although the first geologists in the region, <name type="person" key="Dana, James D.">Dana</name> and <name type="person" key="Newberry, John S.">Newberry</name>, had recognized that extraordinary events had helped shape the landscape of the Pacific Northwest, some key figures in U.S. geology entered the fray, eager to show that the Channeled Scabland could be explained by "leisurely streams with normal discharge."<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0125" n="25"/>
         </p>
         <p>The <name type="place" key="Columbia River Gorge">Columbia River Gorge</name> was an important venue for this debate. Papers by Bretz in 1925 and 1928 described features in the gorge revealing erosion and deposition by floodwaters a thousand feet deep. Bretz calculated the flow rate to have been 70 million cubic feet per second, more than fifty times the largest historic <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name> flood of 1894. Ira Allison of Oregon State College and Edwin T. Hodge of the University of Oregon were quick to form alternative explanations for flood features in the gorge, separately calling on complicated sequences of ice jams and gradual river downcutting to produce Bretz's flood features.<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0126" n="26"/> Thus, they provided a interpretation that "does not require a short-lived catastrophic flood but explains the scablands, the gravel deposits, diversion channels.... as the effects of a moderate flow of water, now here and now there, over an extended period of time. It thus removes the flood from the `impossible' category.<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0127" n="27"/>
         </p>
         <p>
            <name type="place" key="The Dalles of the Columbia">The Dalles of the Columbia</name> in particular provided evidence for Bretz's case for the Spokane Flood. In a 1924 paper, "<name type="place" key="The Dalles of the Columbia">The Dalles of the Columbia</name> Type of River Channel," Bretz linked the actual processes of basalt erosion to the resulting forms of the channeled scabland, especially focusing on the role that plucking by swirling river currents played in forming the large eroded holes, both in the present channel and on the flanking rocky surfaces.<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0128" n="28"/> He also related flat-topped knobs, straight and vertically bound rock channels, circular holes, and rough, hackly rock surfaces—classic scabland—to the plucking and impact abrasion of the extensively fractured but horizontally bedded basalt flows. Bretz linked the intense and swirling currents seen by <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> to the erosional features at <name type="place" key="The Dalles of the Columbia">The Dalles of the Columbia</name> and, by analogy, to scabland topography elsewhere, providing strong support that the waterless tracts of channeled and potholed basalts originated at the bottom of deep, swift, turbulent currents. The dry scabland tracts branching across eastern Washington could only be explained by flows that were vastly larger than any <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name> flood viewed by early white explorers.</p>
         <p>Despite Bretz's careful field observations and sound reasoning, much of the scientific community denied a cataclysmic origin for the channeled scabland. Not until a last field campaign in 1952—specifically conducted to answer critics—coupled with aerial photographs and a new generation of less dogmatic geologists did Bretz's "outrageous hypothesis" become accepted. Bretz may have had his final satisfaction in 1965, when an international field expedition of geologists saw the channeled scabland at the end of a trip and telegrammed him with a message: "We are now all catastrophists."<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0129" n="29"/>
         </p>
         <p>In 1957, one hundred and fifty years after <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>'s final portage eastward around Celilo Falls and only a year after Bretz silenced many critics of the Spokane Flood with the publication of his 1952 field study, the closing gates of <name type="place" key="The Dalles of the Columbia">The Dalles of the Columbia</name> Dam stilled the "great roreing" of <name type="place" key="The Dalles of the Columbia">The Dalles of the Columbia</name>. Nevertheless, echoes from the story of the ice-age flood still reverberate. Students of science in many fields learn about J. Harlan Bretz and the Spokane Flood as a modern example of observation and careful reasoning triumphing over dogmatic paradigms. Geologists, geographers, and planetary scientists continue to draw from features of the Missoula Floods to understand the landscapes of other hugely flooded terrains in North America and Asia. As I write this, nearly 199 years after <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>'s portage over the "rugid black rock," the forefront of U.S. exploration is the probing by NASA's rovers, <hi rend="italic">Spirit</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Opportunity</hi>, which are crawling over now-waterless but perhaps similarly flooded and channeled terrains on Mars.<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0130" n="30"/> Back in October 1805, however, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> paddled downstream in their wooden canoes to landscapes transformed by even more recent cataclysms than the ice-age floods.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
         <head>
            <hi rend="italic">"the grand Schute" "The Submerged Forest of the Columbia"</hi>
         </head>
         <p>After descending the final rapids of the <name type="place" key="The Dalles of the Columbia">The Dalles of the Columbia</name> and onto a calmer <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name> on October 25, 1805, the Corps of Discovery camped at "Fort Rock" near present-day <name type="place" key="The Dalles of the Columbia">Dalles of the Columbia</name>. On October 28, in adverse winds, rain, and little current, they pushed on into the heart of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River Gorge">Columbia River Gorge</name>. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> noted the change in topography, including the "high Mounts. on each side" and "Several places where the rocks projected into the river &amp; have the appearance of haveing Separated from the mountains and fallen promiscuisly into the river," as well as several waterfalls on the south valley walls.<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0131" n="31"/>
         </p>
         <p>In the reach between the Little White Salmon and Wind rivers, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> described the "remarkable circumstance" of what became known as the "submerged forest of the Columbia" when he noted "a number of Stumps at Some distance in the Water."<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0132" n="32"/>
            <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>'s journal on their return trip in 1806 offers more description:</p>
         <p>throughout the whole course of this river from the [<name type="place" key="Cascade Rapids">Cascade</name>] rapids as high as the Chilluckkitequaws [Native American settlement near <name type="place" key="The Dalles of the Columbia">The Dalles of the Columbia</name>], we find the trunks of many large pine trees s[t]anding erect as they grew at present in 30 feet water; they are much doated and none of them vegetating; at the lowest tide of the river many of these trees are in ten feet water.<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0133" n="33"/>
         </p>
         <p>Continuing downstream, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> reached the "Commencement of the grand Schute," later known as <name type="place" key="Cascade Rapids">Cascade Rapids</name> Rapids, forty miles from Fort Rock. At low water, the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name> descended thirty-seven feet over a distance of eight miles, with twenty-one feet of fall accomplished in the first half mile at the main rapids.<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0134" n="34"/> As <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> described it:</p>
         <p>This Great Shute or falls is about 1/2 a mile with the water of this great river Compressed within the Space of 150 paces in which there is great numbers of both large and Small rocks, water passing with great velocity forming [foaming?] &amp; boiling in a most horriable manner.<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0135" n="35"/>
         </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
         <head>
            <hi rend="italic">"many tithes may the trough of this masterful river have been partially or entirely clogged…"</hi>
         </head>
         <p>Like the <name type="place" key="The Dalles of the Columbia">Dalles of the Columbia</name>, both the rapids and the submerged trees upstream were noted by early pioneers, explorers, and geographers, including Rev. Samuel Parker, Frémont, Drayton of the Wilkes Expedition, and Abbot and <name type="person" key="Newberry, John S.">Newberry</name> from the U.S. Corps of Topographical Engineers.<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0136" n="36"/>
            <name type="place" key="Cascade Rapids">Cascade Rapids</name> was later mapped and measured because of its importance to navigation, and the submerged forest attracted attention by its oddity. It was even noted in Lyell's 1833 edition of <hi rend="italic">Principles of Geology</hi>.<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0137" n="37"/> Unlike <name type="place" key="The Dalles of the Columbia">The Dalles of the Columbia</name>, the formation of <name type="place" key="Cascade Rapids">Cascade Rapids</name> and the submerged forest involved cataclysms of only a few hundred years ago, not several thousand. Also, the events at <name type="place" key="Cascade Rapids">Cascade Rapids</name>  had direct and substantial effects on the ecology and human use of the lower Columbia.</p>
         <p>
            <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> interpreted the processes that may have formed the submerged forest and rapids. Before arriving at the rapids, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> noted: "this part of the river resembles a pond partly dreamed leaving many Stumps hare loth in &amp; out of the water...." He continued: "... stumps of pine trees . . . gives every appearance of the rivers damed up below from Some cause which I am not at this time acquainted with....”<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0138" n="38"/> Upon reaching <name type="place" key="Cascade Rapids">Cascade Rapids</name> on October 31, 1805, he saw how the rocks formed the rapids and completed the scenario:</p>
         <p>those obstructions together with the high Stones which are continually brakeing loose from the mountain on the Stard [north] Side and roleing down into the Shute aded to those which brake loose from those Islands above and lodge in the Shute, must be the Cause of the rivers daming up to Such a distance above ...<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0139" n="39"/>
         </p>
         <p>
            <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> expanded on this on during their return:</p>
         <p>certain it is that those large pine trees never grew in that position, nor can I account for this phenomenon except it be that the passage of the river through the narrow pass at the rapids has been obstructed by the rocks which have fallen from the hills into that channel within the last 20 years: the appearance of the hills at that place justify this opinion, they appear constantly to be falling in, and the apparent state of the decayed trees would seem to fix the era of their decline about the time mentioned.<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0140" n="40"/>
         </p>
         <p>These interpretations, which resemble present thinking, were the first of many advanced by explorers, geographers, and geologists over the next hundred years. Reverend Parker described navigating through the "forest" of submerged trees in 1835, looking for evidence that the trees themselves had slid down from the adjacent valley slopes or that there was a downstream dam. Finding no evidence of either, he concluded: "It is plainly evident that here has been a subsidence of a tract of land, more than twenty miles in length, and about a mile in width."<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0141" n="41"/> Daniel Lee and Joseph Frost, also missionaries, disagreed with Parker and explained, much like <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> did:</p>
         <p>The supposition that a subsidence has occurred here appears groundless. Admit a dam at the Cascades, and these appearances perplex no more. their origin seems natural. At the Cascades there are indications that the stream has left its former bed, in which its course was westward, and abruptly turning to the south, rushes and plunges down in that direction nearly a mile.<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0142" n="42"/>
         </p>
         <p>In late June 1841, Drayton of the Wilkes Expedition, traveled up the river at very high flow and, as Wilkes described it:</p>
         <p>He is of opinion that the point on which the pine forest stands, has been undermined by the great currents during the freshets; and that it has sunk bodily down until the trees were entirely submerged.<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0143" n="43"/>
         </p>
         <p>Two years later, in November 1843, Frémont's expedition navigated the river at low flow and on November 17 recorded:</p>
         <p>These collections of dead trees are called on the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> the submerged Pest, and are supposed to have been created by the effects of some convulsion which formed the cascades, and which by damming up the river, placed these trees under water and destroyed them. But I venture to presume that the cascades are older than the trees; and as these submerged forests occur at five or six places along the river, I had an opportunity to satisfy myself that they have been formed by immense landslides from the mountains, which here closely shut in the river, and which brought down with them into the river the pines of the mountain.<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0144" n="44"/>
         </p>
         <p>The first professional geologist to comment on the <name type="place" key="Cascade Rapids">Cascade Rapids</name> and the submerged forest was <name type="person" key="Newberry, John S.">Newberry</name>, attached to Abbot's 1854–1855 Pacific Railroad Survey. Reporting from observations on September 17 and 18, 1855, he wrote:</p>
         <p>...the river is bordered on either side by the erect, but partially decayed, stumps of trees, which project in considerable numbers above the surface of the water. This has been termed the sunken forest, and has been generally attributed to slides from the sides of the mountains, which have carried down into the bed of the stream the standing trees. This phenomenon is, however, dependent on a different cause. As I have mentioned, the vicinity of the falls has been the scene of recent volcanic action. A consequence of this action has been the precipitation of a portion of the wall bordering the stream into its bed. This impediment acting as a dam, has raised the level of the water above the <name type="place" key="Cascades">Cascades</name>, giving to the stream its lake-like appearance, and submerging a portion of the trees which lined its banks. Of these trees, killed by the water, the stumps of many are still standing, and by their degree of preservation attest the modern date of the catastrophe.<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0145" n="45"/>
         </p>
         <p>Subsequent geologists advocated even more scenarios. In 1870, Samuel F. Emmons, a geologist with Clarence King's Geological Exploration of the Fortieth Parallel, proposed that the river in its downcutting through the Cascade Range encountered an opening in an underlying layer of erodible rock and "thus for a certain distance the whole <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> would run underground," only later to "gradually wear away the supports of the overhanging sheet of basalt" until the natural bridge collapsed, leaving "the river dammed up to the present level." In 1887, Clarence Dutton, a geologist with the newly consolidated U.S. Geological Survey, proposed that broad crustal upwarping near <name type="place" key="Cascade Rapids">Cascade Rapids</name> caused upstream impoundment. In 1899, G.K. Gilbert, a renowned early USGS geologist, first speculated that the large land mass diverting the river south at <name type="place" key="Cascade Rapids">Cascade Rapids</name> was perhaps a moraine left by large glaciers flowing through the gorge during the last ice age; a month later, he stated that a landslide was responsible for the blockage. USGS geologist Joseph Silas Diller hedged his bets, suggesting in 1916 that uplift, faulting, or landsliding were all plausible explanations.<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0146" n="46"/>
         </p>
         <p>In 1916, Ira A. Williams (assisted by Bretz) sealed the case with detailed descriptions of the topography and stratigraphy of the area surrounding <name type="place" key="Cascade Rapids">Cascade Rapids</name>, proclaiming in his geologic guidebook for the newly opened <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name> Highway:</p>
         <p>It is no far-drawn speculation that at times large bodies of rock would suddenly slump from these cliffs into the river. Particularly would this be expected from the Table [M]ountain side where so favorable and unsubstantial a combination of strata still exists. We are not at all certain but that many times may the trough of this masterful river have been partially or entirely clogged and its current checked if not actually ponded by gigantic landslides.... What more natural then, than that the latest of these cataclysmic slides of which the channel is not yet wholly cleared, may have swung the river far aside and formed temporarily so much of a barrier as to completely dam the river, and even to permit passage across of the native inhabitants.
<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0147" n="47"/>
         </p>
         <p>This report was the first published statement of current thinking: an immense landslide slid from the northern gorge walls and blocked the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>, forcing the river to cut a new course to the south, circling five miles around the toe of the landslide. The large rocks forming <name type="place" key="Cascade Rapids">Cascade Rapids</name> Rapids are debris within the landslide that are too large for the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name> to remove. The submerged forest upstream was the former valley bottom forest. The Douglas fir, western red cedar, and white oak were once rooted above the level of annual floods but then were submerged by the lake-like river kept forty feet high by the remaining impediment of <name type="place" key="Cascade Rapids">Cascade Rapids</name> Rapids.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
         <head>
            <hi rend="italic">"The Indians say these falls are not ancient"</hi>
         </head>
         <p>The Cascade, or Bonneville, landslide was well-studied over the next two decades as a consequence of dam-siting analyses leading to the 1934–1938 construction of Bonneville Dam.<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0148" n="48"/> The most systematic analysis of the submerged forest was spurred by the impending additional submergence in the pool behind the dam. Donald B. Lawrence, a Portland resident working on a doctorate in botany at Johns Hopkins University, counted, mapped, and photographed the drowned forest during low water in 1934 and 1935.<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0149" n="49"/> He tabulated more than eighteen hundred trees singly and in groups in the twenty-five miles above <name type="place" key="Cascade Rapids">Cascade Rapids</name>. Lawrence determined that the lowest of the submerged snags were rooted at only 33.5 feet above sea level, similar to maximum flood stages downstream of <name type="place" key="Cascade Rapids">Cascade Rapids</name>. This showed that no such rapids (or any significant river gradient) could have existed when the trees were growing.
<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0150" n="50"/>
         </p>
         <p>One of Lawrence's objectives was to determine the age of the landslide and the <name type="place" key="Cascade Rapids">Cascade Rapids</name>. The well-preserved drowned snags hinted of recentness, and <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> suggested that the trees were killed only about twenty years before their visit. Lawrence used dendrochronology to find out. By counting and measuring widths of annual rings from sawn sections of the drowned trees and finding overlapping periods of years by ring-width patterns in nearby live trees, he might cross-date the death of the snags that presumably drowned within months after the landslide dammed the river. With this approach, Lawrence did document that four of the six submerged trees died the same year, but he found no overlap between the drowned trees and the three live trees that he analyzed and so could not determine the precise year. He could only conclude that the submerged trees must have drowned sometime before the germination of the oldest measured live tree in about 1735. Lawrence later searched the landslide debris itself and found from ring counts that the oldest growing tree germinated in 1562, presumably some time after the tumultuous event. In 1958, two decades after the closure of Bonneville Dam, Lawrence submitted two retained samples of the submerged forest to the then-new technique of radiocarbon dating. These gave age estimates of about seven hundred years ago, leading Lawrence to conclude that the landslide and resulting tree submergence had occurred in about 1250. More recent work, including more accurate radiocarbon dating of some of Lawrence's original samples, tentatively indicates that the trees died in about 1450.
<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0151" n="51"/>
         </p>
         <p>The Native American legends describing the Bridge of the Gods, supposedly a natural bridge or blockage across the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>, were either ignored or romanticized into fanciful tales of debacles and debauchery by early observers. But Thomas Condon, a missionary and later Oregon's first state geologist, sifted through oral histories of <name type="place" key="Cascade Rapids">Cascade Rapids</name> and <name type="place" key="The Dalles of the Columbia">The Dalles of the Columbia</name>. Coupling these accounts with his own observations and inferences, Condon in 1869 recognized some of the possible ecological and cultural consequences of the events forming <name type="place" key="Cascade Rapids">Cascade Rapids</name> and the submerged forest.
<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0152" n="52"/> Foremost was the creation of a new barrier to human navigation and fish passage: "The Indians say these falls are not ancient, and that their fathers voyaged [from the sea] without obstruction in their canoes as far as <name type="place" key="The Dalles of the Columbia">The Dalles of the Columbia</name>.” <ref target="nlc.oconnor.0153" n="53"/> The later portage required at <name type="place" key="Cascade Rapids">Cascade Rapids</name> surely affected the movement of people and goods across the Cascade Range, helping to make the area a natural toll gate and trading center.<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0154" n="54"/> The numerous Native American settlements recorded by <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> near <name type="place" key="Cascade Rapids">Cascade Rapids</name> reflect the abundant fishing and commerce there. Most or all of these sites and others abandoned nearby have been shown by archaeological studies to postdate the Bonneville landslide.<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0155" n="55"/>
         </p>
         <p>The Bonneville landslide and <name type="place" key="Cascade Rapids">Cascade Rapids</name> must have affected the migration of that icon of the Pacific Northwest, salmon. At first, the land-slide blocked the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>—and passage—completely. Then, after being overtopped by the impounded river, upstream migration was surely slowed by long, steep rapids. An outstanding question is: "For how long did the Bonneville landslide completely block the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>?" Surrounding topography suggests a temporary dam as high as 240 to 300 feet, matching the cumulative height of today's dams at Bonneville, <name type="place" key="The Dalles of the Columbia">The Dalles of the Columbia</name>, and John Day and perhaps backing up water as far upstream as Wallula Gap. For modern flow rates of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>, this natural dam would overtop in only three to eight months, after which the river eventually incised a new channel through and around it. If erosion of a new channel through the blockage-reducing the total river fall around and through the landslide from perhaps more than two hundred feet at first to about thirty-seven feet at the time of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>-took more than a few years, then upriver salmon pasage would have been either stopped or significantly diminished in the years or decades after the landslide.</p>
         <p>More indirectly but perhaps more significant in the long term, the formation of <name type="place" key="Cascade Rapids">Cascade Rapids</name> may also have enabled fish passage upstream at <name type="place" key="The Dalles of the Columbia">The Dalles of the Columbia</name>. The <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name> had not eroded through the landslide dam completely but left the thirty-seven-foot drop (at low flow) of <name type="place" key="Cascade Rapids">Cascade Rapids</name>through bouldery debris. By elevating the upstream river surface, <name type="place" key="Cascade Rapids">Cascade Rapids</name> may have acted as a natural fish ladder, facilitating passage over the chutes and falls of <name type="place" key="The Dalles of the Columbia">The Dalles of the Columbia</name>. Condon suggested so:</p>
         <p>The five miles of rapids we now call the Cascades have a total fall of thirty-seven feet. If thirty feet of this were, by any cause, now transferred fifty miles above to the other fall at the Tumwater [Celilo Falls, with a low flow drop of about twenty feet], the result would certainly be a barrier to all further progress upward of the salmon of the Columbia.<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0156" n="56"/>
         </p>
         <p>Essentially, Condon proposed that <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> Basin salmon runs upstream of Celilo postdate the landslide, now known to have been in about 1450, implying that the historically huge salmon runs of the upper basin developed in just a few hundred years. This conclusion remains speculative, but aspects may have merit. While recent archaeological research documents at least some early Native American consumption of salmon at upstream sites, some accounts of Native American oral histories suggest little or no upstream fish passage prior to the formation of <name type="place" key="Cascade Rapids">Cascade Rapids</name>.<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0157" n="57"/> The pre-rapids passage conditions through <name type="place" key="The Dalles of the Columbia">The Dalles of the Columbia</name> are not well understood. Condon's premise that total river fall at <name type="place" key="Cascade Rapids">Cascade Rapids</name> was concentrated at Celilo Falls prior to the landslide is unlikely. Then-steeper descents through the intervening rapids of the Short and Long Narrows probably accommodated some of the additional thirty-seven feet of fall. Yet, the total drop at low water (and probably high flow) through the total length of <name type="place" key="The Dalles of the Columbia">The Dalles of the Columbia</name>, including Celilo Falls, would have been about one hundred and twenty feet instead of the post-<name type="place" key="Cascade Rapids">Cascade Rapids</name> drop of about eighty feet. This higher gradient surely hindered passage, perhaps eliminating upstream salmon migration during periods of low flow because of taller falls at the Narrows or Celilo.</p>
         <p>Like <name type="place" key="The Dalles of the Columbia">The Dalles of the Columbia</name>, <name type="place" key="Cascade Rapids">Cascade Rapids</name> and the submerged forest now lie beneath a reservoir. The submerged forest, whose roots are even more deeply drowned than before, fell like much of the bottomland forests of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> valley— by the saw. To reduce navigation hazards in Bonneville Reservoir, the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers cut down most of what remained of the "remarkable circumstance" of "Stumps at Some distance in the Water" that <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> reported on October 30, 1805.<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0158" n="58"/>
         </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
         <head>
            <hi rend="italic">A "Conocol form Covered with Snow" and the "The quick Sand river"</hi>
         </head>
         <p>The Cascade Range near the <name type="place" key="Columbia River Gorge">Columbia River Gorge</name> is built up of volcanic rocks erupted over the last 40 million years. Crowning the range are volcanoes such as Mount Hood and Mount St. Helens, which have risen in the last million years or so and were repeatedly active in the centuries before <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>'s maps show the general extent of the Cascade Range, which he called the "Western Mountains," but it is not evident that <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> knew that the snow-clad peaks were volcanoes.<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0159" n="59"/> Yet, by describing the terrain as they emerged from the <name type="place" key="Columbia River Gorge">Columbia River Gorge</name>, they inadvertently documented effects of a Mount Hood eruption of two decades before. Thus, their maps and descriptions have geological value beyond historical anecdote by providing timely observations of the effects of Cascade Range eruptions on the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>.</p>
         <p>On November 2, 1805, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>'s expedition completed its portage around the "Grande Schute" and floated "on down a Smooth gentle Stream" of the lower <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name> as it exits its gorge through the Cascade Range. Here, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> noted, "the river widens to near a mile, and the bottoms are more extensive and thickly timbered, as also the high mountains on each Side." On the morning of November 3, after camping on the Oregon side, probably near present-day Corbett Station, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> walked three miles downstream along wide, sandy beaches flanking the Oregon shore. He "halted at the mouth of a large river on the Lard [south] Side, This river throws out emence quanty of 〈quick〉 Sand and is verry Shallow . . . much resembling the river Plat[te].”<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0160" n="60"/> In his second entry for the day, he repeated that he:</p>
         <p>arrived at the enterance of a river which appeared to Scatter over a Sand bar, the bottom of which I could See quite across and did not appear to be 4 Inches deep in any part; I attempted to wade this Stream and to my astonishment found the bottom a quick Sand, and impassable. . . . Capt <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and my Self walked up this river about 1 1/2 miles to examine this river which found to be a verry Considerable Stream Dischargeing its waters through 2 Chanels which forms an Island of about 3 miles in length on the river and 1 1/2 miles wide, composed of Corse Sand which is thrown out of this quick Sand river Compressing the waters of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>and throwing the whole Current of its waters against its Northern banks, within a Chanel of 1/2 a mile wide.<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0161" n="61"/>
         </p>
         <p>In the three miles <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> traversed from their camp to the upper (eastern) channel of what is now known as the Sandy River, the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition probably passed the uppermost landing point of the party of Lt. W.R. Broughton, commander of the H.M.S. <hi rend="italic">Chatham</hi>, who was part of Capt. George Vancouver's British expedition that was surveying the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name> coast.<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0162" n="62"/> On October 30, 1792, thirteen years before <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> were in the gorge, Broughton's party landed on "Possession Point," a </p>
         <p>high sandy point of the River, from whence we had a beautiful view of a very remarkable high mountain, whose summit, and a considerable extent below it, was covered with Snow, and presented a very grand view, this Captn Broughton named Mount Hood, the breadth of the River here was between a quarter and half a mile, and depth of the water 6 fathoms.<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0163" n="63"/>
         </p>
         <p>This point of land is now referred to as the Sandy River Delta, a low plain of about six square miles jutting northward from where the Sandy River emerges from its canyon at Troutdale. The two channels of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>'s maps and descriptions correspond to the two distributary branches of twentieth-century maps. While Broughton's chart shows only a single channel that evidently joined the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> about a mile downstream of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>'s westernmost channel, both exploring parties agree on the narrowness of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name> off the northern apex of the delta—a quarter to a half mile wide—in contrast to the two-and-a-half mile width estimated by <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> at their November 2 campsite upstream. The present-day width is nearly a mile at the same place where <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>'s map shows the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> being its most narrow.<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0164" n="64"/>
         </p>
         <p>
            <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> were attentive to the "quick Sand" River upon their return trip, for it was the only watercourse they had seen to drain the immense area between the Cascade Range and the Coast Range south of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>. While camped across the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> from the east branch of the Sandy River from March 31 to April 6, 1806, they learned from visiting Native Americans that another river—the Mult-no-mâh, now called the Willamette—entered downstream, its mouth hidden from the explorers by islands. They were also told that "quick Sand river was Short only headed in Mt. Hood which is in view . . . and is distant from this place about 40 miles." On April 1, three men led by Sergeant Prior were dispatched up the Sandy River. They reported: ". . . the bead [bed] of this river is formed entirely of quick Sand; its banks are low and at present overflown. the water is turbed and current rapid."<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0165" n="65"/>
         </p>
         <p>As later geological studies show, the prominent Sandy River Delta, the constricted and north-pushed <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>, and the sand-laden Sandy River observed by <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> owe their existence to the recent eruptive history of Mount Hood. Much of the delta is formed of sand and lahars-mudflows or debris flows shed from slopes of volcanoes—deposited during and just after Mount Hood eruptions of about the year 500.<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0166" n="66"/> Those deposits displaced the river two miles northward and onto the old volcanic rocks of lone Reef and Missoula Flood mega-boulders of Ough Reef. But the Sandy River's coarse sandbed and extensive sandbars, which <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> recorded in 1805–1806, and Broughton's 1792 "sand bank," which crosses the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name> near the mouth of the Sandy River (called by him the Baring River), were deposited by far younger eruptions. An eruptive episode at Mount Hood, termed the "Old Maid" eruption, probably started in the winter of 1781–1782, only eleven years before Broughton and twenty-four years prior to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>'s map of the Sandy River Delta shows areas of active sand deposition and corresponds closely to modern maps of Old Maid deposits.<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0167" n="67"/> This indicates that twenty-four years after the beginning of the eruption, the Sandy River channel was still aggrading the huge volume of sediment dumped into its headwaters. Sergeant Prior's April 1 six-mile ascent of the Sandy River to where the river "appeared to bend to the East" must have ended near present-day Dabney State Park, where the exploring party would have walked on a sandy channel bed nearly fifty feet above the present cobble-gravel channel.<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0168" n="68"/>
         </p>
         <p>At various places on the journey, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> saw all five high Cascade Range volcanoes visible from the Columbia: Mount Rainier, Mount Adams, Mount St. Helens, Mount Hood, and Mount Jefferson. First seen was Mount Hood shortly after reaching the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name> on their westward trip, its "Conocal form Covered with Snow." Last viewed was Mount Jefferson, which they named for their sponsor on March 30, 1806.<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0169" n="69"/> All of these volcanoes have likely affected the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name> several times during the last several hundred thousand years, but Mount Hood and Mount St. Helens have repeatedly sent lahars and eruption-related sediment to the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name> in the past twenty-five hundred years. These eruptions and the resulting downstream sedimentation built extensive valley bottoms, not just the Sandy River Delta but also where the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and Cowlitz rivers join the Columbia near present-day Woodland and Longview, Washington. A substantial volume of sediment probably entered the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name> via the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, Kalama, and Cowlitz rivers after the Mount St. Helens eruptions of 1480–1482, just a few decades after the Bonneville landslide.<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0170" n="70"/> The May 18, 1980, eruption of Mount St. Helens, which transformed "the most noble looking object of its kind in nature" into its present cratered form, sent a lahar down the Toutle and then the Cowlitz River all the way to the Columbia, depositing 50 million cubic yards of sediment in the Cowlitz River channel and filling the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name> with another 45 million cubic yards.<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0171" n="71"/> Without the extensive dredging and sediment control structures emplaced by the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers in the early 1980s, it is likely that the mouth of the Cowlitz River would now, twenty-four years after the 1980 eruption of St. Helens, look much like the "verry Shallow" and "turbed" Quick Sand River viewed by <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> in 1805, two dozen years after the 1781 start of the Old Maid eruption on Mount Hood.</p>
         <p>
            <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>’s exploration of an overland route to the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name> more than marks a historical turning point for the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>. Their records of the physical landscape and those by the explorers, geographers, and geologists who came after them underlie current understanding of the special geologic situation of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River Gorge">Columbia River Gorge</name>, one that is largely a product of geologic cataclysms. Instead of a landscape of slow geologic processes involving unfathomable "millions and millions of years," as is typically droned out in visitor-center narrations throughout the West, the floods, landslides, and volcanic eruptions shaping the <name type="place" key="Columbia River Gorge">Columbia River Gorge</name> involved tremendous forces over time periods ranging from days to decades. Unraveling the cataclysmic origin of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name> landscape has altered geologic thinking and prompted understanding of other mysterious landscapes throughout the world and even on other planets.</p>
         <p>
            <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> did not set out to change geologic paradigms. Their orders were to describe local conditions, and they noted the effects of the various cataclysms of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> because of their influence on human activities. <name type="place" key="The Dalles of the Columbia">The Dalles of the Columbia</name> and <name type="place" key="Cascade Rapids">Cascade Rapids</name> hindered navigation, promoting human development that took advantage of resulting trading and natural resource opportunities; at first, fisheries and portaging services but later bridges, locks, and dams. Sediment shed during eruptions has built out extensive bottomlands along the Columbia, many hosting Native American settlements before <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> and now the site of airports, river ports, highways, towns, and crops. The recent ages of some of the geologic events that formed these features show quite emphatically that the pre-1805 landscape—including the land, people, and ecosystems—was not static but one of drastic and dramatic change. It is almost certain that the productive fishery and numerous Native American villages at <name type="place" key="Cascade Rapids">Cascade Rapids</name> did not exist before about 1450, and it is possible that the immense salmon runs of the upper <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name> Basin may postdate this time. The large volcanic eruptions of Mount Hood in about 500 and again in the 1780s, as well as the large Mount St. Helens eruptions of about 1480, almost certainly had large effects on the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name> and the ecosystems and occupants that depended on it.</p>
         <p>Many of these geologic cataclysms mirror modern alterations to the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name> within the <name type="place" key="Columbia River Gorge">Columbia River Gorge</name>. Modern dams are analogous to the blockage by the Bonneville landslide in about 1450. Large sediment pulses into the river from volcanic eruptions are analogous to, but far larger than, sedimentation caused by land-use practices. The huge Missoula Floods of the last ice age reshaped and locally dredged the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name> channel beyond the deepest dreams of the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers. Yet, the tremendous natural resources sustaining the Native American populations at the time of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> attest to the resilience of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> ecosystem in the face of such huge disturbances, even ones of just a few decades or centuries before. For some, the recovery by the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name> to past geologic cataclysms could give hope that the "very romantic sceens" beheld by <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> only two hundred years ago—a wild and noisy <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name> boiling and swirling through falls and chutes, the tremendous fisheries in the main stem and tributaries, thick forests carpeting the river bottoms and canyon walls, and the crowded flocks of waterfowl gathering in the annually flooded bottomlands—will once again be seen, perhaps within the next two hundred years.<ref target="nlc.oconnor.0172" n="72"/>
         </p>
        </div>
        <div type="notes">
         <head>Notes</head>
         <p>My work on the geology of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River Gorge">Columbia River Gorge</name> has been in collaboration with <name type="person" key="Waitt, Richard">Richard Waitt</name>, <name type="person" key="Pierson, Tom">Tom Pierson</name>, <name type="person" key="Bourdeau, Alex">Alex Bourdeau</name>, <name type="person" key="Pringle, Patrick">Patrick Pringle</name>, and <name type="person" key="Reynolds, Nathan">Nathan Reynolds</name>. Reviews by <name type="person" key="Waitt, Richard">Waitt</name>, <name type="person" key="Pierson, Tom">Pierson</name>, <name type="person" key="Bourdeau, Alex">Bourdeau</name>, <name type="person" key="Garcia, Miriam">Miriam Garcia</name>, <name type="person" key="Williams, John">John Williams</name>, and <name type="person" key="Grant, Gordon">Gordon Grant</name> improved this manuscript.</p>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0101" n="1">For recent summaries emphasizing changes to the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>, see <name type="person" key="White, Richard">Richard White</name>, <hi rend="italic">The Organic Machine: The Remaking of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>
            </hi> (New York: Hill and Wang, 1995); and <name type="person" key="Dietrich, William">William Dietrich</name>, <hi rend="italic">Northwest Passage: The Great <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>
            </hi> (New York: Simon and Schuster, 1995).</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0102" n="2">
            <name type="person" key="Allen, J. E.">J. E. Allen</name> et al., <hi rend="italic">Cataclysms on the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>
            </hi> (Portland, Or.: Timber Press, 1986).</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0103" n="3">Subhead quote from President <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Thomas Jefferson</name>'s instructions to Capt. Meriwether <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, June 20, 1803, in <name type="person" key="Jackson, Donald">Donald Jackson</name>, ed., <hi rend="italic">Letters of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition</hi>, 2 vols., 2nd ed. (Urbana: University of Illinois Press, 1978), 1:61–6. For a full description of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>'s landscape observations, see <name type="person" key="Moody, John A.">John A. Moody</name> et al., <hi rend="italic">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>'s Observations and Measurements of Geomorphology and Hydrology, and Changes with Time</hi>, U.S. Geological Survey Circular 1246 (Reston, Va.: GPO, 2003).</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0104" n="4">
            <name type="person" key="Playfair, John">John Playfair</name>, <hi rend="italic">Illustrations of the Huttonian Theory of the Earth</hi> (Edinburgh: William Creech, 1802); <name type="person" key="Lyell, Charles">Charles Lyell</name>, <hi rend="italic">The Principles of Geology</hi> (1830–1933; reprint, New York: Johnson Reprint, 1969). For a history of the science oflandform development, see <name type="person" key="Tinkler, Keith J.">Keith J. Tinkler</name>, <hi rend="italic">A Short History of Geomorphology</hi> (Totowa, N.J.: Barnes and Noble, 1985).</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0105" n="5">See <name type="person" key="Rabbitt, Mary C.">Mary C. Rabbitt</name>, <hi rend="italic">Minerals, Lands, Geology for the Common Defense and General Welfare</hi>, 3 vols. (Washington, D.C.: GPO, 1979–1986). See also <name type="person" key="Bartlett, Richard A.">Richard A. Bartlett</name>, <hi rend="italic">Great Surveys of the American West</hi> (Norman: University of Oklahoma Press, 1962); and <name type="person" key="Goetzmann, William H.">William H. Goetzmann</name>, <hi rend="italic">Exploration and Empire: The Explorer and the Scientist in the Winning of the American West</hi> (New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1966).</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0106" n="6">
            <name type="person" key="Waitt, Richard B.">Richard B. Waitt</name>, "Quaternary Research in the Northwest 1805–1979 by Early Government Surveys and the U.S. Geological Survey, and Prospects for the Future," in <hi rend="italic">Frontiers of Geological Exploration of Western North America</hi>, ed. <name type="person" key="Leviton, Alan E.">Alan E. Leviton</name> et al. (San Francisco: American Association for the Advancement of Science, Pacific Division, 1982), 167–207.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0107" n="7">
            <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> chronology, observations, and quotes are from <name type="person" key="Moulton, Gary E.">Gary E. Moulton</name>, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Definitive Journals of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>
            </hi>, vols. 2–8 (Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 2002).</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0108" n="8">See <name type="person" key="McArthur, Lewis A.">Lewis A. McArthur</name> and <name type="person" key="McArthur, Lewis L.">Lewis L. McArthur</name>, <hi rend="italic">Oregon Geographic Names</hi>, 7th ed. (Portland: Oregon Historical Society Press, 2003), 945–6. See also <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, October 24, 1805, in <name type="person" key="Moulton, Gary E.">Moulton</name>, ed., <hi rend="italic">Journals</hi>, 5:331.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0109" n="9">
            <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, October 24, 25, 1805, April 16, 1806, in <name type="person" key="Moulton, Gary E.">Moulton</name>, ed., <hi rend="italic">Journals</hi>, 5:333.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0110" n="10">Ibid., 322, 324.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0111" n="11">
            <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, October 24, 1805, in ibid., 333.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0112" n="12">Ibid., 331.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0113" n="13">
            <name type="person" key="Wilkes, Charles">Charles Wilkes</name>, <hi rend="italic">Narrative of the United States Exploring Expedition, during the Years 1838, 1839, 1840, 1841, 1842</hi> (Philadelphia: C. Sherman, 1844), 4:411.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0114" n="14">
            <name type="person" key="Dana, James D.">James D. Dana</name>, <hi rend="italic">United States Exploring Expedition, during the Years 1838, 1839, 1840, 1841, 1842, Under the Command of Charles Wilkes, U.S.N., Geology</hi> (New York: Putnam, 1849), 10:645–8.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0115" n="15">
            <name type="person" key="Smucker, Samuel M.">Samuel M. Smucker</name>, <hi rend="italic">The Life of Col. <name type="person" key="Frémont, John Charles">John Charles Frémont</name>, and his Narrative of Explorations and Adventures, in Kansas, Nebraska, Oregon and California</hi> (New York: Miller, Orton and Mulligan, 1856), 321–2.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0116" n="16">
            <name type="person" key="Abbot, Henry L.">Henry L. Abbot</name>, <hi rend="italic">Explorations for a Railroad Route, front the Sacramento Valley to the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name> made by Lieut. <name type="person" key="Williamson, R. S.">R. S. Williamson</name>, Corps of Topographical Engineers</hi>, vol. 6, pt. 1 of <hi rend="italic">Reports of Explorations and Surveys, to Ascertain the Most Practicable and Economical Route for a Railroad from the Mississippi River to the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name> Ocean</hi> (Washington, D.C.: A.O.P. Nicholson, 1857), 88.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0117" n="17">
            <name type="person" key="Newberry, J. S.">J. S. Newberry</name>, <hi rend="italic">Geological Report, Routes in California and Oregon Explored by Lieut. <name type="person" key="Williamson, R. S.">R. S. Williamson</name>, Corps of Topographical Engineers</hi>, vol. 6, pt. 2, no. of <hi rend="italic">Reports of Explorations and Surveys</hi>, 54.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0118" n="18">Ibid., 53–5. <name type="person" key="Powell, John Wesley">John Wesley Powell</name>, in <hi rend="italic">Exploration of the Colorado River of the West and Its Tributaries, 1869–1872</hi> (Washington, D.C.: GPO, 1875), 152–3, defines an "antecedent" river as one that maintains its course through a rising geologic structure, as the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name> has through the Cascade Range. A "consequent" river's course is imposed on it by adjacent structures, such as the <name type="place" key="Willamette River">Willamette River</name>, which is confined between the crests of the Cascade and Coast ranges.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0119" n="19">
            <name type="person" key="Michler, N.">N. Michler</name>, 1 inch to 600 feet scale map, <name type="place" key="The Dalles of the Columbia">The Dalles of the Columbia</name> to Celilo, U.S. Engineers, September 1874, copy at Reference Library, Oregon Historical Society, Portland [hereafter OHS Reference Library]. See <name type="person" key="Bretz, J.H.">J.H. Bretz</name>, "<name type="place" key="The Dalles of the Columbia">The Dalles of the Columbia</name> Type of River Channel," <hi rend="italic">Journal of Geology</hi> 32 (1924): 139–49, for calculation of closed depressions. Measurements are based on <name type="person" key="Harza, L.F.">L.F. Harza</name> and <name type="person" key="Reineking, V.H.">V.H. Reineking</name>, <hi rend="italic">The <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name> Power Project near <name type="place" key="The Dalles of the Columbia">The Dalles of the Columbia</name>, Oregon</hi>, Bulletin no. 3 (Salem, Ore.: Office of the State Engineer, 1913).</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0120" n="20">
            <name type="person" key="Bretz, J.H.">Bretz</name>'s first published paper outlining evidence of huge floods was "Glacial Drainage on the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> Plateau," <hi rend="italic">Bulletin of the Geological Society of America</hi> 34 (1923): 573–6608. The term "channeled scabland" was first defined in <name type="person" key="Bretz, J.H.">J. H. Bretz</name>, "The Channeled Scablands of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> Plateau," <hi rend="italic">Journal of Geology</hi> 31 (1923): 617–18, and was drawn from the local terms "scabland" and "scabrock," describing "areas where denudation has removed or prevented the accumulation of a mantle of soil, and the underlying rock is exposed or covered largely with its own coarse, angular debris.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0121" n="21">
            <name type="person" key="Williams, I.A.">I.A. Williams</name>, "The <name type="place" key="Columbia River Gorge">Columbia River Gorge</name>: Its Geologic History Interpreted from the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name> Highway," <hi rend="italic">The Mineral Resources of Oregon</hi> (Oregon Bureau of Mines and Geology) 2 (November 1916): 18. See also <name type="person" key="Baker, V.R.">V.R. Baker</name>, "The Spokane Flood Controversy," in <hi rend="italic">The Channeled Scabland</hi>, ed. <name type="person" key="Baker, V.R.">V.R. Baker</name> and <name type="person" key="Numamedal, D.">D. Numamedal</name> (Washington, D.C.: National Aeronautics and Space Administration, 1978), 3–14. A popular account appears in <name type="person" key="Allen, J.L.">Allen</name> et al., <hi rend="italic">Cataclysms on the Columbia</hi>.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0122" n="22">
            <name type="person" key="Bretz, J.H.">Bretz</name>, "Channeled Scablands," 621; <name type="person" key="Bretz, J.H.">J.H. Bretz</name>, "The Spokane Flood beyond the Channeled Scablands," <hi rend="italic">Journal of Geology</hi> 33 (1925): 259. See also <name type="person" key="Baker, V.R.">Baker</name>, "Spokane  Flood Controversy," 3–14.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0123" n="23">See <name type="person" key="Bretz. J.H.">Bretz</name>, "Spokane Flood," 98; <name type="person" key="Bretz, J.H.">Bretz</name>, "The Lake Missoula Floods and the Channeled Scabland," <hi rend="italic">Journal of Geology</hi> 77 (1969): 509; <name type="person" key="Bretz, J.H.">Bretz</name>, "Bars of the  Channeled Scabland," <hi rend="italic">Bulletin of the Geological Society of America</hi> 39 (1928): 701.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0124" n="24">
            <name type="person" key="Olson, E.C.">E.C. Olson</name>, introduction to Bretz, "Lake Missoula Floods," 503.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0125" n="25">
            <name type="person" key="Flint, R.F.">R.F. Flint</name>, "Origin of the Cheney-Palouse Scabland Tract," <hi rend="italic">Bulletin of the Geological Society of Americ</hi>a 49 (1938): 472.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0126" n="26">
            <name type="person" key="Hodge, E.T.">E.T. Hodge</name> "Geology of the Lower <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>," <hi rend="italic">Bulletin of the Geological Society of America</hi> 49 (1938): 898–911.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0127" n="27">
            <name type="person" key="Allison, I.S.">I.S. Allison,</name>, "New Version of the Spokane Flood," <hi rend="italic">Bulletin of the Geological Society of America</hi> 46 (1933): 677.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0128" n="28">
            <name type="person" key="Bretz, J.H.">Bretz</name>, "Danes Type of River Channel," 139–49.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0129" n="29">
            <name type="person" key="Bretz, J.H.">Bretz</name>, "Channeled Scabland," 957–1049; <name type="person" key="Bretz, J.H.">Bretz</name>, "Lake Missoula Floods," 541.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0130" n="30">
            <name type="person" key="Bretz, J.H.">Bretz</name> et al., "Channeled Scabland," 57–1049. See also <name type="person" key="Baker, V.R.">V.R. Baker</name>, <hi rend="italic">The Channels of Mars</hi> (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1982); and <name type="person" key="Burr, D.M.">D.M. Burr</name> et al., "Recent Aqueous Floods from the Cerberus Fossae, Mars," <hi rend="italic">Geophysical Research Letters</hi> 29 (2002).</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0131" n="31">
            <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, October 30, 1805, in <name type="person" key="Moulton, Gary E.">Moulton</name>, ed., <hi rend="italic">Journals</hi>, 5:355–6.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0132" n="32">Ibid., 354–5.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0133" n="33">
            <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, April 14, 1806, in <name type="person" key="Moulton, Gary E.">Moulton</name>, ed., <hi rend="italic">Journals</hi>, 7:118.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0134" n="34">
            <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, October 30, 1805, ill <name type="person" key="Moulton, Gary E.">Moulton</name>, ed., <hi rend="italic">Journals</hi>, 5:355. Information on the water surface profile is in an October 1874 survey conducted by Maj. <name type="person" key="Michler, N.">N. Michler</name> of the U.S. Engineers. This map as well as a reduced plan and profile show a "low water" drop of 37.3 feet between the upper and lower landings. At the time of the survey, when the water was 4.5 feet above extreme low water, the total drop was 36.7 feet,  with 21.1 feet of the descent in the uppermost half mile of the rapids. Copies of the maps arc in the collection of the OHS Research library.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0135" n="35">
            <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, October 31, 1805, in <name type="person" key="Moulton, Gary E.">Moulton</name>, ed., <hi rend="italic">Journals</hi>, 5:363.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0136" n="36">Summaries of early accounts of the submerged forest are given in <name type="person" key="Barry, J.N.">J.N. Barry</name>, "The Drowned Forest of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>Gorge," <hi rend="italic">Washington Historical Quarterly</hi> 26 (1935): 119–22; and more completely in <name type="person" key="Lawrence, D.B.">D.B. Lawrence</name>, "The Submerged Forest of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River Gorge">Columbia River Gorge</name>," <hi rend="italic">Geographical Review</hi> 26 (1936): 583–5.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0137" n="37">
            <name type="person" key="Lyell, Charles">Charles Lyell</name>, <hi rend="italic">The Principles of Geology</hi> (1833; reprint, New York: Johnson Reprint, 1969), 190.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0138" n="38">
            <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, October 30, 1805, in <name type="person" key="Moulton, Gary E.">Moulton</name>, ed., <hi rend="italic">Journals</hi>, 5:354–6.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0139" n="39">
            <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, October 31, 1805, in ibid., 363.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0140" n="40">
            <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, April 14, 1806, in <name type="person" key="Moulton, Gary E.">Moulton</name>, ed., <hi rend="italic">Journals</hi>, 7:n8.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0141" n="41">
            <name type="person" key="Parker, S.">S. Parker</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal of an Exploring Tour Beyond the Rocky Mountains Under the Direction of the A.B.C.F.M. in the Years 1835, 36 and 37</hi>, 3rd ed. (Ithaca, N.Y.: Mack, Andrus and Woodruff, 1842), 141.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0142" n="42">
            <name type="person" key="Lee, D.">D. Lee</name> and <name type="person" key="Frost, J.H.">J.H. Frost</name>, <hi rend="italic">Ten Years in Oregon</hi> (New York: J. Collard, 1844), 200.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0143" n="43">
            <name type="person" key="Wilkes, Charles">Wilkes</name>, <hi rend="italic">United States Exploring Expedition</hi>, 4:407.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0144" n="44">
            <name type="person" key="Smucker, S.">Smucker</name>, <hi rend="italic">Life of Col. <name type="person" key="Frémont, John Charles">John Charles Frémont</name>
            </hi>, 335.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0145" n="45">
            <name type="person" key="Newberry, J.S.">Newberry</name>, <hi rend="italic">Geological Report</hi>, 56.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0146" n="46">
            <name type="person" key="Emmons, Samuel F.">Emmons</name>, "Submerged Trees," 156–7; Dutton, "Submerged Trees," 82–4; <name type="person" key="Diller, J.S.">J.S. Diller</name> et al., <hi rend="italic">Guidebook of the Western United States</hi>, part D, <hi rend="italic">The Shasta Route and Coast Line</hi>, USGS Bulletin 614 (Washington, D.C.: GPO, 1916), 27. <name type="person" key="Emmons, Samuel F.">Emmons</name>'s paper is the only one to suggest an actual rock bridge over the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>, and it may have inspired <name type="person" key="Balch, F.H.">F.H. Balch</name>'s <hi rend="italic">The Bridge of the Gods, a Romance of Indian Oregon</hi> (Chicago: A.C. McClurg, 1890). On Gilbert's speculation that the blockage was a glacial moraine, sec field note entry for August 12,1899, in his Notebook 3479, RG 57, Records of the USGS, National Archives, Washington, D.C., 87; documentation of a landslide origin is in his field notes for September 4–12, 1899, Notebook 3480, in ibid., 15–33.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0147" n="47">
            <name type="person" key="Williams, I.A.">Williams</name>, "<name type="place" key="Columbia River Gorge">Columbia River Gorge</name>," 92–3.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0148" n="48">An irony perhaps is that the Bonneville landslide created one of the few suitable dam sites along the lower <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>. Reports detailing the geologic conditions of the Bonneville Dam site include <name type="person" key="Schuster, R.L.">R.L. Schuster</name> and <name type="person" key="Pringle, Y.T.">Y.T. Pringle</name>, "Engineering History and Impacts of the Bonneville Landslide, <name type="place" key="Columbia River Gorge">Columbia River Gorge</name>, Washington–Oregon, USA," in <hi rend="italic">Landslides: Proceedings of the First European Conference on Landslides</hi>, ed. <name type="person" key="Rybar, J.">J. Rybar</name> et al. (Exton, Penn.: A.A. Balkema, 2002), 689–99; and <name type="person" key="Sager, J.W.">J.W. Sager</name>," Bonneville Dam," in <hi rend="italic">Engineering Geology in Washington</hi>, ed. <name type="person" key="Glaster, R.">R. Glaster</name>, <hi rend="italic">Washington Division of Geology and Earth Resources Bulletin</hi> 78:1 (1989): 337–46. Early dam-site studies were conducted by <name type="person" key="Hodge, E.T.">E.T. Hodge</name>. See <name type="person" key="Hodge, E.T.">Hodge</name>, <hi rend="italic">Report of Dam Sites on Lower <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>
            </hi> (Portland, Ore.: Pacific Division, Corps of Engineers, U.S. Army, 1932).</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0149" n="49">
            <hi rend="italic">Oregonian</hi>, August 8, 1935.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0150" n="50">
            <name type="person" key="Lawrence, D.B.">Lawrence</name>, "Submerged Forest," 581–92.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0151" n="51">Ibid., 590–1; <name type="person" key="Lawrence, D.B.">D.B. Lawrence</name> and <name type="person" key="Lawrence, E.G.">E.G. Lawrence</name>, "Bridge of the Gods Legend, Its Origin, History and Dating," <hi rend="italic">Mazama</hi> 40:13 (December 1958): 40–1. Four recent radiocarbon dates (unpublished results, <name type="person" key="O'Connor, Jim">Jim O'Connor</name> and others, USGS, Portland, Ore.) from two of <name type="person" key="Lawrence, D.B.">Lawrence</name>'s original samples of the "submerged forest" (in the collection of the World Forestry Center, Portland, Ore.) indicate tree death was between 1415 and 1455. Additional attempts at cross-dating are underway by  Patrick Pringle of the Washington State Department of Natural Resources.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0152" n="52">
            <name type="person" key="Drake, E.T.">E.T. Drake</name>,"Pioneer Geologist <name type="person" key="Condon, Thomas">Thomas Condon</name> of Oregon: Scientist, Teacher, Preacher," in <name type="person" key="Leviton, Alan E.">Leviton</name> et al., eds., <hi rend="italic">Frontiers of Geological Exploration</hi>, 77; <name type="person" key="Condon, Thomas">Thomas Condon</name>, "Geological Notes from Oregon," <hi rend="italic">Overland Monthly</hi> 3:4 (1969): 355–60, reprinted in <name type="person" key="Condon, Thomas">Condon</name>, <hi rend="italic">The Two Islands and What Came of Them</hi> (Portland, Ore.: J.K. Gill, 1902), 177–82.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0153" n="53">
            <name type="person" key="Lee, D.">D. Lee</name> and <name type="person" key="Frost, J.H.">J.H. Frost</name>, <hi rend="italic">Ten Years in Oregon</hi> (New York: J. Collard, 1844), 200.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0154" n="54">
            <name type="person" key="Beckham, Stephen Dow">Stephen Dow Beckham</name>, "This Place Is Romantic and Wild: An Historical Overview of the Cascades Area, Fort Cascades, and the Cascades Townsite, Washington Territory," <hi rend="italic">Heritage Research Reports</hi>, no. 27, to Portland District, U.S. Army Corps of Engineers, 1984.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0155" n="55">
            <name type="person" key="Beckham, S.D.">S.D. Beckham</name> et al., "Prehistory of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River Gorge">Columbia River Gorge</name> National Scenic Area, Oregon and Washington," <hi rend="italic">Heritage Research Reports</hi>, no. 75, U.S. Department of Agriculture Forest Service, <name type="place" key="Columbia River Gorge">Columbia River Gorge</name> National Scenic Area, 1988. For information on Native American oral histories of the Bridge of the Gods, see Lawrence and Lawrence, "Bridge of the Gods," 33; E.E. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, "The Bridge of the Gods in Fact and Fancy," <hi rend="italic">Oregon Historical Quarterly</hi> 53 (March 1952): 29–38.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0156" n="56">
            <name type="person" key="Condon, Thomas">Condon</name>, "Geological Notes," 180.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0157" n="57">
            <name type="person" key="Chatters, J.C.">J.C. Chatters</name> et al., "A Paleoscience Approach to Estimating the Effects of Climatic Warming on the Salmonid Fisheries of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name> Basin," in <hi rend="italic">Climate Change and Northern Fish Populations</hi>, ed. <name type="person" key="Beamish, R.J.">R.J. Beamish</name> (Ottawa: Canadian Special Publications in Fisheries and Aquatic Sciences 121, 1995), 489–96. See <name type="person" key="Lee, D.">Lee</name> and <name type="person" key="Frost, J.H.">Frost</name>, <hi rend="italic">Ten Years in Oregon</hi>, 197; Condon, "Geological Notes from Oregon," 177; and Lawrence and Lawrence, "Bridge of the Gods Legend," 41.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0158" n="58">Lawrence and Lawrence, "Bridge of the Gods Legend," 41.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0159" n="59">
            <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, March 31, 1806, in <name type="person" key="Moulton, Gary E.">Moulton</name>, ed., <hi rend="italic">Journals</hi>, 7:41.The first clear description of the Cascade Range as a volcanic chain was by <name type="person" key="Dana, James D.">Dana</name> of the 1841 Wilkes Expedition in United States Exploring Expedition, 10:625–6, 640. See also <name type="person" key="Orr, E.L.">E.L. Orr</name> et al., <hi rend="italic">Geology of Oregon</hi>, 4th ed. (Dubuque, Iowa: Kendall/Hunt, 1992), 141–66.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0160" n="60">
            <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, November 2, 3, 1805, in <name type="person" key="Moulton, Gary E.">Moulton</name>, ed., <hi rend="italic">Journals</hi>, 6:8–9, n. There is some uncertainty regarding their campsite location for the night of November 2. <name type="person" key="Moulton, Gary E.">Moulton</name> (6:10) suggested a location near the present site of Latourell, but a location fitting better with <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>'s map and descriptions, especially the estimate of three miles to the Sandy River confluence, would be two miles farther west, near present-day Corbett Station, perhaps at Tunnel Point or Onion Rock.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0161" n="61">
            <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, November 3, 1805, in <name type="person" key="Moulton, Gary E.">Moulton</name>, ed., <hi rend="italic">Journals</hi>, 6:12.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0162" n="62">A copy of Broughton's chart is at the OHS Research Library. Vancouver's narrative of Broughton's observations near the Sandy River confluence were published in <name type="person" key="Elliot, T.C.">T.C. Elliot</name>, "The Log of the H.M.S. Chatham," <hi rend="italic">Oregon Historical Quarterly</hi> 18 (June 1917): 73–82. Another log of Broughton's expedition, presumably written by <name type="person" key="Bell, Edward">Edward Bell</name>, a clerk on the Chatham, was published in <name type="person" key="Barry, J.N.">J.N. Barry</name>, "<name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name> Exploration, 1792," pts. 1 and 2, <hi rend="italic">Oregon Historical Quarterly</hi> 33 (March 1932): 31–42; 33 (June 1932): 143–55.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0163" n="63">Entry in <name type="person" key="Bell, Edward">Bell</name>'s journal for October 27, 1792, in <name type="person" key="Barry, J.N.">Barry</name>, "<name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name> Exploration, 1792," 33:145.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0164" n="64">
            <name type="person" key="Moulton, Gary E.">Gary E. Moulton</name>, ed. <hi rend="italic">Atlas of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition</hi>, vol. 1 of <name type="person" key="Moulton, Gary E.">Moulton</name>, ed., <hi rend="italic">Journals</hi> (Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1983), map 79.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0165" n="65">
            <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, March 31, April 1, 1806, in Moulton, ed., <hi rend="italic">Journals</hi>, 7:41, 51.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0166" n="66">The eruptive history of Mount Hood is described in <name type="person" key="Crandell, D.R.">D.R. Crandell</name>, <hi rend="italic">Recent Eruptive History of Mount Hood, Oregon, and Potential Hazards from Future Eruptions</hi>, USGS Bulletin 1492 ( Reston, Va.: GPO,1980); and <name type="person" key="Cameron, K.A.">K.A. Cameron</name> and <name type="person" key="Pringle, P.T.">P.T. Pringle</name>, "A Detailed Chronology of the Most Recent Major Eruptive Period at Mount Hood, Oregon," <hi rend="italic">Bulletin of the Geological Society of America</hi> 99 (1987): 845–51.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0167" n="67">
            <name type="person" key="Pringle, P.T.">P.T. Pringle</name> et al., "A Circa A.D. 1781 Eruption and Lahars at Mount Hood, Oregon: Evidence from Tree-Ring Dating and from Observations of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> in 1805–6," <hi rend="italic">Geological Society ofAmerica Abstracts with Programs</hi> 34:6 (2002): 5u; <name type="person" key="Moulton, Gary E.">Moulton</name>, ed., <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>, map 79. Ongoing studies of the Sandy River Delta area are being conducted by <name type="person" key="Rapp, Elizabeth">Elizabeth Rapp</name>, Portland State University, and <name type="person" key="O'Connor, Jim">Jim O'Connor</name> and <name type="person" key="Pierson, Thomas">Thomas Pierson</name> of the USGS.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0168" n="68">
            <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, April 1, 1806, in <name type="person" key="Moulton, Gary E.">Moulton</name>, ed., <hi rend="italic">Journals</hi>, 7:49; unpublished data courtesy of <name type="person" key="Pierson, Thomas">Thomas Pierson</name>, U.S. Geological Survey, Vancouver, Wash.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0169" n="69">
            <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, October 18,1805, March 30, 1806, in <name type="person" key="Moulton, Gary E.">Moulton</name>, ed., <hi rend="italic">Journals</hi>, 5:298, 7:36.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0170" n="70">See <name type="person" key="Mullineaux, D.R.">D.R. Mullineaux</name> and <name type="person" key="Crandell, D.R.">D.R. Crandell</name>, "The Eruptive History of Mount St. Helens," in <hi rend="italic">The 1980 Eruptions of Mount St. Helens, Washington</hi>, USGS Professional Paper 1250, ed. <name type="person" key="Lipman, P.W.">P.W. Lipman</name> and <name type="person" key="Mullineauz, D.R.">D.R. Mullineaux</name>, USGS Bulletin 1492 (Washington, D.C.: GPO, 1981), 3–16.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0171" n="71">
            <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, March 30, 1806, in <name type="person" key="Moulton, Gary E.">Moulton</name>, ed., <hi rend="italic">Journals</hi>, 7:33; <name type="person" key="Schuster, R. L.">R. L. Schuster</name>, "Effects of the Eruptions on Civil Works and Operations in the Pacific Northwest," in <name type="person" key="Lipman, P.W.">Lipman</name> and <name type="person" key="Mullineaux, D.R.">Mullineaux</name>, eds., <hi rend="italic">1980 Eruptions of Mount St. Helens</hi>, 708–9.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.oconnor.0172" n="72">
            <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, April 14, 1806, in <name type="person" key="Moulton, Gary E.">Moulton</name>, ed., <hi rend="italic">Journals</hi>, 7:118.</note>
         <p>This article has been reprinted with the permission of the <hi rend="italic">
               <!--<ref target="http://www.ohs.org/publications/about_ohq.cfm">-->Oregon Historical Quarterly<!--</ref>-->
            </hi>.</p>
        </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
