<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.sup.ronda.01.02">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> among the Indians</title>
            <title type="sub" level="a">2. The Teton Confrontation</title>
            <title type="sub"/>
            <author>James P. Ronda</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2005</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               
               
               
               
               
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title level="m" type="main">
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> among the Indians</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">2. The Teton Confrontation</title>
               <author>James P. Ronda</author>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1984</date>
               <idno type="ISBN">0-8032-8990-1</idno>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
              <term>Texts</term>
            </keywords>
           <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Books</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-11-01</date>
            <date>2005-02-01</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>File splitting Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="ch2" type="chapter" n="2">
            <quote>
               <lg type="linegroup">
                  <l>"These are the vilest miscreants of the savage race, and must ever remain the</l>
                  <l>pirates of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, until such measures are pursued, by our government, as </l>
                  <l>will make them feel a dependence on its will for their supply of merchandise."
</l>
               </lg>
               <bibl>—<name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark</name>, 1804</bibl>
            </quote>
            <div type="section">
               <p>
On August 30, 1806, as the homeward-bound <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> expedition swept down the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> near present-day <name type="place" key="Yankton, S. Dak.">Yankton</name>, <name type="place" key="South Dakota">South Dakota</name>, the explorers caught sight of more than one hundred well-armed Indians lining the northeast river bank. Salutes of greeting were fired by both parties as the expedition pulled up its canoes on the southwest bank. But the initial welcome vanished when <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> discovered that the Indians were <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">Brulé</name>
                  
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                   of <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo's</name> band.<ref target="n0201" n="1"/> The captain had hoped the Indians were <name type="native_nation" key="Ponca Indians">Poncas</name>, <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Omahas</name>, or perhaps <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Yankton">Yankton</name>
                  
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  . But once their <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">Brulé</name> identity was known, he turned on them with his own brand of invective.</p>
               <p>
Taking instructions from <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, the interpreter <name type="person" key="Jusseaume, René">René Jusseaume</name> shouted across the river that the 
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                   were "bad people" and that "if any [came] near our camp we should kill them certainly." In a second barrage, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had <name type="person" key="Jusseaume, René">Jusseaume</name> tell the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">Brulés</name> that future traders would be "sufficiently strong to whip any vilenous party who dare[d] to oppose them." As a parting shot, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> notified the 
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                   that the Americans had given guns, ammunition, and even a cannon to the 
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>
                   and <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name>—weapons that would surely be turned against <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">Brulé</name> raiders. While most of the Indians retreated in the face of <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> bombast, several warriors remained on a hill, hooting, jeering, and proclaiming their readiness to kill the Americans.</p>
               <p>
Toward sunset, one man, probably <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Chief Black Buffalo</name>, came to the water's edge and invited the expedition to come across. <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Untongarabar, or Black Bull Buffalo</name>, is known in more recent literature as <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Bull</name>. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> consistently called him <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo</name>. He remained a powerful force in <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">Brulé</name> politics and <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri River</name> trade until his death in July 1813. When <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> ignored his request, the Indian returned to the top of the hill and angrily struck the ground three times with his gun. "This I am informed," wrote <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> drily, "is a great oath among the Indians."<ref target="n0202" n="2"/>
               </p>
               <p>
The expedition's members did not sleep well that night. Wet sand, gusty winds, and an exposed campsite made them uncomfortable. Perhaps the unsettling jeers and curses of the 
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                   moved the captains and their men to recall another and even more disagreeable clash just two years earlier with <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo</name> and other <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">Brulé</name> chiefs. A close look at that tense 1804 encounter can reveal much about <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> relations with the Indians as well as the larger history of Upper <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> Indian-white contact.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>
On the evening of September 23, 1804, as the men of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> expedition rested at their camp just below the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Bad (Teton) River (S. Dak.)">Bad River</name>, three 
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                   boys swam across the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> to greet the explorers. The boys came from <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name>
                  
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                   villages along the <name type="place" key="Bad (Teton) River (S. Dak.)">Bad River</name>, opposite present-day <name type="place" key="Pierre, S. Dak.">Pierre</name>, <name type="place" key="South Dakota">South Dakota</name>. From the very beginning of their enterprise, the captains had known they would have to face the feisty <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Tetons</name>. Their reputation for harrassing traders, pilfering merchandise, and demanding large gifts was well known among <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> merchants. <name type="person" key="Truteau, Jean Baptiste">Jean Baptiste Truteau</name>, whose party had been stopped by the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Tetons</name> in 1794, warned that "all voyageurs who undertake to gain access to the nations of the Upper <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> ought to avoid meeting this tribe, as much for the safety of their goods as for their lives even." <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> conversations in <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> with <name type="person" key="Lisa, Manuel">Manuel Lisa</name>, <name type="person" key="Soulard, Antoine">Antoine Soulard</name>, the Chouteaus, and especially <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">James Mackay</name>, had made them aware of the risks in meeting the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Tetons</name>. The expedition's chance encounter with <name type="person" key="Loisel, Régis">Regis Loisel</name>, a trader just back from the 
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                   country, had added to their information.<ref target="n0203" n="3"/> Now the 
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                   boys told of two villages upriver. The captains, anxious to begin the talks, told the boys that their chiefs were invited to a conference the following day.<ref target="n0204" n="4"/>
               </p>
               <p>
After breaking camp on Monday morning, September 24, the expeditions began serious preparations for the long-anticipated parley. Knowing that the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">Brulé</name> chiefs would require substantial gifts for themselves and their people, the captains worked through their bales of trade goods to find suitable presents. Among the items selected for the chiefs were flags, medals, and a red military coat and cocked hat. Also prepared for general distribution were knives, small metal and fabric goods, and a large amount of tobacco. Because their <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> contacts had warned them about the often violent tactics used by the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Tetons</name> to control river traffic, the expedition was armed with more than gifts. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> cryptically recorded that he and <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> "prepared all things for action in case of necessity."</p>
               <p>
That "necessity" seemed to come closer in the afternoon when <name type="native_nation" key="Colter, John">John Colter</name>, who had been on shore hunting, reported that one of their horses had been stolen by some <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name> warriors. No sooner had <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name> made his report than five Indians appeared on shore. The expedition's flotilla, now near the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Bad (Teton) River (S. Dak.)">Bad River</name>, anchored in the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> while the captains tried to talk with these 
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  . <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> felt certain that they were the horse thieves and, employing an old ruse, told them the horse was intended for their chief. The American accusations and the fact that neither group understood the other made the meeting confusing and potentially dangerous. After the Indians left, the expedition made its way to an anchorage opposite the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Bad (Teton) River (S. Dak.)">Bad River</name>. An island in the Bad was selected as the place for negotiations the following day.</p>
               <p>
Later Monday evening, after the event of the stolen horse seemed less confusing and threatening, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> went to the island for a preliminary smoke with the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">Brulé</name> chiefs. They promised to return the missing horse and proclaimed their readiness for serious talk the next day. Once back on the keelboat, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> seemed relieved to report "all well" with the 
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  .<ref target="n0205" n="5"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Monday night was a time for <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> to consider the intricate diplomacy of the coming days. <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name> general instructions emphasized intertribal peace, trade contacts, American sovereignty, and the collection of ethnological material. But he had a special interest in the 
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  . Of all the Indians east of the mountains known to whites, it was the 
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                   that the president singled out for the explorers' particular attention. <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name> concern with the 
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                   was based on his appraisal of both their military strength and their economic potential. The martial power of the 
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                   nation on both sides of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> was well known. <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> was equally sensitive to the economic possibilities and imperial rivalries present in any 
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  -American negotiations. The journal by <name type="person" key="Truteau, Jean Baptiste">Truteau</name> that <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> sent to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> in November 1803 revealed those elements. <name type="person" key="Truteau, Jean Baptiste">Truteau</name> described the 
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                   as "the greatest beaver hunters," whose pelts were worth "double the Canadian for the fineness of [their] fur and parchment."<ref target="n0206" n="6"/> Here was a grand opportunity for American enterprise. Profits from the 
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                   fur trade would be an early vindication of the Louisiana Purchase. But, as <name type="person" key="Truteau, Jean Baptiste">Truteau</name> had observed, the 
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                   trade was firmly in the hands of the North West Company and its posts on the <name type="place" key="Des Moines River">Des Moines</name> and <name type="place" key="Minnesota River (St. Peters)">St. Peters</name> rivers. If American sovereignty and commerce were to triumph, the 
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                   would have to abandon John Bull for dealings with Uncle Sam.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> hoped <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> might begin to lure the 
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                   into the American orbit. But that would be no easy task. As he admitted to Secretary of the Navy <name type="person" key="Smith, Robert">Robert Smith</name>, the United States was "miserably weak" in its newly gained western lands. In an important letter to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> urged the explorers to pay close attention to the 
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  . "On that nation," wrote the president, "we wish more particularly to make a friendly impression, because of their immense power, and because we learn they are very desirous of being on the most friendly terms with us."<ref target="n0207" n="7"/>
                  <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> engaged in wishful thinking when he wrote that the 
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                   were looking for American friendship, but he was closer to the mark in noting "their immense power." <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> would have to confront that power, convince the Indians that <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> merchants did not endanger the 
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                   role in Upper <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> trade, and persuade Teton trappers and hunters to bring their pelts and skins to American posts. The captains would have to deal with Indian leaders who clearly understood tribal needs and had both the diplomatic skill and the military force to command attention. With its tangle of economic, military, and imperial interests, the Teton 
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                   negotiation was perhaps the most demanding piece of Indian diplomacy assigned to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>.</p>
               <p>
If the captains spent Monday night discussing the diplomacy for the next day, then surely men like <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo</name>, the <name type="person" key="Partisan">Partisan</name>, and <name type="person" key="Buffalo Medicine (Tar-ton-gar-wa-ker)">Buffalo Medicine</name> did the same. For the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">Brulé</name> bands and their leaders, the political and economic stakes were very high. In the intricate trade network of the Upper <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name>
                  
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                   played a dangerous and precarious game. <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name>
                  
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                   of the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">Brulé</name>, <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Oglala">Oglala</name>, a Miniconjou bands traditionally traveled each year to a trade fair known as the Dakota Rendezvous, held on the <name type="place" key="James (Jacque) River (S. Dak.)">James River</name> in east-central <name type="place" key="South Dakota">South Dakota</name>. There the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Tetons</name> met <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Sisseton">Sisseton</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Yankton">Yankton</name>
                  
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                   who had obtained manufactured goods from North West Company posts on the <name type="place" key="Des Moines River">Des Moines</name> and <name type="place" key="Minnesota River (St. Peters)">St. Peters</name> rivers. The <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name> bands used those goods and buffalo robes in their agricultural trade with the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> village farmers. With <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name> population growing, a secure food supply was essential. So long as the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Tetons</name> could control the flow of European goods to the villagers, the 
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                   position would be reasonably strong. But if the villagers gained easy direct access to <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> traders, the role of the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Tetons</name> as brokers and middle-men would be lost. These commercial considerations required the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Tetons</name> to, at most, blockade the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri River</name> or, at least, exact considerable tribute from traders coming upriver. The well-armed <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> expedition, representing <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> interests and determined to make direct contact with the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name>, <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>, and <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> villages, was an intrusion that could not be ignored.<ref target="n0208" n="8"/>
               </p>
               <p>
But there was more than economic position at stake for the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">Brulé</name> leaders. As <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> would soon discover, they were about to enter the tangled web of band factional politics. In <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">Brulé</name> politics the leading players were <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo</name>, <name type="person" key="Buffalo Medicine (Tar-ton-gar-wa-ker)">Buffalo Medicine, and Tortohongar</name>, known to the whites as the <name type="person" key="Partisan">Partisan</name>. <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo</name>, chief of the largest <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">Brulé</name> band, was described by <name type="person" key="Tabeau, Pierre-Antoine">Tabeau</name> as a man "of good character, although angry and fierce in his fits of passion." His authority and prestige had been challenged long before the advent of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> by the <name type="person" key="Partisan">Partisan</name>, chief of the second-ranked <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">Brulé</name> band. <name type="person" key="Tabeau, Pierre-Antoine">Tabeau</name>, whose trade goods had been ransacked by the <name type="person" key="Partisan">Partisan</name> and some of his men, described this <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name> as "a true Proteus, who is seen in the selfsame day faint-hearted and bold, audacious and fearful, proud and servile, conciliator and firebrand."<ref target="n0209" n="9"/> The role of <name type="person" key="Buffalo Medicine (Tar-ton-gar-wa-ker)">Buffalo Medicine</name> remains unclear; he was called by <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> the "3rd chief" in the power struggle between <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo</name> and the <name type="person" key="Partisan">Partisan</name>. That struggle for leadership often had unforeseen consequences. When <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo</name> engineered a temporary peace with his <name type="native_nation" key="Ponca Indians">Ponca</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Omaha</name> neighbors in 1803, the <name type="person" key="Partisan">Partisan</name> undercut the effort by organizing a horse-stealing raid on the <name type="native_nation" key="Ponca Indians">Poncas</name>. In retaliation, <name type="native_nation" key="Ponca Indians">Ponca</name> warriors stole nine 
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                   horses and attacked a <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">Brulé</name> village. But the village they raided was <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo's</name> and the peace was broken.<ref target="n0210" n="10"/> Now, as the negotiations with <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> were about to begin, both <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo</name> and the <name type="person" key="Partisan">Partisan</name> looked to use the talks to increase their own prestige. Playing to the Indian galleries, each chief would try to outdo the other in zealous defense of 
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                   privilege.</p>
               <p>
Early on the morning of September 25, the expedition established a council place on a sandbar in the <name type="place" key="Bad (Teton) River (S. Dak.)">Bad River</name>. A canvas awning was put in place and a flagstaff raised. By ten o'clock a large number of Indians began to gather along both river banks. About eleven o'clock <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo</name>, the <name type="person" key="Partisan">Partisan</name>, and <name type="person" key="Buffalo Medicine (Tar-ton-gar-wa-ker)">Buffalo Medicine</name> appeared. Hoping to begin the conference on a generous note, the captains offered the chiefs and thirty <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">Brulé</name> warriors something to eat. Not to be outdone, the chiefs gave the expedition several hundred pounds of fat buffalo meat. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> responded by offering the 
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                   some pork. Both sides had now shown the required hospitality and it was time at last to talk. To their chagrin, the Americans discovered they lacked an interpreter skillful enough for this demanding task. The translator <name type="person" key="Dorion, Pierre, Sr.">Pierre Dorion</name> had remained with the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Yankton">Yankton</name>
                  
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                   to promote peace between that tribe and the <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Omahas</name>. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> unhappily noted, "We feel much at a loss for want of an interpreter." The diplomats would have to rely on "the old frenchman" <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Pierre Cruzatte</name>, who <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> admitted, could "speak but little."<ref target="n0211" n="11"/>
               </p>
               <p>
At noon both sides seemed ready to settle in for the speechmaking. After the usual mandatory smoking, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> stood to make a short speech made shorter for want of an interpreter. No journalist recorded <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> words, but it is likely that at this early stage the captain spoke in no more than generalities. The speech probably followed the pattern established in earlier conferences with other tribes in which the explorer-diplomats touched on issues of intertribal peace, trade and American sovereignty.<ref target="n0212" n="12"/>
               </p>
               <p>
When <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> speech ended, the expedition put on its "traveling medicine show"—a demonstration of martial power and Western technology. This display, with its aim to impress the Indians with American might, had been successfully staged earlier for the <name type="native_nation" key="Oto Indians">Otos</name>, <name type="native_nation" key="Missouri Indians">Missouris</name>, and <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Yankton">Yankton</name>
                  
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  .<ref target="n0213" n="13"/> The performance began with a military parade by uniformed troops marching under the colors of the republic. As the parade ended, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> sought to keep the military splendor and political significance of the moment alive by handing out gifts to the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">Brulé</name> chiefs. Recognizing <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo</name> as the leading chief present, the captains gave him a medal, a red military coat, and a cocked hat. In their rush to gain approval from <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo</name>, the Americans evidently slighted the <name type="person" key="Partisan">Partisan</name>. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> may have been insensitive to the nuances of rank and precedence in <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name> politics, but by trying to make <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo</name> a client chief they were simply following long-established diplomatic practice. From the time of earliest contact, European and later American government officials had always sought one Indian chief or headman, thinking he could both speak for and command the entire tribe. But neglecting the <name type="person" key="Partisan">Partisan</name> was a serious oversight, one that was sure to spark trouble in the coming days.</p>
               <p>
While the last presents were being distributed, the carefully orchestrated show was interrupted. The <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">Brulé</name> chiefs began to complain that the gifts were inadequate, as they had done to earlier traders. They demanded the expedition either stop its upriver progress and remain with them or at least leave a gift-laden pirogue behind as tribute.<ref target="n0214" n="14"/> While the captains must have known that such demands would eventually be made, they seemed unprepared that afternoon to deal with them directly. The niceties of diplomacy and the presence of many armed <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name> warriors called for other measures. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> tried to divert <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">Brulé</name> attention by going on with the military hardware display. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> went through his now-familiar airgun demonstration, charging and firing it several times. Evidently unimpressed, <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo</name> and the other chiefs continued to press their demands. Again hoping to divert the insistent chiefs, the captains offered to take them and some of their soldiers on the keelboat. Once on board, the Indians were shown "such curiossities as was strange to them." One <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">Brulé</name> warrior was given a government certificate proclaiming him "the friend and ally of the said states" and urging all citizens to treat him "in the most friendly manner."<ref target="n0215" n="15"/> Adding to the general milling about on the keelboat was the decision to break out some trade whiskey. Each chief was given one-fourth glass, "which [he] appeared to be very fond of." <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> observed that the Indians "sucked the bottle after it was out. "Amid this confusion the <name type="person" key="Partisan">Partisan</name> made his move both to frighten the Americans and to impress bankside Indian spectators. Feigning drunkenness as a cover "for his racially intentions," the <name type="person" key="Partisan">Partisan</name> became "troublesome." Fearing a bloody melee, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> struggled to get the chiefs back on shore. Those efforts were resisted, and it was only "with great relectiance" that the chiefs and their men boarded the pirogue for shore. Although the <name type="person" key="Partisan">Partisan</name> seemed intent on using the presence of the expedition as a means to advance his own power, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> returned to land "with a view of reconsileing those men to us."</p>
               <p>
When the pirogue landed, an already difficult situation became potentially explosive. Three young <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">Brulés</name>, who may have belonged to the <name type="person" key="Partisan">Partisan's</name> retinue, seized the pirogue's bow cable. At the same moment, another warrior locked his arms around the pirogue's short mast. As the pirogue was being temporarily hijacked, the <name type="person" key="Partisan">Partisan</name> moved directly against <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>. The chief spoke roughly to <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, staggered up against him, and told him that the expedition could not advance. The <name type="person" key="Partisan">Partisan's</name> actions were designed to test <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, to make him weaken and back down as had previous white visitors. Given the presence of so many women and children, the <name type="person" key="Partisan">Partisan</name> had no intention of starting a shooting spree. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> must have sensed the limits of the situation. His response to the jostling and "insolent jestures" was equally firm. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> drew his sword and at the same time alerted <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and the keelboat crew for action. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> ordered the swivel guns readied while expeditionary soldiers around <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> prepared their weapons for firing. Then, as quickly as the <name type="person" key="Partisan">Partisan</name> had created the tension, <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo</name> eased it. Obviously fearing heavy casualities if fighting erupted, <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo</name> took the pirogue's cable and forcefully ordered the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">Brulé</name> warriors away from the boat.</p>
               <p>
Surrounded by warriors with their bows strung and arrows out of quivers, the American captain and the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">Brulé</name> chief now faced each other. The pointed and angry words they exchanged, passed through a very inadequate interpreter, reveal much about expedition-Indian relations and <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name>
                  
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                   policy. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> told <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo</name> that the expedition "must and would go on." To emphasize that determination, he told the Indians that his men "were not squaws, but warriors." Rising to this rhetorical challenge, <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo</name> declared that "he had warriors too and if we were to go on they would follow us and kill and take the whole of us by degrees." Angered by the threats, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> "felt My Self warm and Spoke in verry positive terms." Those terms included a reminder that the expedition was sent by the Chief of the Seventeen Fires, whose warriors could be summoned in a moment to punish the 
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  . And in a burst of temper, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> boasted that he had "more medicine on board his boat than would kill twenty such nations in one day."<ref target="n0216" n="16"/>
               </p>
               <p>
The verbal sparring might have continued a bit longer except for the arrival of a canoe filled with twelve American soldiers "ready for any event." Most of the Indian warriors retreated and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> was now left alone with the chiefs and a core of <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">Brulé</name> soldiers. <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo</name>, still holding the pirogue's cable, asked if the women and children might see the keelboat and its curiosities. This was an easy request to grant, one that might allow both sides to emerge with honor and prestige intact. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> agreed and <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo</name> dropped the cable. Determined to have the last word, the chief declared that "he was sorry to have us go for his women and children were naked and poor and wished to get some goods, but he did not think we were merchants, nor that we were loaded with goods, but he was sorry to have us leave so soon." As <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> and his men stood by the pirogue, the chiefs walked down the bank for a private council. After waiting some time, Clark approached the chiefs and offered to shake hands. The captain was rebuffed and took that as a signal that discussions were over for the day.</p>
               <p>
As <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> and his party paddled back to the keelboat, <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo</name> made one last demand. He and two of his warriors waded out ten feet from shore and asked to be taken on the keelboat. That night, as the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">Brulé</name> chief and his men slept on a board, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> wrote simply of the day: "Their treatment to me was verry rough and I think justified roughness on my part." <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> neglected to add that their diplomacy was being drawn off course and onto the single point of continued upriver progress. The roughness of the day was hardly what <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> had in mind by "a friendly impression." The initiative was clearly in <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">Brulé</name> hands. All <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> could do was react and hope to escape unscathed. And as an indication of the apprehensive mood felt throughout the expedition, the island named "Good humored" was changed to "Bad humored island as we were in a bad humor."<ref target="n0217" n="17"/>
               </p>
               <p>
The tensions of the previous day were not repeated on Wednesday, September 26. With <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo</name> and his soldiers still on board, the keelboat sailed about five miles upriver. The shore was lined with 
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                   spectators closely watching the progress of the chiefs and the explorers. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> noted that "these people Shew great anxiety." With the failure of the bluff-and-bluster tactics the day before and the expedition now moving upriver, perhaps many 
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                   feared they had lost the battle of wits and wills. Hoping to keep the expedition a bit longer, <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo</name> asked the captains to land near his village so his women and children might visit the boat. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> agreed, perhaps feeling that more time with the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Tetons</name> might produce a change in the diplomatic climate.<ref target="n0218" n="18"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Anchoring the keelboat about one hundred yards from shore, the captains divided their forces. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> accompanied <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo</name> to the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">Brulé</name> village while <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> remained on board. The <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">Brulé</name> chief "appeared disposed to make up and be friendly." The 
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                   village the expedition saw that day must have been an impressive sight. <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, one of the expedition's most careful observers, wrote: "Their lodge [village] is very handsome in a circle and about 100 cabbins in nomber and all white, made of buffalo hides dressed white. One large one in the center, the lodge for the war dances."<ref target="n0219" n="19"/>
                  <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> and <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name> estimated that with about ten persons in each tepee the total village population was eight or nine hundred persons. <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name> thought that two-thirds of the 
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                   in the village were women and children.<ref target="n0220" n="20"/>
               </p>
               <p>
As the morning slipped away and no word came from <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, those on the keelboat "became uneasy for fear of Deception." After about three hours, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> sent <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name> to find <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>. <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name> reported back that <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> was well and that the 
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                   were preparing a feast and dance to honor the Americans. That news was a clear indication of a shift in <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">Brulé</name> tactics. If the whites could not be easily bluffed, they might be flattered and impressed by a show of 
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                   hospitality and military prowess. It was <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo's</name> turn to demonstrate "medicine" as the Americans had done earlier. Throughout the afternoon many <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">Brulé</name> folk made "frequent selicitiations" for the expedition to remain one night longer so that they could "Show their good disposition towards us." Once the captains agreed, they were carried with much ceremony on white buffalo robes to the great council lodge.</p>
               <p>
The scene that night in the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">Brulé</name> village made a lasting impression on many members of the expedition. Fires glowed through translucent tepees as women prepared vast quantities of food for the feast. Slabs of buffalo meat roasted over hot coals. In a circle inside the council lodge were seated some seventy elders and prominent warriors. The Americans were placed next to <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo</name>. Directly in front of the chiefs a six-foot sacred circle had been cleared for holy pipes, pipe stands, and medicine bundles. American and Spanish flags were also displayed in the circle. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> noticed the Spanish ensign but decided to ignore it. There is no evidence to suggest that the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Tetons</name> recognized the sovereignty of either <name type="place" key="Spain">Spain</name> or the United States. The flag may have been used simply for colorful decoration.</p>
               <p>
The diplomacy of the evening began when a <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">Brulé</name> elder stood "and Spoke aproveing what we had done." Because the captains still lacked a reliable 
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                   interpreter, they were uncertain about much of what the old man said. The import of his speech seemed to be that the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">Brulé</name> bands were poor and that the expedition should trade with them, not the upriver tribes. No journalist recorded the American reply, but the explorers probably repeated their usual formula about peace with other tribes and the need for the expedition to press on. The concern for intertribal peace was a cornerstone in <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name> Indian policy and also reflected the needs of the <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> merchants. Because <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had learned earlier in the day that there were many <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Omaha</name> prisoners in the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">Brulé</name> villages, the Americans saw this as an opportunity to promote <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name>-<name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Omaha</name> peace. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> called upon <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo</name> to free the <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Omaha</name> captives. <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo's</name> attempt at peacemaking with the <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Omahas</name> had been disrupted by the <name type="person" key="Partisan">Partisan</name> in 1803, and there was little reason to think the chief would release valuable prisoners just to gratify what must have seemed the whim of a distant chief.</p>
               <p>
The council reached its dramatic climax when <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo</name> "rose with great state" to address the gathering. Again hindered by the lack of a skilled interpreter, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> understood little of what the chief said. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> recorded in his journal that the chief spoke "to the same purpose" as did the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">Brulé</name> elder. It seems clear that <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo</name> was employing his oratorical talents to further the fundamental <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name>
                  
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                   aim—to keep the expedition from opening direct trade with the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> and other Upper <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> village people. His speech finished, <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo</name> took up the most holy of the pipes and pointed it in each of the cardinal directions. Before lighting the pipe, he offered a prayer. Still holding the pipe, the chief took some tender dog meat and made a "Sacrefise to the flag." These solemnities over, the pipe was passed around the circle for all to smoke.</p>
               <p>
Food was next on the evening agenda. The captains and their men were presented with all the 
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                   delicacies, including platters of roast dog, buffalo, pemmican, and prairie turnips.<ref target="n0221" n="21"/> The whole assembly ate and smoked with an air of conviviality until dusk. At nightfall a large fire was made in the center of the village to light the way for musicians and dancers. Ten male musicians entered first. Their instruments were of two kinds: a tambourine-like instrument made by stretching a skin over a willow hoop, and various rattles made by tying deer and antelope hooves on a long stick. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> noted that the rattles made a "gingling noise." As the men began to sing and play, women "highly Deckerated in their way" came forward and began to dance in time to the rhythm. In this war dance the women displayed scalps and other war trophies belonging to their male relatives. That night such a display was surely aimed at impressing <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> with <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">Brulé</name> military might. One young man moved away from the players and toward the spectators. In a high singing voice he recounted the daring exploits of band members in combat with their enemies. His words were picked up by the performers behind him and repeated to add power to the whole spectacle.<ref target="n0222" n="22"/> Throughout the evening members of the expedition rewarded the singers and dancers with tobacco. When one warrior thought he had not received his proper due, he broke one drum, threw two more in the fire, and angrily left the dance line. The two drums were hastily retrieved from the fire and the dancing continued.<ref target="n0223" n="23"/> The entertainment, "done with great Chearfullness," went on until midnight. <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> found the music "delightful," but by midnight <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> were plainly weary. Tactfully, they suggested to the chiefs that everyone must now be tired. Taking the hint, the chiefs ended the festivities and returned with the captains to spend the night on the keelboat.<ref target="n0224" n="24"/>
               </p>
               <p>
As <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> left the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">Brulé</name> village, they were offered young women as bed partners. For the 
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  , the proposal combined hospitality and diplomacy. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> understood the meaning of the offer, writing later that "a curious custom with the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Souix</name> as well as the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">rickeres [Arikaras]</name> is to give handsom squars to those whome they wish to Show some acknowledgments to." Repeating the offer the following night, the Indians made clear to <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> that the woman stood for the whole band. He was urged "to take her and not dispise them." Although fully aware of the symbolic significance of sexual intercourse with the proffered woman, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> dismissed her. That rejection must have bewildered the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">Brulés</name> and surely did not foster the friendship and trust <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> was seeking.<ref target="n0225" n="25"/>
               </p>
               <p>
The late night entertainment was unquestionably a great emotional release from the tensions of earlier days, but <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> reported that at least he did not sleep well. On Thursday morning, September 27, both the captains and the chiefs were up early. <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo</name> and the <name type="person" key="Partisan">Partisan</name> were given, or rather they simply appropriated, the blankets they had slept on. After breakfast <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and the chiefs went on shore "as a verry large part of their nation was comeing in" to see the expedition. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> remained on the keelboat, where he wrote a letter to <name type="person" key="Dorion, Pierre, Sr.">Pierre Dorion</name> and prepared a medal and some certificates for <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> to use later in the day.</p>
               <p>
About midafternoon <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, accompanied by <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo</name>, the <name type="person" key="Partisan">Partisan</name>, and the "considerable man" <name type="person" key="Warchapa">Warchapa</name>, returned to the keelboat. After about half an hour, the captains evidently thought it best that all return to the 
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                   village. When <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> began to suggest they go ashore, the chiefs showed "great reluctiance" to leave. That reluctance finally overcome, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> first visited the <name type="person" key="Partisan">Partisan's</name> lodge. A crowd gathered outside the tepee as the American and the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">Brulé</name> spoke "on various subjects." Continuing his round of courtesy calls, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> stopped at the lodge of a <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">Brulé</name> elder and then moved on to <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo's</name> tepee. From there <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> was conducted to a gathering of <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name> elders. Toward evening <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> arrived in the village and both captains enjoyed a display of the same dancing and ceremony as the previous night. And once again, on the way back to the keelboat, they were offered 
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                   women. As before, the offer was rejected.</p>
               <p>
Tired by a full day of talking and visiting, the American party, along with the <name type="person" key="Partisan">Partisan</name> and one of his soldiers, made their way on the white pirogue back to the keelboat. The evening stillness was shattered when some clumsy steering caused the pirogue to slam broadside against the keelboat's anchor cable. The cable broke and both vessels began to swing dangerously. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> at once shouted at his men to get their oars in order to prevent further damage to either vessel. His shouting and the general bustle of men moving quickly in the darkness frightened the 
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  . An alarm ran through the village as <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo</name> spread the word that an <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Omaha</name> attack was at hand. Within ten minutes the chief and two hundred armed men prepared for combat were on the river bank. After about half an hour, most of the warriors made their way back to the village. However, some sixty remained on watch throughout the night.</p>
               <p>
Both <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> believed that the sudden appearance of so many warriors was a "signal of their intentions (which was to Stop our proceeding on our journey and if Possible rob us.)"<ref target="n0226" n="26"/> This harsh view of <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">Brulé</name> motives was not shared by others in the expedition. Sergeants <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> and <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name> and <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Private Whitehouse</name> emphasized both the fear of <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Omaha</name> attack and the genuine desire of the 
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                   to help the endangered vessels.<ref target="n0227" n="27"/> In light of <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">Brulé</name> activities before <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> coming, <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo's</name> fear of <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Omaha</name> attack was well grounded. In early September, some two weeks before the expedition arrived, a <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">Brulé</name> war party had raided an <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Omaha</name> village, burning forty lodges and killing more than seventy-five of the tribe. There were now some forty-eight <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Omaha</name> prisoners in the two <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">Brulé</name> villages along the <name type="place" key="Bad (Teton) River (S. Dak.)">Bad River</name>.<ref target="n0228" n="28"/> In the cycle of raid and reprisal, <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo</name> had every reason to think the confusion in the night was due to something more than a broken cable and a missing anchor.</p>
               <p>
But the Americans also had reason to worry that night. Although <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> stressed the sudden arrival of 
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                   warriors as cause for alarm, it was probably intelligence brought to the captains by <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Pierre Cruzatte</name> that put the expedition on its guard throughout the night. On Wednesday, September 26, <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Cruzatte</name> had been given some trade goods as presents for the <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Omaha</name> prisoners. Now, in return, the prisoners told the interpreter that <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> "were to be stoped." The value of that information gathered from Indians who saw the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name>
                  
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                   as enemies is now hard to judge. Certainly it fit the overall evaluation of 
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                   behavior held by the expedition. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> tense lines "we Shew as little signs of a Knowledge of their intentions as possible, all prepared on board for any thing which might happen, we kept a Strong guard all night in the boat, no Sleep" betray both fear of 
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                   military power and an exaggerated readiness to fight.<ref target="n0229" n="29"/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> and their men had now been with the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name>
                  
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                   for three days. Those were days filled with isolated moments of trouble and misunderstanding and long periods of friendly visiting and good company. The expedition gathered some important ethnographic data, tried to make its point about American sovereignty, and even practiced, albeit with dubious success, some intertribal peace-making. But on the crucial issue of trade—safe passage up the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> for fur traders and <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> merchants—there had been little or no progress. The expedition planned to spend the rest of the year at the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> villages; with winter coming, it was now time to move on. That determination to press upriver collided with the equal determination of the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">Brulé</name> chiefs both to advance their own prestige and to defend <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name>
                  
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                   economic interests. In the eyes of men like <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo</name> and the <name type="person" key="Partisan">Partisan</name>, the continued presence of the American expedition posed something of a dilemma and an embarrassment. Both men needed to act forcefully to vindicate personal claims to power. <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name> bands had come to expect their headmen to obtain gifts from river traders. A chief who could not deliver was bound to have his authority openly questioned. At the same time, faced with a well-armed party under strong leadership, the chiefs feared pressing their demands too far. If there was a bloody incident and Indian casualties were high, the chiefs would surely lose influence. Pressure tactics that proved effective in intimidating poorly armed traders who needed 
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                   cooperation would not work against a military expedition whose goals went far beyond the ledger book. It was against this background of cross purposes, face saving, and <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> determination to leave the <name type="place" key="James (Jacque) River (S. Dak.)">Bad River</name> that the last day of the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name>
                  
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                   confrontation was played out.</p>
               <p>
Much of Friday morning was spent in a fruitless search for the keelboat anchor. By midmorning, when the work parties took breakfast, nearly all the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">Brulés</name> lined the river bank. As the captains were about to order the sail hoisted, <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo</name> and the other chiefs appeared. Once on board, the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">Brulé</name> leaders began their now-familiar demand that the expedition remain with them. <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> noted that the warriors on the bank were well armed with guns, spears, "a kind of cutlashes," and bows with metal-tipped arrows.<ref target="n0230" n="30"/> Anxious to leave, the crew made preparations to cast off the bowline. At that moment several of the <name type="person" key="Partisan">Partisan's</name> warriors took hold of the cable. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, who was inside the cabin with <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo</name>, saw what happened and complained to the chief. Evidently fearing that the seizure of the cable spelled the beginning of very serious trouble, and perhaps resenting the role of the <name type="person" key="Partisan">Partisan</name> in the affair, the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">Brulé</name> chief hurried forward to assure <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> that the warriors simply wanted tobacco. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, weary of the constant demands for gifts, refused to give them anything. He ordered all hands ready for departure, had the sail hoisted, and detailed one man to untie the bow cable.</p>
               <p>
At this critical moment several things happened at once. The bow cable, first untied by a crewman, was again fastened by several of the <name type="person" key="Partisan">Partisan's</name> warriors. At the same time, the <name type="person" key="Partisan">Partisan</name> himself demanded a flag and some tobacco. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> angrily ordered all Indians off the boat while <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> threw a carrot of tobacco on the bank. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> then took the firing taper for the port swivel gun in his hand and "spoke so as to touch his [<name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo's</name>] pride." <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> did not record the sarcasm in his journal but years later told <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Nicholas Biddle</name>, "I threw him tobacco saying to the chief you have told us you are a great man—have influence—take this tobacco and shew us your influence by taking the rope from your men and letting go without coming to hostilities."<ref target="n0231" n="31"/>
                  <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> also had a "rangleing" exchange with the <name type="person" key="Partisan">Partisan</name>. Violence seemed seconds away. Warriors hurried women and children from the bank. But it was <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo</name> who finally calmed the situation. He promised the expedition safe conduct if tobacco, always a ceremonial tribute, was given to the warriors holding the cable. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> balked at the demand, saying that they "did not mean to be trifled with." Seeing the captains hesitate, <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo</name> sarcastically observed that "he was mad too, to see us stand so much for one carrot of tobacco." <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> tossed the tobacco to the Indians and <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo</name> jerked the cable from their hands. At that moment the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name> confrontation was over.<ref target="n0232" n="32"/>
               </p>
               <p>
In those moments when <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> was ready to fire, when the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">Brulé</name> warriors had bows strung, and when the <name type="person" key="Partisan">Partisan</name> was shouting defiance, it was <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo</name> who showed both firmness and the ability to compromise. Perhaps by September 28 the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">Brulé</name> chief realized that nothing further could be gained by delaying <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>. There would be other parties from <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>, less well armed, with more goods, and easier to intimidate. Allowing one boat to pass was hardly a defeat. <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo</name> had obtained ceremonial tribute from the Americans and had lost nothing in the eyes of his own people. But at the beginning of the final day of the confrontation, the political ambitions of the <name type="person" key="Partisan">Partisan</name> were as yet unfulfilled. His contest for influence with <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo</name> still gave him reason to harrass the Americans. The <name type="person" key="Partisan">Partisan</name>, described by <name type="person" key="Buffalo Medicine (Tar-ton-gar-wa-ker)">Buffalo Medicine's</name> son as a "Double Spoken man," seized the initiative that day as one more means to gain precedence over <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo</name>.<ref target="n0233" n="33"/> The last minutes of the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name> encounter were less a conflict between Indians and American explorers and more a tussle between rival band headmen. In the end it was <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo</name> who engineered a compromise allowing each party to escape with some dignity intact and without bloodshed.</p>
               <p>
If <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo</name> is credited with working to avoid violence, then <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> also deserve a share of the glory. They took seriously their instructions from <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> to deal with Indians "in a most friendly and conciliatory manner which their own conduct will admit."<ref target="n0234" n="34"/> The captains also understood the flexibility they had as explorers. They could, with enough determination and good fortune, move up the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>. Unlike the <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> traders, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> did not have to stay with the 
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  , trade with them, and depend on their cooperation. Subsequent <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> parties, from <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Nathaniel Pryor's</name>
                  <name type="person" key="White Man (Sheheke)">Sheheke</name> expedition to <name type="person" key="Hunt, Wilson Price">Wilson Price Hunt's</name> Astorians, would find the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name>
                  
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                   as intransigent as ever.</p>
               <p>
The memory of the 
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                   September was still fresh when <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, writing from <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name> during the winter of 1804–1805, described the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Tetons</name> as "the vilest miscreants of the savage race, and must ever remain the pirates of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>."<ref target="n0235" n="35"/>
                  <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> harsh words masked a harsher reality. The 
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                   talks had failed. The 
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                   were no closer to becoming part of the <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> trade network. No delegation of <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">Brulé</name> dignitaries was prepared to visit the president. <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name> call for <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> to make a "friendly impression" on <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo's</name> folk was lost in a welter of conflicting band and personal quarrels. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> admitted as much when he informed <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> that <name type="person" key="Warfington, Richard">Corporal Richard Warfington's</name> return party bound for <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>, the spring of 1805 was sure to encounter heavy 
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                   fire. 
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                   hostility might endanger not only <name type="person" key="Warfington, Richard">Warfington's</name> men but the keelboat loaded with the expedition's journals, maps, and botanical specimens. The hazard was real enough that <name type="person" key="Warfington, Richard">Warfington's</name> men "pledged themselves to us that they will not yeald while there is a man of them living."<ref target="n0236" n="36"/> This was hardly the sort of diplomatic conclusion <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> sought. At best <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> could say their efforts were inconclusive; at worst they may have exacerbated 
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  -American relations.</p>
               <p>
Nearly 150 years later, Bernard DeVoto voiced what has become historical wisdom about the encounter. DeVoto declared that <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> defeated the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Tetons</name>, forced them to back down, and made them "women" in the eyes of their neighbors. Heaping abuse on the 
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  , he described <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">Brulé</name> soldiers as "bully boys" engaged in "storm trooper tactics." DeVoto maintained that after being defeated by the no-nonsense firmness of the Americans, the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Tetons</name> "were just beggars again."<ref target="n0237" n="37"/> But it was not the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name>
                  
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                   who were defeated. Rather, it was American diplomacy that had been handed a stinging rebuff. As <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> recognized in their 1806 letter to the North West Company trader <name type="person" key="Heney, Hugh">Hugh Heney</name>, the 
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                   would always be a barrier to trade on the Upper <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> "until some effectual measures be taken to render them pacific."<ref target="n0238" n="38"/> They had surely not been rendered "pacific" by three days of playing cat and mouse with <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>. In the next two decades, as English traders retreated from the prairies and plains and 
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                   population grew, the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name> bands did indeed turn to American merchants. But until that happened, <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name> assessment that the United States was "miserably weak" proved a painfully accurate appraisal of northern plains realities. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had done little to transform those political and economic realities.
</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="section">
            <head rend="center">Abbreviations</head>
            <p>
B A E       Bureau of American Ethnology</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">Field Notes.</hi>        Osgood, Ernest, S., ed. <hi rend="italic">The Field Notes of <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain William Clark</name>, 1803–1805.</hi> New Haven: Yale University Press, 1964.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal.</hi>        <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass, Patrick</name>. <hi rend="italic">A Journal of the Voyages and Travels of a Corps of Discovery.</hi> Edited by <name type="person" key="McKeehan, David">David McKeehan</name>. 1807. Reprint, with preface by Earle R. Forrest. Minneapolis: Ross and Haines, 1958.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal.</hi>        Quaife, Milo M., ed. <hi rend="italic">The Journals of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Meriwether Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Sergeant John Ordway</name>.</hi> Madison: Historical Society of Wisconsin, 1916.</p>
            <p>
Thw.       Thwaites, Reuben G., ed. <hi rend="italic">The Original Journals of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition.</hi> 8 vols. New York: Dodd, Mead &amp; Co., 1904–1905.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal.</hi>        "The Journal of <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Private Joseph Whitehouse</name>." In Thw. 7:29–190.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="notes" type="notes">
            <head rend="center">Notes</head>
            <note xml:id="n0201" n="1">The <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">Brulé</name> territory at the time of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> was bounded by the <name type="place" key="North Platte River">North Platte River</name> on the south and somewhat beyond the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri River</name> on the east. The northern boundary was between the <name type="place" key="Bad (Teton) River (S. Dak.)">Bad</name> and <name type="place" key="Cheyenne River">Cheyenne</name> rivers. The <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">Brulés</name> hunted as far west as the <name type="place" key="Black Hills">Black Hills</name>. John C. Ewers, <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name> Dakota Ethnology and History</hi> (Berkeley, Calif.: Western Museum Laboratories, United States Department of the Interior, 1938), p. 9, map 4; Robin W. Wells, <hi rend="italic">Tribal Distribution Map Series, North America</hi> (Toledo: University of Toledo Cartographic Services, n.d.), map for 1760–1810.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0202" n="2">
               <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> pp. 394–95; Thw. 5:365–67.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0203" n="3">
               <name type="person" key="Truteau, Jean Baptiste">Jean Baptiste Truteau</name>, "Journal on the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri River</name>, 1794–1795," in Nasatir, ed., <hi rend="italic">Before <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>,</hi> 1:269; Thw. 1:29. Something of the climate of opinion in <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> concerning the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name> can be seen in: <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> to <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, December 28, 1803, Jackson, ed., <hi rend="italic">Letters,</hi> 1:154–55; <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> to <name type="person" key="Chouteau, Auguste">Auguste Chouteau</name>, January 4, 1804, ibid. 1:161–62; <hi rend="italic">Field Notes,</hi> p. 16.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0204" n="4">Thw. 1:162.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0205" n="5">
               <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> p. 50; <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> pp. 136–37; Thw. 1:162–63; <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> pp. 61–62.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0206" n="6">
               <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, November 16, 1803, Jackson, ed., <hi rend="italic">Letters,</hi> 1:138–39.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0207" n="7">
               <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> to <name type="person" key="Smith, Robert">Robert Smith</name>, July 13, 1804, <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> Papers, Library of Congress; <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, January 22, 1804, ibid. 1:166.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0208" n="8">Annie H. Abel, ed., <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="person" key="Tabeau, Pierre-Antoine">Tabeau's</name> Narrative of <name type="person" key="Loisel, Régis">Loisel's</name> Expedition to the Upper <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>
               </hi> (Norman: University of Oklahoma Press, 1939), pp. 121–23, 131; John C. Ewers, "The Indian Trade of the Upper <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> before <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>," Missouri Historical Society <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi> 10 (1954):429–46; Donald Jackson, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Journals of <name type="person" key="Pike, Zebulon Montgomery">Zebulon Montgomery Pike</name> with Letters and Related Documents,</hi> 2 vols. (Norman: University of Oklahoma Press, 1966), 1:213–15, 221; Thw. 1:189, 6:45, 98; <name type="person" key="Truteau, Jean Baptiste">Trutueau</name>, "Journal," 1:301–2, 310; W. Raymond Wood, "Contrastive Features of Native North American Trade Systems," University of Oregon Anthropological Papers, No. 4 (Eugene, 1972), pp. 153–69. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark's</name> 1810 map contains notations about the location and function of the Dakota Rendezvous. See Wheat, <hi rend="italic">Mapping the Trans<name type="place" key="Mississippi River">mississippi</name> West,</hi> 1: map 291. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> incisive comments, made after the expedition, on the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> trade system are in Thw. 6:45–46.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0209" n="9">Abel, ed., <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="person" key="Tabeau, Pierre-Antoine">Tabeau's</name> Narrative,</hi> pp. 108–9, 111–13. The <name type="person" key="Partisan">Partisan</name> may have been present at an Indian council held by <name type="person" key="Pike, Zebulon Montgomery">Zebulon Pike</name> at the confluence of the <name type="place" key="Minnesota River (St. Peters)">Minnesota</name> and <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name> rivers on September 23, 1805. He was surely at a conference arranged by <name type="person" key="Lisa, Manuel">Manuel Lisa</name> at <name type="place" key="Prairie du Chien">Prairie du Chien</name> in July 1815. See Jackson, ed., <hi rend="italic">Journals of <name type="person" key="Pike, Zebulon Montgomery">Zebulon Pike</name>,</hi> 1:37–38; Richard E. Oglesby, <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="person" key="Lisa, Manuel">Manuel Lisa</name> and the Opening of the Missouri Fur Trade</hi> (Norman: University of Oklahoma Press, 1963), p. 157.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0210" n="10">Richard White, "The Winning of the West: The Expansion of the Western <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name> in the Eighteenth and Nineteenth Centuries," <hi rend="italic">Journal of American History</hi> 65 (1978): 326.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0211" n="11">Thw. 1:164.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0212" n="12">Ibid. 1:129–33.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0213" n="13">Ibid. 1:112–14, 129–33.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0214" n="14">For a similar demand see "Report of Clamorgan and Reihle, <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>, July 8, 1795," Nasatir, ed., <hi rend="italic">Before <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>,</hi> 1:340.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0215" n="15">Thw. 1:113.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0216" n="16">This arresting claim is not in <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> journal or in his field notes, but both <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> p. 51, and <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> p. 63, record it.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0217" n="17">
               <hi rend="italic">Field Notes,</hi> p. 148; <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> pp. 138–39; Thw. 1:164–65.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0218" n="18">Elliott Coues (<hi rend="italic">History of the Expedition under the Command of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>,</hi> 4 vols. in 3 [1893; reprint, New York: Dover Publications, 1964], 1:137) notes that many of the Indians present on September 26 were <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Oglala">Okandanda or Oglala</name>
               <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton Sioux</name>. This is possible but not recorded in any of the expedition's journals. The Elliott Coues edition of <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Nicholas Biddle's</name> 1814 <hi rend="italic">History of the Expedition under the Command of Captains <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>
               </hi> is hereafter cited as <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>-Coues, <hi rend="italic">History.</hi>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="n0219" n="19">Ewers, <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton Dakota</name>,</hi> pp. 26–28; <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> pp. 139, 141.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0220" n="20">
               <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> pp. 51–52; <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> pp. 139–40.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0221" n="21">Paul R. Cutright, <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>: Pioneering Naturalists</hi> (Urbana: University of Illinois Press, 1969), p. 91; Ewers, <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton Dakota</name>,</hi> pp. 16–18.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0222" n="22">George Catlin, <hi rend="italic">Letters and Notes on the Manners, Customs, and Conditions of the North American Indians,</hi> 2 vols. (1844; reprint, New York: Dover Publications, 1973), 1:245–46, plate 104; Frances Densmore, <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton Sioux</name> Music,</hi> Smithsonian Institution, BAE Bulletin no. 61 (Washington, D.C., 1918), pp. 48–51, plates 38, 39, 46; Ewers, <hi rend="italic">Teton Dakota,</hi> p. 65.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0223" n="23">
               <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> p. 140.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0224" n="24">Thw. 1:166–69; <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> pp. 63–64.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0225" n="25">
               <hi rend="italic">Field Notes,</hi> pp. 149–50; Thw. 1:189.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0226" n="26">Ibid. 1:169–70.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0227" n="27">
               <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> pp. 52–54; <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> pp. 141–42; <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> p. 64.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0228" n="28">Thw. 1:168.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0229" n="29">Ibid. 1:169–70.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0230" n="30">James A. Hanson, <hi rend="italic">Metal Weapons, Tools, and Ornaments of the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton Dakota Indians</name>
               </hi> (Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1975), pp. 14–17, 26, 45.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0231" n="31">"<name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name> Notes," Jackson, ed., <hi rend="italic">Letters,</hi> 2:518.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0232" n="32">
               <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> p. 54; <hi rend="italic">Field Notes,</hi> p. 151; <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> pp. 142–43; Thw. 1:170–71; <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> p. 65.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0233" n="33">Thw. 1:171.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0234" n="34">
               <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, "Instructions to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>," 1:64.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0235" n="35">Thw. 6:98.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0236" n="36">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> to <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, April 7, 1805, Jackson, ed., <hi rend="italic">Letters,</hi> 1:233.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0237" n="37">Bernard De Voto, <hi rend="italic">The Course of Empire</hi> (Boston: Houghton Mifflin Co., 1952), pp. 445, 448.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0238" n="38">
               <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> to <name type="person" key="Heney, Hugh">Hugh Heney</name>, July 20, 1806, Jackson, ed., <hi rend="italic">Letters,</hi> 1:310. This is <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> copy of a letter that <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> drafted in early July 1806.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.sup.ronda.01.01" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.sup.ronda.01.00" type="contents"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.sup.ronda.01.03" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
