<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.sup.lavender.01.02">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Way to the Western Sea</title>
            <title type="sub">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>across the Continent</title>
            <title type="sub" level="a">Chapter 2</title>
            <author>David Lavender</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2005</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic
        Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Way to the Western Sea</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">Chapter 2</title>
               <author>David Lavender</author>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>2001</date>
               <idno type="ISBN">0-8032-8003-3</idno>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Supplements</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Texts</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-11-09</date>
            <date>2005-04-20</date>
            <name>Becky Potter</name>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Split into chapters Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-04-12</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="two" type="chapter">
            <head rend="center">TWO. Preparing for the Future</head>
            <div type="section">
               <p>Fortunately 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name>was able to put
          together the expedition as 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>then visualized it, almost
          free from the bedevilments of urgency. As the future would show, he could not handle
          certain harassments. But the breaking point did not come during the Napoleonic crisis.
          First, military pressure in the 
          <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name>Valley dwindled. The
          initial contingent of French troops in 
          <name type="place" key="Santo Domingo">Santo Domingo</name>was scythed down by yellow
          fever and frenzied black resistance. Because of the disaster, the fleet 
          <name type="person" key="Bonaparte, Napoleon">Napoleon</name>had designed for occupying 
          <name type="place" key="New Orleans, La.">New Orleans</name>was shifted to 
          <name type="place" key="Santo Domingo">Santo Domingo</name>. The French, it seemed
          clear, were not likely to move into the 
          <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name>in the near future. That
          being true, the British might not be tempted to counterattack out of 
          <name type="place" key="Canada">Canada</name>. And so the need for immediate
          reconnaissance faded.</p>
               <p>Another benison was the cooling off of the Federalists in Congress. Hoping to
          undercut 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>in his political stronghold
          beyond the 
          <name type="place" key="Appalachian Mountains">Appalachians</name>, the minority party
          scorned as too little and too late the administration's handling of the deposit affair
          at 
          <name type="place" key="New Orleans, La.">New Orleans</name>. They'd end the matter once
          and for all, they boasted. With 
          <name type="person" key="Ross, James">Senator Ross</name>of 
          <name type="place" key="Pennsylvania">Pennsylvania</name>leading the charge, they
          introduced resolutions calling for the raising of five million dollars and fifty
          thousand militiamen for seizing 
          <name type="place" key="New Orleans, La.">New Orleans</name>from 
          <name type="place" key="Spain">Spain</name>before the transfer to 
          <name type="place" key="France">France</name>could be completed.</p>
               <p>Appalled, 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name>Republicans retorted that
          so thoughtless an action would precipitate a general war. Besides, the proposal was
          doubly illegal. It usurped the president's prerogative to handle foreign affairs, and it
          ignored laws that stated militia could not be sent outside the nation. After
          considerable hot rhetoric, the resolutions were voted down. At snail's pace Congress
          returned to discussing the acts 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>had recommended in his
          secret message of January 18—acts for extending both the Indian trading houses and the
          external commerce of the United States. The measures were passed late in February.
          <ref target="n0201" n="1"/>
               </p>
               <p>Officially this left 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name>preparing to take ten
          or twelve chosen men westward to test the possibility of drawing furs out of 
          <name type="place" key="Canada">Canada</name>into the United States. There was no
          tearing hurry about it—not now that military needs had relaxed—but there was a marvelous
          increase in kinetics. The moment Congress agreed to send a cohesive body of American
          troops, however small, into the ambiguously held lands beyond the 
          <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name>, possibilities multiplied.
          An American West: fantasy's new Garden of the Hesperides, where sturdy yeomen would hold
          true to 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name>vision of democracy.
          Scientific inquiry: the range of the wonders that might be found would set the American
          Philosophical Society on fire. Commerce: not only in the interior of the continent, but
          also with busy ports at the far end of some Western river—the fabled passage to 
          <name type="place" key="India">India</name>, dreamed of ever since the unexpected land
          barriers of the New World had frustrated 
          <name type="person" key="Columbia, Christopher">Columbus</name>. All this 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>had contemplated for years
          without making an overt move. Now the time had arrived. 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, the expeditor, must have
          shared the excitement of these almost boundless expectations.</p>
               <p>Boundless, but never impulsive, never ill-considered. Even as his ideas grew, 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>continued speaking in terms
          of fewer than a dozen explorers. As late as July 2, 1803, when 
          <name type="person" key="Dearborn, Henry">Henry Dearborn</name>, secretary of war,
          formally authorized the project, he specifically limited the size of the party, officers
          included, to twelve.
          <ref target="n0202" n="2"/>It was 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>who fudged upward in the memo of
          requirements he wrote out for himself—fifteen rifles, fifteen knapsacks, fifteen
          overcoats, and (multiples of fifteen) thirty shirts, thirty pairs of socks, and so on.
          <ref target="n0203" n="3"/>
               </p>
               <p>The fifteen men would have to be, by his definition, unmarried, robust, persevering,
          and dependable. Some would have to be hunters, for the party would live almost entirely
          off the land. Carpenters, ironworkers, and gunsmiths would be welcome, if such talents
          were available. They might not be. The nation's shrunken army paid its private soldiers
          five dollars a month, plus another five dollars as a clothing allowance. Such rates did
          not appeal to skilled men.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>wrote of his requirements to the
          commanding officers of 
          <name type="place" key="Fort Massac (Ill.)">Fort Massac</name>on the 
          <name type="place" key="Ohio River">Ohio</name>, 
          <name type="place" key="Fort Kaskaskia (Ill.)">Fort Kaskaskia</name>on the 
          <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name>, and 
          <name type="place" key="South West Point, Tenn.">South West Point</name>, near 
          <name type="place" key="Nashville, Tenn.">Nashville</name>, 
          <name type="place" key="Tennessee">Tennessee</name>. (For some unstated reason he
          thought 
          <name type="place" key="South West Point, Tenn.">South West Point</name>would turn out
          to be the most fruitful source.)
          <ref target="n0204" n="4"/>To tempt good men into his special service he authorized his
          correspondents to offer double pay fortified by a promise that those who made the trip
          could leave the army as soon as the journey was over, though the normal enlistment
          period was five years. On being mustered out, each would also receive several hundred
          acres of Western land. If these inducements failed to produce qualified applicants
          within the army itself, the officers could recruit civilians, offering each the standard
          twelve-dollar bonus the army paid men who joined the ranks. Except possibly for
          interpreters, no one could stay a civilian and go along. This was a military
          undertaking, a hangover perhaps of the original nature of the project. Besides, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name>, professional
          soldier, believed that success could be guaranteed best by men working under tight army
          discipline. It was the beginning of a long series of military explorations launched by
          the United States government.</p>
               <p>Finally, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>insisted on the right to
          interview and turn down the volunteers who had been conditionally signed on by the other
          officers. These choices were vital, and ultimate decisions had to be his.</p>
               <p>Having set the size of the party, he made out, over and over again, shopping lists
          for equipment. Hunting shirts, kettles and cutlery, powder, axes, adzes, chisels,
          "muscato curtains" (mosquito netting). There had to be barrels and boxes for storage,
          each with its waterproof covering, and forty yards of oiled linen cut in such a way that
          it could be used for either tents, coverings for canoes, or sails for a keelboat.</p>
               <p>Medicinal supplies were another essential. There was no thought of taking a doctor
          along. Army regulations allowed only one "surgeon" to each forty-five men. Though the
          president might have bent the rule, he chose not to. He had lost several of his family,
          including his wife, to diseases that the doctors had seemed, in his mind, to aggravate
          rather than cure. Nature, he wrote his friend Caspar Wistar, was the best physician. Men
          should not experiment "on a machine so complicated and unknown as the human body and a
          subject so sacred as human life."
          <ref target="n0205" n="5"/>He would make an appointment for 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>to consult with 
          <name type="person" key="Rush, Benjamin">Dr. Benjamin Rush</name>of 
          <name type="place" key="Philadelphia, Pa.">Philadelphia</name>about health rules, but
          once the group was in the field 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether</name>and his ensign, if any,
          would have to diagnose, prescribe, and administer on their own.</p>
               <p>Indian presents clearly would consume more of his initial funds than any other class
          of supplies. The gifts were not bribes, but unconditional statements, in the Indians'
          minds, of goodwill and friendship.
          <ref target="n0206" n="6"/>So down went itemized notations about blue beads and brass
          buttons, favored as ornaments by the natives; kettles, knives, awls, rings, and burning
          (magnifying) glasses; tobacco, cloth, and sewing needles; ear trinkets, vermilion, and
          strips of copper and sheets of tin that could be converted into adornments. He also
          planned to take along three hand-turned mills for grinding corn, a first step in the
          civilizing process. Plus several peace and friendship medals of varying sizes and
          designs, to be passed out to deserving chiefs as tokens of esteem from 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">President Jefferson</name>. The more
          powerful the chief, the bigger the medal.</p>
               <p>For transporting this material he planned on obtaining, at 
          <name type="place" key="South West Point, Tenn.">South West Point</name>, a keelboat
          about sixty feet long, with an eight-ton burden. This would be backed up by a forty-foot
          "canoe." (He meant pirogue—canoe was a misnomer he used consistently. Pirogues were hewn
          from huge tree trunks; they were far heavier and harder to maneuver than the Indians'
          birchbark canoes or the nimble craft used by today's recreationists.)</p>
               <p>He would float his pirogue and keelboat, loaded with soldiers and supplies, down the 
          <name type="place" key="Cumberland River">Cumberland River</name>to the 
          <name type="place" key="Ohio River">Ohio</name>, continue to the 
          <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name>, and ascend that stream to
          the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, long regarded as the gateway to
          the West.
          <ref target="n0207" n="7"/>
               </p>
               <p>After his keelboat and pirogue had ascended the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>as far as possible, then what?
          Some theoretical geographers believed that only a short portage—perhaps as little as
          half a mile—separated the headwaters of the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>from those of the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>. If that proved true, the
          pirogue (though not the big keelboat) could be carried and skidded across the divide.
          The pirogue alone, however, might not be enough for moving the men and supplies to the 
          <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>. If trees were available along the
          portage, additional dugouts could be constructed wherever needed. If . . . but he had
          read somewhere that many miles of treeless plains bordered the upper 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>. As a precaution he therefore
          lovingly designed an iron boat frame that could be disassembled into sections and
          carried in the keelboat until needed. The pieces could then be portaged, along with the
          pirogue, to the nearest west-flowing stream and there sheathed with either bark or
          buffalo hide, according to availability. If the portage proved unexpectedly long, then
          the iron boat alone would have to suffice for the last leg of the journey.</p>
               <p>So far he had contemplated, in the main, physical equipment only. But he also had to
          acquire skills so that during the trip he could gather the kind of scientific knowledge 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>wanted. As an example, let
          us use a book to which the president and his secretary gave concentrated attention: 
          <name type="person" key="Mackenzie, Alexander">Alexander Mackenzie's</name>
                  <hi rend="italic">Voyages from 
          <name type="place" key="Montreal">Montreal</name>. . . through the continent of North
          America to the frozen and 
          <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific Oceans</name>in the years 1789 and 1793 .
          . .</hi>The two volumes were not published until 1801. Another edition, slightly
          revised, appeared in 
          <name type="place" key="Philadelphia, Pa.">Philadelphia</name>in 1802. Quite possibly
          neither version would have been written if 
          <name type="person" key="Mackenzie, Alexander">Mackenzie</name>had not felt the need of
          a powerful propaganda weapon for forcing the British government into revising the
          nation's fur trade. The point was not lost on 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, but our consideration of
          the book's ax grinding needs to wait until after we look at some of 
          <name type="person" key="Mackenzie, Alexander">Mackenzie's</name>intellectual
          successes—and failures—in fields that deeply concerned the American president.</p>
               <p>The Scottish-born trader's primary goal was commercial. (So, ostensibly, was 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>.) Hauling supplies by
          birchbark canoe from 
          <name type="place" key="Montreal">Montreal</name>to the foot of the Canadian 
          <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rockies</name>was costly and laborious. Great
          savings would result if 
          <name type="person" key="Mackenzie, Alexander">Mackenzie</name>could find a navigable
          river opening into the 
          <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>, one that could be used for
          importing trade goods and exporting fur. He made his start, in 1789, from 
          <name type="place" key="Fort Chipewayan">Fort Chipewayan</name>, built near the chill
          west end of 
          <name type="place" key="Lake Athabasca">Lake Athabasca</name>primarily for this purpose.
          Unhappily for himself, he picked the wrong river to probe—today it bears his name, the 
          <name type="person" key="Mackenzie, Alexander">Mackenzie</name>—and he ended, completely
          dismayed, among ice floes in the 
          <name type="place" key="Arctic Ocean">Arctic Ocean</name>. Though he carried a sextant
          with him, he was not adept at determining latitude with it, and he could not measure
          longitude at all. Consequently he returned to 
          <name type="place" key="Fort Chipewayan">Fort Chipewayan</name>with only the haziest
          ideas of where he had been, scientifically speaking. He had learned, however, that
          between 
          <name type="place" key="Athabasca">Lake Athabasca</name>and the 
          <name type="place" key="Arctic Ocean">Arctic Ocean</name>there was no feasible outlet to
          the 
          <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>.</p>
               <p>To remedy his navigational deficiencies he put his trade in order and then spent the
          winter of 1791–92 in 
          <name type="place" key="London">London</name>studying surveying. He returned to 
          <name type="place" key="Fort Chipewayan">Fort Chipewayan</name>during the spring and
          summer of 1792 (as 
          <name type="person" key="Michaux, André">Andre Michaux</name>may well have learned while
          in 
          <name type="place" key="Montreal">Montreal</name>that same season). As soon as the ice
          broke in 1793, he would try again, this time along a more southerly river, the 
          <name type="place" key="Peace River">Peace</name>.</p>
               <p>His crew was about the same size as the one 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>later proposed—six French
          voyageurs, two Indians, and an able second-in-command, 
          <name type="person" key="Mackay, Alexander">Alexander Mackay</name>. (
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>may well have picked up his
          notions about size from 
          <name type="person" key="Mackenzie, Alexander">Mackenzie's</name>account.) Crowded with
          their supplies in a twenty-five-foot birchbark canoe, the group fought their way up the
          howling 
          <name type="place" key="Peace River">Peace</name>, crossed a high, narrow divide, and
          descended to a mighty river the local Indians called 
          <name type="place" key="Fraser (Tacoutche-Tesse) River">Tacoutche Tesse</name>. It ran
          wildly south. Today we know it as the 
          <name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">Fraser</name>. But when 
          <name type="person" key="Mackenzie, Alexander">Mackenzie</name>learned, a little later,
          that an American seaman named 
          <name type="person" key="Gray, Robert">Robert Gray</name>had sailed his ship 
          <hi rend="italic">Columbia</hi>, on May 11, 1792, into a regal stream farther south, 
          <name type="person" key="Mackenzie, Alexander">Mackenzie</name>thought he had stumbled
          onto a higher reach of the same river, named 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>after 
          <name type="person" key="Gray, Robert">Gray's</name>ship.</p>
               <p>Warned by the Indians that he could not negotiate the crushing rapids of the 
          <name type="place" key="Fraser (Tacoutche-Tesse) River">Tacoutche Tesse's</name>lower
          gorge in a canoe, 
          <name type="person" key="Mackenzie, Alexander">Mackenzie</name>cached the fragile craft
          for use on his return journey and led his men west, walking at first and then using an
          Indian canoe. When at last they reached salt water—not the open sea but a long sound—he
          melted some animal fat he had with him and stirred in a generous pinch of the kind of
          vermilion Indians used for painting their faces and the parts in their hair. With this
          red mixture he inscribed on a cliff face, "in large characters, '
          <name type="person" key="Mackenzie, Alexander">Alexander Mackenzie</name>, from 
          <name type="place" key="Canada">Canada</name>, by land, the twenty-second of July, one
          thousand seven hundred and ninety three,' " a statement 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>must have read with envy.</p>
               <p>More to the point, 
          <name type="person" key="Mackenzie, Alexander">Mackenzie</name>used his astronomical
          instruments and skills to find and report, in the 
          <hi rend="italic">Voyages</hi>, the approximate location of his vermilion boast. Before
          that, he had fixed the latitude and longitude of 
          <name type="place" key="Montreal">Montreal</name>; of 
          <name type="place" key="Fort William (N. Dak.)">Fort William</name>on the northwest
          shore of 
          <name type="place" key="Lake Superior">Lake Superior</name>, where his boisterous fellow
          traders of the North West Company held their annual rendezvous; of 
          <name type="place" key="Fort Chipewayan">Fort Chipewayan</name>; and of the narrow
          divide—a mere 817 paces, or about half a mile—that separated the watershed of the 
          <name type="place" key="Peace River">Peace</name>from that of the 
          <name type="person" key="Fraser (Tacoutche-Tesse) River">Tacoutche Tesse</name>(the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>, as he believed). After defining
          those points and hundreds in between he had been able to draw, and publish in the 
          <hi rend="italic">Voyages</hi>, a map that anyone who wished to cross the continent by
          canoe that far north could follow.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>wanted 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>to produce an equally reliable
          map of a more southerly and, the president hoped, a far less difficult crossing to the 
          <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>, for by that time the western sea
          had ceased being a target of opportunity and was emerging as the expedition's primary
          goal. This meant training the young man, as 
          <name type="person" key="Mackenzie, Alexander">Mackenzie</name>had been trained, in the
          arts of celestial observation. 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>could have served as tutor.
          His book 
          <hi rend="italic">Notes on 
          <name type="place" key="Virginia">Virginia</name>
                  </hi>had contained a map originally
          produced by his father and later revised by the son. He had been chairman of the
          committee that had prepared the first draft of the Continental Congress's famed
          Ordinance of 1784, which had laid down the patterns by which the public lands of the
          United States were to be surveyed before being opened for sale to purchasers. Of
          necessity he had done rough and ready surveying around his plantation. We are told,
          moreover, that out of sheer intellectual curiosity, he often lugged his instruments onto
          the roof at 
          <name type="place" key="Monticello (Va.)">Monticello</name>, took sightings on a nearby
          mountain, and, using that as a focal point, happily calculated the latitude and
          longitude of the surrounding points of interest.
          <ref target="n0208" n="8"/>
               </p>
               <p>Skills, then, he had. Time was something else. His presidential duties were pressing,
          and his instruments—none could be had in those days in the nation's swampy capital—were
          at 
          <name type="place" key="Monticello (Va.)">Monticello</name>. Rather than have them
          wrapped and sent to him, he taught 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>theory out of books and invented
          problems whose solutions depended on the young man's mastery of the printed tables and
          abstruse formulas used by navigators. Actual practice would have to come later, under
          the critical eyes of trained astronomers located in busier intellectual centers than 
          <name type="place" key="Washington D. C.">Washington</name>.
          <ref target="n0209" n="9"/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Mackenzie, Alexander">Alexander Mackenzie's</name>scientific
          education had gone no farther than practical astronomy. Candidly he stated in the
          preface to his 
          <hi rend="italic">Voyages</hi>, "I do not possess the science of the naturalist."
          Moreover, the toils and perils of his traverse had not given him time "to dig in the
          earth [or] . . . to collect the plants which nature might have scattered on the way." 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>would do things differently. He
          already was gifted with acute powers of observation and a knack for describing in
          accurate detail what he saw. He knew enough of the flora and fauna in the eastern part
          of the United States to ignore similar items in the West and thus could concentrate on
          what was new and different. But he had a folk approach to natural history, not the
          scientific one that philosophers would expect when he discoursed on the new world's
          climate, soils, minerals, birds, animals, plants, forests, fishes, and fossils.</p>
               <p>Again 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>could have served as tutor
          if time had allowed. His interest in the physical scene, like that of many cultured men
          of the time, was obsessive. The philosophy of the Age of Enlightenment pervaded his
          thinking. The universe, he believed, was an orderly place. A scientist's job (and there
          was more than a mite of elitism in this, a factor that appealed to 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>) was to discover that order and
          fit it into the systematized patterns being developed by the learned men of the time—for
          example, by the great Swedish botanist and taxonomist, Karl Linné, who Latinized his
          name to Carolus Linnaeus so that it would accord with the Linnaean system of
          classification he had originated.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>fit the mold. He solicited,
          planted, and carefully noted the development of seeds and cuttings sent him by as many
          acquaintances in different parts of the world as he could reach. On being elected
          president of the American Philosophical Society in 1797, he took to his inaugural
          meeting, as exhibits for his address, a parcel of ancient bones that had been exhumed in
          western 
          <name type="place" key="Virginia">Virginia</name>and sent him for study. He had deduced
          from the creature's claws that it had been a mighty feline, and he proposed naming it
          Megalonyx: big lion. Actually, as his friend 
          <name type="person" key="Wistar, Caspar">Caspar Wistar</name>showed, the remains were
          those of a huge, extinct ground sloth. No matter. Because of 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name>pioneering work in
          paleontology, the species was given his name, 
          <hi rend="italic">Megalonyx jeffersonia</hi>, much as he had been honored a few years
          earlier by having an American species of the European twinleaf called 
          <hi rend="italic">Jefersonia diphylla</hi>.
          <ref target="n0210" n="10"/>But occasion did not serve for presidential tutoring, and 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>was scheduled to receive instead
          a series of crash courses from some of the country's leading savants in 
          <name type="place" key="Philadelphia, Pa.">Philadelphia</name>.</p>
               <p>Finally, underlying and informing all else was the psychological problem of maps. For
          the sake of his logistics, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>needed to accumulate all
          possible data about distances, topography, and potential enemies he would face on his
          way west. With 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>offering suggestions from
          time to time, he pored over charts purporting to contain enlightenment. Yet at the very
          moment of doing this he knew that much of what was offered was based on nothing more
          than guesswork, dimly understood Indian tales, or academic logic concocted as a
          substitute for actual observation. On occasion he must have felt completely adrift: how
          could he stake his success on the reliability of the very charts he was supposed to
          correct during his travels?</p>
               <p>He began his course in map reading with a geographic preconception that had long been
          a fundamental in American thinking: The gateway to the setting sun was the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri River</name>. This axiom had sprung in
          part from the sheer power of the river as it flooded into the 
          <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name>—"like a conqueror," to
          borrow the words of the early French commentator, Pierre Francois Xavier Charlevoix, who
          had passed the junction in 1721. Surely such a river came from distant sources,
          gathering power as it moved east.
          <ref target="n0211" n="11"/>
               </p>
               <p>Logic added its persuasions. The majestic 
          <name type="place" key="Ohio River">Ohio</name>and the twin tributaries that formed it,
          the 
          <name type="place" key="Monongahela River">Monongahela</name>and the 
          <name type="place" key="Allegheny River">Allegheny</name>, provided natural highways,
          broken by only minor carrying places, from the 
          <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name>Valley to the 
          <name type="place" key="Atlantic Ocean">Atlantic</name>seaboard. Did it not stand to
          reason that the equally majestic 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>would provide comparable routes
          to the 
          <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>?</p>
               <p>There were Indian tales as well. A notable one occurred in a 
          <hi rend="italic">History of Louisiana</hi>written by the Charlevoix cited above. In the
          spring of 1721, at the tiny French mission of Notre Dame de Cascasquios (
          <name type="place" key="Kaskaskia, Ill.">Kaskaskia</name>) on the 
          <name type="place" key="Illinois">Illinois</name>bank of the 
          <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name>, he encountered a woman of
          the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Missouri Indians">Missouris</name>tribe who told him,
          "The 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>rises from very high and very
          bare mountains, behind which there is another river, which probably rises there also and
          runs westward." Charlevoix's 
          <hi rend="italic">History</hi>was a popular book and went through several French
          editions and some in English. 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>considered the account
          necessary for good libraries to own, and it is easier to believe that 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>read it than to suppose he did
          not.
          <ref target="n0212" n="12"/>
               </p>
               <p>Once the far western river entered men's imaginings, it began receiving names. An
          early one came from the pages of a different 
          <hi rend="italic">History of Louisiana</hi>, this one published in 1763 by Antoine Simon
          le Page Du Pratz, who had lived beside the 
          <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name>for twenty-five years.
          During part of that time an Indian whom he called Moncacht-Apé enthralled him with tales
          of traveling far up the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>and then disembarking to wander
          happily north across a fertile plain, or perhaps over a low plateau, to a beautiful
          river flowing gently to the 
          <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>. (The 
          <name type="place" key="Ohio River">Ohio</name>, perhaps not coincidentally, was also
          called La Belle Riviêre by the French.)</p>
               <p>Now note: Moncacht-Apé did not go 
          <hi rend="italic">west</hi>over a height of land to La Belle Riviêre, as one might
          assume. No, he walked north, at right angles to the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, until he reached the dreamy
          river. In other words he (or Du Pratz) acted on the ancient concept of interlocking
          rivers, that is, the existence of neighboring, parallel streams that flow in opposite
          directions. Thus if a traveler discovered a short portage from an upbound course to a
          downward one, he could save many weary upstream miles. No wonder Moncacht-Apé called his
          "discovery" La Belle Riviêre. 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>read about the adventure in
          a copy of Du Pratz's 
          <hi rend="italic">History</hi>he purchased in 
          <name type="place" key="Paris">Paris</name>. 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name>picked up an English
          edition in 
          <name type="place" key="Philadelphia, Pa.">Philadelphia</name>and carried it with him to
          the 
          <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>and back."</p>
               <p>Du Pratz's name La Belle Riviêre for the Great River of the West (which itself is a
          name) was soon supplanted by Ourigan, or Ouragan, or Aurigan, or (as it eventually
          became) Oregon. The source was Jonathan Carver's 
          <hi rend="italic">Travels through the Interior Parts of North America in the Years 1766,
          1767, and 1768</hi>, published first in 1778. Carver had fought in the French-Indian
          Wars under the famed ranger Robert Rogers, and afterwards the two had gone to the 
          <name type="place" key="Great Lakes">Great Lakes</name>area to embark in the fur trade.
          Out of their work came Indian rumors (so Rogers claimed) of a great 
          <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>-bound river called Ouregan. Carver
          swiped the name and fitted it into his 
          <hi rend="italic">Travels</hi>, which sold several editions on both sides of the 
          <name type="place" key="Atlantic Ocean">Atlantic</name>. 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>read the tales avidly, and 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>was surely familiar with them.
          <ref target="n0213" n="13"/>
               </p>
               <p>But was there really such a river or was it the product of centuries of vaporing? 
          <name type="person" key="Mackenzie, Alexander">Alexander Mackenzie's</name>1793
          discovery of the 
          <name type="place" key="Fraser (Tacoutche-Tesse) River">Tacoutche Tesse</name>seemed to
          be the first solid evidence. Hadn't he been knighted for his work? Besides,
          corroboration came belatedly from two more sources, an English captain, 
          <name type="person" key="Vancouver, George">George Vancouver</name>, and an American
          ship trader, 
          <name type="person" key="Gray, Robert">Robert Gray</name>. In 1792 while coursing the
          Northwest coast in search of sea-otter pelts that could be exchanged in 
          <name type="place" key="China">China</name>for tea, spices, and porcelain, 
          <name type="person" key="Gray, Robert">Gray</name>had noticed through the mist a set of
          formidable breakers crashing across a bar that masked the entrance to what was probably
          a large estuary. Other traders and official explorers, both Spanish and English, had
          noticed the same tumult but had not wanted to confront it. 
          <name type="person" key="Gray, Robert">Gray</name>, though, bulled across and found
          himself in the mouth of a huge river that he named 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>, after his ship. He spent
          upwards of a profitable week trading with the river's 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinook Indians</name>and then sailed
          north to the west coast of 
          <name type="place" key="Vancouver Island">Vancouver Island</name>. There he encountered
          one of Britain's great navigators, 
          <name type="person" key="Vancouver, George">George Vancouver</name>, for whom the island
          would be named, and told him about the river. 
          <name type="person" key="Vancouver, George">Vancouver</name>was one of those who had
          seen the breakers but had sailed by. Now he decided that as an official explorer of 
          <name type="place" key="England">Great Britain</name>, he had better take a more careful
          look.</p>
               <p>The rough waves and shallow water of the bar beat his flagship back, but a small
          tender commanded by 
          <name type="person" key="Broughton, W. R.">Lieutenant W. R. Broughton</name>broke
          through. This was October 1792, and the water was low. 
          <name type="person" key="Gray, Robert">Gray</name>had been in the estuary during the
          high water of spring five months earlier, and his descriptions did not tally with what 
          <name type="person" key="Broughton, W. R.">Broughton</name>saw. Convincing himself that
          the Yankee had never left the saltwater estuary and hence could not be credited with
          discovering whatever river entered the huge sound (actually 
          <name type="person" key="Gray, Robert">Gray</name>had sailed thirty-six miles upstream),
          
          <name type="person" key="Broughton, W. R.">Broughton</name>decided to take a hand in the
          expansion of the British Empire. He ordered some of his men to lower a longboat and row
          him a hundred miles east and south to the approximate vicinity of today's 
          <name type="place" key="Portland, Oreg.">Portland</name>, 
          <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>, well within sight of the magnificent snow
          cones of 
          <name type="place" key="Mount St. Helens">Mount Saint Helens</name>and 
          <name type="place" key="Mount Hood (Timm, Falls Mountain)">Mount Hood</name>, which he
          named. In the bright moonlight of October 30, 1792, he landed and claimed possession of
          the entire watershed for his king and country.
          <ref target="n0214" n="14"/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>learned all this when the six
          liberally illustrated volumes of 
          <name type="person" key="Vancouver, George">Vancouver's</name>
                  <hi rend="italic">Voyage of Discovery to the North 
          <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific Ocean</name>
                  </hi>were published in 1801,
          the same year 
          <name type="person" key="Mackenzie, Alexander">Mackenzie's</name>book appeared. They had
          heard of 
          <name type="person" key="Gray, Robert">Gray's</name>discovery, of course, but details
          were maddeningly vague, for neither the trader nor his mate, 
          <name type="person" key="Boit, John">John Boit</name>, had yet published a word or drawn
          a map. 
          <name type="person" key="Vancouver, George">Vancouver's</name>work removed the
          uncertainties and convinced the president and his secretary that a great River of the
          West did exist, its mouth scientifically located by a trained navigator. 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name>was excited enough
          that he copied, from 
          <name type="person" key="Vancouver, George">Vancouver's</name>book, charts depicting the
          course Broughton had covered in reaching a landmark he had named 
          <name type="place" key="Point Vancouver">Point Vancouver</name>.
          <ref target="n0215" n="15"/>
               </p>
               <p>An unspoken but unsettling corollary followed. The River of the West, La Belle
          Riviêre, the Oregon, the 
          <name type="place" key="Fraser (Tacoutche-Tesse) River">Tacoutche Tesse</name>, the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>—whatever it was called—was up
          for grabs. 
          <name type="place" key="Spain">Spain</name>definitely owned 
          <name type="place" key="California">California</name>and might insist that its province
          extended far enough north to embrace the stream. 
          <name type="person" key="Mackenzie, Alexander">Mackenzie</name>, it was generally
          thought, had established a British claim to the upper river and 
          <name type="place" key="Broughton, W. R.">Broughton</name>to its lower reaches. Though 
          <name type="place" key="Gray, Robert">Gray</name>had preceded both Britons by a small
          margin, the effectiveness of his short stays was disputable. A visit by a party
          traveling overland might help strengthen the American claim to the Northwest, even
          though occupation rather than mere declarations of possession were considered paramount
          in disputes over sovereignty.
          <ref target="n0216" n="16"/>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>
                  <anchor/>Another fragment of reality was added to the
          continent's geography by definite proof, published in 1801 and 1802, that the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri River</name>extended much farther north
          than had been supposed. The key was the earthen, riverside villages occupied by the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>and 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name>Indians. Bold French
          explorers, led by the brothers Vérendrye, had visited those settlements in 1738, during
          a very premature attempt to reach the 
          <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>overland. After their withdrawal,
          darkness closed in until a small, loosely organized trade based on 
          <name type="place" key="Canada">Canada's</name>
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Assiniboine (Ossiniboine) River">Assiniboine
          River</name>was introduced during the late 1780s. By chance, Spanish traders out of 
          <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>reached the villages shortly
          thereafter (more of that later) and conflict developed. In order to determine whether
          the villages lay in Spanish or English territory, the North West Company of 
          <name type="place" key="Canada">Canada</name>sent its chief astronomer, 
          <name type="person" key="Thompson, John B.">David Thompson</name>, south to make the
          necessary observations.
          <ref target="n0217" n="17"/>
               </p>
               <p>He started out in December 1797 with nine men, "fine, hearty, good humoured . . .
          fond of full feeding, willing to hunt for it, but more willing to enjoy it"—eight pounds
          of fresh deer, elk, or buffalo meat per man per day. Hoping to do some independent
          trading, the nine took along four or five heavily laden sleds pulled by thirty wolfish
          dogs. (
          <name type="person" key="Thompson, John B.">Thompson</name>rode a horse.) Temperatures
          that fell to 32°F below zero stretched a ten-day journey to thirty-three days. For 
          <name type="person" key="Thompson, John B.">Thompson</name>there were compensations. He
          had his instruments with him and used the delays to determine "the latitude of six
          different places and the longitude of three, on the Road to the River."
          <ref target="n0218" n="18"/>
               </p>
               <p>During his short stay with the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandanes</name>, as he spelled the name,
          he grew disgusted with their sexual practices (not so his men; they had agreed to make
          the trip partly so they could enjoy the rewards of the flesh), but he swallowed his
          scruples, made anthropological notes about everything he saw, and questioned his hosts
          in detail about the course of the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>above and below the villages. In
          the process he determined to his own satisfaction that the villages lay in Spanish
          territory. Whether or not his English superiors would thereafter keep their men out of
          the area was not his to determine. In February 1798, he returned with his party to their
          starting point.</p>
               <p>Copies of the charts 
          <name type="person" key="Thompson, John B.">Thompson</name>drew were sent by his company
          to 
          <name type="place" key="London">London</name>. 
          <name type="person" key="Mackenzie, Alexander">Alexander Mackenzie</name>saw them and
          used them to indicate, on the map he issued with his 
          <hi rend="italic">Voyages</hi>in 1801, the short stretch of the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>with which Canadian traders were
          in contact. Another recipient of a copy was 
          <name type="person" key="Arrowsmith, Aaron">Arrasmith</name>, a conscientious and able
          British cartographer who had made a huge map of North America in 1795 and who published
          thoroughly revised versions in 1801 and 1802. Finally, 
          <name type="person" key="Thornton, Edward">Edward Thornton</name>, British chargé
          d'affaires in 
          <name type="place" key="Washington D. C.">Washington</name>, apparently got hold of yet
          another copy of 
          <name type="person" key="Thompson, John B.">Thompson's</name>map of the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>area and loaned it to 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Thomas Jefferson</name>. Almost certainly 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name>traced the chart
          while waiting for Congress to pass the appropriation bill that would launch the Western
          reconnaissance.
          <ref target="n0219" n="19"/>
               </p>
               <p>Those maps, obtained almost simultaneously, gave 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>the approximate longitude and
          latitude of three key points along his hypothetical route: 
          <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>, the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>villages, and the mouth of
          the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>. . . handles on space, so to
          speak. Because 
          <name type="place" key="Arrowsmith, Aaron">Arrowsmith</name>had known the direction of
          the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri's</name>flow as it left the Indian
          towns and also as it drove across the present-day state of 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>into the 
          <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name>, he had felt free to draw
          the rest of its lower course with confident, if generalized, strokes. West of the
          villages, however, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>was faced with tantalizing
          choices that derived, in large part, from an Indian called 
          <name type="person" key="The Feathers">The Feathers</name>.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="The Feathers">The Feathers</name>was a 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians, Piegan">Piegan</name>of the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfoot</name>Confederacy.
          Somewhere in the wastelands he had run into 
          <name type="place" key="Fidler, Peter">Peter Fidler</name>, a surveyor for the Hudson's
          Bay Company, who himself was supposed to have ranged south along the 
          <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rockies</name>as far as the forty-fifth
          parallel of latitude, the present boundary between 
          <name type="place" key="Wyoming">Wyoming</name>and 
          <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>. Using primitive media of some sort—a
          twig in the earth, a charred stick on a buffalo hide—
          <name type="person" key="The Feathers">The Feathers</name>drew for 
          <name type="person" key="Fidler, Peter">Fidler</name>a chart of the headwaters of the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>. It was a crude representation
          of many channels flowing east, like the veins of a leaf, into one main stem.
          <ref target="n0220" n="20"/>
                  <name type="person" key="Fidler, Peter">Fidler</name>sent this data, along with his own
          observations, to the Hudson's Bay Company. The company allowed 
          <name type="person" key="Arrowsmith, Aaron">Arrowsmith</name>to see them. He refined
          them to fit his conception of how a river should take shape and transferred the result
          to the revised 1802 map that 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name>studied with almost
          agonizing care.</p>
               <p>A little above the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>towns, according to 
          <name type="person" key="Arrowsmith, Aaron">Arrowsmith's</name>conjectures (which he
          labeled as such by using dotted instead of solid lines), the river forked into two
          tributaries fed by several smaller streams, as 
          <name type="person" key="The Feathers">The Feathers</name>had suggested. The tributaries
          gradually spread apart like the legs of a large, reclining isosceles triangle. A ridge,
          already known as the 
          <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky or Stony Mountains</name>, formed the
          base of the triangle. High points along this mountain base were named: the King in the
          north, the Heart midway, the Bear's Tooth in the south. The ridge as a whole was
          represented as rising, on the average, 3,520 feet above the plain. The altitude was
          comparable to that of the 
          <name type="place" key="Blue Ridge Mountains">Blue Ridge Mountains</name>of 
          <name type="place" key="Virginia">Virginia</name>, and 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>probably visualized them as
          such—heavily forested and creased by many steep-sided rills. It is unlikely that he
          imagined even the King or the Bear's Tooth as barren peaks, like those described to
          Charlevoix by the Indian woman at 
          <name type="place" key="Kaskaskia, Ill.">Kaskaskia</name>. Yet did he never wonder why
          the Western uplift was called the 
          <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky Mountains</name>?</p>
               <p>The 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri's</name>northern tributary, to which 
          <name type="person" key="Arrowsmith, Aaron">Arrowsmith</name>gave no name, headed at the
          peak called the King. This brought it close to one of the branches of the 
          <name type="place" key="South Saskatchewan River">South Saskatchewan</name>; this meant
          it might be used to further 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name>plan of siphoning furs out
          of 
          <name type="place" key="Canada">Canada</name>. On the western side of the King and drawn
          with a solid line was a fragmentary rendition of a stream called Great Lake River. A
          dotted line suggested that the Great Lake River continued southwest to join the southern
          reaches, also portrayed with dots, of 
          <name type="person" key="Mackenzie, Alexander">Alexander Mackenzie's</name>
                  <name type="place" key="Fraser (Tacoutche Tesse) River">Tacoutche Tesse</name>. After
          continuing south for some distance, the combined rivers bent east to join the Oregan (
          <hi rend="italic">sic</hi>), whose lower course had been charted for 
          <name type="person" key="Vancouver, George">Vancouver</name>by 
          <name type="person" key="Broughton, W. R.">Lieutenant Broughton</name>and hence had been
          given a solid line by 
          <name type="person" key="Arrowsmith, Aaron">Arrowsmith</name>.</p>
               <p>An exciting legend appeared beside the presumed lower reaches of the Great Lake
          River: "The Indians say they sleep 8 Nights in descending the River to the Sea." Only
          eight nights after crossing a pass north of the King—a pass that probably did not exceed
          the half-mile portage 
          <name type="person" key="Mackenzie, Alexander">Mackenzie</name>had found up where the
          land was reputedly sterner. Here, indeed, was a way to the 
          <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>!</p>
               <p>But was it any better than the southern branch?</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Arrowsmith, Aaron">Arrowsmith</name>believed the southern fork
          to be the main one and had labeled it "River Mississury." If it carried more water than
          the unnamed north fork, it might be more easily navigated. There was another point.
          Though the River Mississury ran due west from the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>villages to the Bear's
          Tooth, it received several large southern branches that flowed out of a section bearing
          the note, "Hereabouts the Mountains divide into several low ridges." So it might be
          possible for 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>party to work through those
          low hills to some southern tributary of the Oregan. This would enable the explorers to
          stay in American territory, whereas following the north fork might cause them to
          trespass on British soil. And if reaching the Oregan by the southern branch proved
          impossible, they might try the 
          <name type="place" key="Colorado River">Colorado River</name>instead—it was shown as
          rising no great distance to the south—and float down it to the 
          <name type="place" key="California, Gulf of">Gulf of California</name>and the 
          <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>, an option 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>himself had suggested.
          <ref target="n0221" n="21"/>
               </p>
               <p>Secretary of the Treasury 
          <name type="person" key="Gallatin, Albert">Albert Gallatin</name>added to the
          uncertainties. If 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>carried with him all the
          available maps of the trans-
          <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name>region, the packet would be
          unwieldy. Why not have 
          <name type="person" key="King, Nicholas">Nicholas King</name>, official surveyor of the
          city of 
          <name type="place" key="Washington D. C.">Washington</name>, combine all relevant data
          into a single master chart?
          <ref target="n0222" n="22"/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="King, Nicholas">King</name>agreed, but in transferring 
          <name type="person" key="Arrowsmith, Aaron">Arrowsmith's</name>data to his own map, he
          made several revisions. Some arose from different interpretations of the 
          <name type="person" key="Thompson, David">David Thompson</name>material, and some, it
          would appear, from 
          <name type="person" key="King, Nicholas">King's</name>(and 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>?) own flights of fancy. He
          thought the north tributary, left unnamed by 
          <name type="person" key="Arrowsmith, Aaron">Arrowsmith</name>, was the main one, for he
          labeled it "Missesourie" (it, too, was portrayed with dotted lines) and he shifted the
          Great Lake River far enough south so that a portage between the two streams would not
          encroach on British territory. He renamed the dotted southern tributary, which 
          <name type="person" key="Arrowsmith, Aaron">Arrowsmith</name>called the main stem, as
          the "Lesser Missesourie." He wiped out the low hills south of the Bear's Tooth. Most
          intriguing of all, he showed a conjectural great southern fork of the Oregan (even he,
          an American, disdained 
          <name type="person" key="Gray, Robert">Gray's</name>name 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>) sweeping around the southern
          foothills of the Bear's Tooth, to rise well east of the Lesser Missesourie's headwaters.
          That is, the Lesser Missesourie and the south fork of the Oregan (if it existed) now
          interlocked. 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>explorers, following the
          example of Du Pratz's Indian, Moncacht-Apé, could walk readily from one stream to the
          other without crossing a major divide. Moncacht-Apé, of course, had walked north from
          the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>to La Belle Riviêre, but it is
          not beyond the realm of possibility that the nature of the feat was in 
          <name type="person" key="King, Nicholas">King's</name>mind when he produced a similar
          situation south of the Bear's Tooth. And it was probably thoughts of the Oregan's
          southern tributary and of possible approaches to the 
          <name type="place" key="Colorado River">Colorado River</name>that led 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>to urge, in his
          instructions, that 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>keep a sharp eye on the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri's</name>southern confluences.
          <ref target="n0223" n="23"/>
               </p>
               <p>Choice. 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name>had at his fingertips
          two speculative maps prepared by two of the world's best cartographers from the latest
          information available. He could not ignore them. Yet which route, if any, could he
          depend on to take him and his party safely and successfully to their destination? Had
          not the great 
          <name type="person" key="Mackenzie, Alexander">Alexander Mackenzie</name>made an almost
          fatal choice that had spun him off to the sterile ice of the Arctic in 1789? 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>could afford nothing like
          that.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>These plans for transcontinental exploration were more daring in 1803 than they seem
          now. 
          <name type="place" key="France">France</name>still owned 
          <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name>and might continue to do so;
          America's envoys, 
          <name type="person" key="Livingston, Robert">Livingston</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Monroe, James">Monroe</name>, had been instructed to dicker
          only for 
          <name type="place" key="New Orleans, La.">New Orleans</name>and West 
          <name type="place" key="Florida">Florida</name>. Yet 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>wanted to push an American
          commercial highway across that foreign territory into another area—the 
          <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>country—to which title was by no means
          clear. More complications arose from 
          <name type="person" key="Mackenzie, Alexander">Alexander Mackenzie's</name>recently
          published Voyages. The Scot was less interested in obtaining book royalties than in
          bending the British government to his will. He concluded his tale by urging Parliament
          to charter a huge monopoly that could control the entire fur trade of 
          <name type="place" key="Canada">Canada</name>. The proposed firm would introduce goods
          into the heart of the continent by way of 
          <name type="place" key="Hudson Bay">Hudson Bay</name>in the East and the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>, over which Britain must spread
          its sovereignty, in the West. The new company would have the right to dispose of its
          Western fur harvest in the profitable markets of the Orient without interference from
          the South Sea or East Indian monopolies. Faced with so much power, America's exploitive
          ship captains, currently the dominant force in the sea-otter trade of the Northwest
          Coast, "would instantly disappear," or so 
          <name type="person" key="Mackenzie, Alexander">Mackenzie</name>argued. Even the beaver
          trade of the upper 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>would be lost, for 
          <name type="person" key="Mackenzie, Alexander">Mackenzie</name>also proposed moving 
          <name type="place" key="Canada">Canada's</name>boundary with 
          <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name>Territory south from the forty-ninth
          parallel to the forty-fifth. If all this came to pass what point would there be in the
          American president and his secretary nosing along speculative river courses and over
          dreamed-of portages, searching for the 
          <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>?</p>
               <p>There is no way to explain the president's audacity except to believe he was
          deliberately playing the odds. If the French did occupy 
          <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name>, there was a possibility they would
          send the same kind of expedition to the 
          <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>he was contemplating—and he
          certainly wanted to beat them to that, for the sake of American glory if nothing else.
          <ref target="n0224" n="24"/>But there was a much better chance that 
          <name type="person" key="Bonaparte, Napoleon">Napoleon</name>would be unable to move
          into 
          <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name>. His armies were stalled in 
          <name type="place" key="Santo Domingo">Santo Domingo</name>, and he faced, in Europe, a
          renewal of his desperate wars against 
          <name type="place" key="England">England</name>, as 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>correctly sensed. (The new
          conflict broke out in May 1803.) So the president was willing to move ahead on the
          assumption 
          <name type="place" key="France">France</name>would not—could not—interfere.</p>
               <p>What of 
          <name type="place" key="Spain">Spain</name>? No formal transfer of territory had taken
          place. Hoping perhaps that none would because of 
          <name type="person" key="Bonaparte, Napoleon">Napoleon's</name>other involvements, the
          Spanish government might prove as intransigent as 
          <name type="person" key="Yrujo, Marqués de Casa">Yrujo</name>had predicted when 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>had approached him earlier.
          In that event, 
          <name type="place" key="Madrid, Spain">Madrid's</name>longstanding policy of using 
          <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name>as a buffer to protect 
          <name type="place" key="Mexico">Mexico</name>might lead the officials in 
          <name type="place" key="New Spain">New Spain</name>to disregard 
          <name type="place" key="France">France's</name>ownership and resist 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>"invasion" with force. But 
          <name type="place" key="New Spain">New Spain</name>was, in the main, lethargic, and 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>was willing to take that
          chance, too.</p>
               <p>Then there were the Britons, whom 
          <name type="person" key="Mackenzie, Alexander">Mackenzie</name>was trying to stir into
          more empire building in the Northwest. The British were not averse to such thinking, but
          in order to turn 
          <name type="person" key="Mackenzie, Alexander">Mackenzie's</name>blueprint into
          actuality, Parliament would have to tread on the toes of three powerful monopolies, the
          Hudson's Bay, South Seas, and East India companies. That the government would do this
          for a private entrepreneur's hustling company seemed unlikely to 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>. Furthermore, 
          <name type="person" key="Mackenzie, Alexander">Mackenzie's</name>own partners in the
          North West Company were reluctant, as the president may have known, to support the
          Scot's expensive dream, even though some of their traders were already groping for a new
          way across the 
          <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rockies</name>from the headwaters of the 
          <name type="place" key="Saskatchewan River">Saskatchewan</name>.
          <ref target="n0225" n="25"/>So 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>did not look for immediate
          objection there, either, and, in fact, probably warmed himself with the thought that by
          getting Americans to the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>ahead of the British, he could
          throw yet another roadblock in 
          <name type="person" key="Mackenzie, Alexander">Mackenzie's</name>way.</p>
               <p>He concealed his audacity by lying about his purposes. Immediately after Congress had
          passed and he had signed, on February 28, 1803, the act appropriating money for
          extending the commerce of the United States, he asked the British and French ministers
          to grant passports to 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>party.
          <ref target="n0226" n="26"/>He assured both diplomats that only the language of the act
          was devious. 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>was furthering science, not
          commerce or territorial acquisition, and would carry with him only such merchandise as
          he needed to mollify suspicious Indians. The act spoke of commerce, the president said,
          only because the American Constitution forbade the government's financing enterprises
          devoted to advancing science or promoting geographical discoveries.</p>
               <p>Such statements were a calculated deception. Though 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>did earnestly wish to
          promote science and geographical knowledge, he also hoped to draw as many furs out of
          the British area of influence as possible. Developing good will among the Indians while
          learning trade routes and navigable river systems was essential to the realization of
          that mercantile goal.</p>
               <p>Only the French minister, 
          <name type="person" key="Pichon, Louis André">Louis André Pichon</name>, raised an
          eyebrow. Inasmuch as 
          <name type="place" key="Spain">Spain</name>still administered 
          <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name>, he said, was its minister, 
          <name type="person" key="Yrujo, Marqués de Casa">Carlos Martinez, Marqués de Casa
          Yrujo</name>, also granting passage? 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>evaded the question, saying
          only, "
          <hi rend="italic">Qu'il devait le donner</hi>": he ought to grant it. He went on with a
          great show of candor, tracing out 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>proposed route on 
          <name type="person" key="Arrowsmith, Aaron">Arrowsmith's</name>map and then lending 
          <name type="person" key="Pichon, Louis André">Pichon</name>the British passport so he
          could use it as a model in preparing his own.</p>
               <p>A final and very strange bit of camouflage was his telling, and ordering 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>to tell, anyone who noted
          preparations for the expedition and wondered about its goal that it was bound up the 
          <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name>.
          <ref target="n0227" n="27"/>The French and British ministers knew better, as did the
          Federalists in Congress who had seen the enabling act passed. So why this last cover? No
          one can be sure. Possibly the president hoped to keep Federalist newspaper editors from
          raising a commotion about the true nature of the exploration. Perhaps he worried lest
          Western frontiersmen, feeling they could go wherever an official government party went,
          might create an incident by trying to follow 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>into 
          <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name>. Or perhaps he believed, with his
          usual predilection for secrecy, that any questionable enterprise needed concealment as a
          matter of course and acted accordingly.</p>
               <p>Whatever the reason, seldom has an expedition of such momentous potentials been
          prepared for with so little fanfare.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="notes" type="notes">
            <head rend="center">Notes</head>
            <div type="section">
               <note xml:id="n0201" n="1">Malone, IV, 278–81. McMaster, II, 448–99, 631–33. [Benton]
          Abridgement, 672–92, passim.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0202" n="2">Manpower is given variously as between eight and twelve in 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name>letters to Barton, 
          <name type="person" key="Wistar, Caspar">Wister</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Rush, Benjamin">Rush</name>, and 
          <name type="person" key="Patterson, Robert">Patterson</name>, all of them members of the
          American Philosophical Society. (Jackson, 
          <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, 16–20.) See also 
          <name type="person" key="Dearborn, Henry">Dearborn</name>to 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, ibid., 70.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0203" n="3">Ibid., 70.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0204" n="4">Ibid., 38.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0205" n="5">Quoted in Chuinard, 99.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0206" n="6">Ronda, 8.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0207" n="7">Jackson, 
          <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, 38.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0208" n="8">Cutright, 
          <hi rend="italic">Pioneering Naturalists</hi>, 4.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0209" n="9">I hypothesize this paragraph from 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name>letter to 
          <name type="person" key="Patterson, Robert">Robert Patterson</name>, March 2, 1803
          (Jackson, 
          <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, 21): "He [
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>] has for some time been
          qualifying himself for taking observations of Longitude and latitude ... but little
          means are possessed here for doing that; and it is the particular part in which you
          could give him valuable instruction."</note>
               <note xml:id="n0210" n="10">Cutright, 
          <hi rend="italic">Pioneering Naturalists</hi>, 5, 25.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0211" n="11">Theoretical geography and mapmaking therefrom are covered in
          fascinating detail in Wheat, I, and Allen, passim. See also DeVoto, 
          <hi rend="italic">Course</hi>, 51–79.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0212" n="12">For Charlevoix, Du Pratz 
          <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi>: Allen, 14; DeVoto, 
          <hi rend="italic">Course</hi>, 199–200; Lavender, Westward, 23–24.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0213" n="13">Carver, passim. Allen, 16–30, 91, 96 (the citations also
          cover map reproductions); Lavender, 
          <hi rend="italic">Westward</hi>, 50–64; Jackson, 
          <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>II, 695.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0214" n="14">For 
          <name type="person" key="Gray, Robert">Gray</name>: Boit, "Log of the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>," Howay, 
          <hi rend="italic">Voyages of the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>
                  </hi>. For 
          <name type="person" key="Vancouver, George">Vancouver's</name>men on the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>: Barry, "
          <name type="person" key="Broughton, W. R.">Broughton</name>," and "Who Discovered the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>?"</note>
               <note xml:id="n0215" n="15">Allen, 96–97.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0216" n="16">This is DeVoto's contention in his foreword to the 
          <hi rend="italic">Journals</hi>, 1–1ii. The whole foreword can be read with profit, even
          though (in my opinion) DeVoto is quite wrong-headed in some of his dogmatic
          declarations—for instance, his insistence that 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>was not surprised by the
          Louisiana Purchase.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0217" n="17">Wood and Thiessen, 26–27, 42–47, and appendix, Table
          1.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0218" n="18">D. Thompson, 160–81.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0219" n="19">Allen, 87–90. Portions of the 
          <name type="person" key="Thompson, David">Thompson</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Mackenzie, Alexander">Mackenzie</name>, and 1802 
          <name type="person" key="Arrowsmith, Aaron">Arrowsmith</name>maps are in ibid., 80, 84,
          92.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0220" n="20">Ibid., 87, 79. 
          <name type="person" key="Fidler, Peter">Fidler's</name>copy of the Indian map is on 22.
          See also Wheat I, 178.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0221" n="21">Jackson, 
          <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, 27–28.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0222" n="22">For 
          <name type="person" key="King, Nicholas">King's</name>map, Allen, 100, 116. See 47,
          96–104, 117 for a discussion of the relationship of the 
          <name type="person" key="King, Nicholas">King</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Arrowsmith, Aaron">Arrowsmith</name>maps. For Allen's belief
          that 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>took the 
          <name type="person" key="King, Nicholas">King</name>map to the 
          <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>with him: 97–98, 132, and, by
          implication, 165–66.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0223" n="23">Jackson, 
          <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, 63.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0224" n="24">Ibid., 26.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0225" n="25">Morton, 466–68.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0226" n="26">Jackson, Letters, 19–27.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0227" n="27">Ibid., 38, 44.</note>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.lavender.01.01" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.lavender.01.00" type="contents"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.lavender.01.03" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
