<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.lc.lavender.01.15">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Way to the Western Sea</title>
            <title type="sub">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>across the Continent</title>
            <title type="sub" level="a">Chapter 15</title>
            <author>David Lavender</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2005</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic
        Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Way to the Western Sea</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">Chapter 15</title>
               <author>David Lavender</author>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>2001</date>
               <idno type="ISBN">0-8032-8003-3</idno>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-11-09</date>
            <date>2005-04-20</date>
            <name>Becky Potter</name>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Split into chapters Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-04-12</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="fifteen" type="chapter">
            <head rend="center">FIFTEEN. Wild Water</head>
            <div type="section">
               <p>After so many days of plodding, the discoverers must have felt a heady exhilaration
          when the swift current of the 
          <name type="place" key="Clearwater Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Clearwater</name>, as
          the river is called today, whipped their loglike dugouts downstream toward the 
          <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>. But the water was also low in
          October, and every so often clusters of black rocks rose ominously above tangles of
          frothing waves.
          <ref target="n1501" n="1"/>
               </p>
               <p>The first wreck, which can typify the rest, came just one day after the launching.
          They had successfully passed "fifteen rapids, four islands, and a Creek." Perhaps they
          were cocky. Anyway, the boat 
          <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Sergeant Gass</name>was steering, either with a
          sweep oar or a big, Indian-style paddle, banged into a boulder and tossed him overboard.
          One side of the dugout split open, letting water pour in. Fortunately, that part of the
          river, though swift, was only waist deep and salvage was possible. 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>described it: "the men, Several of
          which Could not swim hung onto the Canoe. I had one of the other Canoes unloaded &amp;
          with the assistance of our Small Canoe and one Indian Canoe took out everything &amp;
          toed the empty Canoe on Shore, one man 
          <name type="person" key="Thompson, John B.">Tompson</name>a little hurt."
          <ref target="n1502" n="2"/>
               </p>
               <p>Most of the cargo was soaked, of course, and had to be spread out to dry while the
          canoe was repaired—under guard, for many Indians, alert for anything loose, had gathered
          quickly during the rescue work. At that point the two 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name>guides, 
          <name type="person" key="Old Toby">Old Toby</name>and his son, vanished, either because
          they feared being ducked in some later rapid or they had decided there were too many
          strange Indians around for comfort. Actually the defection did not matter much, for the
          two 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Percé</name>chiefs, 
          <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">Twisted Hair</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Tetoharsky">Tetoharsky</name>, had already taken over as river
          guides and ambassadors of good will among the stream-side Indians.</p>
               <p>What did matter was the way the river was forcing the captains into a familiar
          dilemma of the Western world: lose time by hurrying. "we should make more portages," 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>admitted, "if the season was not so
          far advanced and time precious with us." They tried to compromise by adding precautions.
          On approaching an unusually heavy rapid—they were warned either by their 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>guides or by the
          deep-throated roar of the water—
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>would signal for the flotilla to
          land while they walked ahead with the guides and the steersmen to read the water. If it
          looked particularly rugged, they would have the nonswimmers walk to the foot of the tail
          waves, carrying what they could. Men able to swim would then take their chances with the
          partially lightened craft. Generally no more than one or two boats went through such
          stretches at a time. This precaution left the others perched in handy eddies, ready to
          dart out if rescue operations became necessary. As they did—at least five times during
          the first ten days. "we have great cause to lament," 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>wrote after one of the wrecks,
          while the salvaged goods were drying, "as all our loose Powder two canisters, all our
          roots prepared in the Indian way, and one half our goods [are lost]." To say nothing of
          time.
          <ref target="n1503" n="3"/>
               </p>
               <p>As they bobbed and twisted downstream, the nature of the country changed radically.
          The 
          <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Clearwater</name>was
          breaking out of the last foothills of the 
          <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rockies</name>and entering the bowl-shaped 
          <name type="place" key="Great Columbian Plain">Columbian Plain</name>in an area where,
          because of the rain shadow cast by the coastal 
          <name type="place" key="Cascade Range">Cascade Range</name>, precipitation averaged less
          than ten inches a year. Pine trees disappeared from the hills, as did all vegetation,
          except stunted willows and weeds, from the stream margins. "Barren and broken" became
          the common words in the journals for the lands stretching out beyond the canyon walls.
          Prickly pear cactus covered the wind-scoured ground, but that and spaciousness were the
          only traits the region shared with the High Plains bordering the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>. There were no great, clotted
          herds of buffalo, elk, deer, or antelope. Food was limited to salmon, most of it dried,
          and to roots, and a slowly increasing number of dogs, all purchased from the stream-side
          Indians with articles reluctantly drawn from the expedition's shrinking supply of trade
          goods.</p>
               <p>Stalks, twigs, and bits of driftwood served as fuel, and often had to be purchased.
          The captains, heedful of 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name>admonition about treating
          the Indians fairly, were scrupulous about paying for everything that was not clearly
          offered as a gift. But one night, after yet another wreck had left them cold and hungry
          and with a canoe-load of sodden goods in need of drying, they did break into a cache of
          unguarded wood they stumbled across. We know because all the journal keepers admitted to
          the theft, perhaps to exorcise their guilt by confessing it—or perhaps to help readers
          understand how dire their straits had become.
          <ref target="n1504" n="4"/>
               </p>
               <p>Yet how marvelous those crystal rivers were! Five days out of 
          <name type="place" key="Canoe Camp (Idaho)">Canoe Camp</name>, they were hurried by the 
          <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Clearwater</name>into
          a stream more than a quarter of a mile wide, its water a faint, translucent green as it
          surged out of the south. The 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Percé</name>called it 
          <name type="place" key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Fork Columbia) River">
          Kimooenim</name>. After recalling his explorations of the 
          <name type="place"
                        key="Salmon (Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">Salmon
          River</name>and remembering his many talks with Indians about the lie of the land, 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>decided this "new" river was
          actually a reappearance of the 
          <name type="place"
                        key="Salmon (Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">
          Salmon</name>, swollen now by many tributaries. 
          <name type="place"
                        key="Salmon (Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">Lewis's
          River</name>, he had named it—the great South Fork of the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>as postulated on their maps.</p>
               <p>His only mistake was not realizing that 
          <name type="place"
                        key="Salmon (Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">Lewis's
          River</name>, instead of being the main stream, was actually a tributary of the majestic
          
          <name type="place" key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Fork Columbia) River">
          Snake</name>. Right then, however, the error was irrelevant. For as the captains knew
          from the Indians, a bigger river than the 
          <name type="place" key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Fork Columbia) River">
          Kimooenim</name>lay only a short distance ahead. This newest one had to be the main fork
          of the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>, which the Corps still
          identified with 
          <name type="person" key="Mackenzie, Alexander">Alexander Mackenzie's</name>
                  <name type="place" key="Fraser (Tacoutche-Tesse) River">Tacoutche Tesse</name>. Riding a
          surge like that, they would surely reach the 
          <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>in short order. Or so they must
          have joyfully believed, pleased meanwhile that their guess-work geography, born of many
          hours of speculation, was turning out to be correct—except in the one vital matter of a
          short portage across the 
          <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rockies</name>.</p>
               <p>On October 16, having traveled by 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>calculation 3,714 miles from 
          <name type="place" key="Camp Dubois (Camp Wood, River Dubois) (Ill.)">Camp Wood</name>at
          the mouth of the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, they reached the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>. It was one of the great rivers
          of North America and a primary goal of the expedition, yet the journals record no
          elation. The matter-of-factness has baffled some commentators. But exhilaration had come
          to the explorers two months earlier, after the crossing of 
          <name type="place" key="Lemhi Pass">Lemhi Pass</name>, where most of them, stooping
          beside a small rivulet, had first "tasted the water of the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Great Columbia</name>." This last encounter,
          however welcome, was no more than a confirmation.</p>
               <p>Still it merited a halt. The captains wanted to make observations for latitude. (They
          again sidestepped the tricky calculations involved in computing longitude.) 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>was anxious to collect
          comparative vocabularies, and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>hoped to explore upstream toward
          another tributary he had heard of, today's 
          <name type="place" key="Yakima (Tapteete) River">Yakima</name>. The men needed to mend
          their clothes and put their arms in order, "always a matter of attention with us," for
          they never forgot that the expedition was, essentially, a military force crossing lands
          held by potential enemies. And, as always, they had to replenish their larder as best
          they could.</p>
               <p>From time immemorial the junction of the 
          <name type="place" key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Fork Columbia) River">
          Snake</name>and 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>rivers had been a favorite
          gathering place for Indians from throughout the 
          <name type="place" key="Great Columbian Plain">Columbian Plain</name>. Topographically,
          the place was not dramatic, for the river bluffs were low there, affording a view of
          empty scablands stretching endlessly toward nowhere. But if the land was empty, the
          river teemed each summer with salmon coming in repeated hordes to the forks. There the
          fish instinctively chose the branch that would lead them to the headwaters where they
          had been spawned and where those that survived the journey would spawn in their turn
          before dying—intense swarms whose pulsing, thrashing magnitude can scarcely be imagined
          today.</p>
               <p>When the Corps of Discovery reached the confluence, the last of that year's migration
          was ending. Though myriads of fish still undulated in transparent water fifteen to
          twenty feet below the boats, an even greater number lay dead in putrefying windrows
          along the banks or floated on the surface of the streams. The Indians, too, were
          leaving. Many of their settlements, frequently located where salmon congregated at the
          bottoms of the rapids, were empty. But, like the living salmon, many still remained, the
          men busy with spears, nets, and weirs, while the women dexterously slit in half and
          disemboweled, one by one, the fish brought to them and then laid the pieces on wooden
          scaffolds to dry. Amazed by the number of the structures, 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>tried to find out how far the
          people had rafted the timbers used in their building, but his gestured questions, turned
          into words by 
          <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">Twisted Hair</name>, were not
          understood.</p>
               <p>As 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>soon learned from his vocabulary
          work, the crowds of Indians in the vicinity all spoke dialects of the same Sahaptian
          tongue. Meanwhile both captains took note of the unusual houses. They were simple
          rectangles, fifteen to sixty feet long. Forked timbers supported the ridgepoles; the
          roof slopes and walls were covered with large mats made of rushes. An open slit along
          the entire ridge top of each dwelling gave egress to smoke from fires built along the
          center of the interior. The gap, said 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, "proves to me rains are not
          common in this country."
          <ref target="n1505" n="5"/>Several families, each with its own fireplace, occupied each
          house.</p>
               <p>The 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Percé</name>of the foothills, the
          captains found, were more "dressy" than their relatives at the junction. The former's
          hide garments were garishly decorated, as were the twin braids of the men's hair, which
          hung forward over their chests. The women of the 
          <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Clearwater</name>wore
          belted dresses that reached to their ankles, and they were far more modest than the men
          about "
          <hi rend="italic">secreting the parts</hi>[emphasis by 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>]." The women downstream, however,
          eschewed ornaments and long dresses and wore only "a pece of leather tied around them at
          their hips and drawn tite between their legs and fastened before So as barly to hide
          those parts which are so sacredly hid &amp; s[e]cured by our women."</p>
               <p>These benighted people, the captains agreed, seemed happy. They had many horses; the
          men shared more tasks with women than was customary in most tribes. Monogamy was the
          rule; age was respected. But there were problems. One widespread affliction was sore
          eyes and, often, blindness—the result, the captains thought, of the sun's unbroken glare
          on water during the fishing season and on snow during winter. Many teeth were worn to
          the gums or missing entirely. The whites explained this by saying the grit of unwashed
          roots ground away the teeth. More recent theories suggest that both the trachoma and
          gonorrhea forms of conjunctivitis should bear most of the blame for the ailing eyes, and
          that sand worn from mortars and pestles during the grinding of food (roots were
          generally washed, 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>notwithstanding) accounted for the
          bad teeth.
          <ref target="n1506" n="6"/>
               </p>
               <p>The Indians returned the whites' curiosity in full. The afternoon the Corps arrived
          at the confluence, they were greeted by two hundred natives, singing and pounding on
          their drums. They formed a half-circle around the visitors, smoked a little, and made
          what they could out of gestures concerning trade and universal peace. Chiefs were
          "made," and small gifts distributed. Acquiring food from the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Percé</name>who lived along the
          river continued to be an all-important problem. With the greatest politeness, the
          captains turned down the salmon that were offered them, for they feared some of the fish
          might have been picked up dead or dying and be contaminated. But they did purchase an
          amazing heap of forty dogs. Unless the unfortunate creatures were bought already dressed
          and in individual transactions, the barking, howling, teeth-bared massacre must have
          been too gruesome even to contemplate.</p>
               <p>At four o'clock in the afternoon of October 18, the explorers again took to their
          boats, still accompanied by 
          <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">Twisted Hair</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Tetoharsky">Tetoharsky</name>. The next day the wide 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>, which had been running south,
          veered west through the 
          <name type="place" key="Wallula Gap">Wallula Gap</name>into new canyons. Barren, dark
          brown cliffs of basalt, the result of ancient lava flows, climbed higher and higher.
          There were more snarling rapids to run. More Indians to contact, including one group 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>inadvertently frightened out of
          their wits.</p>
               <p>The episode occurred near the bottom of a rush of white water two miles long. He and
          some others walked ahead to lighten the boats for the passage. It turned out to be slow,
          and to kill time 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>climbed to the top of a
          two-hundred-foot cliff to see the view. Far to the west he made out, with what must have
          been a spark of excitement, a tall, snow-covered peak. 
          <name type="place" key="Mount St. Helens">Mount Saint Helens</name>, he thought, named
          in 1792 by the British naval captain 
          <name type="place" key="Vancouver, George">George Vancouver</name>, who had sighted the
          mountain from the mouth of the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>. If 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>identification was correct, the
          continental gap had been closed: two inquiring humans, separated by only a few miles and
          years, had stared in wonder at the same dazzling object, albeit from different sides.
          (Actually, the identification was not accurate; 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>had sighted a huge new peak later
          named 
          <name type="place" key="Mount Adams">Mount Adams</name>. 
          <name type="place" key="Mount St. Helens">Mount Saint Helens</name>was only twenty-five
          miles farther west, however.) The ocean lay 
          <hi rend="italic">just yonder</hi>, tangible at last. Englishmen had been there; the
          American 
          <name type="person" key="Gray, Robert">Robert Gray</name>had entered the river with his
          ship 
          <hi rend="italic">Columbia</hi>. But though part of the coast was known, the dark
          interiors of the land could still be frantically primordial, as 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark</name>learned on his return to
          meet the boats.</p>
               <p>The setup was this. The smallest of the dugouts had reached the foot of the rapids,
          but the larger ones were still upstream, having trouble. Nor was 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>the only watcher. Across the river
          from where he settled down to wait were five long houses. Their inhabitants, who
          evidently had not noticed 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>as he descended the cliffs, were
          scattered out on ledges, staring at the fleet. At that point 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>half-negligently snapped a shot at
          a crane flying over- head, barely visible against fleecy clouds. A lucky hit: the bird
          dropped with a puff of feathers into the river. Instantly the Indians across the way,
          who never before had heard a gun, fled in panic into their long houses.</p>
               <p>Not connecting the incidents but wanting to keep all Indians on a friendly footing, 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>called to 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name>and the 
          <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph and Reubin">Field brothers</name>, who were
          waiting nearby. Boarding the small boat, they rowed across the river. Along the way 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>shot at a duck. It, too, fell into
          the river.</p>
               <p>Arrived at the closest house, the whites shoved aside the upright mats that blocked
          the doors and entered. Abject terror greeted them. Thirty-two men, women, and children
          crouched on the floor, heads hanging as they wailed and moaned and wrung their hands.
          The thought crossed 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>mind that he could go among them
          tomahawking each in turn without encountering resistance.
          <ref target="n1507" n="7"/>It was an instinctive, bloodthirsty reaction born in his own
          dark, unexplored interior, and psychologists might like to play with it. In the event,
          however, 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>simply took each person by the hand
          and offered trinkets and bits of ribbon. As the people calmed, he sent his men to the
          other lodges to repeat the performance.</p>
               <p>To seal the peace, he produced his pipe and loaded it with tobacco prior to passing
          it around for a ceremonial smoke. Sunlight falling through the slit in the roof led him
          to light the tobacco with a burning (magnifying) glass—no pocket matches in those days.
          At that the terror returned full force. Fire drawn by a demi-god from the sun!</p>
               <p>Realizing what he had done, 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>retreated outside and sat on a
          rock, holding the pipe in a welcoming position. No one ventured out, however, until 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>arrived with 
          <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">Twisted Hair</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Tetoharsky">Tetoharsky</name>. The two 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Percés</name>jabbered questions.
          The Indians explained. They had heard roars like thunder; dead birds had fallen from the
          sky. Clearly the white man was from the sun. 
          <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">Twisted Hair</name>clucked. No,
          this was the way of it. But what really wiped the fears away was the sight of 
          <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name>coming up the hill with her
          eight-month-old 
          <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Jean Baptiste">son</name>in his carrier on her
          back. "This ... confirmed those people of our friendly intentions, as no woman ever
          accompanies a war party of Indians in this quarter."
          <ref target="n1508" n="8"/>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>As the miles fell away, the desolation of the land increased. The lava-rock
          precipices, particularly those bordering the north side of the river, climbed hundreds
          of feet high. Over the eons they had shed huge chunks of basalt into the water. These
          dark, forbidding rocks split the river into many fretful channels, some stirred in
          places by whirlpools as if with a giant spoon. And these were but preludes. From the
          natives the explorers kept hearing the word 
          <hi rend="italic">timm</hi>, spoken in deep tones to imitate the roar of unseen falls
          ahead. As for the Indians, most continued to be of Sahaptian stock—
          <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Percé</name>and their relatives.
          Here and there, however, the whites began coming across squat, unkempt, loose-haired,
          bandy-legged members of the Chinookan language group.</p>
               <p>The 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookans</name>were true flatheads.
          Foreheads, molded when infant bones were soft, sloped backward without indentation from
          the tip of the nose to a pointed cranium. Protrusions at the back of the head were also
          flattened out, to intensify the peaked-head look that among the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookans</name>signified beauty and
          nobility. Two or three of the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookans</name>had blankets of red
          and blue cloth; one wore a sailor's jacket. The articles clearly came from the mouth of
          the river. But did the whites who had traded the merchandise live in permanent posts, as
          the Indians seemed to indicate, or did they simply make occasional visits by ship to the
          coast? At that point the destitute explorers probably did not care greatly either way,
          so long as ship or post, even if manned by Britons, was well stocked with supplies.</p>
               <p>On October 22, after speeding down a roaring channel between the south shore and a
          long island spiked with fantastic towers and pinnacles of basalt, they came to the brink
          of a massive, perpendicular, twenty-foot waterfall—
          <hi rend="italic">timm</hi>water, shrouded in mist. If 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>felt any resurgence of the awe
          that had gripped him at the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">Great Falls of the
          Missouri</name>, it is not mentioned. Nor does 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>reveal anything more than a concern
          to get on down the river as efficiently as possible. Aesthetics and adventure were
          losing their savor.
          <ref target="n1509" n="9"/>
               </p>
               <p>Because this was a heavily traveled Indian route, the captains had no trouble
          planning procedures. Accompanied by an old Indian, they located a rough,
          twelve-hundred-foot portage across solid rock and windblown sand. By hiring a few horses
          for transporting the heaviest bundles and letting the men carry the rest, they completed
          moving their cargo by nightfall and camped near "5 lod[g]es of natives drying and
          prepareing fish for market."</p>
               <p>The steep, winding route would not do for the heavy dugouts, however. So the next
          morning 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>and the greater part of the men
          rowed the boats to the south side of the river and, with great difficulty, "hauled" them
          a quarter of a mile through the debris of a recently abandoned fishing camp. The fleas
          swarming there infested the men. Frantic, they tore off their hide clothing and worked
          naked so they could brush away the vermin as opportunity allowed. They could not abandon
          their overrun clothing, however, for they had nothing else to wear. So they took the
          fleas with them on a swift ride through a narrow channel that ended at the top of a
          snarling cascade whose total drop was about eight feet. The pitching banks allowed no
          room for portaging big dugouts, and the tremendous surge of the water created a
          maelstrom unsafe for the men to ride. Finding perches on rocks above the fury, the men
          lined the empty craft through with elkskin ropes. One broke loose and was pounced on by
          Indians waiting below the falls; ransoming the boat was costly. The full drop of falls
          and cataracts, a unit later called 
          <name type="place" key="Celilo (Great) Falls">Celilo Falls</name>, was, by 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>calculations, thirty-eight and a
          half feet.</p>
               <p>Another bit of foresight here. In a back eddy below the falls the captains saw two
          beautiful canoes different from any they had witnessed before. Tapering gracefully at
          both ends, they were unusually wide in the middle. Their sides, "dug thin" in 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>words, were strengthened by
          crossbars; these also served as handles for lifting the relatively light vessels out of
          the water onto the shore. The bows were decorated by fanciful figureheads. Such canoes,
          they learned through their 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Percé</name>interpreters, were
          constructed to ride high waves and carry huge burdens. Since the Corps dugouts most
          assuredly could not do those things, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>sought out the owner of one of
          the vessels and, after much bargaining, obtained it in exchange for the expedition's
          small dugout plus a hatchet and some trinkets.
          <ref target="n1510" n="10"/>
               </p>
               <p>A couple of miles below 
          <name type="place" key="Celilo (Great) Falls">Celilo Falls</name>, a massive black
          promontory thrust into the stream as if trying to touch a shorter span on the opposite
          bank. Accompanied by several Indians who lived near the obstruction, 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>climbed to its top to study what he
          later called the 
          <name type="place" key="Short (Little) Narrows)">Short Narrows</name>. It was
          awesome—the entire 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>pouring into a gap forty-five
          yards wide as if into a high-pressure nozzle. Yet avoiding the stretch by portaging the
          heavy dugouts across the steep, broad obstruction was impossible.</p>
               <p>After studying "this agitated gut swelling, boiling &amp; whorling in every
          direction," 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Pierre Cruzatte</name>, the principal
          boatman, decided it could be run. Presumably the captains sent all nonswimmers,
          including 
          <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name>and her baby, and the most valuable
          goods around the cauldron. 
          <hi rend="italic">But</hi>he doesn't say so, as he does every other time the group is
          divided, and the exception tantalizes. Did 
          <hi rend="italic">everyone</hi>run the gut—a rougher run, 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>admitted later, than he had
          anticipated and one that amazed the Indians watching from the rocks above? After
          clearing the agitated whorls, the boats raced on through a slightly wider slot to a
          "very bad place, the current divided by two islands." 
          <hi rend="italic">There</hi>, at the 
          <name type="place" key="Short (Little) Narrows)">Short Narrows</name>, nonswimmers did
          carry the expedition's most valuable "papers Guns &amp; amunition" by land while the
          dugouts took on the "very bad place" without casualties.</p>
               <p>Between the 
          <name type="place" key="Short (Little) Narrows)">Short Narrows</name>and the next rapid,
          which 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>named the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">Long
          Narrows</name>, stood a strong village of 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Wishram-Wasco Indians">Wishram</name>Indians, a 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookan</name>band. Called 
          <name type="place" key="Nixluidix">Nixluidix</name>, the town consisted of twenty-one
          long, plank houses, their foundations dug deeply into the earth—the first wooden town
          the captains had seen since leaving the 
          <name type="place" key="Illinois">Illinois</name>country. Along with a settlement of
          related 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Wishram-Wasco Indians">Wascos</name>located on the
          southern shore (a village the captains did not visit), 
          <name type="place" key="Nixluidix">Nixluidix</name>dominated the twelve-mile stretch of
          furious water later named 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">La Grande
          Dalle de la Columbia</name>, or, more simply, 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The
          Dalles</name>.
          <ref target="n1511" n="11"/>
               </p>
               <p>From mid-April to mid-October, salmon of several species could be taken in almost
          unlimited numbers as they struggled upward toward their spawning grounds. Cleaned,
          dried, and pounded into a powder, the catches were stored in big baskets lined with fish
          skins. The storage baskets were then stacked in pyramids, seven below and five above.
          Mats were wrapped around the stacks and cinched tight with cords. 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>counted 107 stacks scattered around
          the environs of 
          <name type="place" key="Nixluidix">Nixluidix</name>—by his estimate, ten thousand pounds
          of "neet" fish (fish unmixed with other substances). The fish meal, he was assured,
          would stay edible for several years and was a principal source of winter food. The
          odorous region—fish entrails, excrement, and decay in general—also attracted innumerable
          fleas and polecats.
          <ref target="n1512" n="12"/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Percés</name>and other Sahaptian
          groups from higher up the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>came to the area to increase
          their own supplies of fish and also to swap their furs, hides, bear claws, bear grass
          (used in making baskets), and dried meat with 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookan</name>visitors for dried
          clams, tools whittled out of wood, cloth and metal items from ship traders who stopped
          by the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia's</name>mouth, and choice dentalium
          shells that trickled south along the coast from 
          <name type="place" key="Vancouver Island">Vancouver Island</name>. The shells were about
          two inches long and curved like tiny walrus tusks. 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinooks</name>liked to wear them in
          their noses, and a few 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Percés</name>imitated the custom,
          just as some Sahaptians flattened their children's heads according to the Chinookan
          style. Other exchanges at the great mart consisted of folk stories, dances, and whatever
          was staked on the interminable gambling games.</p>
               <p>The 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Wishram-Wasco Indians">Wascos and Wishrams</name>who
          lived along 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The
          Dalles</name>were as intent on retaining control of the Indian commerce that flowed
          through their part of the gorge as the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton Sioux</name>had been in
          mastering the trade of the middle 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>. Of the two groups at 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The
          Dalles</name>, the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Wishram-Wasco Indians">Wishrams</name>were the more
          belligerent, and it was among them that 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>camped during their descent of the
          river. The Indians were suspicious. Just what did these strangers want? According to 
          <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">Twisted Hair</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Tetoharsky">Tetoharsky</name>, the villagers were even planning
          to attack the expedition. No problem, the captains said, but made a show of examining
          the men's arms and issuing enough ammunition to give each soldier a hundred rounds.</p>
               <p>Evidently the demonstration had its effect. The Indians became civil. With 
          <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">Twisted Hair</name>and 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Tetoharsky">Tetoharsky</name>acting as representatives
          of the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Percés</name>, the captains
          arranged a peace between the tribes. Pax Americana, just what 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">President Jefferson</name>wanted, even out
          here where his nation exerted no sovereignty—as yet. From this moment on, 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>wrote with astounding naiveté,
          "those two bands or nations will be on the most friendly terms." In celebration 
          <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Pierre Cruzatte</name>fiddled and the
          soldiers danced, to the delight of the natives.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>On October 25, the explorers successfully passed the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">Long
          Narrows</name>, boiling and whirling just below the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Wishram-Wasco Indians">Wishram</name>settlements. The
          thirty-five miles of relatively quiet water that followed served to take them out of the
          arid 
          <name type="place" key="Great Columbia Plain">Columbian Plain</name>into the humid rain
          forests of the coastal Northwest. The change was extraordinary. Average annual rainfall
          (which of course the explorers had no way of measuring) rises from fourteen inches at 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The
          Dalles</name>to sixty-five inches—more than five feet!—on the western slope of the 
          <name type="place" key="Cascade Range">Cascade Mountains</name>. Under the influence of
          the repeated deluges, the stunted pines and oak coverts the explorers had noticed at 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The
          Dalles</name>gave way to Douglas firs, red cedars, spruce and hemlock of unbelievable
          size. Rioting underneath the high canopy of the branches were almost impenetrable
          tangles of lesser trees, brush, and giant ferns.</p>
               <p>The Indians changed too. The 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Tenino Indians">Eneeshur</name>band of Sahaptians, who
          lived near 
          <name type="place" key="Celilo (Great) Falls">Celilo Falls</name>, could not understand
          the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Wishram-Wasco Indians">Echeloot Wishrams</name>who lived
          only half a dozen miles away.
          <ref target="n1513" n="13"/>Although salmon were an important part of the economy of
          the Sahaptians, and especially of the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Percé</name>, their chief
          orientation was toward the grassy, untimbered land where their horse herds ranged. In
          the thick forests west of the 
          <name type="place" key="Cascade Range">Cascade Mountains</name>, however, horses were
          useless. The 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookans</name>were people of the 
          <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>littoral and of its great rivers,
          and of fantastic canoes that were capable of riding across waves that would keep the
          cumbersome log dugouts of the Americans pinned to the shore for days at a time. They
          were a people of wood. They built plank houses covered with riven fir and cedar; they
          carved not only domestic utensils from the produce of the forest but also decorative
          figureheads for their boats and curious images of human forms to set up beside their
          wooden burial vaults.
          <ref target="n1514" n="14"/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>distrusted them. Part of the
          prejudice came from 
          <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">Twisted Hair</name>and Tetoharsky,
          who accompanied the expedition through the 
          <name type="place" key="Short (Little) Narrows)">Short</name>and 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">Long
          Narrows</name>with great reluctance and then hurried home on horses they had purchased
          near 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Great Falls of the">Celilo Falls</name>. One of
          the duties of the Corps, however, was to be friendly, so they could acquire, through
          observation and pantomime, knowledge that might some day be useful to their country. For
          themselves they needed to create a good will they could draw on while toiling back up
          the river the following spring.
          <ref target="n1515" n="15"/>Each day, accordingly, they smoked with most of the groups
          they encountered on the river, and at night entertained neighborhood villagers with the
          well-tested devices of fiddle music, the soldiers' dancing, 
          <name type="person" key="York">York's</name>exuberant jigging, and demonstrations of the
          airgun. They also needed to buy fish meal and edible dogs from the people they met, and
          so the underlying antipathy they felt did not surface visibly until they had reached the
          discomforts of the lower river.</p>
               <p>The transition into wetness was complete by the time the Corps reached the infamous
          rapids that became known, during immigrant days, as the Upper and Lower 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Cascades (Great Rapids, Great Shute)">Cascades
          of the Columbia</name>—rapids that gave their name to the mountain range through which
          the river bored. (Today those once powerful and startlingly beautiful waters are buried
          underneath the reservoir backed up by 
          <name type="place" key="Bonneville Dam">Bonneville Dam</name>.) Like the 
          <name type="place" key="Short (Little) Narrows">Short</name>and 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">Long
          Narrows</name>higher upstream, both Cascades were compression rapids, the confined
          waters rushing "in a most horriable manner" among a clutter of boulders "both large and
          small." 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>promptly named the Upper Cascade
          the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Cascades (Great Rapids, Great Shute)">Great
          Shute</name>(
          <hi rend="italic">sic</hi>).</p>
               <p>The 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Cascades (Great Rapids, Great Shute)">Great
          Shute</name>was so formidable that the captains decided they would have to portage the
          dugouts as well as the cargo around it. They accomplished the difficult feat by having
          the men place poles across the ragged crevices between the boulders littering the shore
          and then skidding the heavy boats across the timbers. The work, handicapped by rain and
          slippery footing, was so onerous that on reaching the Lower Cascade they decided to
          portage only their shrunken packs of merchandise and equipment and again risk the empty
          dugouts to the white turbulence. All five slammed through right side up.</p>
               <p>A briefly joyful climax rewarded them. Just beyond the bottom of the last rapid,
          under the shadow of a stone pillar almost nine hundred feet high called 
          <name type="place" key="Beacon Rock">Beacon Rock</name>, they encountered the first
          tides of the ocean they were striving to reach. It would come as a shock to learn,
          gradually, that in spite of the fluctuations, the sea was still more than a hundred
          miles away.</p>
               <p>They were miserable miles, even though the confining mountains soon gave way, in a
          stretch where the river ran northward, to broad, almost level forests broken by
          occasional prairies. For the days were short, fogs common, rains all but unending.
          Curious, light-fingered Indians were everywhere, some in high-prowed canoes that put the
          whites' clumsy dugouts to shame, others on the flat, tree-covered islands that dotted
          the widening river or in clearings on the shore. The natives carried guns, swords,
          sailors' clothing, copper and brass trinkets, and other articles that could have reached
          them only through white traders. And some of those traders, the Indians kept insisting,
          insofar as the Americans could read their gestures, lived in houses near the mouth of
          the river.
          <ref target="n1516" n="16"/>
               </p>
               <p>The increasing ambivalence with which the two races regarded each other became
          evident on November 4, on what is now 
          <name type="place" key="Sauvie (Wapato) Island">Sauvie Island</name>near present-day 
          <name type="place" key="Portland, Oreg.">Portland</name>. (The Corps was skirting the
          north shore of the big island; as a result they did not see the many-channeled mouth of
          the 
          <name type="place" key="Willamette (Multnomah) River">Willamette River</name>, which
          enters the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>from the south.) During the
          morning they landed at a village of twenty-five long houses. On the shore in front of
          the houses were fifty-two canoes, many very large and high in the bow. The inhabitants
          consisted of two hundred male 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skilloots</name>and their families, one
          of the many 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookan</name>bands. "We were treated
          very kindly by them," 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>wrote, "they gave us round root
          near the size of a hens egg roasted which they call 
          <hi rend="italic">Wap-to</hi>to eat." This was a happy introduction to a food more
          commonly spelled wapatoo (and known to later immigrants as swamp potato) that would
          serve the travelers well throughout the winter.</p>
               <p>After purchasing four bushels of the roots, the Corps went on several miles before
          pausing to eat. Hard behind them came several canoe-loads of armed 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skilloots</name>dressed in garish
          combinations of sailor clothing and native garb. This meeting was not as pleasant as the
          earlier one. The Indians, who were armed, were "assumeing and disagreeable, however we
          Smoked with them and treated them with every attention &amp; friendship." Taking
          advantage of the hospitality, the visitors adroitly purloined 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>pipe tomahawk and a capote
          belonging to one of the interpreters. At that the captains' tempers slipped the leash.
          While the soldiers held their rifles at ready, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>searched both the persons and boats
          of the Indians.</p>
               <p>In the captains' minds the effrontery was justified. "Finding us determined not to
          suffer any imposition . . . they showed their displeasure in the only way which they
          dared, by retreating in an ill humor to their village." But were the Indians pilfering
          as the word is defined by property-conscious Anglo-Saxons? Apologists say no and argue
          that the Indians were not appropriating the articles for personal gain, but to force the
          whites to notice them and enter into what one commentator calls "mutually rewarding
          reciprocal relations." All the Indians wanted was honest payment for the use of their
          territory, the theory holds.
          <ref target="n1517" n="17"/>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>On November 7, three days and roughly eighty river miles from the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skilloot</name>town, the explorers
          entered a broad indentation on the north side of the river. By then the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>, flowing mostly west again, was
          penetrating the 
          <name type="place" key="Pacific Coast">Pacific Coast</name>Range. The gentle banks that
          had prevailed farther upstream were gone. In their place were "high rugid hills with
          Steep assent the shore boalt [bold] and rockey, the fog so thick we could not See across
          the river." The tide was in, islands were numerous; without a hired Indian pilot, the
          travelers would have had difficulty finding the proper channel. (They also bought three
          dogs, some wapatoo roots, and salmon at the pilot's home village.) In the afternoon the
          fog lifted partially, though a light rain persisted, and they saw the great river of the
          West widening into what seemed an endless expanse of water. "Great joy in camp," 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>wrote. "we are in 
          <hi rend="italic">view</hi>of the 
          <hi rend="italic">Ocian</hi>... the great 
          <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific Octean</name>which we have been so long
          anxious to See, and the roreing or noise made by the waves brakeing on the rockey Shores
          (as I suppose) may be heard distictly."</p>
               <p>Technically he was wrong. Those waves were breaking on the steep shores of 
          <name type="place" key="Grays (Shallow) Bay">Gray's Bay</name>, and the ocean was still
          about twenty direct-line miles away. And yet psychologically 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>was right. 
          <name type="place" key="Grays (Shallow) Bay">Gray's Bay</name>had been named for the
          American ship captain 
          <name type="person" key="Gray, Robert">Robert Gray</name>, who, on the bright spring
          morning of May 11, 1792, had entered the mouth of the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>and a little later had anchored
          in that bay, the first white man to do so.
          <ref target="n1518" n="18"/>On entering the same bay from the east, the first whites to
          do so, the Corps of Discovery was finally tying the middle section of North America
          together.</p>
               <p>There were other reasons to celebrate. 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>had long since given up their
          initial plan, expressed in a letter of early April to 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">President Jefferson</name>, of returning at
          least as far as the headwaters of the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>before going into winter
          quarters. Now they were thinking in terms of the lower river. If a settlement, even a
          British settlement, did exist near the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia's</name>mouth, as they understood the
          Indians to say, many of the problems of wintering in the storm-swept land, among natives
          of unpredictable moods, would be largely solved. If there was no settlement, as the
          captains were inclined to believe, at least a trading ship was likely to appear—perhaps
          the one commanded by a Captain Haley, whose name was well and favorably known to the
          Indians. They could replenish their alarmingly depleted store of trade goods; they could
          send messages, specimens, and copies of their journals to 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, as he had requested. Above
          all, they would have the satisfaction of talking to others of their own kind, and of
          learning, in the language of home, what had been going on in the distant world during
          their long absence.</p>
               <p>And so there was joy in camp.</p>
               <p>Premature joy, as events developed. Because of frenzied weather and booming tides,
          they never did get their canoes to the river's mouth. Half of the group never did stand
          on the great north headland known as 
          <name type="place" key="Cape Disappointment">Cape Disappointment</name>and look across
          the white-capped rollers that were pounding toward the coast, uninterrupted, all the way
          from the Kuril Islands north of Japan.</p>
               <p>The miseries began in the very camp from which they peered with such joy at what they
          supposed was the ocean. The shore was so narrow they escaped high tide only by spreading
          their sleeping mats on heaps of round stones at the edge of the forest—in the rain,
          inevitably. The next day, November 8, they crept along the shore for a meager eight
          miles. The waves were high. The dugouts twisted and sheared and bobbed. Many of the
          crew—
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>listed 
          <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">Reuben Field</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Weiser, Peter">Peter Wiser</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="McNeal, Hugh">Hugh McNeal</name>, and 
          <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name>—vomited in agonized seasickness
          over the sides of the dugouts they were in. (What of the baby? No one says.) Giving up
          finally, they camped on a narrow shingle between the water and a hill too steep and
          brushy for the hunters to ascend in search of food.</p>
               <p>That night the roar of the rising tide awakened them. Scrambling to the dugouts, they
          unloaded them in the rain-swept darkness and boosted the baggage onto log platforms. The
          next day they spent struggling to keep the tossing boats from being crushed by
          gale-driven driftwood trees two hundred feet long and up to seven feet thick. But, 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>said, the men were still cheerful,
          thinking of the nearby ocean.
          <ref target="n1519" n="19"/>
               </p>
               <p>Whenever the gales slackened briefly during the next several days, the explorers
          reloaded the dugouts and rowed toward the next bay to the west—
          <name type="place" key="Baker (Haley's) Bay">Baker's Bay</name>, named by 
          <name type="person" key="Vancouver, George">George Vancouver's</name>men for a trader
          who had entered the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>only a few weeks behind 
          <name type="person" key="Gray, Robert">Robert Gray</name>. Trading ships often anchored
          there, or so the whites understood from Indian gestures. They might even find the
          rumored settlement. But the approach was blocked by a cliff-sided promontory later named
          
          <name type="place" key="Point Ellice (Point Distress)">Point Ellice</name>. (
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>labeled it 
          <name type="place" key="Point Ellice (Point Distress)">Point Dismal</name>on his sketch
          map.) Each time the dugouts neared the obstruction, screaming winds and heavy seas drove
          them back to a landing that seemed worse than the one before. In one place they had to
          build their fires and lay their beds on a driftwood raft that during high tide was "all
          on flote." In another place they sought to protect their canoes from the waves by
          filling them with rocks and sinking them.</p>
               <p>For eleven days and nights rain fell almost ceaselessly. Elkskin clothing and
          moccasins rotted. Tents and sails were in tatters. The Corps's merchandise, which was
          their only bank account, was constantly soaked and much was spoiled. Only occasionally
          were they able to spear a few salmon, shoot a few waterfowl, or buy a few roots from
          passing Indians. Otherwise they made their meals from the dry, pounded, tasteless fish
          they had laid by for emergencies far back at 
          <name type="place" key="Celilo (Great) Falls">Celilo Falls</name>. They watched
          enviously as the Indians rode as easily as gulls over the towering waves—"the best Canoe
          navigaters I ever Saw," 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>wrote. Resentment and frustration
          filled him: "the most disgreeable time I have experienced confined to a tempiest
          [tempestuous] coast wet, where I can neither git out to hunt, return to a better
          situation, or proceed on."
          <ref target="n1520" n="20"/>
               </p>
               <p>Gradually, though, they did proceed. First 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and a small advance party
          managed to break around 
          <name type="place" key="Point Ellice (Point Distress)">Point Dismal</name>into the
          eastern part of 
          <name type="place" key="Baker (Haley's) Bay">Baker's Bay</name>. From there they could
          see the full expanse of the five-mile-wide ocean gateway between 
          <name type="place" key="Cape Disappointment">Cape Disappointment</name>on the north and 
          <name type="place" key="Point Adams">Point Adams</name>on the south.
          <ref target="n1521" n="21"/>Neither town nor ship was visible. But some of the beaches,
          though windswept, were broad and sandy. An abandoned Indian settlement of thirty-six
          plank houses stood nearby; the ruins were full of fleas, but the Corps could take away
          enough boards to build shelters at a safe distance. Also nearby were two camps of
          Indians who called themselves 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinooks</name>—the first meeting of
          either captain with the dominant tribe of the area and one whose name soon spread
          generically to related bands speaking the same language. After sending a suggestion to 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>that the Corps move to this
          propitious spot as wind and tides allowed, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>continued west—on foot, because
          the waves rolling in from the sea were rougher than he wanted to attempt by boat. His
          intent: to investigate the bays on the coast north of 
          <name type="place" key="Cape Disappointment">Cape Disappointment</name>(
          <name type="person" key="Vancouver, George">Vancouver's</name>chart showed at least one)
          for possible ships and/or winter quarters.</p>
               <p>By the evening of the 16th, the rest of the Corps were ashore in 
          <name type="place" key="Baker (Haley's) Bay">Baker's Bay</name>, at a location northwest
          across the river from the present city of 
          <name type="place" key="Astoria, Oreg.">Astoria</name>, 
          <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>. The men worked busily at creating the
          first decent camp, relatively speaking, they had lived in for more than a week. When 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>party rejoined the main group
          on the 17th, morale was up again.</p>
               <p>Who else wanted a closeup view of the ocean that had been their goal across
          two-thirds of a continent? 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark</name>, born explorer and
          mapmaker, certainly did. He told all who wished to go with him to be ready at daylight
          on the 18th. At the appointed time he started hiking with 
          <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Sergeants Pryor</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>; 
          <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Weiser, Peter">Wiser</name>, and 
          <name type="person" key="Bratton, William E.">Bratton</name>; 
          <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name>, and 
          <name type="person" key="York">York</name>. 
          <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph and Reubin">Joseph and Reuben Field</name>, who
          had been with 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>party, went along for a second
          look. The rest of the Corps stayed put; they could see all the salt water they wanted
          from their new camp.</p>
               <p>After climbing to the rocky top of the cape and watching, in astonishment, giant
          breakers exploding against the cliffs, they turned north. They walked and slept in
          intermittent rains, crashed through brush, traversed grassy slopes, and carved their
          names on trees, as their predecessors had done. 
          <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">Reuben Field</name>shot a condor with an amazing
          wingspan of nine and a half feet. 
          <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">Reuben's</name>brother, 
          <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Joe</name>, killed a hitherto unknown species of
          black-tailed deer; it provided, on the morning of the 19th, "a Sumptious brackfest of
          Venison which was roasted on Stiks exposed to the fire." That same day 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>named a distant, striking height of
          land "after my particular friend 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>." Today it is known as North
          Head. They saw no ships, although they undoubtedly scanned the ocean's misty face as
          closely as 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>group had.</p>
               <p>Perhaps they wondered, as some later critics have, why 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">President Jefferson</name>did not send a
          ship to succor them.
          <ref target="n1522" n="22"/>Yet why should he have? Supposedly the expedition had left 
          <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>with all the equipment it
          needed. On April 7, 1805, at the time of departing from the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>villages, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>had written 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>that he expected to reach
          the 
          <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>and return at least as far as the
          headwaters of the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>before winter set in. He had said
          nothing about being short of supplies. Schedules could go awry, of course; indeed, the
          Corps might never reach the 
          <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>. In view of those uncertainties,
          exactly when should a reinforcing ship appear off the mouth of the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>? And would a Congress speckled
          with 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name>political enemies
          authorize outfitting a vessel—an expensive undertaking for an administration that
          trumpeted of economy—to circle 
          <name type="place" key="Cape Horn">Cape Horn</name>on so tenuous a mission? Sensing
          these deterrents long in advance, 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>had provided 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name>with the only
          reasonable escape available: the right to contact whatever trading vessels he saw for
          whatever he needed, even to returning home on one if such proved necessary.</p>
               <p>The right, however, did not bring a vessel with it. That being true, what should be
          done now?</p>
               <p>Making the decision seems to have plagued the captains more than any other problem
          they had faced so far. They hated to give up all hope of a vessel, and yet they could
          not stay in this estuary, exposed to an endless sequence of storms. A week's hard
          experience had showed them that they could not count on their guns to provide them with
          the food they needed, yet they did not have enough merchandise left to buy a winter's
          supply of food from the hard-bargaining Indians.</p>
               <p>If they did not stay, where should they go? The men who accompanied 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>to the coast expressed a desire to
          winter near 
          <name type="place" key="Celilo (Great) Falls">Celilo Falls</name>.
          <ref target="n1523" n="23"/>The climate there would be dry—but cold and short of the
          kind of large animals from which clothing could be made. Another possibility was the 
          <name type="place" key="Sandy (Quicksand) River">Sandy River</name>, which drained off 
          <name type="place" key="Mount Hood (Timm, Falls Mountain)">Mount Hood</name>into the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>a little west of the Lower
          Cascade. Meadows broke the forests there; deer would probably abound and the climate
          would be mild.</p>
               <p>So there was talk. Yet after 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>returned to the 
          <name type="place" key="Baker (Haley's) Bay">Baker's Bay</name>camp a little after
          midday on November 20, the days went by as though nothing serious pressed on anyone's
          mind. The captains made chiefs and distributed medals among the canoe-borne Indians who
          kept coming in and out despite a ferocious new storm. (
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>simply could not reconcile himself
          to such weather: "O! how horriable is the day waves brakeing with great violence against
          the Shore throwing the water into our camp &amp;c. all wet and confined to our
          Shelters.") Red traders, impervious to the deluge in conical hats tightly woven of split
          twigs, hawked their wares. Both 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>yearned for a luxurious robe of
          otter skins that one Indian would sell only for more blue beads, a valued medium of
          exchange throughout the Northwest, than the Americans could afford to dip out of the
          expedition's skimpy supply. Eventually they solved the problem by persuading 
          <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name>to part with a belt of blue beads
          she habitually wore around her waist; in return they gave her a blue cloth coat that was
          more adaptable than her buffalo-skin robe.</p>
               <p>Another trade article in great demand was produced by a 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinook</name>madam, wife of a chief,
          who showed up with six of her daughters and nieces "for the purpose of gratifying the
          passions of our men." 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>diary entries for November 21
          grew puritanical. The young women's countenances, he admitted grudgingly, were pretty—if
          one ignored their slanted foreheads. But they were short of stature, their hair hung
          loose and long, they had "large swelled legs &amp; thighs." Their limbs were tattooed.
          Venereal scabs were plain on some of them. They "sport openly with our men." But there
          was no use objecting: "we divided some ribin between our men . . . to bestow on their
          favorite Lasses, this plan to save the knives &amp; more valueable articles."</p>
               <p>What finally ended the indecision was the arrival, late on November 23, of seven 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsop</name>traders from the south
          side of the river. Undisturbed by the whites' refusal to buy the furs they offered for
          sale, the Indians cheerfully suggested their own territory as winter quarters. Over
          yonder, their gestures said, elk abounded, a source of food and of skins for clothing.
          The ocean and the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia's</name>estuary were close by. The
          first meant the whites could prepare salt to improve the taste of their food. The second
          would allow them to contact, through the Indians, any trading vessel that dropped anchor
          in the river's protected bays. The one obvious drawback would be living for months in
          the dreadful weather, as the newcomers considered it, of the coast.</p>
               <p>Reluctant to impose their own preferences on the men—nothing could be more damaging
          to already shaky morale—the captains called for a vote from everyone, soldiers,
          interpreters, black 
          <name type="person" key="York">York</name>and red 
          <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name>. A few favored going to 
          <name type="place" key="Celilo (Great) Falls">Celilo Falls</name>; more declared for 
          <name type="place" key="Sandy (Quicksand) River">Sandy River</name>. But the majority
          followed the captains in choosing the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsop</name>lands, with this
          qualification: if, after an examination, hunting and living conditions proved
          inadequate, they could move up the river.
          <ref target="n1524" n="24"/>
               </p>
               <p>On the 25th they started out. Not daring to risk the broad estuary in their log
          dugouts, they labored upstream to a narrower spot, crossed, and crept back along the
          shore to 
          <name type="place" key="Tongue Point (Point William)">Tongue Point</name>, a promontory
          about four miles long but only fifty yards wide at its narrowest section. They had
          succeeded in rowing around this obstruction when a new storm pinned them to its exposed
          ocean side.</p>
               <p>On the 29th 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, always impatient, broke loose.
          The big dugouts might not be able to handle the huge swells, but the small Indian canoe
          he had purchased at 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The
          Dalles</name>could. Accompanied by 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">Reuben Field</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name>, and 
          <name type="person" key="Labiche, François">Labiche</name>, he explored the coast of
          what 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>would later name 
          <name type="place" key="Youngs (Meriwether's) Bay">Meriwether Bay (now Young's
          Bay)</name>in his honor. After considerable trial and error, he found an inlet into
          which the 
          <name type="place" key="Lewis and Clark (Fort, Netul) River">Netul River</name>flowed.
          (Today it is the 
          <name type="place" key="Lewis and Clark (Fort, Netul) River">Lewis and Clark
          River</name>.) The party followed its windings through marshy ground thick with small
          trees and brush, a mix they called "slashes." The knolls rising out of the slashes
          supported much larger evergreens, and when they came to one whose top was some thirty
          feet above high tide level and when they saw elk tracks everywhere around it, they
          decided this would do for their winter camp. On the morning of December 5, three of them
          started back to summon the others. Two stayed behind to hunt. Nothing was said, at least
          in the journals, about a two-or three-week examination before a final choice was made.
          <ref target="n1525" n="25"/>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>Waiting for 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>return was another doleful
          experience for 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark</name>. Winds strong enough to
          blow down trees raged through the camp. Thick smoke from wet fuel hurt 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>eyes. The roar of the sea
          depressed him more and more. It had assaulted his ears for "24 days Since we arrived in
          Sight of the Great Western; (for I cannot say 
          <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>) Ocian as I have not seen one
          pacific day . . . [just] emenc waves . . . tempestous and horiable."
          <ref target="n1526" n="26"/>
               </p>
               <p>Though there were elk in the vicinity of 
          <name type="place" key="Tongue Point (Point William)">Tongue Point</name>, the hunters
          were rarely able to bring down one of the animals as they raced away among the thick
          trees and through the pelting rain. Except for occasional hawks and waterfowl, their
          food again was fish meal boiled in salty water dipped from the ocean side of the point.
          Digestive disturbances left 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>and some of the men too unwell to
          eat even that. Deciding the salt water was to blame, he directed the cooks to use fresh
          water from the upper side of the point. It helped, he thought.</p>
               <p>During the days of waiting he wandered around the vicinity, observing plants and
          wildlife and faithfully recording what he saw. It seems likely, too, that he passed some
          of the time reading from 
          <name type="person" key="Mackenzie, Alexander">Alexander Mackenzie's</name>account of
          his own crossing of the continent, with its climactic lines, "I now mixed up some
          vermilion, in melted grease, and inscribed, in large characters, on the South-East side
          of the rock on which we had slept, this brief memorial—'
          <name type="person" key="Mackenzie, Alexander">Alexander Mackenzie</name>, from 
          <name type="place" key="Canada">Canada</name>, by land, the twenty-second of July, one
          thousand seven hundred and ninety-three.' "</p>
               <p>With that in mind the American found a large tree and carved into its bark, "
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt William Clark</name>December 3rd 1805. By
          Land. U. States in 1804–05." In thus imitating 
          <name type="person" key="Mackenzie, Alexander">Mackenzie</name>, he may have only been
          reassuring himself in his doldrums. Or he may have been announcing to all who read his
          words, which he copied in his journal, that 
          <name type="person" key="Mackenzie, Alexander">Mackenzie's</name>feat had been matched.
          Or the lines may have carried implications of national sovereignty to come, as 
          <name type="person" key="Mackenzie, Alexander">Mackenzie's</name>most certainly had.</p>
               <p>Or perhaps all three motives were involved. Today there is no way to be sure.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="notes" type="notes">
            <head rend="center">Notes</head>
            <div type="section">
               <note xml:id="n1501" n="1">From 
          <name type="place" key="Canoe Camp (Idaho)">Canoe Camp</name>to the junction of the 
          <name type="place" key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Fork Columbia) River">
          Snake</name>and 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>: III, 97–119; 
          <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>, II, 407–26; 
          <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>in Quaife, 295–99; 
          <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse</name>in VII, 166–74. When 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>took over full responsibility for
          the journals on this stretch, he first prepared a rough draft, which generally included
          compass readings and mileage estimates between prominent points. When opportunity
          allowed, he elaborated on the other data in the draft. Thwaites presents each day's
          drafts in sequence. One should read both versions since the trial drafts sometimes
          convey incidents and impressions omitted from the final copy.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1502" n="2">III, 99. 
          <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>, II, 407. 
          <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse</name>, in VII, 168.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1503" n="3">III, 113. 
          <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>, II, 417.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1504" n="4">III, 115–16.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1505" n="5">At the junction of the 
          <name type="place" key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Fork Columbia) River">
          Snake</name>and 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>: III, 119–30.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1506" n="6">Sore eyes: III, 126; 
          <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>, II, 423; Cutright, Pioneering
          Naturalists, 223.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1507" n="7">The thought of tomahawking the frightened Indians appears in 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>rough draft, not in the finished
          one. (III, 133–36.) The run from the junction to 
          <name type="place" key="Celilo (Great) Falls">Celilo Falls</name>: III, 130–50; 
          <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>, II, 429–46; 
          <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>in Quaife, 100–104; 
          <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse</name>, in VII, 174–87.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1508" n="8">
                  <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name>: III, 136. See also ibid.,
          III.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1509" n="9">
                  <name type="place" key="Celilo (Great) Falls">Celilo Falls</name>through the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">Long
          Narrows</name>: III, 150–58. See 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>sketch maps, one as frontispiece
          of III, the other facing 158. Also 
          <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>in Quaife, 304–5; 
          <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse</name>, in VII, 182–88; Biddle,
          II, 429–48.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1510" n="10">III, 151.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1511" n="11">Water roaring through compressed straits tends to wear the
          confining stone into relatively thin strata. These layers cracked into pieces that
          looked like flagstones (
          <hi rend="italic">dalles</hi>) to French voyageurs who, after 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>time, took boats through the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>narrows for Canadian trading
          companies. Hence by association the rough-water stretch became known as 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The
          Dalles</name>—a name applied to several other North American rapids. Still later, 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The
          Dalles</name>, as a name, slid downstream to a mission station located just below the
          narrows. Today 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The
          Dalles</name>is a town—the only one in the U.S. with "The" as a legal part of its name. 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The
          Dalles</name>as white water have been lost under a reservoir's flat surface. For the
          area in 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>time: Josephy, 22–23; Ronda,
          173–74; Hodge under "Wishram" and "Vasco."</note>
               <note xml:id="n1512" n="12">III, 148, 155.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1513" n="13">III, 164. For the transit from the narrows through 
          <name type="place" key="Cascade Range">the Cascades</name>; III, 159–90; Riddle, II,
          448–64; 
          <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>in Quaife, 305–7; 
          <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse</name>in VII, 182–88. 
          <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse's</name>diary ends,
          incidentally, after his entry of November 6.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1514" n="14">III, 178.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1515" n="15">Ibid.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1516" n="16">The lower river to the estuary: III, 192–208; 
          <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>, II, 464–87; 
          <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>in Quaife, 307–9.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1517" n="17">The 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skilloot</name>encounter: III, 194–99; 
          <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>, II, 465–68; Ronda, 172,
          176.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1518" n="18">
                  <name type="place" key="Grays (Shallow) Bay">Gray's Bay</name>was named five months
          after 
          <name type="person" key="Gray, Robert">Gray's</name>discovery of the river by 
          <name type="person" key="Broughton, William">Lieutenant William Broughton</name>of 
          <name type="person" key="Vancouver, George">Vancouver's</name>fleet. 
          <name type="person" key="Broughton, William">Broughton</name>ascended the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>about a hundred miles in a ship's
          longboat during the latter part of October. By contrast, 
          <name type="person" key="Gray, Robert">Gray</name>had halted in the estuary; in 
          <name type="person" key="Broughton, William">Broughton's</name>opinion that didn't count
          as far as establishing national sovereignty was concerned. He named 
          <name type="place" key="Grays (Shallow) Bay">Gray's Bay</name>to emphasize his point:
          the American had gone no farther than that. 
          <name type="place" key="Baker (Haley's) Bay">Baker's Bay</name>, just west of 
          <name type="place" key="Grays (Shallow) Bay">Gray's Bay</name>, was named for an English
          trader who entered the estuary a few weeks after 
          <name type="person" key="Gray, Robert">Gray's</name>departure. (See Fuller, 56.)</note>
               <note xml:id="n1519" n="19">III, 211–14. For the problems of the estuary in general:
          III, 208–48; Biddle, II, 473–87; 
          <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>in Quaife, 309–14.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1520" n="20">III, 223.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1521" n="21">A good map of the estuary (but with inexact trails) is in
          Appleman, between pages 198 and 199. See also 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>sketch map in III, facing 234. 
          <name type="place" key="Cape Disappointment">Cape Disappointment</name>was named by the
          English trader John Meares in 1788. He had heard of a great river in the vicinity, but
          when he rounded the then-unnamed cape, he thought he was looking at another bay. The
          name reflects his feelings.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1522" n="22">Bakeless, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, 284. DeVoto, 
          <hi rend="italic">Course</hi>, 550. Dillon, 224.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1523" n="23">III, 231.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1524" n="24">III, 247–49, gives the votes and arguments, but contains
          several small, inexplicable inconsistencies.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1525" n="25">
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>kept a journal on November 29
          and 30, and then ceased again. Details of his search for the campsite have to be
          surmised from what 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>saw and briefly commented
          on.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1526" n="26">III, 263.</note>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.lavender.01.14" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.lavender.01.00" type="contents"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.lavender.01.16" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>