<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.sup.lavender.01.19">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Way to the Western Sea</title>
            <title type="sub">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> across the Continent</title>
            <title type="sub" level="a">Chapter 19</title>
            <author>David Lavender</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2005</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               
               
               
               
               
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Way to the Western Sea</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">Chapter 19</title>
               <author>David Lavender</author>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>2001</date>
               <idno type="ISBN">0-8032-8003-3</idno>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
              <term>Texts</term>
            </keywords>
           <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Books</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-11-09</date>
            <date>2005-04-20</date>
            <name>Becky Potter</name>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Split into chapters Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="nineteen" type="chapter">
            <head rend="center">NINETEEN. Hurrying Home</head>
            <div type="section">
               <p>
As <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> prepared to go their separate paths from <name type="place" key="Lolo (Traveler's Rest) Creek (Mont.)">Traveler's Rest</name> to the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, they began to wonder, inevitably, about ways to rescue the diplomatic assignments whose completion had eluded them on their way up the river. Except for their hard-earned horse herd they were dirt poor and could offer the Indians few shiny, colorful, mechanically helpful manufactured goods and inducements. How, then, could they persuade <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> chiefs to visit <name type="place" key="Washington D. C.">Washington</name> with them? How could they persuade the belligerent <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton Sioux</name> to quiet down and let the expedition pass safely along the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> with its Indian delegations, if any? How, indeed, could they purchase what they themselves would need for this last leg of their journey home?</p>
               <p>
Horses—perhaps they could provide the answers.<ref target="n1901" n="1"/> Horses could he traded for food and merchandise at the <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name>-<name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> villages. Properly manipulated, they might even be the key to making peace with the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>—if the Canadian fur trader, <name type="person" key="Heney, Hugh">Hugh Heney</name>, could he induced to come to the Americans' aid. A native of <name type="place" key="Montreal">Montreal</name>, <name type="person" key="Heney, Hugh">Heney</name> had become associated in the fur trade with another Canadian, <name type="person" key="Loisel, Régis">Regis Loisel</name>, head of the Spanish-licensed Missouri Company, operating out of <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>. In the strangely intricate ways of commerce, <name type="person" key="Heney, Hugh">Heney</name> also was connected with the North West Company of <name type="place" key="Canada">Canada</name>. His base, when <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had encountered him at the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> villages during the winter of 1804—5, had been one of the Nor'Westers' trading posts on the <name type="place" key="Assiniboine (Ossiniboine) River">Assiniboine River</name>.</p>
               <p>
He had been very cordial with the captains. He had showed <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Indian maps of the country west of the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> towns. He had given <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> a plant reputedly useful as an antidote to the bites of rattlesnakes and rabid wolves—a specimen so curious that <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> had sent it to <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, with a special note, when the keelboat went back down the river in April 1805.<ref target="n1902" n="2"/>
               </p>
               <p>
During the Corps's recuperative pause at <name type="place" key="Lolo (Traveler's Rest) Creek (Mont.)">Traveler's Rest</name>, June 30 through July 2, 1806, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> composed a long letter to <name type="person" key="Heney, Hugh">Heney</name> while sitting under a net to protect himself from mosquitos. The letter offered <name type="person" key="Heney, Hugh">Heney</name> a job pacifying the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton Sioux</name>, whom the Canadian knew well through his trading. If he succeeded—that is, if he freed the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> from harassment by the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>—he could look forward to being appointed U.S. Indian agent, salary $111 a month, at a trading post to be built at the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Cheyenne River">Cheyenne River</name>, assuming the government followed <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> recommendations. As a part of the pacification program, <name type="person" key="Heney, Hugh">Heney</name> should persuade several influential <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name> chieftains to accompany the captains "to the U. States, where they will have an ample view of our population and resources . . . and on their return convince their nations of the futility of an attempt to oppose the will of our government."<ref target="n1903" n="3"/>
               </p>
               <p>
That was where the horses came in. As soon as <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> detachment reached the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone</name> and no longer needed the animals, they would be entrusted to several soldiers under <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Sergeant Pryor</name> for delivery to the North West Company post on the <name type="native_nation" key="Assiniboine Indians">Assiniboine</name>. <name type="person" key="Heney, Hugh">Heney</name> could use twelve of them for purchasing the presents needed to win the good will of the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>. He could use three more for mounting himself and whomever he hired to help reach the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name> camps. He would receive a dollar a day salary and all expenses while he was on this mission, regardless of whether or not 
he won the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name> over. The captains would use whatever animals were left over for their own needs.</p>
               <p>
What the letter did not say, though <name type="person" key="Heney, Hugh">Heney</name> could fill in the silence well enough from his own knowledge, was that the <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> emissaries the captains hoped to enlist for a downriver trip would be more willing to go along if they knew the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name> had embraced American peace overtures. And then the letter did say that the expedition had reached the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> and that its planned exploration of a river they had named <name type="place" key="Marias River">Maria's</name> would soon push the American presence close to British claims along the <name type="place" key="Saskatchewan River">Saskatchewan</name>. The United States, in other words, was on the move and Britain's fur traders should know it. Yet they expected <name type="person" key="Heney, Hugh">Heney</name> to cooperate on an American plan concerning the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>. There always was a certain naiveté in <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> diplomatic thinking.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> was to carry the letter to <name type="person" key="Heney, Hugh">Heney</name> with him until he needed to hand it over to <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Sergeant Pryor</name> for delivery, along with the horses, to the Canadian trader. (At the time of <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Pryor's</name> departure, which would occur somewhere along the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone</name>, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> would make a copy for his records.) Between them <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Pryor</name> and <name type="person" key="Heney, Hugh">Heney</name> would decide on a place for meeting the expedition and reporting on results—perhaps even in the country of the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton Sioux</name>.</p>
               <p>
Arrangements completed, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> started north down the <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">Bitterroot River</name> toward <name type="place" key="Hellgate Canyon">Hellgate</name>. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> much larger party reined north up the stream, riding and driving a total of forty-nine horses and one colt. In his group were black <name type="person" key="York">York</name>, <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name>, <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name>, and her eighteen-month-old son <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Jean Baptiste">Jean Baptiste</name>, called <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Jean Baptiste">Pomp</name> by <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>. On this trip <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name> achieved a role of his own. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> identified him not just as an interpreter but, specifically, as
an interpreter for the <name type="native_nation" key="Crow Indians">Crows</name>, the only major tribe with whom the expedition as yet had had no contact. Until the <name type="native_nation" key="Crow Indians">Crows</name> received the American message, the explorers' survey of the upper <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri River</name> basin would not be complete.</p>
               <p>
It was a beautiful season for riding along the <name type="place" key="Bitterroot Valley">Bitterroot Valley</name>. To the east were the high, rhythmic swells of the <name type="place" key="Sapphire Mountains">Sapphire Range</name>; to the west, the jagged summits of the <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Snow) Mountains">Bitterroot Mountains</name>, culminating in what became known as <name type="place" key="Trapper's Peak">Trapper's Peak</name>. At 10,153 feet above sea level it rose more than a mile higher than the lush, well-watered valley floor with its "great variety of Sweet cented plants, flowers, and grass." The only disruptions to the serenity 
were the swollen streams that plunged out of the western range. The water was so swift that when the riders forded the creeks, the current hit the horses broadside with such force that it billowed over the backs of the smaller animals, wetting the baggage and causing more of what by then must have seemed interminable stops to dry the contents.</p>
               <p>
Late in the afternoon of July 5 they reached <name type="place" key="Ross's Hole">Ross's Hole</name>, the lovely basin where they had met the <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Flatheads</name> the year before. At that time the Indians had told them of a trail across the <name type="place" key="Continental Divide">Continental Divide</name> to the <name type="place" key="Beaverhead (Jefferson) River">Beaverhead</name> that would eliminate the arduous crossing to the <name type="place"
                        key="Salmon (Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">Salmon River</name> and the long ride to <name type="place" key="Lemhi Pass">Lemhi Pass</name>. Though it was a cold shortcut—hard frosts at night in July—it confronted the riders with neither steep, rocky climbs nor down timber, and it saved them two days of riding, by <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> estimate. The enormous vistas of the <name type="place" key="Big Hole (Sensable, Wisdom) River">Big Hole</name> Basin were stimulating, the camas lilies were beginning to touch the meadows with spots and streamers of blue, and <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name>, who as a child had visited the region with parties of <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name> root diggers, was able to point across the blue distance to gaps in the hills through which the explorers should make their way. On the afternoon of July 8, after covering 164 miles in six days, they reached the pond in which they had cached their dugouts the preceding August before tackling <name type="place" key="Lemhi Pass">Lemhi Pass</name>.</p>
               <p>
The first order of business was a frenzied unearthing of the caches by those who chewed tobacco, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> among them. They'd not had a chew since leaving <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name> and the strain, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> admitted, had been severe. After they had unearthed a few carrots of the stuff, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> gave each man a tangled strand two feet long; the rest was boxed for carriage in the dugouts down the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> to the portage at <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">Great Falls</name> and, eventually, to a rendezvous with
<name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> equally tobacco-starved group somewhere near the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Marias River">Marias</name>.</p>
               <p>
Comfort restored, they dragged the boats out of the pond. They had wintered well and repairs were quickly made. A high wind dried out the wood overnight, and on the frigid morning of July 10—three-quarters of an inch of ice on a cooking pot—down the <name type="place" key="Beaverhead (Jefferson) River">Beaverhead</name> they went, some in the dugouts and some coursing the banks with the horses. In spite of sore-footed animals, headwinds, the snakelike windings of the river, and a pause to make paddles out of the dugout <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had abandoned beside the stream the year before, the two units reached the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Three Forks of the">Three Forks of the Missouri</name> almost simultaneously at midday on July 13. The men must have bandied joyful remarks about the swiftness. The descent of the river from the caches had taken three and a half days; ascending the same stretch the previous year had required two and a half weeks.</p>
               <p>
They paused at <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Three Forks of the">Three Forks</name> only long enough to rearrange the baggage according to destination. At 5:00 P.M. <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> and nine men left in the dugouts for the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">Great Falls</name>. At the same time <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> and eight volunteers, together with <name type="person" key="York">York</name> and the <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name> family, turned the horse herd up the <name type="place" key="Gallatin (South, Southeast Fork) River">Gallatin</name> toward the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone</name>, or, as <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> persistently wrote the name, the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Rochejhone</name>, his version of the French Roche Jaune. As they traveled, he noted 
several buffalo and Indian trails leading toward a pronounced gap in the mountains eastward and some eighteen miles distant from where they were. He asked <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name> if they should go that way. She said no, the pass they wanted lay farther south—<name type="place" key="Bozeman Pass">Bozeman Pass</name>, to use its current name. A "great service," <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> commented. From that and a few other expressions of appreciation has sprung the overblown legend of <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name> the pathfinder. More statues, most of them showing her with her child on her back and her index finger pointing ahead, have been erected to her, it is said, than to any other American woman. These remarks are not intended to depreciate her charm and patient fortitude as a person.</p>
               <p>
The next day they floundered through a welter of marshes created by the overflowing of beaver ponds, worked up a fork of the <name type="place" key="Gallatin (South, Southeast Fork) River">Gallatin River</name> into the mouth of the pass, and camped.<ref target="n1904" n="4"/> At two in the afternoon of the following day they reached the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone</name> slightly below the gateway where it breaks swiftly and spectacularly out of the mountains. When <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name> killed a fat bull buffalo twenty-four hours later, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> devised a way of shoeing some of the sore-footed, far-traveled horses. He had the men cut the hide into pieces and make round bags for fitting over the hoofs of the lamest animals.</p>
               <p>
It had been the party's intention to make dugouts out of cottonwood trees as soon as they reached the river. The trees in the bottomlands were too small, however. They discussed making substitute boats out of buffalo hides and flexible willow poles, like those they had seen <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> women paddling up and down the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> near their villages. But the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone's</name> current looked dangerously swift, capable of carrying them without warning into rapids they could not manage in the fragile craft. So on they rode, driving the extra horses with them, looking for suitable trees and finding none, but marveling at such staggering numbers of buffalo, antelope, elk, and deer that <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> gave up trying to estimate how many. The tally was "increditable. I shall therefore be silent on the subject further."<ref target="n1905" n="5"/>
               </p>
               <p>
The problem of boats came to a head on July 18, some seventy-five miles down the river from the point where the cavalcade had first struck it. While running full speed after a buffalo, <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau's</name> horse stepped into a badger hole and catapulted the rider to the ground. He was not seriously hurt, but might have been. How would they have transported him then? Later that day, <name type="person" key="Gibson, George">George Gibson</name> forced the question. As he was trying to mount after killing a deer, his horse whirled and he fell backward onto a snag whose fire-blackened point drove two inches into "the Muskeler part of his thy." <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> dressed the wound, almost as rough a procedure as the piercing, and that night pain kept <name type="person" key="Gibson, George">Gibson</name> from sleeping. The next morning he could not ride, though the men padded his saddle with a buffalo robe and blankets and put him on the gentlest horse in the bunch. If the party was to avoid a long delay while he healed, they would have to build a boat in which he could stretch out.<ref target="n1906" n="6"/>
               </p>
               <p>
A diligent search through the groves in the nearby bottomlands revealed no cottonwood big enough for the dugout <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had in mind. (While combing the woods, the searchers did see a plume of smoke in the distance, but paid it little heed.) Of necessity <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> turned to what was available and had his axmen hew out of smaller trees a pair of canoes twenty-eight feet long, sixteen inches deep, and from sixteen to twenty-four inches wide. When the slim little craft were finished, he had them lashed together for greater stability.</p>
               <p>
The horses were sloppily guarded at night during the construction period, in spite of the smoke plume. On the morning of July 21, the camp awoke to find half the animals gone—stolen by Indians who knew their business, for they had either led or driven the horses in almost total silence across land so dry and hard their tracks could not be followed. Well, at least enough still remained to fund <name type="person" key="Heney, Hugh">Heney's</name> work with the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>.</p>
               <p>
While the canoes were being loaded, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> made a copy of the letter to the Canadian trader and then handed the original to <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Sergeant Pryor</name> for delivery. Privates <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name> and <name type="person" key="Windsor, Richard">Windsor</name> were assigned to help him drive the herd first to the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> villages and, if necessary, on to the <name type="native_nation" key="Assiniboine Indians">Assiniboine</name>. Three men, it developed, were not enough for the job. Most of the horses had been trained by the <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Percé</name> for buffalo hunting. Whenever they saw a herd of the shaggy beasts, they took after them pell-mell. Totally exasperated, <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Pryor</name> and his men drove the horses back to the river, intercepted the dugout, and asked for an additional man who could ride far ahead of the remuda to chase buffalo out of the way. <name type="person" key="Hall, Hugh">Hugh Hall</name>, who could not swim and was nervous in the crowded double canoe, volunteered for the job. He was practically without clothing, a lack that would do on the river but not on horseback. So <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> gave him "one of my two remaining Shirts a par of [hip-high] leather Legins and 3 pr. of mockersons," and sent him on his way.</p>
               <p>
It was not a way that was calculated to reduce <name type="person" key="Hall, Hugh">Hall's</name> fear of water. Two days after the quartet had left the main group, Indians stole the rest of the horses. Desperate, the four whites pursued the raiders afoot, gave up, and returned to their camp. Packing their gear on their backs, they struck for the river. Their first plan was to build a single leather boat, the hair still on the hide, that all four men could crowd into with their bits of baggage. But if that boat overturned and dumped them, their rifles, and their powder into the water, they would not be able to hunt for food. So they decided that in spite of their hurry to catch <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, they had better construct two bull boats and divide themselves and their essential possessions between them.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name> produced the buffalo. From the skins they cut out circular pieces of hide big enough to form basins seven feet three inches in diameter at their tops. Each was sixteen inches deep. They tied inch-thick willows together to form, for each boat, two hoops, one for the top rim and a smaller one for the bottom. They crisscrossed fifteen inch-thick, flexible willow sticks to form the frame. They tied the pieces of frame to the rim and to each other 
where they crossed with leather thongs. They then waterproofed the surfaces with melted buffalo fat mixed with ashes. The sealing was not impervious; every night they would have to take the boats out of the water and turn them upside down to let the leather dry.</p>
               <p>
Down the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone</name> they went, two men in each craft. The man in front knelt, reached over the rim, and drew his crudely whittled paddle toward him rather than working it off to the side. Paddles were used, too, to keep the round vessels from spinning. The second man, though also equipped with a paddle, acted mostly as ballast. Undoubtedly the men changed places from time to time, and one assumes <name type="person" key="Hall, Hugh">Hugh Hall</name> quickly learned how to manage his fear of water. They bobbed without trouble down one rapid where <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, still far ahead, lined his double canoe through with ropes. Their only adventure came one night when a wolf slipped into the camp, bit the sleeping <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Pryor</name> in the hand, and was swinging around to attack <name type="person" key="Windsor, Richard">Windsor</name> when <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name> awakened, grabbed his rifle, and put an end to that. Reading of the episode today, one suspects rabies. <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Pryor</name>, however, showed no such symptoms, and his hand healed cleanly.<ref target="n1907" n="7"/>
               </p>
               <p>
His party reduced to nine persons by the departure of the horses, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> wooden dugouts floated briskly ahead on a fast current. The day after the parting from <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Pryor</name>, he spotted a flat-topped butte rising in isolation from the bottomlands. Landing, he and the others walked through the tall grass and among the scattered trees to look it over. <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea's</name> baby was of toddling age by then, but she probably carried him to keep him from holding her back, for she was curious and wanted to see everything, just as she had wanted to see the beached whale on the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name> shore. The butte, an odd erosional remnant, turned out to be four hundred paces in circumference. Its sides were gray, gritty cliffs two hundred feet high and unscalable except where they were broken on the northeastern side by a steep gully.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> clambered up the break with an unspecified number of his crew. Just below the rim, where Indians had left many petroglyphs, he carved his name and the date into the soft stone. (The graffiti, protected now, is still visible.) On top he found two Indian cairns and a delightful prospect of distant mountains and of "the extensive country around, and the emence herds of Buffalo, Elk and wolves in which it abounds." Did <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name> toil up that far with little <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Jean Baptiste">Baptiste</name> on her back? It is impossible to be sure. Still, it is intriguing to try to read <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> mind at that particular moment. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and he had already named streams for <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name> and <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name>. One or the other of them had named, or soon would name, other landmarks for every member of the expedition, including themselves and the dog <name type="person" key="Seaman">Seaman</name>. And suddenly <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark</name> thought "This rock . . . I shall call <name type="place" key="Pompeys Pillar (Pompy's Tower)">Pompy's [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>] Tower</name>." Today it is called <name type="place" key="Pompeys Pillar (Pompy's Tower)">Pompey's [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>] Pillar</name> through vague association with Pompey's Pillar in ancient <name type="place" key="Egypt">Egypt</name>. But <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark</name> meant <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Jean Baptiste">Pomp</name>, his nickname for little <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Jean Baptiste">Jean Baptiste Charbonneau</name>, of whom he had grown very fond. It is also the nickname he used many years later for one of his own sons.<ref target="n1908" n="8"/>
               </p>
               <p>
On they went, "glideing down this Smooth Stream passing maney Isld. and Several Creeks and brooks." The noise of buffalo at night so disturbed the men's sleep that they would jump up with shouts of rage and fire guns to scare the beasts away. They filled <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> with alarm lest the marching columns of them trample their boat to pieces. Occasionally the travelers had to sit on the banks while herds miles long swam across the river ahead of them. Elk 
were almost as numerous. Although <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> count of the game killed is not always as specific as <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>, it is clear that in the presence of such animal wealth his party was equally unrestrained. They killed to get skins for shelter, for clothes, for trade. And for fun. Why not? They were living off the country, and all their exuberance after so many hungry days west of the divide was not making the slightest dent in the vast, rich life around them. Yet like frontiersmen throughout the continent they were helping create, bit by bit, an American attitude with each unnecessary shot they fired. One thinks of Africa today.</p>
               <p>
Each evening <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> wrote down his impressions of the countryside they had passed. He made detailed sketch maps of the part of the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone</name> they covered. He noted seams of coal that might be useful sometime in the future. (This was near the <name type="place" key="Powder (Wah-har-sa, Redstone) River">Powder River</name>, where many years later gargantuan machines would tear the ground apart, strip mining for energy.) He collected botanical and zoological specimens. One day he walked so far up the tributary <name type="place" key="Bighorn (Ar-sar-ta) River">Bighorn</name>, wondering about its course, that on his return to camp he went straight to bed, too fatigued to eat. In anticipation of meeting roving parties of <name type="native_nation" key="Crow Indians">Crow Indians</name>, he prepared an elaborate "Children" speech for them. His goal was to lure some of their chiefs to join him—and, he hoped, some <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> chiefs as well—for a visit to the great father, <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Thomas Jefferson</name>, "and receive from his own mouth his good counsel and from his own hands abundant gifts."<ref target="n1909" n="9"/> No <name type="native_nation" key="Crow Indians">Crows</name> rode to the riverbanks to greet the whites, however, for probably members of the tribe were the ones who had stolen the whites' horses and they were keeping out of sight. Their absence left a disappointing gap in the expedition's surveys.</p>
               <p>
On August 3, they entered the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>. There was no sign of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>. Strangely, there were no buffalo in the vicinity, either. But there were excruciating swarms of mosquitos. Looking for a place where the party could find more of the one and fewer of the other while they waited for <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, they drifted on.</p>
               <p>
At 8:00 A.M. on August 8, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> was astonished to see <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Pryor</name> and the horse herders come bobbing around a bend in two skin boats. With growing dismay he listened to their story. So much for <name type="person" key="Heney, Hugh">Hugh Heney</name> and the plan to quell the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>. And for the captains' hope of using the extra animals for buying from the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name> corn, beans, and whatever else they needed for the rest of the trip to <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>. The only bargaining substitutes for the horses he could think of were deer- and elkskins. In order to provide as many as possible, he decided to lay over for a day and turn his hunters loose. He also built, at another camp farther down the river, a rack on which meat could be dried, for that commodity, too, had some trade value.<ref target="n1910" n="10"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Disturbing portents continued to pile up. On August 11, the contingent met the <name type="place" key="Illinois">Illinois</name> trappers, <name type="person" key="Hancock, Forest">Forest Hancock</name> and <name type="person" key="Dickson, Joseph">Joseph Dickson</name>. From them <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> picked up information that the wounded <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> must also have learned but for some reason had failed to record. The pair said that they and a trader whose name <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> recorded as Ceautoin had spent the winter with the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Tetons</name> and had been ill treated. So that band was as bad as ever. The <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name>, the trappers went on, were fighting with the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> again. So much for the peace the captains thought they had established between those tribes during the spring of 1805. So much, too, for their hope of persuading influential <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> chiefs to run the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name> gauntlet with the Corps in order to reach <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> and <name type="place" key="Washington D. C.">Washington</name>. The mess looked bad, at least as the trappers described it. Yet the explorers had to tidy it up somehow, or the ambitious Indian program they had believed was in their grasp a year ago would evaporate. Well, at least they would have <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> persuasive oratory to rely on, or so <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> thought.</p>
               <p>
That comfort, too, collapsed when he rejoined <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> party and saw how disabling his friend's wounds were. Clearly <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> would not be able to participate in the councils <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> felt had to be held when they reached the <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> villages a few days thence.</p>
               <p>
Indians riding along the bank saw them coming and spread the word. By the time the little fleet hove in sight, the river's edge was lined with crowds. Salutes of gunfire rattled back and forth. After pausing at the two lower <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> towns to greet friends and prepare groundwork for the meetings, the whites moved on and camped between the clusters of dome-shaped, earth-covered huts that made up the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> towns. When the grand council assembled, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> delivered the usual pitch about going "to see their great father and hear his good words &amp; receve his <hi rend="italic">bountiful gifts</hi> [<name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> emphasis]." The chiefs were amiable and heaped the visitors with gifts of corn. But whenever <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> thought one was on the point of agreeing to take the trip, minds changed. They feared the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>, they said, and did not believe <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> insistence that he would keep them safe, both during the trip down and on their return. His nerves tightening, he scolded the <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name> for sending war parties against the <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name> in violation of their promise to be peaceful. (But where, except on the warpath, could a young man prove himself?) He was mocked in turn for boasting, during the Corps's first visit to the villages, that the Americans had won promises of good behavior from the allied <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> when, in fact, warriors of those tribes had attacked people from the <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> towns as if nothing had changed. (Could old alliances and ingrained hostilities be changed by words from the outside?)</p>
               <p>
In a final attempt to sway <name type="person" key="Le Borgne (One Eye)">Le Borgne</name>, the grand chief of <name type="place" key="Big Hidatsa site">Big Hidatsa town</name>, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> fired off the swivel gun that had once been mounted on the keelboat but had proved unsuited to the white pirogue. He then ceremoniously gave the weapon and some powder to <name type="person" key="Le Borgne (One Eye)">Le Borgne</name>. The chief was delighted, but still declined to join the fleet. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> must have felt totally frustrated. Were the failures somehow his? There is no evidence that <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> attended any of the councils (as yet he could not walk) or that he would have made any difference if he had. The two cultures, red and white, were talking on different levels.</p>
               <p>
At some point during the verbal seesawing, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> may have created trouble for himself by making a reckless promise to <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Toussaint Charbonneau</name>. He told him that if any <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> chiefs joined the expedition, he would hire <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name> as interpreter. <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name>, furthermore, could bring <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name> and his son <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Jean Baptiste">Pomp</name> along. If he chose to remain near civilization at the end of the trip,<name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> would help him find employment. <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name> merited a reward for her services to the Corps, and "As for your little Son (my boy <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Jean Baptiste">Pomp</name>) you well know of my fondness for him and my 
anxiety to take him and raise him as my own child." When no <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name> would agree to go along, the proposal died. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, however, offered to take <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Jean Baptiste">Pomp</name> down without his parents, educate him, and help him become a trader. It was an obtuse statement for him to make at the time, for he must have noticed that the child, in keeping with Indian custom, was not yet weaned though nineteen months old by then. The parents declined. Next year, perhaps....<ref target="n1911" n="11"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Quite possibly, that rascally trader to the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>, <name type="person" key="Jusseaume, René">JRené essaume</name>, learned of the proposal. Anyway, he was prepared when <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, trying to salvage some crumb from the councils, asked his help in persuading a <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> chief to join the trip. If <name type="place" key="Jusseaume, René">René</name> was successful, he would be hired to go along as interpreter. <name type="person" key="Jusseaume, René">Jessaume</name> responded with a vengeance. He won over <name type="person" key="Big White (Sheheke)">Sheheke</name> (<name type="person" key="Big White (Sheheke)">Big White</name>), a chief of the lowest village and a friend from the days of the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> wintering, by promising that the Americans would transport not only <name type="person" key="Big White (Sheheke)">Sheheke</name> and his wife and son but also <name type="person" key="Jusseaume, René">Jessaume's</name> wife and two children. "we were obliged to agree," <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> wrote angrily, with no way of foreseeing that a few years later the bargain would help bring about <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis's</name> death.</p>
               <p>
One last parting remained. The trappers <name type="person" key="Dickson, Joseph">Dickson</name> and <name type="person" key="Hancock, Forest">Hancock</name> had followed the explorers to the villages, hoping at first to prevail on some French-Canadian voyageur to join them as helper. The plan shifted when they talked to <name type="person" key="Colter, John">John Colter</name>. Stirred by his stories, they asked whether he could obtain an early discharge from the army and join them as a partner. Forgetting the joys of civilization, which perhaps were not joys to him, <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name> said he'd try. The captains, feeling his exceptional work on the trip had earned him this opportunity, agreed—with one proviso, which they explained at a meeting of the men. <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name> would be free to go if no other enlisted man asked for a release before the expedition arrived at <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>. The soldiers shouted compliance; everyone, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> included, chipped in to give the new civilian traps and supplies, and away he paddled with his new friends. Where the trio wintered is unknown. <name type="person" key="Dickson, Joseph">Dickson</name> and <name type="person" key="Hancock, Forest">Hancock</name> vanish from the records, but during the next few years <name type="person" key="Colter, John">John Colter</name> became one of the heroic figures in that surge of trappers and traders—the mountain men—who were the true pathfinders of the American West.</p>
               <p>
On August 17, having fastened two dugouts together with poles and having perhaps put a platform on the poles as a houseboat of sorts for <name type="person" key="Big White (Sheheke)">Sheheke's</name> and <name type="person" key="Jusseaume, René">Jessaume's</name> families, the Corps of Discovery left the villages, bucking high waves created by the unremitting winds of the plains. The 19th turned out to be a red-letter day. "<name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis'es</name> wounds," <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> wrote, "are healing very fast, I am in hope of his being able to walk in 8 or 10 days." Later, when the party camped, <name type="person" key="Jusseaume, René">Jessaume</name>, after eyeing an approaching rain cloud, loaned <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> a piece of a tepee. The two Indian women "Stretched it over Some Sticks, under this piece of leather I Slept dry, it is the only covering which I have had Sufficient to keep off rain Since I left the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>." The next morning, following a downpour at dawn, he boasted smugly, "all wet except myself and the Indians."<ref target="n1912" n="12"/> Sleeping wet and cold during four months and more than fifteen hundred miles of travel through frequent and often violent storms—of such glum realities are high adventures made.</p>
               <p>
They were moving fast now. On the 21st, a short distance upstream from the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> towns, they met three French traders, one of whom, a mere lad, they let join them as an oarsman. From the others they learned that, yes, <name type="person" key="Gravelines, Joseph">JoeGravelines</name> had taken an <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> chief downstream on the keelboat in the spring of 1805, as scheduled. Rumor said the chief had died somewhere in the United States; anyway, he had not returned home. Bad news, but in spite of it the captains were determined to meet <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name> instructions by rounding up a few more <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> chiefs to travel East with them, for the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> occupied strategic sites along the riverbanks and, unless they were turned into allies, could cause trouble to future traders. After ordering the men to check their guns, on they went to the Indians' towns.</p>
               <p>
It was another fruitless meeting despite considerable puffing of smoke and exchanging of gifts. Both the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> chiefs and <name type="person" key="Big White (Sheheke)">Big White</name>, the latter speaking for the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>, blamed the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name> for breaking the peace. But, they all said solemnly, their ears were open now; they understood what the Americans were saying; there would be no more trouble. As for visiting the Great Father, not yet. First they wanted to talk to the chief who had been there. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> carefully refrained from mentioning the rumor he had heard, and found solace by spreading the Corps's message to a band of wild <name type="native_nation" key="Cheyenne Indians">Cheyennes</name> from the <name type="place" key="Black Hills">Black Hills</name> who were visiting the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> to trade. No, they'd not visit the Great Father, either. But they had many beaver in their land and would be glad if Americans visited them.<ref target="n1913" n="13"/> That, at least, was a small gain.</p>
               <p>
On the 22d <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> walked for the first time; on the 27th, pushing himself too hard with characteristic impatience, he broke the wounds open and was immobilized again. So when they sighted the first <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton Sioux</name> on August 30, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had to set the whites' course of action alone, except for the assistance of <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Cruzatte</name> and <name type="person" key="Labiche, François">Labiche</name>, who knew a smattering of the Sioux language. There were eighty or ninety of them, mounted, silhouetted strongly on the skyline across the river from the explorers' anchored boats. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> meant to keep them at a distance, but he also wanted them to know how he regarded them: they were the spoilers of all he and <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> had worked for on the upper <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>. He rowed in a small canoe with his interpreters to a sandbar in midstream. Several Indians rode to the water's edge on their side of the stream. Dismounting, three young men swam to the bar. Grimly <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> cut off their overtures. Using some of the signs he had learned and letting <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Cruzatte</name> and <name type="person" key="Labiche, François">Labiche</name> supply such words as they knew, he used the trio as a conduit for roasting the entire tribe. Even <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo">Black Buffalo</name>, who had acted with more restraint than any of the other Indians of the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name> band during the confrontation of two years ago, was unacceptable, and the encounter ended with threats, insults, and jangled nerves all around.<ref target="n1914" n="14"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Except for a brief meeting with some noisy <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Yankton">Yankton Sioux</name>, it was their last significant encounter with Indians. Travel grew tiresome, partly because of the crew's own impatience to reach home. The heat was often suffocating. Repeatedly <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> complained to his journal, "Musquetors troublesom." Lightning storms flared. Buffalo disappeared; deer and elk, whose presence could not always be depended on, became the main source of food. The Indian passengers fussed; the children cried. But by September 9, "My worthy friend <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Cap Lewis</name> has entirely recovered ... can walk and run nearly as well as ever he could."<ref target="n1915" n="15"/>
               </p>
               <p>
As they neared and then passed the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Platte River (Nebr.)">Platte</name>, they encountered increasing numbers of traders whom they hungrily asked for news of the outside world. On September 12, at about the point where the city of <name type="place" key="Saint Joseph, Mich.">St. Joseph</name>, <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, now stands they met a party of old friends. Joe <name type="person" key="Gravelines, Joseph">Gravelines</name> was one; <name type="person" key="Dorion, Pierre, Sr.">Pierre Dorion</name>, the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name> interpreter whom they had commissioned to take some <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Yankton">Yankton</name>
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>, <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Omaha</name>, <name type="native_nation" key="Oto Indians">Oto</name>, and <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> chiefs to <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> and <name type="place" key="Washington D. C.">Washington</name>, was another. The third was <name type="person" key="McClellan, Robert">Robert McClellan</name>, an army scout who had gained a deserved reputation for derring-do 
during the Indian wars in the <name type="place" key="Ohio River">Ohio</name> country.<ref target="n19unnumbered" n="*"/> The three were associated in a common project that spelled one more defeat for <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Gravelines, Joseph">Gravelines</name> told the story. After a debilitating illness and fits of indecision in <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>, the missing <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> chief had gone to <name type="place" key="Washington D. C.">Washington</name> with twenty-seven other Indians, traveling by rented horse, boat, and stagecoach. No, those others had not been the <name type="native_nation" key="Oto Indians">Otos</name>, <name type="native_nation" key="Missouri Indians">Missouris</name>, <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Omahas</name>, and <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Yankton">Yankton Sioux</name>
                  <name type="person" key="Dorion, Pierre, Sr.">Dorion</name> had collected for the trip. <name type="person" key="Dorion, Pierre, Sr.">Dorion's</name> Indians, stranded in red tape, some of them ill, and all of them bored, had finally left <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> for home. Better if the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> had followed suit. He died during the <name type="place" key="Washignton D. C.">Washington</name> jaunt. Worried about the repercussions this might have on the tribe, <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> had sent <name type="person" key="Gravelines, Joseph">Gravelines</name> back up the river with a letter of condolence to the tribe and three hundred dollars' worth of presents for the chief's family and influential friends. Dorion had been hired to help <name type="person" key="Gravelines, Joseph">Gravelines</name> pass the unruly <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton Sioux</name> and, if possible, recruit new chiefs to replace those who had dropped out in 1805. <name type="person" key="McClellan, Robert">McClellan</name> was going along with a few soldiers as bodyguard. He was instructed to search for some trace of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> expedition, of whom nothing had been heard for more than a year.<ref target="n1916" n="16"/>
               </p>
               <p>
The newly found captains had no way of foreseeing, of course, how these frayed Indian junkets they had been instrumental in launching would come back to haunt them. After spending the night with their friends, the Corps rose early, downed a dram <name type="person" key="McClellan, Robert">McClellan</name> provided for everyone—they had been dry for a long, long time—and set out a little after sunrise, pummeled by headwinds as they worked through an "eme[n]city of Snags" and sawyers. More traders hailed them and, learning who they were, offered the soldiers all the liquor they could drink, which was considerable. Hunting grew poor. Soon they had no food other than a few "buiskits" and papaws they gathered in the hot bottomlands. Then only papaws remained. Never mind: home was close: "the party appear perfectly contented, and tell us they can live very well on papaws."</p>
               <p>
Endless sun glare on water: on September 20, three of the crew were unable to row "from the state of their eyes." Accordingly the captains abandoned the double canoe <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had built on the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">River Rochejhone</name> and put the three ailing members in other dugouts. Their companions, "being extreemly anxious to get down ply their oars very well." As they neared <name type="place" key="La Charette, Mo.">La Charette</name>, westernmost village on the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri River</name>, "we saw cows on the bank [plain, ordinary, wonderful cows] which caused a shout to be raised for joy." Springing to their oars, they soon reached the village itself and swung in beside five trading barges tied to the bank. Because the men were in the army still, they requested permission to fire a three-round salute, with cheers. Granted. Villagers poured to the docks, dumbfounded. Back from the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>! "every person, both French and americans seem to express great pleasure at our return"—but not so much pleasure that the tavernkeeper neglected to charge eight dollars, in cash, for two gallons of whiskey the captains bought for the men. An imposition, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> grumbled to his diary.</p>
               <p>
Because another rain threatened, the citizens opened their doors to the soldiers. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> accepted the invitation of two Scotch traders, <name type="person" key="Reed, James">James Reed</name> and <name type="person" key="Crooks, Ramsay">Ramsay Crooks</name>, who later became field manager of <name type="person" key="Astor, John Jacob">John Jacob Astor's</name> American Fur Company, to share dinner with them and sleep in their tent.<ref target="n1917" n="17"/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> does not say so, but there must have been endless questions. Places that before had been names too dim even to picture—upper <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone</name>, <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">Great Falls</name>, <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rockies</name>, <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>—what <hi rend="italic">were</hi> they like? What of their plants and animals? Their people?</p>
               <p>
The rain thrummed on the canvas. The candle guttered. Those sky-filling peaks, snowy even in the summer, the buffalo herds, trees so big it was an affront to the listeners to expect them to believe what they heard, Indians skimming the stormy seas in a way to put white boatmen to shame—how was it possible to make them comprehend?</p>
               <p>
But somehow, and very soon, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark</name> were going to have to find ways to tell <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">President Jefferson</name> and the American Philosophical Society, and, indeed, the whole nation just what was out there in the West.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         
      </body>
      <back>
        
        <div xml:id="notes" type="notes">
          <head rend="center">Notes</head>
          <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n1901" n="1">I assume and perhaps oversimplify the steps by which the captains arrived at this idea. But since they do not say how the notion developed, "educated guesswork" seems to be the only substitute.</note>
            <note xml:id="n1902" n="2">Jackson, <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, 214n, 220–21. Nasatir, <hi rend="italic">Before <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>
            </hi>, 112–14.</note>
            <note xml:id="n1903" n="3">Jackson, <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, 309–13.</note>
            <note xml:id="n1904" n="4">V, 260. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> journal says his party traveled 4 miles before camping. His "Course Distance" gives 6 miles. He estimates the distance from <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Three Forks of the">Three Forks</name> to the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone</name> as 48 miles. It is about 40. Throughout the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone</name> exploration <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> overestimated distances, sometimes by as much as one hundred percent. (V, 262, 264; Brown, 35.)</note>
            <note xml:id="n1905" n="5">V, 290.</note>
            <note xml:id="n1906" n="6">V, 272–76.</note>
            <note xml:id="n1907" n="7">V, 325–26.</note>
            <note xml:id="n1908" n="8">Bakeless, <hi rend="italic">
              <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>
            </hi>, 349–50.</note>
            <note xml:id="n1909" n="9">V, 299–301.</note>
            <note xml:id="n1910" n="10">
              <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> tucks into the middle of his diary entry for August 10 an exact copy of the description of a "singular cherry," with which the wounded <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, lying on his stomach, closed his entry of August 12. Although the wording is definitely <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>, my hunch is that <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> spotted the plant ("I found a Sepies of Cherry ..." he wrote) and took along a sprig to show his friend. Later, while bringing his notes up to date, he borrowed <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> botanical description of what was <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> discovery. (V, 243–44, 328.)</note>
            <note xml:id="n1911" n="11">The councils: V, 338–46; <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>, III, 775–81; Ronda, 244–48. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>  interest in <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau's</name> family: V, 344; Jackson, <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, 315–16.</note>
            <note xml:id="n1912" n="12">V, 348–49.</note>
            <note xml:id="n1913" n="13">V, 349–57.</note>
            <note xml:id="n1914" n="14">V, 365–68.</note>
            <note xml:id="n1915" n="15">V, 380.</note>
            <note xml:id="n1916" n="16">V, 382–83. Jackson, <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, 242–43, 261. Lavender, Fist, 64, 72.</note>
            <note xml:id="n1917" n="17">V, 389–90. Lavender, Fist, 78, 80.</note>
          </div>
          <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n19unnumbered" n="*" type="footnote">
              <name type="person" key="McClellan, Robert">Robert McClellan</name> first heard of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> from the captains that September, as did <name type="place" key="Crooks, Ramsay">Ramsay Crooks</name>, a young Scot whom they would meet a week later at <name type="place" key="La Charette, Mo.">La Charette</name>. In 1811 both <name type="person" key="Crooks, Ramsay">Crooks</name> and <name type="person" key="McClellan, Robert">McClellan</name> went to the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> on a nearly disastrous trip with a group of overland Astorians.</note>
          </div>
        </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.sup.lavender.01.18" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.sup.lavender.01.00" type="contents"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.sup.lavender.01.20" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
