<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.sup.johnsgard.01.01">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Lewis and Clark on the Great Plains</title>
            <title type="sub">A Natural History</title>
            <title type="sub" level="a">Chapter 1</title>
            <author>Paul A. Johnsgard</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               
               
               
               
               
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title level="m" type="main">
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> on the <name type="place" key="Great Plains">Great Plains</name>
               </title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">Chapter 1</title>
               <author>Paul A. Johnsgard</author>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <publisher>Center for Great Plains Studies, University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
               <date>2003</date>
               <idno type="ISBN">0-8032-7618-4</idno>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
              <term>Texts</term>
            </keywords>
           <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
             <term>Books</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-10-07</date>
            <date>2004-10-26</date>
            <name>Becky Potter</name>
            <name>Andrew Jewell</name>Split into chapters Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="ch1" type="chapter" n="1">
            <head rend="center">Historical Overview</head>
            <p>When <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark</name> set off up the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri
River</name> in mid-May of 1804 with their 26-man contingent (3 sergeants,
22 privates, and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> slave <name type="person" key="York">York</name>) and about 10 additional
boatmen and interpreters, they had no detailed knowledge of what lands or
adventures lay before them. When the group returned more than two years
later, in late September of 1806, they had made more discoveries of landscapes,
rivers, native cultures, zoology, and botany of our continent than has any North
American scientific expedition, either before or since. They traversed upstream
across the entire <name type="place" key="Great Plains">Great Plains</name> region, which for present purposes is defined as
including that part of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> Valley between the current <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>-<name type="place" key="Kansas">Kansas</name>
border and the vicinity of <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Three Forks of the">Three Forks</name>, <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>, where three mountain-fed
rivers merge to form the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>. By the time they reached what is now western
<name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name> in late July of 1805 and were about to challenge the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rockies</name>, they
had already ascended nearly 4,000 feet of elevation. They also had explored and
carefully described roughly 2,500 river miles of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> Valley since leaving
the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi River</name>, a task that by itself represents a heroic if not Herculean
physical effort.</p>
            <p>Over the 14-month period during which the explorers crossed the <name type="place" key="Great Plains">Great
Plains</name> on their way to the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name> they collected specimens of plants later found
to represent at least 20 new species, not counting an unknown number of additional
specimens that either were lost or damaged beyond repair in the course
of the expedition or have disappeared from any present-day museum or herbarium
records. </p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> also discovered or carefully described for the first time at
least seven <name type="place" key="Great Plains">Great Plains</name> species of mammals, including the pronghorn, grizzly
bear, swift fox, black-tailed prairie dog, white-tailed jackrabbit, bushy-tailed
woodrat, and mule deer. The Columbian ground squirrel was first encountered,
and thus discovered, in western <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>, but it was not carefully described
until after the group arrived in <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>. Several <name type="place" key="Great Plains">Great Plains</name> birds representing
new genera (depending on the taxonomy source chosen) were described for
the first time, including the greater sage-grouse, common poorwill, McCown's
longspur, and <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> namesake species, the Lewis's woodpecker. The woodpecker,
whose previously unique genus <hi rend="italic">Asyndesmus</hi> has recently been merged
with <hi rend="italic">Melanerpes</hi>, was first seen along the edge of the <name type="place" key="Big Belt Mountains">Big Belt Mountains</name> near
present-day <name type="place" key="Helena, Mont.">Helena</name>, <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>. However, this woodland-edge woodpecker was
not actually collected until the following spring, near <name type="place" key="Kamiah, Idaho">Kamiah</name>, <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>. A skin
of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> woodpecker is in Harvard University's Museum of Comparative
Zoology and is perhaps the only remaining intact museum specimen of all the
animals collected during the expedition. The least tern was also carefully described
and measured, based on two specimens they had shot. There can be no
doubt that these five species of birds, at minimum, were discovered by <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>
and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> on the <name type="place" key="Great Plains">Great Plains</name>.</p>
            <p>In his valuable summary of the natural history of the entire expedition,
Paul R. Cutright listed a total of 30 then-undescribed vertebrate species or subspecies
that were noted by <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> during the <name type="place" key="Great Plains">Great Plains</name> phase and
possibly as many as 9 additional ones that were encountered but not adequately
described to identify them with certainty. Virginia Holmgren more recently
summarized the bird discoveries of the entire expedition, listing 25 that she believed
were sufficiently well described to warrant "discovery" status, 9 species
that might have been considered as newly discovered if they had been better
described, and 11 species that were already well known by some common
name but had not yet been formally described and named scientifically. In the
category of definitely discovered <name type="place" key="Great Plains">Great Plains</name> birds, she listed the trumpeter
swan, greater sage-grouse, semipalmated plover, mountain plover, upland sandpiper,
long-billed curlew, least tern, common poorwill, Lewis's woodpecker,
Sprague's pipit, McCown's longspur, western meadowlark, and Brewer's blackbird.
Of these, the mountain plover and upland sandpiper are distinctly questionable
as to their identification. There is no evidence that the highly elusive
Sprague's pipit (<hi rend="italic">Anthus spragueii</hi>) was ever seen, and the "small Kildee" observed
along the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri River</name> was probably the piping plover rather than
the migratory and arctic-breeding semipalmated plover (<hi rend="italic">Charadrius semipalmatus</hi>).
The identities of several <name type="place" key="Great Plains">Great Plains</name> shorebirds mentioned briefly by
<name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, such as the mountain plover and long-billed curlew, are especially
problematic, as they used terms like "plover" and "curlew" rather indiscriminately
for shorebirds generally. The tundra swan (<hi rend="italic">Cygnus columbianus</hi>)
(previously known as the whistling swan) was initially described from observations
made by <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> during the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>-slope phase of their expedition,
but it or the trumpeter swan was seen earlier in what is now <name type="place" key="North Dakota">North Dakota</name>.
The trumpeter swan is the semiresidential breeding swan of the northern plains,
whereas the arctic-breeding tundra swan is a spring and fall migrant only. Thus,
the chances of their having seen the trumpeter swan on the northern plains
were fairly good. At least eight previously unknown species—the trumpeter
swan, greater sage-grouse, piping plover, least tern, common poorwill, Lewis's
woodpecker, McCown's longspur, and western meadowlark—are well enough
documented to count as having certainly been seen by <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, and
the greater sage-grouse, least tern, and Lewis's woodpecker were as carefully
described as any practicing ornithologist of the day might have done. </p>
            <p>Among reptiles and fishes, the western rattlesnake, western hognose snake,
cutthroat trout, blue catfish, channel catfish, goldeye, and mountain sucker are
certain or likely to have been newly discovered species. Several <name type="place" key="Great Plains">Great Plains</name>
mammal and reptile species that were known but only poorly documented,
such as the bison, gray wolf, coyote, western garter snake, and bullsnake, were
described by <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> to a much greater degree than previously known.
Many other plains animals that later were determined to represent new subspecies
of previously known species were described, or at least mentioned, for
the first time.</p>
            <p>For the trip collectively, nearly 100 previously unknown species or subspecies
of vertebrate animals were encountered and variously described by <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and
<name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, judging from a recent summary by the Sierra Club. About 40 percent of
these now have a state- or federal-level designation indicating that active protection
or conservation concern is warranted. Of these, 13 species are now classified as nationally endangered, including such classic <name type="place" key="Great Plains">Great Plains</name> animals as the
gray (prairie) wolf, whooping crane, and the interior race of the least tern. <name type="place" key="Great Plains">Great
Plains</name> species that were seen by the expedition members but are now federally
threatened include the piping plover and grizzly bear. In the past two centuries
the grizzly bear has changed from being the commonest large carnivore of the
upper <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> Valley to having been completely eradicated from it. Similar
comments might be made of the gray wolf and the whooping crane.</p>
            <p>Cutright listed a total of 22 new plant species collected by <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>
during their journey upstream between the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Kansas (Decaugh, Kaw) River">Kansas River</name> and the
vicinity of <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Three Forks of the">Three Forks</name>, <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>. They include such plants as Indian tobacco
(a species not native to the northern <name type="place" key="Great Plains">Great Plains</name>), curly-top gumweed, and
three species of sagebrush. A surprising number of the plants they collected were
species believed by Native Americans to possess medicinal or other functional
properties, and thus were very familiar to and highly valued by the tribes of the
upper <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> Valley. Most of them are now considered only to be weeds, and
none is listed as threatened or endangered.</p>
            <p>The expedition's return trip across the <name type="place" key="Great Plains">Great Plains</name> in 1806 was entirely
downstream and consequently much faster, thus accounting for the expedition's
far fewer zoological or botanical discoveries. However, at least five <name type="place" key="Great Plains">Great Plains</name>
plants collected during the return trip were later described as new species, according
to Cutright. These included salt sage, red false mallow, gumbo evening
primrose, black greasewood, and snow-on-the-mountain. These discoveries
primarily consisted of plants obtained by <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Lewis</name> while exploring the
upper <name type="place" key="Marias River">Marias River</name> valley of northwestern <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>. Although no new plants
were obtained, several new topographic features and some significant wildlife
observations were documented by <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain Clark</name> on his separate route down
the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone River</name>.</p>
            <p>Frederick Pursh initially examined 155 of the roughly 200 plant specimens
that successfully made their way back to the safety of the American Philosophical
Society collections in <name type="place" key="Philadelphia, Pa.">Philadelphia</name>. At the time he published his studies
(1814), he classified four of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> specimens as representing new
genera and 123 as new species. A recent summary by James Reveal, Gary Moulton,
and Alfred Schuyler indicate that Pursh associated the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> materials
with 132 botanical names, 94 of which were newly proposed by him and
nearly all of which were taxonomically valid. These authors also determined
that <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> collected at least 202 different kinds of plants. However,
many of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> specimens have since been lost. If all the plants encountered
and variously described but not necessarily preserved by <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and
<name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> during their entire expedition are tallied, 176 previously unknown species
or subspecies can be listed, judging from a recent summary by the Sierra Club.
At least 17 new plant species were discovered while the explorers were in the
<name type="place" key="Great Plains">Great Plains</name> region. Gary Moulton has summarized the specimen and archival
data from all the herbarium sheets currently known to exist in volume 12 of
his definitive 13-volume <hi rend="italic">Journals of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition</hi>. Names of
the plants mentioned here follow this reference, sometimes with parenthetical
synonyms of Latin or English vernacular names that have appeared in relevant
literature, such as the books of Paul Cutright and Raymond Burroughs. The
plants and animal species described in the text are arranged in alphabetic sequence
using English names, and both the Latin and English names are those
currently recognized as official. Alternate names given in quotes, including a
few place names, are those used by <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, and their often innovative
spelling has in such cases been retained.</p>
            <p>In the course of the expedition the group lived off the land, killing and eating
almost anything they could. Burroughs compiled a list of game killed in
the course of the expedition, largely for human consumption. At minimum, it
included 1,001 deer, 35 elk, 227 bison, 62 pronghorns, 113 beaver, 104 geese and
brant, 48 shorebirds ("plovers"), 46 grouse, 45 ducks and coots, and 9 turkeys.
They also killed 43 grizzly bears, 23 black bears, 18 wolves, and 16 otters. This
level of resource exploitation marked the beginning of a century of unrestrained
wildlife slaughter in America, ending in the elimination of the bison, elk, gray
wolf, and grizzly bear from the <name type="place" key="Great Plains">Great Plains</name>, and the complete extinction of the
passenger pigeon, Carolina parakeet, and Eskimo curlew.</p>
            <p>Exactly a century after the beginning of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> expedition
(1903), President Theodore Roosevelt established in Florida the first of our national
wildlife refuges, and the long road toward the preservation and restoration
of our wildlife resources was at last under way. There are now more than 530
national wildlife refuges in the United States, of which the Charles M. Russell
National Wildlife Refuge in <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name> is much the largest of those situated along
the Lewis and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> route. There are 20 national grasslands, totaling 4 million
acres, 17 of which are in the western <name type="place" key="Great Plains">Great Plains</name> from <name type="place" key="North Dakota">North Dakota</name> and <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>
to <name type="place" key="New Mexico">New Mexico</name> and <name type="place" key="Texas">Texas</name>. There are now also 155 national forests, covering
almost 200 million acres, including the Lewis and Clark National Forest, located
between the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> and <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone</name> Rivers of <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>. Also, there are 300
Indian reservations, now still home to members of about 500 tribes; ten of these
reservations occur along the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri River</name> between <name type="place" key="Nebraska">Nebraska</name> and <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>,
some of them supporting direct descendants of the people first encountered by
<name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>.</p>
            <quote>
               <lg type="linegroup">
                  <l>I shall vanish and be no more,</l>
                  <l>But the land over which I now roam</l>
                  <l>Shall remain, and change not.</l>
               </lg>
               <bibl>
                  <hi rend="italic">Anonymous <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Omaha</name> Indian</hi>
               </bibl>
            </quote>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.johnsgard.01.ack" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.johnsgard.01.00" type="contents"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.johnsgard.01.02" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
