<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.lc.almost">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of Lewis and Clark: Almost Home</title>
            <title type="sub"/>
            <title type="sub"/>
            <author>Gary E. Moulton</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic
        Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
              <bibl></bibl>
          </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-07-14</date>
            <date/>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>
            <name/>Initial creation Transcribed</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-04-12</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="main">The Journals of Lewis and Clark: Almost Home</head>
         <head type="sub"/>
         <div type="article">
            <p>
               <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/lc.moulton.xml" rend="new">by Gary E.
        Moulton</ref>
               <lb/>
               <lb/>(This essay first appeared in 
        <hi rend="italic">
                  <ref target="http://www.his.state.mt.us/pub/magazine/" rend="new">Montana: The Magazine of
          Western History</ref>
               </hi>, Volume 48, Summer 1998, pgs. 72–79.)</p>
            <p>Meriwether Lewis and William Clark have been called "the writingest explorers of their
        time." President Thomas Jefferson instructed them to keep meticulous records on the
        geography, ethnology, and natural history of the trans-Mississippi West they explored from
        1804 to 1806. In leather-bound notebook journals they filled hundreds of pages with such
        observations, and the result is a national treasure: a complete look at the Great Plains,
        Rocky Mountains, and Pacific Northwest, reported by men who were intelligent and well
        prepared, at a time when East Coast Americans knew almost nothing about those regions.</p>
            <p>A narrative based on the journals was published in 1814. Most of the journals were then
        deposited in the American Philosophical Society in Philadelphia, but they lay largely
        unused and almost forgotten for nearly a century until an edition of all known materials
        was published in 1905. That work, edited by Reuben Gold Thwaites, was a superb tool for
        studying the expedition, but over the years it suffered the kinds of erosion that besets
        all such editions: new manuscripts were discovered; new information became available with
        which to annotate the journals; and editorial procedures underwent profound changes. These
        deficiencies led to a project to publish an entirely new comprehensive edition of the
        journals.</p>
            <p>A new and complete edition of the journals of the Lewis and Clark expedition had been a
        hope of scholars and enthusiasts for many years before the project I am just completing
        began. Donald Jackson, an expedition scholar, may have been the first to call for a new
        edition in a presentation in 1967. Jackson noted what had been apparent for some time:
        that using the multiple published editions of the journals was difficult and that some
        kind of unified work was needed. At the time there were at least five different versions
        of expedition materials, some out of print and in varying degrees of completeness. But
        Jackson's call for action went unheeded for nearly a decade.</p>
            <p>In 1977 an article recommending reissuing Lewis and Clark's epic work caught the
        attention of Steve Cox, then of the University of Nebraska Press. Cox turned to the
        university's 
        <ref target="http://www.unl.edu/plains/" rend="new">Center for Great Plains Studies</ref>to
        discover the level of interest. Established just the preceding year, the center grew out
        of a desire of university professors to take a broad approach to studying the Great
        Plains. The center's board of directors embraced the idea of sponsoring a new edition of
        the journals immediately. They knew that Lewis and Clark were the first Americans to cross
        and describe the Great Plains and that much of the territory that the captains were
        assigned to examine lies within the region.</p>
            <p>The center then moved to discover the feasibility of such an endeavor. Don Jackson,
        serving as a consultant, sought the cooperation of manuscript-holding institutions and
        ascertained the availability of financial support. His work was a success throughout. Not
        only did all the institutions with Lewis and Clark journals agree to share their materials
        with the anticipated project, but the principal holding institution, the 
        <ref target="http://www.amphilsoc.org/" rend="new">American Philosophical Society</ref>,
        came on as cosponsor.</p>
            <p>The next step was to hire an editor. The university showed its commitment to the plan
        by providing an appointment slot in the appropriate department to the successful
        candidate. I was the fortunate person selected as editor and came to Lincoln with a
        position in the history department.</p>
            <p>My entry into the world of Lewis and Clark was quite indirect. My wife Faye saw an ad
        for the editorial position in a professional journal in 1978 and encouraged me to apply.
        That I was to be unemployed the next year was a compelling incentive. My professional
        interests in the American West, Native Americans, and historical editing gave me an edge.
        In fact, I was just completing editing the papers of Chief John Ross of the Cherokees,
        supported for four years by the National Historical Publications and Records Commission
        (NHPRC) of the National Archives.</p>
            <p>I must admit that I had no special knowledge of Lewis and Clark. Indeed, I probably
        knew less about the expedition than many of you reading this essay. My greatest assets
        were my abilities as a historical editor— who had proven that he could get an editorial
        project launched, funded, and finished in reasonable time. I was a little embarrassed when
        I first met Don Jackson and he spoke on the finer points of the expedition while I
        cautiously nodded my head in feigned acknowledgment. He also told me of an organized group
        of expedition enthusiasts, the 
        <ref target="http://www.lewisandclark.org/" rend="new">Lewis and Clark Trail Heritage
        Foundation</ref>, whose members would query me closely on minute details of expedition
        history. He said that I better get the story straight and know the precise location of
        places like the Lolo Trail. Again, I nodded knowingly, although I hadn't the faintest idea
        where or what the Lolo Trail was. I hit the books right way.</p>
            <p>So by mid-1979 the project to publish a completely reedited version of the journals was
        under way at the University of Nebraska with me as editor. The edition was co-sponsored by
        the Center for Great Plains Studies and by the American Philosophical Society, with the
        cooperation of all the manuscript-holding repositories. The 
        <ref target="http://www.nebraskapress.unl.edu/" rend="new">University of Nebraska
        Press</ref>had agreed to be the publisher. The 
        <ref target="http://www.archives.gov/nhprc_and_other_grants/index.html" rend="new">
        NHPRC</ref>had endorsed the project and the 
        <ref target="http://www.neh.gov/" rend="new">National Endowment for the Humanities
        (NEH)</ref>, a principal funding agency for editorial projects, had our first grant
        application. We were ready to go.</p>
            <p>Lest you think that it was all too easy, let me say that our first application to NEH
        was turned down. It did not help my self-esteem when reviewers, panelists, and Endowment
        administrators liked the project but were not so sure about me. They could see I knew very
        little about Lewis and Clark. I could not do much about that right away, but I did rewrite
        the proposal, cutting the monetary request and trying to correct some deficiencies. The
        new downsized proposal, with appended letters extolling my editing skills and with extra
        financial support from the university, was accepted in 1980. NEH has funded the project
        generously ever since. That fact, along with reviewers' accolades and editorial prizes
        since then, have more than made up for the initial rebuke.</p>
            <p>In later allocations NEH stipulated that the project had to find private matching money
        to go along with the endowment's outright award. On the second grant I had to secure more
        than $42,000 in outside money over three years to tap a like amount from NEH and meet our
        budgetary needs. That sum was an incredible amount of money to me. The American
        Philosophical Society and the University of Nebraska Foundation came up with about half of
        it, but even then I needed more than $20,000, still a lot of money. Fortunately, I had
        already begun to make friends with Lewis and Clark buffs and one, Robert Levis of Alton,
        Illinois, told me to drop him a line if I ever needed any help. Now I sent Bob a well
        thought out and carefully worded letter and was astonished when he replied that he would
        be happy to cover the entire amount. But that wasn't necessary because I soon met Robert
        Betts of New York City at a Lewis and Clark conference in Philadelphia. At a candlelight
        reception in Independence Hall he told me he wanted to give the project $5,000 but then
        handed me a check for $7,500, saying he'd sweetened the pot a little. These individuals
        and ten other private supporters, plus the Lewis and Clark Trail Heritage Foundation, have
        aided the project financially over the years. Their gifts lifted my spirits as much as
        they filled the project's coffers. Ready money makes editing easier.</p>
            <p>When completed 
        <ref target="n01" n="1"/>the 
        <ref target="http://www.nebraskapress.unl.edu/Catalog/ProductSearch.aspx?filter=&amp;search=&amp;cid=0&amp;sort=Name&amp;itemsperpage=10&amp;view=List&amp;currentpage=&amp;pf=&amp;sf=&amp;sj=283"
                    rend="new">new edition</ref>will number twelve regular volumes and a 
        <ref target="http://www.nebraskapress.unl.edu/product/Definitive-Journals-of-Lewis-and-Clark-Vol-13,672833.aspx"
                    rend="new">comprehensive index</ref>, including an 
        <ref target="http://www.nebraskapress.unl.edu/product/Journals-of-the-Lewis-and-Clark-Expedition-Volume,671334.aspx"
                    rend="new">atlas of maps</ref>, the journals of Lewis, Clark, 
        <ref target="http://www.nebraskapress.unl.edu/product/Definitive-Journals-of-Lewis-and-Clark-Vol-9,672070.aspx"
                    rend="new">John Ordway, Charles Floyd</ref>, 
        <ref target="http://www.nebraskapress.unl.edu/product/Definitive-Journals-of-Lewis-and-Clark-Vol-10,672071.aspx"
                    rend="new">Patrick Gass</ref>, and 
        <ref target="http://www.nebraskapress.unl.edu/product/Definitive-Journals-of-Lewis-and-Clark-Vol-11,672072.aspx"
                    rend="new">Joseph Whitehouse</ref>—all the extant journals of the expedition—a 
        <ref target="http://www.nebraskapress.unl.edu/product/Definitive-Journals-of-Lewis-and-Clark-Vol-12,672832.aspx"
                    rend="new">volume of the expedition's botanical specimens</ref>, and an 
        <ref target="http://www.nebraskapress.unl.edu/product/Definitive-Journals-of-Lewis-and-Clark-Vol-13,672833.aspx"
                    rend="new">index</ref>. When Don Jackson initially proposed the venture, he projected an
        edition of nine volumes to be completed in nine years. That was unrealistic and may have
        been a ploy to entice funding agencies that were beginning to worry about editing projects
        that seemed to have no end. By the time I was knowledgeable enough about the endeavor to
        make some projections, I was counting eleven volumes to be completed in seventeen years.
        We altered that somewhat when the press suggested separating the journals of Patrick Gass
        and Joseph Whitehouse into two volumes and printing the comprehensive index as an
        individual book. Those changes and the vicissitudes of editing added two more years.</p>
            <p>The first volume of the new edition, 
        <ref target="http://www.nebraskapress.unl.edu/product/Journals-of-the-Lewis-and-Clark-Expedition-Volume,671334.aspx"
                    rend="new">Atlas of the Lewis and Clark Expedition</ref>, was published in 1983. The maps
        were published first so they could be used as a resource and reference tool for succeeding
        volumes. Not all of the 129 historic maps in the atlas came directly from the hand of
        Clark, the principal mapmaker, but all were closely associated with the expedition and
        most of them were Clark's handiwork. Being my first foray into expedition materials, I was
        amazed at the beauty, elegance, and precision of Clark's cartography. With no apparent
        training, working with crude and often unreliable instruments, and using dead reckoning
        for distances, one stands in awe of his draftsmanship. Clark's maps are a model of
        cartographic excellence, and his example was admired and emulated by generations of
        explorers and mapmakers.</p>
            <p>We had some difficult decisions to make concerning the publishing of the maps. I knew
        we did not want to have them folded up and slipcased in the way Thwaites had presented
        them. His atlas volume, numbering 53 maps, was the book probably most in need of revision.
        Working with Richard Eckersley and others at the press, we finally decided to go with a
        large-sized book, nearly fourteen by twenty inches. Even with this big book all sorts of
        design problems bedeviled us—Clark's erratic orientation of the maps, the difficulties of
        following from one route map to another, composite maps that interrupted the route maps,
        gaps in maps, missing maps, multiple maps, and questionable maps—all called for decisions
        in areas that were entirely new to me.</p>
            <p>I was lucky that W. Raymond Wood, a professor from the University of Missouri, was in
        Lincoln for a year during this time. Ray, an expert on the exploration and cartography of
        the Missouri River, was a great help to me, as was John Allen, a geographer at the
        University of Connecticut and the leading authority on expedition geography. Also, Richard
        Eckersley was remarkable at finding ways to solve the most vexing of design dilemmas. He
        also came up with the idea to put a wavy blue line across the Atlas cover and then a
        trailing wavy line across the spine of the journal volumes. The Atlas is now out of print
        <ref target="n02" n="2"/>, very expensive on the rare book market, and nearly impossible
        to find. The press may reprint the Atlas in the next few years; the journal volumes have
        been reprinted as necessary and are readily available.</p>
            <p>The journal volumes presented their own set of challenges. I decided to keep Lewis and
        Clark's materials together and to publish the diaries of the enlisted men in separate
        volumes. This follows the plan adapted by Thwaites and for many reasons seemed the most
        sensible approach. I also kept Thwaites's chapter divisions except for some small
        modifications. His chapters followed those of the 1814 edition and were now quite familiar
        to readers. I thought readers might want to compare text from each of the three major
        editions and this would facilitate such a study. Journal 
        <ref target="http://www.nebraskapress.unl.edu/Catalog/ProductSearch.aspx?filter=&amp;search=&amp;cid=0&amp;sort=Name&amp;itemsperpage=10&amp;view=List&amp;currentpage=&amp;pf=&amp;sf=&amp;sj=283"
                    rend="new">volumes 2 through 8</ref>cover the diaries of Lewis and Clark and were
        published between 1986 and 1993. Volumes 
        <ref target="http://www.nebraskapress.unl.edu/product/Definitive-Journals-of-Lewis-and-Clark-Vol-9,672070.aspx"
                    rend="new">9</ref>, 
        <ref target="http://www.nebraskapress.unl.edu/product/Definitive-Journals-of-Lewis-and-Clark-Vol-10,672071.aspx"
                    rend="new">10</ref>, and 
        <ref target="http://www.nebraskapress.unl.edu/product/Definitive-Journals-of-Lewis-and-Clark-Vol-11,672072.aspx"
                    rend="new">11</ref>comprise the enlisted men's journals—they were published in 1996 and
        1997—and 
        <ref target="http://www.nebraskapress.unl.edu/product/Definitive-Journals-of-Lewis-and-Clark-Vol-12,672832.aspx"
                    rend="new">volume 12</ref>, the botany book, is now in press. We look to complete the
        project this year, but the 
        <ref target="http://www.nebraskapress.unl.edu/product/Definitive-Journals-of-Lewis-and-Clark-Vol-13,672833.aspx"
                    rend="new">comprehensive index</ref>will not be available until next year, making the
        entire undertaking a 20-year endeavor from beginning to absolute end.</p>
            <p>The principal goal of the new edition is to present users with a reliable, definitive
        text. Earlier editors, pressed for time and working virtually alone, were not able to make
        multiple and careful readings of their transcriptions against the original text. Perhaps
        that explains why one editor had Clark struggling to the top of a hill near the Pacific
        Coast and saying, "I cue my hare [hair]," when the captain actually wrote that he had cut
        his hand. Every effort was made now to prepare an accurate transcription that is nearly
        identical to the original text. The new edition will also give readers a thorough
        explication of the journals. Scholars have been hampered by the paucity of notes in
        earlier editions and users complained about inaccuracies and obsolescence. We aimed to be
        thorough, accurate, and complete in our annotation, but we understood that we were
        preparing source material to be borrowed from and enlarged on and we were not supposed to
        be writing essays in the notes. The notes in the new edition are full, but we hope not
        rambling. Our general rule on annotation was to treat matter in the notes in relation to
        its prominence in the text.</p>
            <p>After the exhilaration of publishing the atlas volume, I knew that I now faced the hard
        task and daily grind of editing the journals. Seeing the atlas in print was probably the
        high point for me in this long process. I now felt somewhat confident that I could do the
        work, and with a book in print I could be fairly certain of continued financial support.
        As I delved into the journals more deeply, however, I began to think the NEH people were
        onto something when they questioned my abilities. All that botany, all that zoology, those
        astronomical readings, the geology, archaeology, ethnology, linguistics, meteorology, and
        medicine to be annotated and understood. What was a mere historian doing among all this
        science? I knew about as much about binomials as do Beavis and Butthead. Was I out of my
        depth? Was I out of my mind?</p>
            <p>I had quite a few fitful nights before it came to me—consultants. Hadn't the great
        captains welcomed native guides in order to accomplish their explorations, I reasoned? Of
        course, I had already had the help of Ray Wood and John Allen on the Atlas, and I also had
        the center's list of Great Plains scholars. These people provided wonderful assistance in
        numberless disciplines. My problem at first was that I did not know the questions to ask
        or the language to use. I was addressing specialists in areas that were completely foreign
        to me. They displayed the patience of Job, especially when I had to call for multiple
        rewrites of submitted material. I thought that if I could understand the explanations of
        the captain's scientific endeavors, then other readers could also. Later I got into the
        wide world of Lewis and Clark and discovered experts in every conceivable area. I know I
        could not have completed this project without the assistance of these specialists and
        dedicated lay people. Our guides were friendly, wise, and generous. Over the years the
        project has utilized the talents of more than one hundred people as consultants and
        friendly advisors.</p>
            <p>The most difficult areas to annotate were in geology and botany, largely because I was
        least knowledgeable about the subjects and was slow to find the right people to help me.
        Once I secured the services of Robert N. Bergantino of Butte, Montana, for aid in geology
        questions, and the advise of A. T. Harrison, formerly of Lincoln but now in Sandy, Utah,
        in botany, I could move the process along. I would print out journal entries that
        pertained to geology or botany, highlight the appropriate passages, provide the date and
        place, and ask Bob or Ty for some explanation. In time, back came carefully worded notes
        for each item. Often I would do a rewrite to make the phrasing conform to our other notes
        or to remove some scientific jargon or awkward language. Some notes called for a long
        series of correspondence, phone calls, and lengthy discussions in order to get the wording
        scientifically correct but universally understandable. As you can guess, this process was
        repeated many times and across all the disciplines with which I was unfamiliar.</p>
            <p>Linguistics, another field of study for the captains, proved the most demanding and
        time-consuming for me. Following Jefferson's instructions, Lewis filled numerous loose
        sheets with vocabulary notes as he passed through an incredible array of native languages.
        These notes are now lost, and what is left are incidental and irregular jottings in the
        journals of native terms. I initially resisted assuming the task of annotation and had the
        support of some linguists who thought the small amount of linguistic material in the
        journals did not call for the efforts that we would have to expend to explain them. Truth
        is, I was looking for a way to extricate myself from the morass of science, not seeking to
        add another branch.</p>
            <p>A conference of specialists convinced me otherwise. Moreover, I obtained a promise of
        assistance from Raymond J. DeMallie of Indiana University, one of the nation's leading
        linguists. As the expedition passed from one language family to another and took notes on
        native terms, I followed the procedure I had developed for geology and botany. Ray served
        as the clearinghouse for linguistic matters. He determined the language family, forwarded
        the material to language experts (who provided transliterations and translations of the
        native words), and then he rewrote the material and sent it on to me. Again, I did a bit
        of rewriting, and a sizable amount of correspondence ensued, with the added chore of going
        through an intermediary. I knew just how the captains felt when they had to go through
        five languages to speak to the Salish people in the Bitterroot Mountains of Montana, but
        they did not have to deal with linguistic symbols and diacritical marks.</p>
            <p>One of the more interesting results of the linguistic work was when we uncovered a
        phantom tribe of Indians. When Lewis and Clark met native peoples they always asked for
        their tribal name and the names of nearby tribes. In notes we brought these names
        up-to-date, using the latest terminology. In this work we did not have to turn to experts
        but could find the information in available literature. Often, Lewis's western tribal
        names were the starting point for synonymies that traced the names up to the present
        designation. When the party met Chinookan speakers along the Columbia River in October
        1805, one informant identified a neighboring downriver group as the Chil-luckit-te-quaws
        and we found them identified as such in American Indian literature with a reference to an
        expedition passage but no modern name. Linguistic work unraveled the mystery. The term
        translates from Chinookan to the phrase, "he is pointing at him." Lewis or Clark must have
        pointed downriver and asked the name of neighboring people and got a reply to the action
        rather than to the question. A nation of native people vanished in the light of linguistic
        analysis.</p>
            <p>The project also had the assistance of persons right on the job. Tom Dunlay, a doctoral
        graduate of the University of Nebraska, did a great deal of the editing chores over the
        years—writing notes, proofing text, checking journal transcriptions, and indexing volumes.
        Tom did most of the general annotation—determining the party's location and identifying
        native peoples—while I took care of the science and explained textual problems and
        journal-keeping procedures. Working full-time for many years, Tom came in on an irregular
        basis for a while and now has retired from the project altogether. Several persons over
        the years have attended to secretarial, clerical, and word processing duties. The staff at
        the center keeps track of the financial aspects and serves the project in countless ways.
        We have also had undergraduate and graduate students working with the project over the
        years, and we have occasionally brought in people to assist with other editing tasks, such
        as indexing the volumes. As the project nears its end, two individuals are now helping
        with the work on the comprehensive index, which will comprise the final volume in the
        edition
        <ref target="n01" n="1"/>.</p>
            <p>Indexing. Had I realized the enormity of the indexing task when I began this work, I
        might have been as much concerned with it as I was about science. Here again some
        ignorance and naïveté; helped me through the early days. Also I had a short reprieve since
        I could publish the Atlas without an index. By the time the first journal volume was
        completed, the first book to require an index, we were into word processors. It was a
        dedicated word processor, a real relic by today's standards, but still it had functions
        that would make the indexing easier. I had already indexed two works the old way and was
        committed to doing something different than assembling hundreds of three-by-five-inch
        notecards, the way I'm sure historians have been doing it since the days of
        Thucydides.</p>
            <p>I already knew the basics—index all proper names and geographic terms. Easy enough, I
        thought. But some of these indexing basics about which I felt so confident were frustrated
        by the ambiguities of the journals. Thankfully, we did miss some glaring blunders. For
        instance, we did not index the party's barking squirrels under "Squirrel, barking," but
        put it in its proper place under "Prairie dog." But I wish I could explain how we ever
        came up with an entry like "Bird, black" for "Blackbirds" or "Snake, rattle" for
        "Rattlesnakes." At least we never had an entry, "Fish, cat."</p>
            <p>But what about indexing subjects, themes, ideas, and concepts? I made lists of what I
        considered the most important of these and then combed the indexes of expedition
        literature for more. The final list included terms like arms and ammunition, astronomical
        observations, clothes, discipline, equipment, journal-keeping methods, medical problems,
        provisions, and weather conditions. Then we added cross-references. For instance, in
        addition to a general entry on boats, we also pointed readers to specific types of boats
        mentioned in the text, such as bateaux, bull boats, canoes, keelboats, pirogues, and the
        iron-frame boat. When entries became too long, we added subcategories. Under canoes, for
        instance, we had accidents, construction, loaded, navigational problems, obtained,
        portaged, problems with, repaired, and unloaded.</p>
            <p>I eventually established twenty general policies for our indexing guidelines, then
        added fifteen pages of examples and addenda over the years. Even these elaborate rules did
        not save us from errors other than those I have already mentioned. When indexing Lewis and
        Clark you have to be prepared for the unexpected. Realizing that Clark spelled the Indian
        tribe "Sioux" twenty-seven different ways, we knew we faced some real oddities.
        Idiosyncrasies abounded. For instance, in the journals carrots are not vegetables and cows
        are not bovines. Carrot was the contemporary term for twists of tobacco, and cows (spelled
        as such in the journals) is actually the plant cous (pronounced "cows"), an important
        foodstuff of Columbia River Indians.</p>
            <p>I wish I could say that the current great interest in Lewis and Clark has come as a
        result of my work, but that would not be true. Many of the important published works on
        the expedition that have come out in recent years were either underway or were in print
        before I started getting books out. John Allen had already completed his study of the
        expedition's geographic endeavors, James P. Ronda was well into the book that became 
        <ref target="http://www.nebraskapress.unl.edu/product/Lewis-and-Clark-among-the-Indians-Bicentennial-Ed,672119.aspx"
                    rend="new">Lewis and Clark among the Indians</ref>, and even Stephen Ambrose's biography
        of Lewis was in planning, although he was not able to devote time to the writing until a
        few years ago. What the new edition provides for recent writers (Ambrose among them) is
        easy access to the complete corpus of expedition journals and annotation that touches on
        the full range of the diaries' discussions. It also expedited the production of Ken Burns'
        and Dayton Duncan's recent film on the expedition.</p>
            <p>What is left to be done on the Lewis and Clark expedition? For me there is an immediate
        project on the horizon. Once the edition is completed I plan to develop a 
        <ref target="http://www.nebraskapress.unl.edu/product/Lewis-and-Clark-Journals-Abridged-Edition,671160.aspx"
                    rend="new">one-volume abridgment of the journal volumes</ref>
               <ref target="n03" n="3"/>. I believe that I can add important scientific and cultural
        matters to a condensed version that are missing in existing treatments, but I will not
        ignore the dramatic story the diaries tell. Despite the extensive literature on Lewis and
        Clark and the rush of publishing in the last two decades, one large area remains
        overlooked. There is no comprehensive study of the enlisted men on the expedition. We have
        a book of brief biographies, now outdated, but no one has told us what it was like to
        soldier and serve with Lewis and Clark. Certainly we need a modern biography of Clark and
        a book-length study of the Charbonneaus. Without such works, real deficiencies in the
        literature still exist.</p>
            <p>It has been my privilege and great honor to serve the Corps of Discovery for this
        generation. My Lewis and Clark colleagues and I stand as the fourth generation of
        expedition scholars. I hope that I can pass on the love and joy of working with these
        materials as I received the same from Nicholas Biddle, Elliott Coues, Reuben Gold
        Thwaites, Ernest Staples Osgood, and their contemporaries. May my work and theirs inspire
        future students of the expedition to new areas of study and help to keep the story alive
        for another two hundred years.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n01" n="1">The final volume of the Journals of the Lewis and Clark
        Expedition, the 
        <ref target="http://www.nebraskapress.unl.edu/product/Definitive-Journals-of-Lewis-and-Clark-Vol-13,672833.aspx"
                    rend="new">comprehensive index</ref>, was published in 2001.</note>
            <note xml:id="n02" n="2">The 
        <ref target="http://www.nebraskapress.unl.edu/product/Journals-of-the-Lewis-and-Clark-Expedition-Volume,671334.aspx"
                    rend="new">Atlas</ref>is again available from the University of Nebraska Press, having
        been reprinted in 1999.</note>
            <note xml:id="n03" n="3">The one-volume abridgment, 
        <ref target="http://www.nebraskapress.unl.edu/product/Lewis-and-Clark-Journals-Abridged-Edition,671160.aspx"
                    rend="new">The Lewis and Clark Journals: An American Epic of Discovery</ref>, was
        published in 2003.</note>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>