<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.sup.missing">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Missing Journals of Meriwether Lewis</title>
            <title type="sub"/>
            <title type="sub"/>
            <author>Gary E. Moulton</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska
     Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               
               
               
               
               
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
              <term>Texts</term>
            </keywords>
           <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Articles</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-07-14</date>
            <date/>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>
            <name/>Initial creation Transcribed</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="main">The Missing Journals of Meriwether Lewis</head>
         <div type="article">
            <p>
               <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/read/?_xmlsrc=lc.moulton.xml&amp;_xslsrc=LCstyles.xsl"
                    rend="new">by Gary E. Moulton</ref>
               <lb/>
               <lb/> (This essay first appeared in <hi rend="italic">
                  <ref target="http://his.state.mt.us/pub/magazine/default.asp" rend="new">Montana: The Magazine
       of Western History</ref>
               </hi>, Volume 35, Summer 1985, pgs. 28–39.) </p>
            <p> The journals of the Lewis and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>
     expedition are one of our country's national treasures. These diaries, written by the two
     captains and four enlisted men, contain over a million words. The breadth of these writings is
     unmatched by any similar enterprise, and the depth of the leaders' observations and insights
     has been universally admired. The careful record of daily activities, the extensive scientific
     observations of plants, animals, weather, and terrain, and the writing style with its charming
     peculiarities in spelling, grammar, and punctuation make the journals the hallmarks of that
     great voyage of discovery. On those records rest all the expedition's claims to greatness. The
     men set a standard of record-keeping for later expeditions and left a literary heritage for the
     ages. In large measure, the scope and quality of the documents account for much of the
     continuing fascination in the Lewis and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>
     story. </p>
            <p> Despite the quantity of the Lewis and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>
     legacy in field notes, notebook journals, field journals, and scraps of diary writings, there
     persists a nagging question: Is the record complete?</p>
            <p> Over the years, numerous documents of the expedition have come to light, some in the most
     unexpected places. In 1903, Reuben Gold Thwaites, editor of the centennial edition of the
     journals, discovered unknown <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> diaries and
     papers in the possession of <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>'s
     descendants; in 1915, <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Sergeant John Ordway's</name>
     journal and Lewis and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>'s Eastern Journal
     were found among the papers of <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Nicholas
     Biddle</name>, editor of the 1814 paraphrase of the journals; in 1953, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>'s Field Notes were discovered in an attic roll-top desk in
     St. Paul, Minnesota; and as recently as 1966, a fair copy of <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Private Joseph Whitehouse</name>'s journal, which extended the
     narrative almost five months, appeared in a bookstore in Philadelphia.</p>
            <p> These discoveries seem to support the notion of other lost items yet to be found. No hope of
     discovery ranks so high as the hope of finding Meriwether Lewis's diaries, which would fill the
     large gaps in his writing during and about the expedition. This essay looks at Lewis's known
     journals, considers where gaps might be filled with the discovery of new materials, and
     concludes that there are few possibilities of new finds. To a large degree, these
     considerations are interpretative and speculative and the conclusions are tentative. We can
     only hope that more of Lewis's writings are still to be found.</p>
            <p> The gaps in Lewis's writings are numerous and extensive. They include missing days from the
     trip on the Ohio and Mississippi rivers from September 19 to November 11, 1803, a nearly
     complete lapse from May 14, 1804, to April 7, 1805, only spotty entries from August 26, 1805,
     to January 1, 1806, and a final hiatus from August 12, 1806, to the completion of the
     expedition. The last gap can be explained by Lewis's being partially disabled from a wound; in
     contrast to other lapses in writing, he noted at the time that he was laying down his pen. One
     might also include the period from November 28, 1803, to May 14, 1804, during the winter in the
     St. Louis area, a time for which no Lewis journal is known. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> at least kept a rough diary during that time. In all, from
     May 1804 to September 1806, there are over four hundred days of missing entries by Lewis during
     the expedition proper.<ref target="n01" n="1"/>
            </p>
            <p> Lewis seems to have displayed a pattern of laxness in consistent journal-writing from the
     start. He began a diary, the Eastern Journal, when he left Pittsburgh in August 1803 on his way
     down the Ohio River to St. Louis. From September 19 to November 11, however, he made no entries
     and left thirty-nine pages blank in the notebook between these separated entries, perhaps with
     the intention of supplying the missing information later. Lewis never filled in the gap, which
     suggests that he probably had no preliminary notes to furnish the missing material.<ref target="n02" n="2"/> He certainly had ample time to supply the omitted information during the
     five months that he spent in the St. Louis area preparing for the expedition. Lewis returned to
     his journal writing on November 11 but gave the journal to <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> on November 28 near Kaskaskia, as the two captains
     separated, Lewis going ahead by land to St. Louis while <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> led the boat party forward to establish Camp Dubois. From
     that point on, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>'s faithful journal-keeping
     provides us with a nearly complete record.</p>
            <p> Lewis may have felt no need for a full journal account because he was traveling across
     well-known terrain from Pittsburgh to St. Louis and because he was corresponding with <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">President Jefferson</name> about his travels.
     Administrative duties in preparation for the expedition, which kept Lewis away from the party's
     camp, and the knowledge of <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>'s diary may
     account for the lack of a diary during that first winter. Lewis's early lapses may be the
     result of his view that the expedition, at least at that point, had not actually begun.</p>
            <p> More difficult to explain is Lewis's lack of journal-keeping once the expedition got
     underway. No Lewis journals are known to exist that cover the first phase of the expedition,
     from May 14, 1804, until the group left Fort <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> on April 7, 1805. This is the longest hiatus in Lewis's writing and to
     historians it is the most curious gap. It is particularly bewildering because one would expect
     Lewis to be more conscientious at the outset of the expedition, especially considering <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>'s explicit instructions about the
     keeping of multiple journals. <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>
     admonished Lewis: "Several copies ... of your other notes should be made at leisure times,
     &amp; put into the care of the most trust-worthy of your attendants, to guard, by
     multiplying them, against the accidental losses to which they will be exposed."<ref target="n03" n="3"/> Some observers, incredulous that this gap exists, have speculated that
     Lewis was probably keeping field drafts or standard journals of the party's
     activities—notes that have since been lost.</p>
            <p> The captains wrote in a variety of notebooks during the expedition. Most of them are five-
     by eight-inch, morocco-bound books that open from the end—the socalled red books.
     There are also four notebooks bound in pasteboard with marbled covers, a couple of
     leather-bound books, and one field book made from loose sheets and bound in elkskin. In 1893,
      <name type="person" key="Coues, Elliott">Elliott Coues</name> codified most of this material,
     at least that which was available to him at the American Philosophical Society, and labeled the
     journals Codex A, Codex B, and so on. To say that Lewis was keeping no journal in such form
     from the outset is not precisely correct. There exist two small fragments for the dates May 15
     and May 20 and September 16–17, 1804, which Coues labeled codices Aa and Bb. These
     sheets, apparently torn from one of the red books, suggest to some that Lewis was keeping a
     journal for the initial period and that the remaining pages were discarded because they were
     soiled, ruined, or unnecessary. Or perhaps the remaining pages are simply lost. Another
     explanation seems plausible: the two codices are singular and not a rescued portion of a larger
     whole.</p>
            <p> In the case of Codex Aa it is noteworthy that the order of days is reversed: the entry for
     May 20 precedes the entry for May 15, with no break between the two. The entry for May 20
     recounts Lewis's activities for that day as he set out by land from St. Louis for St. Charles
     where he was to rendezvous with <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, who was
     leading the party upriver. He also reported on the activities of <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>'s party. Perhaps Lewis saw this entry as the beginning of
     his journal-keeping, since the captains had previously determined to set out on May 21. If this
     is true, then why the addition of notes for May 15? A more detailed report of <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>'s trip upriver, written as if Lewis had been
     present, the May 15 entry presents more information than <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> has for that day in either of his two accounts. Lewis
     probably got this information directly from <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>. Perhaps Lewis thought he ought to add an entry for May 15 to give a more
     detailed account of the actual start of the expedition. Although <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> set out from Camp Dubois on May 14, the men had earlier
     decided on May 15 as the date to begin, and perhaps Lewis still had that date in mind. The
     entry of May 15 stops in mid-page, seeming to indicate that nothing followed.</p>
            <p> Codex Ba presents a different situation. On September 16 and 17, 1804, the group was
     encamped at "Corvus" Creek just above today's White River in South Dakota. While there, the
     leaders changed plans and decided not to send a pirogue back to St. Louis with artifacts and
     other items representing their journey thus far. Perhaps Lewis had planned to send their notes
     to St. Louis along with the other materials, knowing that everything would eventually reach
      <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">President Jefferson</name>. Thus, Lewis may have
     considered that he was now beginning a journal, in a sense the first for him since he had
     apparently quit writing after his May 15 entry. But having made the decision not to send a boat
     and crew back, he may have ceased his journal writing (indeed, he stopped at mid-page in
     mid-sentence) and perhaps decided not to write again until after the winter at Fort <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> also may have had some notion of a shift in writing here. A
     note on one sheet of his Field Notes after the September 16 entry reads: "refur to the Book No.
     2." The book would be his Codex B, and the note could signify his intention to abandon his
     Field Notes in favor of keeping only a notebook journal.</p>
            <p> Some writers have supposed that Lewis was keeping field notes similar to <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>'s during the trip from Camp Dubois to Fort <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> and that he intended to use that
     material to fill regular notebooks later. Other persons might consider the fragments for May
     and September as part of a complete set of notes from a regular notebook that is now lost.
     Donald Jackson has made the strongest case for Lewis having kept a journal during the first leg
     of the journey, but he emphasizes the speculative nature of his conclusions. Jackson believes
     that a mishap on May 14, 1805, may indicate a loss of journals. On that day, one of the
     pirogues turned on its side, filled with water, and soaked some papers and notebooks. Jackson
     discovered that within a few days of the accident <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> began conscientiously copying Lewis's natural history notes into his own
     journal, something he had not previously done. Jackson argues that the spoilages may have been
     greater than the leaders first realized, convincing the men that duplicate records were
     necessary, not just multiple diaries. He also conjectures that "perhaps Lewis's notes for the
     entire first leg of the expedition were either badly water-soaked or entirely lost." Thus,
     Jackson believes that the entries by Lewis for May and September 1804 are fragments of a larger
     journal from that early period.<ref target="n04" n="4"/>
            </p>
            <p> Reuben Gold Thwaites also thought that Lewis was a regular journal-keeper, but his reasoning
     is less plausible than Jackson's. Thwaites supposed that the journals might have been lost
     after Lewis's death in Tennessee in 1809. Surely <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> or <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> would have
     bemoaned so serious a loss, but neither man ever made reference to it in any known source.
     Jackson speculates that there is no mention of the supposed loss of journals in May 1805,
     because Lewis would have told <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>
     about the accident after his return and that there was no need to announce it to the world in
     his diary.<ref target="n05" n="5"/>
            </p>
            <p> Postulating about the writing of field notes by either man in cases where none has been
     found and where there is no strong evidence of their having existed seems unwise. Further, it
     is not necessary to believe that for every finished journal there was a preliminary set of
     field notes nearly duplicating it. Theories involving the existence of such notes ought to be
     avoided unless clear evidence requires them. The sheer amount of labor involved in composing
     multiple sets of notes and journals argues against such suppositions and, in fact, no field
     notes for Lewis have ever been discovered. What miscellaneous items that have been found hardly
     compare to <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>'s Field Notes or to his later
     field book, the elkskin-bound journal that describes activities from September to December
     1805. Still, considering the history of journal discoveries to date, no one can assert with
     certainty that there are no lost notes or journals or that none will ever be found.</p>
            <p> Those who think Lewis kept a journal or field notes during the trip to Fort <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> have found strong evidence in letters
     from Lewis and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> to <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> just before the party set out from that post. The
     opening phrase of <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>'s letter has been
     struck out and other words substituted by Lewis. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> wrote, "As <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name> has not
     Leasure to Send 〈write〉 a correct Copy journal of our proceedings &amp;c.,"
     and Lewis substituted, "It being the wish of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt.
      Lewis</name>." Those who argue that Lewis kept a journal interpret Lewis's change to mean that
     he had not converted field notes into an acceptable journal or that he had not completed a
     journal on hand. There are other ways to read the excised parts: Did Lewis not have time to
     send his journal, did he not have time to write it, or did he not have time to make a correct
     copy? Lewis's letter stated that he would send a canoe with some men back from the extreme
     navigable point of the Missouri River (a scheme later rejected) and with that boat "I shal send
     you my journal." Again, one can read the phrase variously: Was Lewis to send a journal he had
     been keeping or one he intended to write? Only Ernest S. Osgood has concluded that Lewis kept
     no journal: "I do not think there is enough available evidence to support a conclusion that
     Lewis was keeping a journal on the first leg of the journey." But even he hesitates to dismiss
     the idea entirely. In another instance he writes, "Field notes ... must have been taken by both
     Lewis and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> during the whole journey."
     Rather than speculate on a hidden meaning that can never be determined, it is probably better
     to examine the totality of Lewis's writing during the early period and to interpret from that
      perspective.<ref target="n06" n="6"/>
            </p>
            <p> The lack of consistent daily entries by Lewis from St. Charles to Fort <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> does not mean that Lewis performed no
     writing duties during this time. Quite a bit of Lewis's writing is extant, and additional
     material is known to be missing. As the expedition's naturalist, he kept fairly extensive notes
     on the flora and fauna of the region through which the party passed. In Codex R, he made a list
     of herbarium specimens that he was collecting. The descriptive writing is occasionally lengthy
     and shows not only Lewis's powers of observation but also his record-keeping activities. His
     observations about animals are almost as extensive and cover over fifty pages of Codex Q. He
     also noted mineral deposits and geologic features along the Missouri and took astronomical
     observations—both time-consuming tasks that included record-keeping. And although
     Lewis cannot be directly credited, it is known that the captains were keeping lists of Indian
     vocabularies during this period, work that may have amounted to extensive note-taking. The
     vocabularies are the missing material that might include additional writing by Lewis.</p>
            <p> From January to May 1804, Lewis also kept a weather diary in a separate little notebook.
     These observations are repeated in <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>'s
     Codex C, and it may be that Lewis was copying <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>'s entries. After May 14, there is a gap of weather data in both the men's books
     until September 19; the notations are then resumed with hardly an interruption until April 3,
     1805, when Lewis began including weather data in his daily entries. It may be significant that
     September 19 is the date of again taking up the weather notations, since it is about the time
     Codex Ba was begun and when the captains decided not to send pirogues back to St. Louis. If
     Lewis was keeping the weather diary independent of <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> was copying the
     weather data into his Codex C, then there may be missing field notes, at least Lewis's remarks
     on weather during this period. The weather notes indicate a substantial amount of writing
     because they consist of two temperature readings for each day, the general state of the
     weather, the wind direction, and the rise and fall of the river. There are also comments on
     natural history, including sightings of animals and the budding and fading of flora. It is
     uncertain whether Lewis made the notes on his own along the way or copied from <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>'s journal at the time or at Fort <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>. In either case, it was a
     collaborative effort.</p>
            <p> There is the potential for more extensive writing by Lewis. A single loose sheet from <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>'s Field Notes is entirely in Lewis's hand and
     contains on one side a draft for his description of the Platte River, which he later
     transferred into Codex O as his survey of rivers and creeks. Although there is a date of July
     21 (1804) on the document, the reverse contains lunar observations (also in Lewis's hand) for
     February 23, 1805, while the party was at Fort <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>. It could be that the draft describing the Platte was copied into Codex O at
     Fort <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>. The draft from the Field
     Notes is incomplete, so it is certain that other pages are missing, but whether these pages
     describe only the Platte or contain a full draft of his summary may never be known. If Lewis
     was keeping thorough topographical notes such as these throughout the first portion of the
     trip, it helps explain why no daily entry material is to be found. It may simply have amounted
     to too much writing.</p>
            <p> One incident on the way to Fort <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> may corroborate the notion that Lewis kept no journal of daily events during
     that period. On July 14, 1804, a sudden storm hit the river and great gusts of wind turned one
     boat on its side and it began to fill with water. Cool heads and quick action saved the vessel
     from destruction, but <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> reported that his
     notes of the previous day had blown overboard during the accident. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> mentioned that the loss "obliges me to refur to the
     〈notes〉 Journals of Serjeants, and my own recollection [of] the accurences
     Courses Distance &amp;. of that day." If Lewis had been keeping a journal of events during
     this time, why would <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> go to the journals
     of the sergeants or depend on his own recollection for the "accurences"? Certainly he would
     have trusted Lewis's notes over his memory or the notes of enlisted men if any journals by
     Lewis had been available.<ref target="n07" n="7"/>
            </p>
            <p> Taken together Lewis's recording activities up to Fort <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> add up to a large amount of "journalizing" and may
     represent a proportional share of the writing duties of the captains. What emerges is a picture
     of the two men sharing journal-keeping chores, though not following <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>'s prescription to the letter. It strains credulity to
     believe that all of Lewis's daily entry journals (except for a few pages of writing for May and
     September 1804) from St. Charles to Fort <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> and during the winter of 1804–1805 could be lost. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> filled three notebooks of writing for that period, and
     Lewis, the more verbose, would have written even more. Short of discovering actual journals by
     Lewis or definite references to such writing, one must suppose that he kept no record of daily
     events for this portion of the expedition.<ref target="n08" n="8"/>
            </p>
            <p> From the expedition's departure from Fort <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> on April 7, 1805, to late August 1805, complete notebook journals for both
     captains exist, with no fragmentary or parallel journals until August, although the two leaders
     copied each others' writings. There is no indication that either of them followed <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>'s earlier practice of writing field notes and
     transferring them, with revisions, into notebook journals. Indeed, there is no reason to assume
     that the captains consistently followed any one plan or procedure throughout the expedition.
     Their responsibility was to keep as complete a record as possible of the many kinds of
     information that <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> wanted and to
     preserve that record from harm or loss. They could follow any procedure that suited their
     convenience and the conditions of the moment, so far as was consistent with this mission.
     Conditions varied so much throughout the trip that there was every reason to change
     journal-keeping procedures. When they were inconsistent in so much else, there is no reason to
     expect them to be consistent in how they kept their journals.</p>
            <p> Duplication of journals served as insurance against loss or damage, but with both men
     keeping journals after April 7, 1805, there would have been less need for keeping both field
     notes and notebook journals, a time-consuming task. Field notes would be of value, however, in
     situations where there was an increased risk of damage or loss from weather or difficult travel
     conditions, where it seemed wise to put away the notebooks and keep field notes easily
     accessible. Such precautions might also be taken when one of the captains was scouting ahead on
     foot, accompanied by only a few men; he might leave his notebook journals with the main body,
     both for convenience and for safety. After such separations, one leader might copy the
     experiences of the other into his own journal to ensure the preservation of a complete record.</p>
            <p> As they moved up the Missouri around the Great Falls, the captains were separated at various
     times in June, July, and August 1805, as one or the other was ahead, portaging the falls or
     later looking for the <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name>
     Indians. During these intervals, Lewis sometimes copied <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>'s journals for the days of separation under the date of
     their reunion, which suggests that he was keeping the notebook journal day by day. At other
     times, Lewis gave an account of <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>'s
     activities in his own entries for each day, which indicates that these entries must have been
     written after they were reunited. During this period, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> did not ordinarily copy Lewis's record of daily events while they were
      separated.<ref target="n09" n="9"/>
            </p>
            <p> By late August, Lewis's journal writing began to fall off. His journal entries became very
     sporadic and raise a different set of questions about his journal-keeping activities. There are
     four fragmentary journals by Lewis from August and September 1805, which Coues designated
     codices Fa, Fb, Fc, and Fd. Each consists of a few loose sheets covering periods of from two to
     five days. Codex Fa describes events that are related in more detail in Lewis's regular
     journal, Codex F (July 17–August 22, 1805). The other codices are all from periods
     after the end of Codex F, during a hiatus of over four months for which there are no other
     known Lewis journals, except for a later fragment, Codex Ia (November 29–December 1,
     1805).</p>
            <p> It is tempting to regard the little diaries as being literally "fragments," that is,
     portions of a lost body of field notes or regular journals by Lewis covering perhaps the entire
     gap in his journal-keeping from late August 1805 to January 1, 1806. But the fragments
     themselves provide no evidence for this hypothesis. If they included portions of a previous
     day's entry at the beginning or of the next day's entry at the end, there would be good reason
     to regard them as portions of a larger body of lost notes. On the contrary, they appear to be
     complete in themselves. At the end of an entry in Codex Fa, for example, there is a dated
     heading without a following entry. Only a blank space follows the date on the last sheet of the
     codex. Moreover, all of the fragments except Fc relate to periods when the leaders were
     separated: Fa chronicling a scouting excursion ahead of the main body when Lewis might have
     preferred not to risk his notebook journal, the other two describing periods when <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> scouted ahead and Lewis had to keep a record
     of the movements of the main party. Codex Fc derives from two days of relative leisure for the
     expedition at Travelers' Rest in western Montana when Lewis may have intended to resume
     journal-keeping after a lapse of about two weeks. Perhaps Lewis started Codex Fc in the middle
     of a blank book (Codex P) because he intended to fill in the space left with his journal
     entries for the two weeks after August 26, the last date in Codex Fb. If so, he surely must
     have had notes of some kind on which to base the entries, but none are extant. Apparently he
     never got around to it, and there is no sign that he continued writing after September 10, at
     least not in Codex P. Lewis's later Codex Ia (November 29–December 1, 1805) also
     covers part of a period of separation and gives no indication of being part of a larger
      whole.<ref target="n10" n="10"/> Again, we should ask why it is necessary to assume missing
     journals without evidence and with creditable explanations to the contrary.</p>
            <p> Lewis began a new journal (Codex J) on January 1, 1806, and continued writing until August
     12 when he laid his pen down, ending his record of the expedition. As far as is known, this was
     the first journal writing by him since August 1805, except for the scattered fragments. Perhaps
     this is another point of beginning, as has been conjectured with codices Aa, Ba, and Fc. In
     this instance, at least, he fulfilled his good intentions of journal-keeping (combined perhaps
     with a New Year's resolution). Codex J is a detailed record, to March 20, of life at Fort
     Clatsop. It contains extensive descriptions of local flora and fauna and the life of the nearby
     Indians, with numerous illustrations. Nowhere else did Lewis devote more time and record so
     much in fulfilling the scientific objectives of the expedition. All of his observations are
     incorporated in the daily entries, generally after the record of the day's events. In what was
     evidently an additional measure to ensure the preservation of this material, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> copied most of it into his journals almost
     verbatim. For some reason, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> did not always
     copy this material under the same date as Lewis had, and sometimes he placed it under an entry
     several days earlier than Lewis's.<ref target="n11" n="11"/>
            </p>
            <p> Interestingly, Lewis's Codex J includes natural history material appropriate to the Rocky
     Mountains and Interior Basin, notes additional to the few fragments extant for that period. If
     Lewis had a journal for that period (August through December 1805), why copy it into daily
     entries for the time at Fort Clatsop? Why not copy it into a separate journal covering the
     actual dates? These are questions that we cannot answer. There must have been some sort of
     natural history field notes or other journals for that period that are now lost. Perhaps they
     were similar to codices Q and R from the first leg of the expedition and not daily entry
     journals in the usual sense. If Lewis did have notes in daily journal form covering the
     August–December gap, why did he not copy them into his own journal at Fort Clatsop
     when he would have had time? One answer might be that the notes he had were mainly natural
     history and ethnographic material and that he did copy them and they went into Codex J under
     current dates.<ref target="n12" n="12"/>
            </p>
            <p> Having returned to Travelers' Rest, the leaders split the party on July 3, Lewis going
     northeast to seek a shorter route to the Missouri River, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> southeast to explore the Yellowstone River. By all previous
     experience, Lewis should have kept a journal during the period of separation, especially since
     he would be covering territory previously unexplored by the party.</p>
            <p> Lewis's Codex L runs to July 4, then resumes after eighteen blank pages with an entry for
     July 15; in no other expedition notebook journal is there such an unfilled gap in time. The
     fragmentary Codex La (July 3–15) covers this period, and Lewis probably intended it
     as the first draft. He probably packed away the notebook, Codex L, for safekeeping while
     traveling through the mountains, then resumed writing in it on July 15, leaving the blank pages
     to fill in later from the material in Codex La. He never got around to this, probably because
     he quit writing entirely on August 12, by which date all the writing in Codex L was probably
     complete. He probably wrote his account of the violent encounter with the Piegan Blackfeet on
     July 27–28 at least a few days later, after he had rejoined his party following a
     hurried ride across country. He continued Codex L to August 8, after which the fragmentary
     Codex Lb covers August 9–12; on August 12, Lewis stopped writing entirely because of
     discomfort from the accidental gunshot wound inflicted by <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Pierre Cruzatte</name> the day before. He had rejoined <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> and his group on August 12, and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> could now keep a record for the whole party.</p>
            <p> The loose pages, which constitute Codex Lb, evidently were once part of a red notebook found
     among <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>'s papers by Thwaites, which bears
     on its cover the notation "9 to 12 Augt. 1806"; it now contains no material about the
     expedition. Lewis evidently began writing in this book after finishing Codex L, then stopped
     after a few days because of the pain of his wound. In later years, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> removed these few pages to use the book for other purposes.
     Considering the unfilled gap in Codex L, it appears that Lewis's journal-keeping ceased
     entirely on August 12, 1806, and was then complete as it now stands.</p>
            <p> Nine of Lewis's fragmentary codices (Aa, Ba, Fa, Fb, Fc, Fd, Fe, Ia, and Lb) are apparently
     pages taken from notebooks, all but one (Ia) from red books. It is possible that Lewis removed
     these pages before writing on them, but it is equally possible that he wrote in the books and
     the pages were removed at some later period. Codex Fc, for instance, came from Codex P, and
     there is reason to believe that those pages were not removed until 1810, when the book was used
     to copy natural history notes for <name type="person" key="Barton, Benjamin Smith">Benjamin
      Smith Barton</name>. Many of these fragments represent periods when the captains were
     separated or when weather and travel conditions posed a special risk to the journals. On such
     occasions, Lewis may have used a book that was largely blank, containing perhaps some
     relatively unimportant or duplicated data. Thus, if the books he was carrying with him were
     damaged by weather or a dip in a river or if he failed to return from a scouting mission,
     important material would not be lost, as would be the case if he used a regular daily journal.
     This may strengthen the likelihood that the "fragments" are complete in themselves, and not
     part of a body of lost field notes.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>'s references to the red books as
     "travelling pocket journals," although he was not present when they were written, at least
     suggests that some of them were at some times carried on the person.<ref target="n13" n="13"/>
     They were small enough to carry in a pocket. The "fragment" pages could have been removed from
     the books during the expedition, after the return, or when <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> and <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Nicholas
      Biddle</name> were working on the journals in 1810. If Lewis had daily field notes and did not
     get them copied, what happened to them? When they saved so much else—so many
     fragments, scraps, and sketches—why not save material by the expedition leader,
     covering periods when there is no other writing by him? Once again we have hypothetical lost
     journals for whose existence there is no real evidence.</p>
            <p> We may assume, then, that Lewis's writings from the expedition are nearly complete. The
     fragments from his journal that cover the expedition from Camp Dubois to Fort <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> are probably just
     that—fragments—and not part of a larger whole. Other writing helps explain
     a method devised by the captains for sharing writing chores: Lewis's journal entries at Fort
      <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> exist only because he was
     filling in for the absent <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>; and the
     sporadic journal writing in late August and September 1805 may also be considered Lewis's
     stand-in writing for <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> and not portions of
     missing journals. Only one period provides a possibility of missing journals: from September to
     December 1805. Those notes, which cover mainly natural history, may be available in an existing
     journal, Codex J, but under different dates. Extant correspondence between <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, and Biddle after the expedition, when the journals were being extensively
     discussed and widely sought for deposit at the American Philosophical Society, gives no
     indication of missing journals, although <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> does mention other missing material, such as the Indian vocabularies. One can
     only wonder at Lewis's lapses and never explain them entirely. Certainly this is not the final
     word on a topic that likely will never be closed, unless, of course, someone discovers Lewis's
     missing journals. </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n01" n="1"> Reuben Gold Thwaites, ed., Original Journals of the Lewis and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition, 1804–1806, vol. 1 (New
     York: Dodd, Mead and Company, 1904–1905), xxxv n. 2; Paul Russell Cutright, A History
     of the Lewis and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Journals (Norman:
     University of Oklahoma Press, 1976), 9–10. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>'s "rough diary" is that published in Ernest S. Osgood, The Field Notes of
     Captain <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark</name>, 1803–1805 (New
     Haven, Connecticut: Yale University Press, 1964). Those particular notes are here distinguished
     from field notes in general by capitalizing the first letters. Lewis's daily journals are:
     Eastern Journal (August 30–September 18, November 11–28, 1803), Codex Aa
     (May 20 and 15, 1804), Codex Ba (September 16–17, 1804), Codex D (April
     7–May 23 1805), Codex E (May 24–July 16, 1805), Codex F (July
     17–August 22, 1805), Codex Fa (August 1–4, 1805), Codex Fb (August
     23–26, 1805), Codex Fc (September 9–10, 1805), Codex Fd (September
     18–22, 1805), Codex Ia (November 29–December 1, 1805), Codex J (January
     1–March 20, 1806), Codex K (March 21–May 23, 1806) Codex L (May
     24–July 4, July 15–August 8, 1806, Codex La (July 3–15, 1806,
     Codex Lb (August 9–12, 1806).</note>
            <note xml:id="n02" n="2">
               <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Nicholas Biddle</name> later
     filled in the blank pages of the Eastern Journal with notes.</note>
            <note xml:id="n03" n="3">
               <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>'s instructions
     are in <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> to Lewis, June 20, 1803,
     Donald Jackson, ed., Letters of the Lewis and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition with Related Documents, 1783–1854, 2d ed., vol. 1 (Urbana:
     University of Illinois Press, 1978), 61–66.</note>
            <note xml:id="n04" n="4">Jackson may consider the lost notes to be field notes. At one point he uses
     the term "unrevised notes." Donald Jackson, <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Thomas
      Jefferson</name> and the Stony Mountains: Exploring the West From Monticello (Urbana:
     University of Illinois Press, 1981), 192–195.</note>
            <note xml:id="n05" n="5">Thwaites, Original Journals, vol. 1, xxxv, n. 2; Jackson, <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, 194.</note>
            <note xml:id="n06" n="6">
               <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> to <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, April 1, 1805, Lewis to <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, April 7, 1805, Jackson, Letters, vol.
     1, 226, 231–232. Jackson presumes that Lewis's substitutions mean that he wanted
      "<name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>'s statement to <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> to be completely noncommittal." Ibid., 226 headnote.
     Cutright thinks that the words imply that Lewis had not completed converting his field notes
     into a regular journal. His interpretation of Lewis's letter is that it cannot be taken as
     "prima facie evidence that he had a journal in form to send to <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>." Cutright's wording ("journal in form") leaves an
     opening for supposing field notes, as he does with <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>'s letter. Paul Russell Cutright, Lewis and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>: Pioneering Naturalists (Urbana: University of Illinois
     Press, 1969), 120; Osgood, Field Notes, xxii, xv.</note>
            <note xml:id="n07" n="7">
               <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> does not report the
     loss in Codex A, but only in his Field Notes. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>'s entry (Field Notes), July 13, 1804. <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> reported that <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>'s notes for
     two days had blown overboard. <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>'s entry,
     July 14, 1804.</note>
            <note xml:id="n08" n="8">Jackson almost concludes as much. He writes: "[Lewis] gathered a great
     amount of information, whether or not it was in journal form." Jackson, Letters, vol. 1, 226
     headnote. It may be noteworthy that the only time the leaders were separated before leaving
     Fort <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> was during a period when
     Lewis filled journal pages for the absent <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>
     (February 3–13, 1805) in <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>'s own
     journal, Codex C.</note>
            <note xml:id="n09" n="9">On many occasions the leaders copied from each others' journals; judging
     from vocabulary and phrasing, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> most often
     copied from Lewis, who was more literate and better versed in scientific terminology.</note>
            <note xml:id="n10" n="10">A final fragment, Codex Fe, consists of ten pages torn from Codex D and
     records only weather data, April 1–June 30, 1805, and six pages taken from another
     red book also recording only weather data, July 1–September 30, 1805. Lewis was the
     principal author, but <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> shared some of the
     writing.</note>
            <note xml:id="n11" n="11">
               <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>'s copying of Lewis
     for this period is investigated in Thomas W. Dunlay, " 'Battery of Venus': A Clue to the
     Journal-Keeping Methods of Lewis and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>," We
     Proceeded On 9 (August 1983): 6–8.</note>
            <note xml:id="n12" n="12">Cutright, Pioneering Naturalists, 263; Jackson, <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, 192–1/a93; Dunlay, "Battery of Venus."</note>
            <note xml:id="n13" n="13">
               <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> to <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, September 8, 1816, Jackson, Letters, vol. 2,
     619.</note>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
