<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.lc.ronda.01.01">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>&amp; 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>among the Indians</title>
            <title type="sub" level="a">1. The Voyage Begins</title>
            <title type="sub"/>
            <author>James P. Ronda</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2005</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic
        Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title level="m" type="main">
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>&amp; 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>among the Indians</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">1. The Voyage Begins</title>
               <author>James P. Ronda</author>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1984</date>
               <idno type="ISBN">0-8032-8990-1</idno>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-11-01</date>
            <date>2005-02-01</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>File splitting Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-04-12</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="ch1" type="chapter" n="1">
            <quote>
               <lg type="linegroup">
                  <l>"In all your intercourse with the natives, treat them in the most friendly and</l>
                  <l>conciliatory manner which their own conduct will permit."</l>
               </lg>
               <bibl>—
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Thomas Jefferson</name>, "Instructions to 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, June, 1803"</bibl>
            </quote>
            <div type="section">
               <p>The Indian relations of the 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>expedition began long before the
          explorers nosed their boats into the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>current and headed upriver. 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Thomas Jefferson</name>knew that as his
          explorers moved over the visible world of rivers, mountains, and plains, they would also
          pass through a more important world—a sometimes invisible universe of Indian politics
          and European rivalries. He grasped what so often escaped others, that the American West
          was a crowded wilderness. Although nudged by reading 
          <name type="person" key="Mackenzie, Alexander">Alexander Mackenzie</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>did not need the dour Scot
          to tell him that lands from 
          <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>to the great western sea were
          neither empty nor unclaimed. The political and economic face of the land had already
          been transformed by a generation of intense competition between tribal peoples and
          agents of 
          <name type="place" key="Spain">Spain</name>, 
          <name type="place" key="France">France</name>, and 
          <name type="place" key="England">Great Britain</name>. The president understood at least
          the outlines and implications of that struggle and the place of a latecoming American
          republic in it. If the 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>expedition was to be successful,
          whether for science, commerce, or statecraft, it would need to navigate through troubled
          Indian waters.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>From the beginning, 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>sought to fashion an
          expedition capable of gathering valuable information about western Indians while living
          at peace with them. That search became plain as he drafted instructions for his young
          secretary, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name>. The president loved
          questionnaires. He used them to explore new areas of knowledge and then to organize what
          he had learned. 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name>only published book, 
          <hi rend="italic">Notes on 
          <name type="place" key="Virginia">Virginia</name>,</hi>was written in response to a
          questionnaire from the French diplomat and scientist 
          <name type="person" key="Barbé-Marbois, François">François Barbé-Marbois</name>and
          retained the question-and-answer form in its chapters.
          <ref target="n0101" n="1"/>
                  <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name>instructions to 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>were a series of interlocking
          questions ranging from mineralogy to medicine. The ethnographic queries covered nearly
          every aspect of Indian life, including languages, customs, occupations, diseases, and
          morals.</p>
               <p>Where did those very precise questions come from? The traditional answer has been
          that the Indian objectives pursued by 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>reflected 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name>lifelong fascination with
          native American cultures. But there was more than one mind and one set of motives behind
          the expedition's Indian questions and its general policy toward native people. Early in
          1803 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>began to write friends both
          in and out of government asking their aid and advice for his western enterprise. In
          February he wrote three prominent 
          <name type="place" key="Philadelphia, Pa.">Philadelphia</name>scientists, 
          <name type="person" key="Wistar, Caspar">Caspar Wistar</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Barton, Benjamin Smith">Dr. Benjamin Smith Barton</name>, and 
          <name type="person" key="Rush, Benjamin">Dr. Benjamin Rush</name>, asking each to
          prepare some thoughts "in the lines of botany, zoology, or of Indian history which you
          think most worthy of inquiry and observation."
          <ref target="n0102" n="2"/>
               </p>
               <p>Even before his consultants submitted their questions, 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>began to prepare a
          preliminary draft of the instructions. By mid-April 1803 he was ready to circulate it
          among certain cabinet members for their responses. The remarks of 
          <name type="person" key="Gallatin, Albert">Secretary of the Treasury Albert
          Gallatin</name>focused on western geography and the future expansion of the United
          States. Later in his career 
          <name type="person" key="Gallatin, Albert">Gallatin</name>made a major contribution in
          collecting and systematizing Indian material in his "Synopsis of the Indian Tribes." But
          just how much he had to do with framing the expedition's Indian questions remains
          unclear.
          <ref target="n0103" n="3"/>On the other hand, the reply from 
          <name type="person" key="Lincoln, Levi">Attorney General Levi Lincoln</name>clearly
          influenced 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name>thinking. This important
          member of 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name>official family has not
          received much attention from students of western exploration. 
          <name type="person" key="Lincoln, Levi">Lincoln</name>, an able New England lawyer and a
          skillful Republican politician, understood that the expedition served many purposes. 
          <name type="person" key="Lincoln, Levi">Lincoln's</name>April 17 letter to 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>suggests that the early
          draft of instructions he saw contained very little about Indians. To remedy this
          deficiency, Lincoln urged 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>to include questions about
          tribal religions, native legal practice, concepts of property ownership, and Indian
          medical procedures. Although 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>was acquainted with smallpox
          inoculation, it appears that 
          <name type="person" key="Lincoln, Levi">Lincoln</name>was the first to suggest that 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>take some cowpox matter along to
          administer to the Indians. If they were to have extensive contact with whites, they
          needed to be protected against smallpox. Dead Indians could not participate in an
          American trade network and dying natives could only blame the explorers for spreading
          disease. The attorney general's suggestions were of major importance, although he made
          them more out of political expediency than scientific curiosity. 
          <name type="person" key="Lincoln, Levi">Lincoln</name>was very sensitive to Federalist
          opposition to the journey, and indeed to any American westward expansion. He realized
          that the administration would need to justify the expedition on the high ground of
          science if it failed.
          <ref target="n0104" n="4"/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Lincoln, Levi">Levi Lincoln's</name>helpful comments sharpened 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name>focus on Indians. That
          focus was further enlarged and refined in May 1803 when 
          <name type="person" key="Rush, Benjamin">Benjamin Rush</name>gave 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>a detailed list of ethnographic
          queries. In 1774 
          <name type="person" key="Rush, Benjamin">Rush</name>had presented a long paper before
          the American Philosophical Society titled "Natural History of Medicine among the Indians
          of North America." That discourse presented his thoughts on all physical aspects of
          Indian life from diet and hygiene to sexual performance and pregnancy.
          <ref target="n0105" n="5"/>The same wide range of interests was evident in a list 
          <name type="person" key="Rush, Benjamin">Rush</name>prepared for the expedition. That
          document was divided into three sections, with medical concerns predictably taking first
          place. Under the heading "Physical history &amp; medicine," 
          <name type="person" key="Rush, Benjamin">Rush</name>proposed twenty separate questions.
          He asked the explorers to record Indian eating, sleeping, and bathing habits as well as
          native diseases and remedies. The 
          <name type="place" key="Philadelphia, Pa.">Philadelphia</name>savant wanted to know when
          Indians married, how long children were breast fed, and how long they lived. 
          <name type="person" key="Rush, Benjamin">Rush</name>even urged 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>to find time to check Indian
          pulse rates morning, noon, and night both before and after they ate.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Rush, Benjamin">Rush's</name>interests went well beyond
          medicine, encompassing Indian customs and values as well. The second part of 
          <name type="person" key="Rush, Benjamin">Rush's</name>list included four questions
          touching on crime, suicide, and intoxication. His third section probed native American
          worship practices, sacred objects, and burial rituals. Like so many other European and
          American scientists, 
          <name type="person" key="Rush, Benjamin">Rush</name>was fascinated by Indian religions.
          Moreover, he believed, as did many of his contemporaries, that studies of Indian
          languages and religious ceremonies might prove or disprove a very old and persistent
          notion about the origin of native people. A widespread academic theory held that Indians
          might constitute one of the lost tribes of the children of Israel. If the 
          <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Mandan.html" rend="box">
          Mandans</ref>were misplaced Welshmen, as so many thought, why not see if there were any
          Jewish Indians in the West?
          <ref target="n0106" n="6"/>
               </p>
               <p>By June 1803 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>had before him all the
          suggestions from fellow scientists and government officials. He also had delivered in
          January the confidential message to Congress that justified the expedition on grounds of
          extending the Indian trade. He could draw on instructions written for the abortive 
          <name type="person" key="Michaux, André">Michaux</name>expedition a decade before.
          <ref target="n0107" n="7"/>Sometime during June, 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>synthesized these documents
          into a final draft of instructions for the expedition—instructions that now contained
          detailed questions in seventeen areas of Indian life and culture. Those questions
          covered everything from language and law to trade and technology. The explorers were to
          record what Indians wore, what they ate, how they made a living, and what they believed
          in. In short, 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>told 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>: "You will therefore endeavor
          to make yourself acquainted as far as a diligent pursuit of your journey shall admit,
          with the names of the nations &amp; their numbers."
          <ref target="n0108" n="8"/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name>reasons for converting two
          army officers and at least some of their companions into ethnographers were central to
          the many purposes of the journey. One of those aims linked exploration and business
          enterprise to national expansion. Finding the passage to the 
          <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>was supposed to yield financial
          rewards. "The commerce," wrote 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, "which may be carried on
          with the people inhabiting the line you will pursue, renders a knolege of those people
          important."
          <ref target="n0109" n="9"/>The president did not fully understand the complex character
          of trade systems already functioning on the northern plains and in the 
          <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>Northwest. But he was intent on
          expanding American commercial influence. 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>knew that fur traders and
          other eager entrepreneurs needed to know about future markets and sources of supply. He
          envisioned western America as a vast trade empire to rival a similar system already
          being forged by agents of the Hudson's Bay Company and the North West Company. If the
          United States was to compete in the great western space race, Indians needed to be wooed
          away from John Bull's Canadian traders and written into the ledger books of Uncle Sam's 
          <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>merchants.</p>
               <p>But there was something else behind 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name>requirement that the 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>expedition be an ethnographic
          enterprise—something beyond sea otters and beaver pelts. 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>were to gather material for another
          empire—the empire of the mind, the kingdom of knowledge. Like his friends at the
          American Philosophical Society, 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>wanted the expedition to
          make a lasting contribution toward the scientific understanding of North America. That
          was what he meant when he described the venture as a "literary expedition." The
          knowledge was not to be gathered by the explorers for its own sake, however, but in the
          service of government and commerce.</p>
               <p>Finally, and not to be overlooked, there was 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name>vision of the future of
          the American republic. He believed that accurate information about Indians was essential
          in order to shape a peaceful environment for both peoples. The desire for fact to
          replace speculation about native Americans was nothing new in 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name>mind. From boyhood he had
          had a passionate interest in things Indian. "In the early part of my life," he wrote, "I
          was very familiar with the Indians, and acquired impressions of attachment and
          commiseration for them which have never been obliterated."
          <ref target="n0110" n="10"/>
                  <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name>fascination with Indian
          life and lore was part boyish curiosity and part scientific enquiry, all bound up in the
          optimistic notion that if native Americans surrendered their traditional "savage" ways
          and adopted a white "civilized" life, both peoples could enjoy the continent in peace.
          "Acuiqre what knolege you can of [their] state of morality, religion &amp; information"
          was the way 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>put it to 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>.
          <ref target="n0111" n="11"/>It was a Jeffersonian fundamental that if the two peoples
          knew each other more fully, each would treat the other with respect and consideration.
          Ethnography could make federal policy better informed and hence more humane. With an
          optimism based more on Enlightenment faith than American reality, 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>assumed that a benevolent
          government would use such information to civilize and Christianize Indians. Whether or
          not native people would welcome the spiritual and cultural blessings of European
          civilization was, of course, the unasked question.</p>
               <p>Ethnographical research was neither the prime nor the sole duty of the expedition. 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>wanted his explorers to take
          their scientific tasks seriously as they collected information and artifacts, but he had
          much more in mind. As representatives of the United States, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>were expected to pursue the Indian
          policy goals of the republic. By 1803 those goals for the tribes east of the 
          <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name>were quite clear.
          Reflecting long colonial experience, federal Indian policy sought to acquire native
          lands at low cost while urging tribal people to shuck off hunting and breechcloths for
          plows and trousers. Couched in the language of Christian philanthropy, Jeffersonian
          Indian policy pursued national expansion with single-minded zeal. But in the West of the
          Louisiana Purchase, Jefferson was less certain of both policy and strategy. Those new
          lands were for traders, not white settlers. They might even provide refuge for native
          people dispossessed by the farming frontier.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name>different approaches to
          tribes east and west of the 
          <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name>are plain in the language
          he used in addressing delegations from the various regions. In speaking to eastern
          delegations the president always coupled his program for civilization with land
          acquisition. To western delegations, including those organized by 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, trade was the prime focus. When 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>drafted instructions for 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>in 1803, negotiations with 
          <name type="place" key="France">France</name>were underway but the outcome was yet
          unclear. For that reason the diplomatic objectives enumerated in the directions for 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>focused on trade while tactfully
          ignoring questions of power and sovereignty. The expedition was ordered to acquaint
          Indians with "the position, extent, character, peaceable and commercial disposition of
          the United States, and of our dispositions to a commercial intercourse with them." The
          factory system, a chain of government trading posts, had been an integral part of
          American policy since the mid-1780s. 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>knew that attractive goods
          and suitable post locations were essential in the face of powerful British competition.
          For that reason 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>was told to confer with Indians
          on "the points most convenient as mutual emporiums" as well as "the articles of most
          desirable interchange for them and us."
          <ref target="n0112" n="12"/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>expected that 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>would hold frequent conferences
          with Indians. But he also knew that the rigorous demands of travel made extensive talks
          impossible. Therefore 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>was instructed to organize
          delegations of chiefs and elders to be sent to 
          <name type="place" key="Washington D.C.">Washington</name>. Just as colonial Indian
          agents once sent 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Mohawk Indians">Mohawks</name>and 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Cherokee Indians">Cherokees</name>to 
          <name type="place" key="London">London</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>assumed that 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Omahas</name>and 
          <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html" rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref>in the Federal City would be properly impressed with the wealth and power of the
          new nation. And in an afterthought whose origins looked back to the earliest days of
          Indian-European encounter, the president hoped the expedition might find some young
          Indians willing to be "brought up with us, and taught such arts as may be useful to
          them." It was a dream that had haunted missionary and bureaucrat alike—native children
          gladly leaving their parents to embrace new fathers.</p>
               <p>The creation of Indian delegations and a search for good trade sites were as close as
          
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>got in June 1803 to giving
          his explorers explicitly imperial and political directives. Although his commitment to
          an expanding nation was already plain, 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>was not about to give 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>instructions that violated
          territorial bounds as they existed before the Louisiana Purchase. The spread of American
          commercial influence would be quite sufficient. But once the purchase was diplomatic
          reality, announcing American sovereignty to native people became a vital part of the
          expedition's Indian policy. Parts of 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name>January 22, 1804, letter
          to 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>can be seen as an appendix to
          the original instructions. 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>were now formally to extend
          American power up the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>and toward the mountains. 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name>own words indicate how
          much the diplomatic role of the expedition had expanded since the summer of 1803: 
          <quote>Being now become sovereigns of the country, without however any diminution of the
          Indian rights of occupancy we are authorized to propose to them in direct terms the
          institution of commerce with them. It will now be proper you should inform those through
          whose country you will pass, or whom you may meet, that their late fathers the Spaniards
          have agreed to withdraw all their troops from all the waters and country of the 
          <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name>and 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, that they have surrendered to
          us all their subjects Spanish and French settled there, and all their posts and lands:
          that henceforward we become their fathers and friends, and that we shall endeavor that
          they shall have no cause to lament the change.</quote>In that same letter 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>gave 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>the only order specifically
          naming a tribe and the policy to be pursued with it. The president drew on sources that
          included Jonathan Carver's 
          <hi rend="italic">Travels through the Interior Parts of North America in the Years 1766,
          1767, and 1768</hi>(1778) and 
          <name type="person" key="Mackenzie, Alexander">Alexander Mackenzie's</name>
                  <hi rend="italic">Voyages . . . to the Frozen and 
          <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific Oceans</name>
                  </hi>(1801). More immediate
          information came from 
          <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>contacts. 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>recognized the central role
          played by 
          <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html" rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref>Indians in 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>Valley trade and politics. He did
          not know the full complexity of the system that bound together British traders, 
          <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html" rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref>hunters, and village farmers, nor did he realize just how far west 
          <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html" rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref>power had expanded. But the president did know that a 
          <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html" rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref>blockade on the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>could strangle an American fur
          trade empire based in 
          <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>. "On that nation," he
          commanded 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, "we wish most particularly to
          make a favorable impression, because of their immense power." 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name>claim that the 
          <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html" rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref>bands were "very desirous of being on the most friendly terms with us" was mostly
          wishful thinking. But that exercise in hope ultimately pointed the expedition toward
          what proved a nearly fatal confrontation with the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">Brulé</name>
                  <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html" rend="box">
          Sioux</ref>.
          <ref target="n0113" n="13"/>
               </p>
               <p>The expedition's success ultimately depended on friendly relations with the Indians. 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>was not about to unleash
          undisciplined adventurers to ride roughshod over them. Hostility between explorers and
          Indians could only endanger lives and weaken American influence. 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>knew firsthand what
          historian Charles Royster has written about American army officers in the late
          eighteenth century. Those men "saw threats and slights everywhere and reacted with
          fury."
          <ref target="n0114" n="14"/>Fear of overreaction, especially on the part of 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name>, was also on 
          <name type="person" key="Lincoln, Levi">Levi Lincoln's</name>mind when he counseled 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>to avoid instructions that
          might lead the young officer to risk his life unnecessarily. "From my ideas of 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name>," wrote 
          <name type="person" key="Lincoln, Levi">Lincoln</name>, "he will be much more likely, in
          case of difficulty, to push too far, than to recede too soon" 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>saw the wisdom in 
          <name type="person" key="Lincoln, Levi">Lincoln's</name>comments and changed the
          sentence in the instructions that once contained the phrase "certain destruction" to
          read instead "we value too much the lives of our citizens to offer them to probable
          destruction."
          <ref target="n0115" n="15"/>
                  <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>had shown considerable
          wisdom in making the exploration a military affair with proper organization and
          discipline. But he did not want the bumps and bruises of wilderness travel and
          encounters with strangers to provoke fatal overreaction. "In all your intercourse with
          the natives treat them in the most friendly and conciliatory manner which their own
          conduct will permit." That advice was not intended to understate the potential dangers
          or deny the expedition the ability to defend itself. 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>understood the hazards. What
          he feared was that after months of hardship and frustration, some small incident might
          touch off a sudden burst of violence. 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>were not to court self-destruction
          nor were they to wreak destruction on others. Survival would mean at least partial
          success; a glorious but futile death whether by accident or at the hands of an unknown
          foe would spell real failure.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>Colonial experience taught that fruitful diplomacy and peaceful relations with native
          people required the exchange of gifts at each meeting. French and English forest
          diplomats learned that lesson early and did their best to offer goods of substance and
          quality. While some Europeans may have perceived those gifts as bribes to ensure
          compliance with treaty terms, heaps of blankets, pots, and guns meant something else to
          the Indians. In the act of reciprocal gift giving, different peoples symbolized their
          concern for each other. Neglecting to give gifts meant failure to "brighten the chain of
          friendship" that bound Europeans and Indians together. Giving and receiving soothed hurt
          feelings and reestablished broken relations. By the time 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>created the Corps of
          Discovery, gifts were a recognized part of the protocol of Indian diplomacy. To venture
          up the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>without a carefully selected
          store of goods was to challenge foolishly the river gods.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>knew the gift-giving tradition
          and early in 1803 made note of funds to be set aside for presents for the Indians. In
          his initial tally of expedition costs, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>allocated $696 for trade goods.
          <ref target="n0116" n="16"/>Once in 
          <name type="place" key="Philadelphia, Pa.">Philadelphia</name>early in May 1803, he set
          about the task of locating and purchasing a wide variety of goods. In notes made on what
          might be obtained as trade items, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>demonstrated a sure grasp of
          frontier economics. Blue glass beads headed his list of most sought-after objects. It is
          probable that 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>learned from sources in the
          Pacific Northwest fur trade that those beads were "far more valued than the white beads
          of the same manufacture and answer[ed] all the purposes of money." Second on his list
          were common brass buttons, which the same sources may have told him were "more valued
          than any thing except beads." The explorer was also determined to find red-handled
          knives of the sort used by North West Company traders. Axes, tomahawks, moccasin awls,
          and camp kettles rounded out 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>catalog of high priorities. In
          addition to those items, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>planned to purchase substantial
          quantities of wampum, tobacco, and textiles. Vermilion face paint, one hundred cheap
          rings with glass stones, and a number of pairs of scissors completed his stock of
          essentials.
          <ref target="n0117" n="17"/>
               </p>
               <p>Using the services of 
          <name type="person" key="Whelan, Israel">Israel Whelan</name>, purveyor of public
          supplies, and 
          <name type="person" key="Irvine, William">General William Irvine</name>, superintendent
          of the 
          <name type="place" key="Schuylkill Arsenel">Schuylkill Arsenel</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>was able to amass a substantial
          outfit of Indian goods. From merchants in and around 
          <name type="place" key="Philadelphia, Pa.">Philadelphia</name>came everything from 4,600
          sewing needles and 500 brooches to 8 brass kettles and 2,800 fishhooks. There were
          stocks of hawks bells, thimbles, ruffled shirts, and eleven dozen of those red-handled
          knives. 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>was to discover only later that
          there were not nearly enough blue beads or brass buttons, an oversight that cost the
          expedition dearly among the 
          <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html" rend="box">Nez
          Perce</ref>and 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookan</name>Indians. And at 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name>direct command there were
          two corn grinders. They were there, one might guess, for use in teaching native farmers
          how to make pone and grits.
          <ref target="n0118" n="18"/>
               </p>
               <p>All of the gifts stowed in the expedition's luggage for transport to 
          <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>had a purpose beyond
          diplomatic protocol. Those items, everything from ivory combs to calico shirts,
          represented what the United States offered to potential trading partners. As 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>repeated to every delegation
          of western Indians, Americans sought commerce, not land. 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>were on the road to show American
          wares. The expedition was the mercantile and hardware display case for a trade empire on
          the move. Moccasin awls and brass kettles were as much symbols of American power as the
          medals and flags destined for headmen and warriors. Few of those manufactured products
          were new to Indians, but the promise of regular supplies and fair prices was bound to
          have some result. The Industrial Revolution had come to the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>Valley half a century before and
          it was equally well established on the Northwest coast. But 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, surrounded by bright mirrors and
          yards of red flannel, offered more than goods. They proposed membership in a system with
          well-established posts and dependable delivery schedules. And always in the background,
          visible but rarely mentioned, were guns and ammunition. 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>did not carry a special supply of
          weapons to offer for trade or as gifts, but they were not reluctant to promise firearms
          to potential customers and allies. Although 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>and his explorers honestly
          pursued intertribal peace as a requisite to trade, arming friends seemed equally
          reasonable. What all those gifts represented was, in fact, the fundamental element in 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name>western Indian policy.
          Trade and diplomacy, commerce and sovereignty were all parts of the engine that drove
          American expansion and guided the 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>expedition.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>On a snowy day at the end of December 1803, 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark</name>moved into his hut at what
          has come to be known as 
          <name type="place" key="Camp Dubois (Camp Wood, River Dubois) (Ill.)">Camp
          Dubois</name>. Situated on 
          <name type="place" key="Dubois River">Wood River</name>across the 
          <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name>from 
          <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>in present-day 
          <name type="place" key="Illinois">Illinois</name>, the camp provided the Corps of
          Discovery with a convenient place to prepare for the first season of exploration. The
          winter of 1803–1804 at 
          <name type="place" key="Camp Dubois (Camp Wood, River Dubois) (Ill.)">Camp
          Dubois</name>was more than a time to fit an odd lot of soldiers and frontiersmen to the
          discipline 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>believed essential for the
          expedition's success. The 
          <name type="place" key="Dubois River">Wood River</name>interlude allowed explorers time
          to gather and evaluate a large amount of information about the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri River</name>Indians. That material,
          coming from 
          <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>sources and from 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>himself constituted a crash
          course in Middle and Upper 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>tribes: their numbers, locations,
          and possible reactions to the expedition.</p>
               <p>No other city could have provided 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name>explorers with such a
          range and quality of information about the Indians. The currents of the 
          <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name>and 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>brought to 
          <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>not only pelts and skins but a
          vast store of knowledge and lore about the natives. Traders, merchants, government
          officers, and rough handed engagés all had experience that could prepare 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>for their Indian duties. The
          explorers needed to enter quickly that 
          <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>world and tap its resources.
          That meant cultivating a friendly relationship with the brothers Chouteau, 
          <name type="person" key="Chouteau, Pierre">Jean Pierre</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Chouteau, René Auguste">René Auguste</name>, who had come to
          dominate the Indian trade around 
          <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>and were anxious to expand
          their influence under the new American regime. The Chouteaus and their circle of friends
          and relatives quickly sought out the explorers. Social calls at 
          <name type="person" key="Chouteau, Pierre">Pierre's</name>house combined good food,
          friendly company, and valuable information. 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>went so far as to boast that the
          Chouteau house became a virtual Corps of Discovery outpost during the winter.
          <ref target="n0119" n="19"/>
               </p>
               <p>The Chouteau connection brought 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>into contact with the city's
          best-informed merchants. There was so much information available that 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>found it necessary to draft a
          form letter to give the data some structure. As he explained to 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, "I have proposed many
          quiries under sundry heads to the best informed persons I have met with at 
          <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>and within the vicinity of
          that place; these gentlemen have promised me answers in due time." A list of questions 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>sent to 
          <name type="person" key="Chouteau, René Auguste">René Auguste Chouteau</name>early in
          January 1804 indicates the range of information the explorer was seeking. While most of
          the questions referred to white settlers and their current economic and political
          situation, there was room to comment on Indians and trade matters.
          <ref target="n0120" n="20"/>
               </p>
               <p>Because the Chouteaus made themselves so available and accommodating to 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, there has been a tendency to
          overlook others who provided vital and perhaps more relevant Indian information. Chief
          among those were 
          <name type="person" key="Hay, John">John Hay</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">James Mackay</name>. Hay, United States
          postmaster at 
          <name type="place" key="Cahokia, Ill.">Cahokia</name>, was an experienced Indian trader
          on the 
          <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name>. He also spoke French, and
          when 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>visited 
          <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>commandant 
          <name type="person" key="Delassus, Don Carlos Dehault">Carlos Dehault Delassus</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Hay, John">Hay</name>and his fellow trader 
          <name type="person" key="Jarrot, Nicholas">Nicholas Jarrot</name>went along to
          interpret. Even more important, 
          <name type="person" key="Hay, John">Hay</name>provided the link to 
          <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">James Mackay</name>. 
          <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">Mackay</name>was perhaps the most widely
          traveled of the many traders 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>met during the 
          <name type="place" key="Camp Dubois (Camp Wood, River Dubois) (Ill.)">Camp
          Dubois</name>winter. During the 1780s, 
          <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">Mackay</name>explored the 
          <name type="place" key="Assiniboine River">Assiniboine</name>and 
          <name type="place" key="Souris (Mouse) River">Mouse river</name>s and visited the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>villages, along with North
          West Company employees from 
          <name type="place" key="Fort Esperance (Canada)">Fort Esperance</name>on the 
          <name type="place" key="Qu'Appelle (Catapie, Cappell) River">Qu'Appelle River</name>. By
          the mid-1790s the Scot had switched his political loyalties and was employed by the 
          <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>-based and Spanish-controlled
          Missouri Company. When he met 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>early in 1804, 
          <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">Mackay</name>had already ascended the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri River</name>as far as the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Omaha Indians</name>in what is now 
          <name type="place" key="Dakota County, Nebr.">Dakota County</name>, 
          <name type="place" key="Nebraska">Nebraska</name>. Even more important, he had sent his
          Welsh lieutenant, 
          <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">John Evans</name>, to the 
          <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Mandan.html" rend="box">
          Mandans</ref>and had entertained notions of sending 
          <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name>across the mountains to the 
          <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>. 
          <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">Mackay's</name>call at 
          <name type="place" key="Camp Dubois (Camp Wood, River Dubois) (Ill.)">Camp
          Dubois</name>on January 10, 1804, brought a lifetime of information on native people and
          Indian-white relations on the northern plains. Although 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>did not record what passed between
          the two explorers, there can be little doubt that their conversation was enlivened by 
          <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">Mackay's</name>rich supply of experiences with
          the Indians.
          <ref target="n0121" n="21"/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>recognized that men like 
          <name type="person" key="Hay, John">Hay</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">Mackay</name>, and the Chouteaus could offer
          invaluable information. But there were other sources of information in 
          <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>, men of the river perhaps
          less literate but with more immediate experience among Indians. 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>needed that sort of firsthand
          knowledge. While the captains could question their own engagés, some of whom had logged
          considerable river time, there were others beyond easy reach. As 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>explained it to 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, "Some of the traders of
          this country from their continued intercourse with the Indians, possess with more
          accuracy many interesting particulars in relation to that people, than persons in a
          higher sphere of life." The problem was that those men lacked "both leasure and
          abilities to give this information in any satisfactory manner in detail." Determined to
          get that material, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>hit upon the idea of drawing "a
          form of paper containing 13 or 14 columns," each headed with a different topic relating
          to native people. 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>had already circulated such
          forms by late December 1803 and felt certain that his plan would yield important data.
          The questionnaires may have proved successful, but unfortunately, neither blank forms
          nor completed ones have survived.
          <ref target="n0122" n="22"/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>got more than talk from their 
          <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>contacts. Friendly meetings
          brought maps and journals produced by earlier expeditions up the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>. Of all the written material the
          explorers were able to study, none was more valuable for its Indian content than the
          journals and notes produced by 
          <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">James Mackay</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">John Evans</name>. In a letter to 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>reported that he had obtained 
          <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">Mackay's</name>journal material dating from 1795
          to 1797. Those entries, written in French, were being translated by the ever-useful 
          <name type="person" key="Hay, John">John Hay</name>.
          <ref target="n0123" n="23"/>No explorer destined for the northern plains could miss the
          import of those documents. Taken together, the 
          <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name>-
          <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">Mackay</name>file made several major points.
          There was the prospect of a rich trade to be exploited among both villagers and nomads.
          But success in that trade hinged on a reliable system with dependable Indian partners. 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>could not have missed 
          <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">Mackay's</name>singling out of the 
          <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Mandan.html" rend="box">
          Mandans</ref>as the Indians most helpful to traders. "The 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandaines</name>," wrote 
          <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">James Mackay</name>, "as well all other nations
          that inhabit to their West, near the 
          <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky Mountains</name>, are in general people
          as good as they are mild who lay a great value on the friendship of the Whites." The 
          <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name>-
          <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">Mackay</name>material also revealed the extent
          of international competition for trade on the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>. French, Spanish, and English
          interests were already on the river, and reading 
          <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">Mackay</name>reminded the explorers that their
          diplomacy would be for high stakes. 
          <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">Mackay's</name>observation that courting the 
          <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Mandan.html" rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>
                  </ref>could "put a Stop to the unjust progress of the English" was written for Spanish
          eyes, but its meaning was not lost on the Americans.
          <ref target="n0124" n="24"/>Finally, the 
          <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name>-
          <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">Mackay</name>journals brought home how much
          Indian opposition might be provoked by an American trade empire based in 
          <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>. The 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Omahas</name>, 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name>, and some of the 
          <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html" rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref>bands had already made life miserable for traders bound upriver. 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>would have to deal with Indians who
          assumed it was their right to collect tolls on the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>highway.</p>
               <p>The 
          <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">Mackay</name>materials were of such great
          importance that 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>probably took along 
          <name type="person" key="Hay, John">Hay's</name>translation of 
          <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">Mackay's</name>journal. It is more certain that
          a second document from 
          <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">Mackay</name>made the transcontinental passage.
          Sometime during the winter at 
          <name type="place" key="Camp Dubois (Camp Wood, River Dubois) (Ill.)">Camp Dubois</name>
                  <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">Mackay's</name>"Notes on Indian Tribes" came
          into the possession of the expedition. That twelve-page report summarized the trader's
          early experiences with the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians, Piegan">Piegans</name>and his 1787
          visit to the 
          <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Mandan.html" rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>
                  </ref>. In the "Notes" 
          <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">Mackay</name>offered a blend of current opinion
          on the origin and condition of the Indians and his own observations of their ways. He
          had something chatty to say on everything from religion to burials. Most important for
          the expedition's purposes, the trader made astute comments on the lives of the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri River</name>villagers. Drawing on his
          own visit to the 
          <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Mandan.html" rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>
                  </ref>and 
          <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans's</name>experiences with the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name>and 
          <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Mandan.html" rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>
                  </ref>, 
          <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">Mackay</name>briefly described the construction
          of earth lodges, the layout of towns, and the yearly patterns of farming and hunting. 
          <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">Mackay's</name>"Notes" was yet another text in 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>education.
          <ref target="n0125" n="25"/>
               </p>
               <p>The last piece of written material on Indian subjects had a 
          <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>source but came to 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>from 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>. In his November 16 letter
          to 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, the president sent along
          extracts from the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri River</name>trade journal attributed to
          
          <name type="person" key="Truteau, Jean Baptiste">Jean Baptiste Truteau</name>. Working
          for the Company of Explorers of the Upper 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Truteau, Jean Baptiste">Truteau</name>traded upriver as far as
          the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name>from 1794 to 1796. What 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>sent was a compilation of
          the tribes living along the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>and its tributaries. By studying
          the list, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>could gain further information
          about their numbers and locations. Many tribes that figured in the expedition's future
          were briefly noted in the journal. Those included the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Oto Indians">Otos</name>, 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Omahas</name>, the 
          <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html" rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref>bands, 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name>, and 
          <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Mandan.html" rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>
                  </ref>. Although the extracts did not plainly spell out the complex relations between
          those groups, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>were at least beginning to fix
          peoples and places in the mental geography of the expedition.
          <ref target="n0126" n="26"/>
               </p>
               <p>Establishing hunting territories and village locations in their minds was made easier
          by several important maps 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>examined during the winter at 
          <name type="place" key="Camp Dubois (Camp Wood, River Dubois) (Ill.)">Camp
          Dubois</name>. When 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>gathered and compared maps, he was
          primarily in search of information to guide the expedition over the best route to the 
          <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>. But 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, who emerged as the expedition's
          cartographer, could not have missed the substantial body of Indian data contained in
          many of the maps he studied. Three maps in particular held valuable information on
          village sites and native populations. Those maps gave visual expression to the written
          material coming into 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>hands.</p>
               <p>Among the maps that the explorers looked at was one 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>described as "a general map of
          Uper 
          <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name>." It had been drawn by 
          <name type="person" key="Soulard, Antoine">Antoine Soulard</name>, surveyor general of
          Spanish Louisiana. 
          <name type="person" key="Soulard, Antoine">Soulard</name>prepared the Spanish version in
          1794–95 at the direction of Governor Carondelet to guide the explorations of 
          <name type="person" key="Truteau, Jean Baptiste">Jean Baptiste Truteau</name>. Sometime
          after the journeys of 
          <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">Mackay</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Soulard, John Thomas">Soulard</name>drafted versions of the map
          with English and French legends. It was the English version, entitled "A Topographical
          Sketch of the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>and Upper 
          <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name>Exhibiting the Various
          Nations and Tribes who inhabit the Country," that now came into 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>possession. 
          <name type="person" key="Soulard, Antoine">Soulard's</name>map demonstrated with
          remarkable accuracy the locations of western Indians at the end of the eighteenth
          century. Along the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>and its tributaries 
          <name type="person" key="Soulard, Antoine">Soulard</name>placed the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Oto Indians">Oto</name>, 
          <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Pawnee.html" rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Pawnee Indians">Pawnee</name>
                  </ref>, and 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Omaha</name>peoples. Using simple circle
          and triangle symbols, the surveyor general noted 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name>and 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>villages and the
          territories of nomadic 
          <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html" rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref>, 
          <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Cheyenne.html" rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Cheyenne Indians">Cheyennes</name>
                  </ref>, and 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Assiniboine Indians">Assiniboins</name>. Farther north
          Soulard sites the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name>and 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Chippewa Indians">Chipewyans</name>. The 
          <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Crow.html" rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Crow Indians">Crow</name>
                  </ref>and 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Snakes</name>(
          <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Shoshoni.html" rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshonis</name>
                  </ref>) marked the western limit of 
          <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>knowledge. Looking at 
          <name type="person" key="Soulard, Antoine">Soulard's</name>map must have been a
          reassuring experience for the explorers: it showed the headwaters of the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>within easy travel to what 
          <name type="person" key="Soulard, Antoine">Soulard</name>labeled "Oregan or R. of the
          West." Indians that 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>had heard about from 
          <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>traders were on the map and in
          the expected places. This was not a map to chart a daily course on the river, but it did
          offer the sort of overview of the tribes that the explorers would need for much of their
          diplomacy. And because such diplomacy was closely linked to trade, 
          <name type="person" key="Soulard, Antoine">Soulard's</name>careful delineation of trade
          routes was a valuable bonus.
          <ref target="n0127" n="27"/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>certainly could have extracted a
          good deal of ethnographic information from the map. But at its best 
          <name type="person" key="Soulard, Antoine">Soulard's</name>creation did not reflect the
          kinds of immediate river and Indian contact the explorers sought. That sort of
          information could come only from maps drawn by 
          <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">James Mackay</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">John Evans</name>. After 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>wrote to Indiana territorial
          governor 
          <name type="person" key="Harrison, William Henry">William Henry Harrison</name>seeking
          his help in locating accurate western maps, 
          <name type="person" key="Harrison, William Henry">Harrison</name>sent 
          <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">Mackay's</name>chart of the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>from 
          <name type="place" key="Saint Charles, Mo.">St. Charles</name>to the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>villages. While having a
          far narrower range than the 
          <name type="person" key="Soulard, Antoine">Soulard</name>map, 
          <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">Mackay's</name>work did offer a precise,
          firsthand view of tribes and villages along the river. 
          <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">Mackay's</name>sequence of Indian sites on the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>was essentially correct, but his
          location of the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>villages at longitude 110°
          west put those earth lodges some four hundred miles farther west than they actually
          were. Whatever its geographical misconceptions, the 
          <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">Mackay</name>map brought 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>another step closer to knowing what
          Indians were around the next bend in the river.
          <ref target="n0128" n="28"/>
               </p>
               <p>The 
          <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">Mackay</name>map was an important addition to
          the expedition's understanding of the plains landscape and its people. But a map made by
          
          <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">John Evans</name>became what one recent
          scholar has called a major "road map" for the expedition for no less than seven hundred
          miles.
          <ref target="n0129" n="29"/>The 
          <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name>map of the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri River</name>consisted of seven sheets
          depicting the course of the river and the location of the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Omaha</name>, 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Ponca Indians">Ponca</name>, 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name>, 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>, and 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name>villages. Those places
          along the river frequented by 
          <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html" rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref>bands were also noted. By examining the 
          <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name>map along with the ones by 
          <name type="person" key="Soulard, Antoine">Soulard</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">Mackay</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>could know with some certainty what
          Indian would be encountered next. The 
          <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name>map was taken on the voyage and
          became an invaluable tool for both navigation and diplomacy. All these maps completed
          what might be termed the expedition's academic education in the Indian geography of the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>Valley. The maps, journals, and
          river talk could not lessen the shock of encounter that lay ahead, but they might at
          least give the explorers a sense of the predictable in an uncertain land.</p>
               <p>The first test of that education came even before leaving 
          <name type="place" key="Camp Dubois (Camp Wood, River Dubois) (Ill.)">Camp
          Dubois</name>. The Indian presents so carefully purchased in 
          <name type="place" key="Philadelphia, Pa.">Philadelphia</name>needed to be organized in
          some logical order. It made good sense to package trade goods, medals, flags, and fancy
          dress uniforms in the order in which they were to be distributed. Here again 
          <name type="person" key="Hay, John">John Hay</name>proved indispensable. As an
          experienced trader he knew the finer points of packaging and merchandising. It was
          probably 
          <name type="person" key="Hay, John">Hay</name>who suggested putting a variety of gifts
          into bags protected by waterproof fabric. Those bags were first divided into two general
          groups, one for the Indians on the river up to the 
          <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Mandan.html" rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>
                  </ref>and a second set for "foreign nations." All told, there were to be twenty-one
          bags of Indian goods. As 
          <name type="person" key="Hay, John">Hay</name>worked on packing in late April 1804, the
          explorers showed that they had learned their lessons well. Bundles were made up for the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Oto Indians">Otos</name>, 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Ponca Indians">Poncas</name>, and 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Omahas</name>. Knowing the great power of
          
          <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Omaha</name>leaders like the late 
          <name type="person" key="Blackbird">Chief Blackbird</name>, they set aside a separate
          part of one bag for the leading 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Omaha</name>chief. That bag had
          everything from a pair of scarlet leggings to a military officer's coat and American
          flag. There were similar bags for the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name>and 
          <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Mandan.html" rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>
                  </ref>. For those Indians beyond the 
          <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Mandan.html" rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>
                  </ref>there were five bales stuffed with peace medals, fancy handkerchiefs, hat bands,
          and mirrors.
          <ref target="n0130" n="30"/>The careful order in which those bales were packed annd
          numbered testified to how much 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>had learned during the months at 
          <name type="place" key="Camp Dubois (Camp Wood, River Dubois) (Ill.)">Camp
          Dubois</name>. On paper, at least, they knew the human contours of the land ahead. Those
          neatly tied packages should have been reassuring. But 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>was not confident. Just one day
          before leaving 
          <name type="place" key="Camp Dubois (Camp Wood, River Dubois) (Ill.)">Camp
          Dubois</name>he looked at the presents and thought they were "not as much as I think
          necessary for the multitude of Indians thro which we must pass on our road across the
          Continent."
          <ref target="n0131" n="31"/>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>As the 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>flotilla—keelboat and
          pirogues—rocked against the river current, it represented months of careful preparation.
          Armed with calico shirts, peace medals, and blank vocabulary sheets, the expedition
          seemed ready to carry out its many Indian missions. But there was still one unanswered
          question, one nagging doubt that no talk, map, or journal could resolve. How would the
          explorers cope with the inevitable tensions hidden in dozens of encounters with the
          Indians? 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>had long recognized the dangers.
          While working out travel schedules, he admitted that the accuracy of those time tables
          depended on "the probability of an oppisition from roving parties of Bad Indians which
          it is probable may be on the R[iver]."
          <ref target="n0132" n="32"/>Unchecked emotions, moments of fury from either Indians or
          explorers, could cost lives and destroy the expedition. Perhaps the greatest uncharted
          space ahead was a human space.</p>
               <p>Into that emptiness went men of diverse backgrounds and unknown temperaments. Young
          frontiersmen recruited by 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>might have been crack shots, but
          would memories of Indian warfare on the dark and bloody ground of 
          <name type="place" key="Kentucky">Kentucky</name>boil up whenever they saw Indians? The
          expedition matched young privates like 
          <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">George Shannon</name>with old hands 
          <name type="person" key="Hall, Hugh">Hugh Hall</name>and the 
          <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph and Reubin">Field brothers</name>
                  <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Joseph</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">Reuben</name>. 
          <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>engagés added river wisdom and
          colorful songs to the Corps. Among them 
          <name type="person" key="Labiche, François">François Labiche</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Pierre Cruzatte</name>stood out for their two
          winters spent at the mouth of the 
          <name type="place" key="Nodaway River">Nodaway River</name>some 450 miles up the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>. Towering over them all as a
          frontiersman was 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">George Drouillard</name>. Born of French
          and Shawnee parents, he had spent years in the 
          <name type="place" key="Illinois">Illinois</name>country. Woodsman, tracker, adept at
          sign language, 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name>emerged as the
          expedition's chief hunter and scout. Young 
          <name type="person" key="Colter, John">John Colter</name>could not have had a better
          teacher. 
          <name type="place" key="New Hampshire">New Hampshire</name>-born 
          <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">John Ordway</name>quickly caught the captains'
          attention and became the Corps of Discovery's sergeant major. And there was 
          <name type="person" key="York">York</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>slave, whose blackness would
          fascinate and frighten so many Indians.</p>
               <p>Finally, there were the captains themselves. Despite 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name>assertion that 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>was chosen for his "familiarity
          with the Indian character," the young officer had neither fought Indians nor lived with
          them.
          <ref target="n0133" n="33"/>He spoke no Indian languages. 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name>library might have been
          filled with books about Indians, but there is no direct evidence that 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>read any of those volumes. His
          contacts with 
          <name type="person" key="Rush, Benjamin">Benjamin Rush</name>and other 
          <name type="place" key="Philadelphia, Pa.">Philadelphia</name>students of native
          cultures were all too brief. In fact, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>frontier experience was
          limited to travel in the 
          <name type="place" key="Ohio River">Ohio</name>country on missions for army paymasters
          and recruiters. Those journeys gave 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>firsthand knowledge of the
          officer corps—one of the reasons 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>selected him as private
          secretary—but they did not fit him to negotiate with confident chiefs and experienced
          warriors. 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>life as soldier and surveyor did
          bring him into direct contact with Indians. Unlike many in his position, he had become
          an acute observer of native life and a confidant of chiefs and warriors—both
          ethnographer and diplomat. In ways that are beyond easy explanation, he enjoyed the
          company of Indians. Throughout his life 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>courted them, smoked with them, and
          shared food and stories with them. But this personal history was just a beginning. The
          expedition was to challenge each man in ways yet unimagined. Surveying their untested
          crew and themselves, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>could only hope that the patience,
          skill, and courage of some would sustain all until the Corps of Discovery found its own
          soul.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>The "road across the Continent" began in mid-May 1804 as the expedition steadily left
          behind the familiar sights of 
          <name type="place" key="Camp Dubois (Camp Wood, River Dubois) (Ill.)">Camp
          Dubois</name>and 
          <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>. In the days that followed
          there was time for a green crew to learn the dangers of falling banks, swirling
          currents, and hidden sawyers that could rip and overturn a craft. Those first weeks on
          the river brought reminders that the fur trade already reached far up the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>. The explorers saw rafts and
          canoes filled with furs from the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Omaha</name>and 
          <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Pawnee.html" rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Pawnee Indians">Pawnee</name>
                  </ref>villages. River traffic also brought the expedition some valuable information.
          Late in May, around the isolated village of 
          <name type="place" key="La Charette, Mo.">La Charette</name>, the explorers met 
          <name type="person" key="Loisel, Régis">Régis Loisel</name>. A prominent member of the
          Missouri Fur Company, he was on his way back downriver after establishing a post to
          garner the 
          <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html" rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref>and 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name>trade. The experienced 
          <name type="person" key="Loisel, Régis">Loisel</name>gave 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>"a good Deel of information" about
          Indian relations far up the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>. He may well have urged the
          explorers to obtain additional aid from his partners 
          <name type="person" key="Tabeau, Pierre-Antoine">Pierre Antoine Tabeau</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Garreau, Joseph">Joseph Garreau</name>at their 
          <name type="place" key="Dorion Island No. 2 (Cedar Island)">Cedar Island</name>post.
          <ref target="n0134" n="34"/>
               </p>
               <p>Early in June there was another fortunate meeting, this time with an Indian language
          interpreter. The expedition was not well prepared to deal with translation problems,
          especially those involving important conferences with the 
          <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html" rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref>. 
          <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Pierre Cruzatte</name>knew a few words and
          phrases and there were 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard's</name>signs. Coming upon
          another 
          <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>-bound party of traders, the
          captains met 
          <name type="person" key="Dorion, Pierre, Sr.">Pierre Dorion</name>. The Frenchman had
          spent some twenty years with the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Yankton">Yankton</name>
                  <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html" rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Yankton">Sioux</name>
                  </ref>and their neighbors. He was just the sort of agent 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>needed to interpret at crucial
          conferences and to organize important delegations. 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Dorion, Pierre, Sr.">Dorion</name>was promptly hired
          with the understanding that he would remain with the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Yankton">Yanktons</name>to promote the
          expedition's Indian policy.
          <ref target="n0135" n="35"/>
               </p>
               <p>By the last days of July the expedition had passed the mouth of the 
          <name type="place" key="Platte River (Nebr.)">Platte River</name>, known to old river
          hands as the dividing line between the lower 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>and the middle reach of the
          river. Mosquitoes, gnats, and a prairie landscape were all unmistakable signs of the
          expedition's progress. Information gathered at 
          <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>and the words of engagés told 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>to prepare for their first meetings
          with Indians. Along these parts of the river the explorers expected to see 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Oto Indians">Oto</name>, 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Missouri Indians">Missouri</name>, 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Omaha</name>, 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Ponca Indians">Ponca</name>, and perhaps 
          <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Pawnee.html" rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Pawnee Indians">Pawnee</name>
                  </ref>Indians. On July 20, camped above present-day 
          <name type="place" key="Nebraska City, Nebr.">Nebraska City</name>, 
          <name type="place" key="Nebraska">Nebraska</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>speculated that from his location a
          man could walk in two days to the 
          <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Pawnee.html" rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Pawnee Indians">Pawnees</name>
                  </ref>on the 
          <name type="place" key="Platte River (Nebr.)">Platte</name>and in one day to the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Oto Indians">Otos</name>. Those Indians ought to be
          close at hand. Perhaps it was 
          <name type="person" key="Labiche, François">Labiche</name>or 
          <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Cruzatte</name>who told 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>that at this time of year most
          river folk left their villages to hunt buffalo. Those hunts threatened to scuttle
          expedition diplomacy even before it was launched.
          <ref target="n0136" n="36"/>
               </p>
               <p>Two days later, some ten miles above the 
          <name type="place" key="Platte River (Nebr.)">Platte</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>settled into a place on the 
          <name type="place" key="Iowa">Iowa</name>side of the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>with the delightful name of 
          <name type="place" key="Camp White Catfish (Iowa)">Camp White Catfish</name>. From that
          spot the explorers planned to send out parties to invite Indians for formal talks. On
          July 23 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">George Drouillard</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Pierre Cruzatte</name>were given parcels of
          tobacco and ordered to find the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Oto Indians">Otos</name>and 
          <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Pawnee.html" rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Pawnee Indians">Pawnees</name>
                  </ref>. Some signs, undisclosed in expeditionary records, suggested that at least a few
          river Indians had returned from hunting to obtain additional corn supplies. Taking this
          as a hopeful sign, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>confidently raised a flagstaff and
          waited anxiously for their native guests. Those preparations ended suddenly two days
          later when 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Cruzatte</name>returned with unwelcome news.
          They had quickly found the major 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Oto Indians">Oto</name>town but it was quite empty.
          There were some traces of a small Indian party in the area, but neither scout could
          locate it. Disappointed and concerned, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>decided to press upriver in the
          hope that they might still come upon some Indians.
          <ref target="n0137" n="37"/>
               </p>
               <p>The expedition's fortunes took a change for the better on July 28 when 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name>happened on a 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Missouri Indians">Missouri Indian</name>. Once back at
          the expedition's camp, the Indian revealed that his own band was quite small, no more
          than twenty lodges. Their numbers now seriously depleted by smallpox, the surviving 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Missouri Indians">Missouris</name>lived with the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Oto Indians">Otos</name>. The main body of Otos was
          still out hunting. Acting on that information, the captains sent the engagé 
          <name type="person" key="La Liberté">La Liberté</name>, who could speak the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Oto Indians">Oto</name>language, back with the Indian to
          deliver a formal council invitation. The expedition planned to continue upriver and the
          Otos could find them farther along. At the end of July, in bottomland on the west bank
          of the river at what became 
          <name type="place" key="Fort Atkinson (Nebr.)">Fort Atkinson</name>, 
          <name type="place" key="Nebraska">Nebraska</name>, the expedition once again halted and
          waited for the Indians.
          <ref target="n0138" n="38"/>
               </p>
               <p>After two days of patient waiting, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>were plainly worried. They knew it
          might take some time for "much scatred" hunters to be located and to make their way to
          the river. Nonetheless, 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>could not help admitting, "We fear
          Something amiss with our messenger or them." The captains sent out another man to hurry 
          <name type="person" key="La Liberté">La Liberté</name>and the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Oto Indians">Otos</name>.
          <ref target="n0139" n="39"/>All that worry vanished at sunset on August 2 when a party
          of 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Oto Indians">Otos</name>and 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Missouri Indians">Missouris</name>appeared at the 
          <name type="place" key="Council Bluff (Nebr.)">Council Bluff</name>camp. Along with them
          was a trader whose name 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>rendered as 
          <name type="person" key="Farfonge">Fairfong</name>, although he has never been properly
          identified. 
          <name type="person" key="Farfonge">Fairfong</name>knew the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Oto Indians">Otos</name>and had their trust. The leading
          
          <name type="native_nation" key="Oto Indians">Oto</name>and 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Missouri Indians">Missouri</name>chiefs, 
          <name type="person" key="Little Thief">Little Thief</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Big Horse">Big Horse</name>, were not with the delegation but 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>were gratified to see six headmen.
          At dusk the explorers arranged a hasty greeting, sent gifts of roasted meat, and asked
          the Indians to attend a council the next day.
          <ref target="n0140" n="40"/>
               </p>
               <p>As fog hung in the river bottoms on Friday morning, August 3, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>set about preparing for their first
          conference with the Indians. What the explorers did that morning linked them to
          generations of forest diplomats. The form and substance were dictated by common
          expectations resulting from years of woodland encounters. It was the sort of ritual 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>had seen at the council negotiating
          the Treaty of Greenville with 
          <name type="person" key="Wayne, Anthony">General Anthony Wayne</name>in 1795. If the
          subsequent history of the expedition is any guide, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>spent those early hours
          finishing his draft of a long speech proclaiming American sovereignty and the coming of
          new traders. 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>may well have spent the same time
          supervising the preparation of gifts. Opening bale number thirty, the men took out red
          leggings, fancy dress coats, and blue blankets. Setting aside flags and medals, they
          carefully packed the trade goods in individual bundles whose size and quality were
          determined by the rank of each chief. A special package was made up for the absent chief
          Little Thief. Although gifts and speeches had long been part of any Indian meeting,
          warriors and soldiers always made it a point to show military prowess as well. 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>were determined to impress every
          Indian they met with the power of the young republic. Sergeants 
          <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Floyd, Charles">Floyd</name>, and 
          <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Pryor</name>must have been busy that
          morning readying their squads for a formal dress parade. At the same time, other men
          were detailed to convert the keelboat's main sail into a temporary awning to shield the
          diplomats from the August sun. A flag and flagstaff completed the setting. What would
          become routine in the months ahead was still new and fresh, and there must have been an
          electric excitement in camp as the Corps of Discovery waited for the Indians to
          arrive.</p>
               <p>At midmorning the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Oto Indians">Oto</name>and 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Missouri Indians">Missouri</name>delegation, with trader
          
          <name type="person" key="Farfonge">Fairfong</name>in tow, assembled under the sailcloth
          awning to watch something like a 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>Medicine Show. At the command, the
          expedition's troops shouldered arms, dressed right, and passed in review. 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>then stepped forward to deliver
          a long speech summarizing federal Indian policy. Because its language and themes were to
          be repeated many times in the coming months, the speech is worth careful attention.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>began with the grand
          announcement of American sovereignty over the newly purchased lands. The 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Oto Indians">Otos</name>and 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Missouri Indians">Missouris</name>were told bluntly that
          their Spanish and French fathers had retreated beyond the eastern sea and would never
          return. In their place was a new father, the "great chief of the Seventeen nations," and
          it was his will that all would "now form one common family with us." Explaining the
          nature of the expedition's mission always proved a difficult task; the first time 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>tried it the best he could do
          was declare that the explorers were on the river "to clear the road, remove every
          obstruction, and make it a road of peace." Just who was to mark out that "road of peace"
          and where it might lead were matters 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>addressed next. Urging the
          Indians to "shut [their] ears to the councils of Bad birds," the diplomat insisted that
          the new American father and his sons would bring peace and prosperity to "red children
          on the troubled waters." Those "red children" were required to make peace with their
          neighbors and trade with 
          <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>merchants. If those words were
          heeded, advised 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, traders would come, a post
          would be built near the mouth of the 
          <name type="place" key="Platte River (Nebr.)">Platte</name>, and the Indians would
          "obtain goods on much better terms than . . . before." But 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>words had the edge of threat
          as well. If river Indians ignored American orders and followed the "bad birds," trade
          would be cut off and there would be much suffering.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>concluded with what he saw as a
          crucial test of native willingness to accept the new order. He urged 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Oto Indians">Oto</name>and 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Missouri Indians">Missouri</name>chiefs to form a
          delegation to visit the great 
          <name type="place" key="Washington D.C.">Washington</name>chief. Those delegates could
          see for themselves both the wealth of the American nation and the contentment of Indians
          already living under the federal father. And if they submitted to the great chief, those
          in the delegation would be showerd with gifts and honors. Declaring that the traders of
          yesterday were gone, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>held out 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>and the American nation as
          "the only friend to whom you can now look for protection."
          <ref target="n0141" n="41"/>
               </p>
               <p>Because chiefs like 
          <name type="person" key="Little Thief">Little Thief</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Big Horse">Big Horse</name>were not in camp, the responses
          offered by those Indians who were present did not capture much of the expedition's
          attention. But what fragments are in the record remain important to gauge early native
          reaction to 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>. 
          <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Patrick Gass</name>, soon to become a sergeant
          after the untimely death of 
          <name type="person" key="Floyd, Charles">Charles Floyd</name>, said that the Indians
          were "well pleased" with the change in government. But that supposed pleasure at seeing
          new fathers was not widely felt by tribes along the lower river. Generated by news of
          the Louisiana Purchase, rumors had been flying for months that the Americans would
          radically change trading rules. In December 1804 a fearful 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Osage Indians">Osage</name>came to 
          <name type="place" key="Camp Dubois (Camp Wood, River Dubois) (Ill.)">Camp
          Dubois</name>filled with stories from an English trader who alleged that once the
          Americans had the country, trade would be disrupted.
          <ref target="n0142" n="42"/>The reaction of some 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Osage Indians">Osages</name>on the 
          <name type="place" key="Arkansas River">Arkansas River</name>was even more forceful.
          When a Chouteau agent announced the purchase, his letter was seized and burned, "the
          Indians not believing that the Americans had possession of the Countrey."
          <ref target="n0143" n="43"/>Some 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Oto Indians">Otos</name>and their neighbors, who got
          goods from traders of various nationalities, may well have shared those concerns. The
          delegates at 
          <name type="place" key="Council Bluff (Nebr.)">Council Bluff</name>did nothing so
          dramatic, but they may have wondered about the economic consequences of new flags and
          medals hearing unfamiliar faces. In fact, what the chiefs did talk about was trade. The 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Oto Indians">Otos</name>and their neighbors wanted a
          dependable source of goods. After years of spotty contact with English and French
          traders, the Indians were intent on finding and joining a reliable system. Complaining
          that Spanish and French traders "never gave them as much as a knife for nothing," it was
          plain that the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Oto Indians">Otos</name>and 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Missouri Indians">Missouris</name>hoped the Americans
          would be more generous. Although 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>was unimpressed with the replies,
          calling the chiefs "no oreters," 
          <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>found the speeches "very
          sensable."</p>
               <p>The day ended with more gifts—powder, whiskey, face paint, and fancy garters—and
          ceremony. Peace medals were distributed and 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>gave the first of many airgun
          demonstrations. That silent weapon was impressive, but promises of trade meant more to
          the assembled Indians. And if the explorers could negotiate a peace between the feuding 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Oto Indians">Otos</name>and 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Omahas</name>, that would surely add to
          American prestige. The Indians were both cautious and interested and 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>finished the meeting with a sense
          of achievement. Although 
          <name type="person" key="Little Thief">Little Thief</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Big Horse">Big Horse</name>had not spoken, the captains were
          confident that the wisdom of American policy, the lure of 
          <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>trade, and the force of
          federal arms would prevail.
          <ref target="n0144" n="44"/>
               </p>
               <p>Several days later 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>followed up what they viewed as an
          initial diplomatic success by sending a copy of 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>speech and a parcel of gifts
          to 
          <name type="person" key="Little Thief">Little Thief</name>. That an equally suitable
          gift and a medal of proper grade were not sent to the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Missouri Indians">Missouri</name>chief 
          <name type="person" key="Big Horse">Big Horse</name>was an oversight due to the hurry to
          press upriver. The party transporting the goods was instructed to ask the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Oto Indians">Otos</name>to send a delegation toward the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Omaha</name>village, there to cement good
          relations. By August 12 the expedition had passed the hilltop grave of the mighty Omaha
          chief 
          <name type="person" key="Blackbird">Blackbird</name>near present-day 
          <name type="place" key="Macy, Nebr.">Macy</name>, 
          <name type="place" key="Nebraska">Nebraska</name>, and expected to meet his successors
          at any moment. While the main body of the expedition stopped to prepare for an 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Omaha</name>council, 
          <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>was sent to find the Indians. At 
          <name type="place" key="Omaha (Mahar) Creek">Omaha Creek</name>near present-day 
          <name type="place" key="Homer, Nebr.">Homer</name>, 
          <name type="place" key="Nebraska">Nebraska</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>and his squad walked into the empty
          village of 
          <name type="place" key="Tonwontonga village">Tonwantonga</name>. In the 1790s, during
          the years of 
          <name type="person" key="Blackbird">Blackbird's</name>leadership, the earth lodge
          village had held over one thousand 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Omahas</name>. But the smallpox epidemic
          of 1800–1801 had dramatically reduced those numbers. 
          <name type="place" key="Tonwontonga village">Tonwantonga</name>was vacant now as the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Omahas</name>were on the plains hunting
          buffalo. Although the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Omahas</name>were less powerful in the
          face of mounting 
          <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html" rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref>influence, their absence from home was a major disappointment. Any hope of
          negotiating an 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Oto Indians">Oto</name>-
          <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Omaha</name>peace and bringing the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Omahas</name>into the 
          <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>trade system now seemed
          remote. Equally worrisome was the continued absence of the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Oto Indians">Oto</name>and 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Missouri Indians">Missouri</name>chiefs and the
          expedition party sent to find them.
          <ref target="n0145" n="45"/>
               </p>
               <p>At least some of those problems were resolved on August 17. By this time the party
          had moved further up the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, edging toward modern-day 
          <name type="place" key="Sioux City, Iowa">Sioux City</name>, 
          <name type="place" key="Iowa">Iowa</name>. Toward evening 
          <name type="person" key="Labiche, François">François Labiche</name>came into camp; he
          had been with the group sent to find the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Oto Indians">Otos</name>and track down a deserter, 
          <name type="person" key="Reed, Moses B.">Moses Reed</name>. He reported that the rest of
          the party, including 
          <name type="person" key="Reed, Moses B.">Reed</name>and the chiefs 
          <name type="person" key="Little Thief">Little Thief</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Big Horse">Big Horse</name>, would arrive the next day. 
          <name type="person" key="Labiche, François">Labiche</name>further explained that the
          Indians were intent on making peace with the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Omahas</name>. "As the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Omahas</name>are not at home," sourly
          wrote 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark</name>, "this great Object cannot
          be accomplished at the time." The explorers could only hope that this would not deter
          the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Oto Indians">Otos</name>from accepting American
          proposals.
          <ref target="n0146" n="46"/>
               </p>
               <p>On the following afternoon both the deserter and the chiefs came to camp. Making some
          shade near the keelboat, the captains briefly entertained the Indians before moving on
          to more immediate business—the trial of 
          <name type="person" key="Reed, Moses B.">Moses Reed</name>. As 
          <name type="person" key="Little Thief">Little Thief</name>and the rest watched intently,
          
          <name type="person" key="Reed, Moses B.">Reed</name>was tried, found guilty, and
          sentenced to run the gauntlet four times. Shocked by this spectacle of public punishment
          and humiliation, the chiefs asked that 
          <name type="person" key="Reed, Moses B.">Reed</name>be pardoned. Had it not been for the
          need to establish firm discipline early in the voyage, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>might have sought to satisfy the
          visitors by granting their request. But it was not to be, and after they carefully
          explained the reasons for such punishment, the whole unhappy affair was done.</p>
               <p>Even if the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Omahas</name>could not be part of the
          coming council, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>were anxious to know the reasons
          for trouble between those Indians and the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Oto Indians">Otos</name>. 
          <name type="person" key="Little Thief">Little Thief</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Big Horse">Big Horse</name>found no reason to conceal causes
          for the tensions. The chiefs promptly gave a quick lecture on the river realities of
          raid and truce. If the Americans expected 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Oto Indians">Oto</name>-
          <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Omaha</name>conflict to turn on high
          policy disputes that could be settled by formal treaty, they were sorely mistaken. What
          unfolded was the tale of a horse-stealing raid by two 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Missouri Indians">Missouri</name>warriors against the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Omahas</name>. The adventure had gone
          awry and in the fighting that followed, both men had been killed. Their deaths demanded
          retaliation. The 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Oto Indians">Otos</name>and 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Missouri Indians">Missouris</name>also had stormy
          relations with the 
          <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Pawnee.html" rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Pawnee Indians">Pawnees</name>
                  </ref>. The chiefs admitted that theft of 
          <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Pawnee.html" rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Pawnee Indians">Pawnee</name>
                  </ref>corn while those people were off buffalo hunting was sufficient reason to fear
          revenge. What 
          <name type="person" key="Little Thief">Little Thief</name>recited were the common
          clashes that shaped prairie life. None of that denied the issues of trade and the
          struggles of the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Oto Indians">Otos</name>, 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Omahas</name>, and 
          <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html" rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref>to secure that trade. But the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Oto Indians">Oto</name>chief was offering a vision of
          the oridinary, the kind of affairs that 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>had neither the time nor the talent
          to understand and control. The explorers listened but did not seem to comprehend. They
          were already prisoners of grand but ill-conceived designs to reshape 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>Valley Indian politics and
          economics to the requirements of American policy and commerce. The realities of personal
          insult and family revenge must have seemed petty by comparison. Yet those were the human
          passions that outlived all official plans from any new father. Even so, that evening, as
          everyone enjoyed a dance and an extra gill of whiskey to celebrate 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>birthday, problems personal
          and national seemed far away.
          <ref target="n0147" n="47"/>
               </p>
               <p>How different the Indian and expedition agendas were became plain the next day.
          Assembled under a shade awning, chiefs and warriors listened as 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>again explained American plans
          for intertribal peace and trade from 
          <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>. Only bits and pieces of the
          replies from 
          <name type="person" key="Little Thief">Little Thief</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Big Horse">Big Horse</name>have survived, but what was recorded
          strongly suggests Indian expectations that did not match American designs. 
          <name type="person" key="Little Thief">Little Thief</name>agreed that peace would
          benefit all. He said that the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Oto Indians">Otos</name>had always been friendly with
          white traders, whether they were English or French. What counted, so argued the chief,
          was not nationality but the price and quality of trade goods. 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>could not have been pleased to
          learn that along the river the Stars and Stripes meant no more than the Union Jack or
          the Spanish ensign. Adding demand to insult, 
          <name type="person" key="Little Thief">Little Thief</name>wanted generous gifts from the
          hand of the new father. 
          <name type="person" key="Big Horse">Big Horse</name>added to the growing confusion by
          insisting that without "a spoonful of your milk"—a polite way to ask for alcohol—his
          younger warriors could not be restrained from attacking the 
          <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Pawnee.html" rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Pawnee Indians">Pawnees</name>
                  </ref>and 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Omahas</name>. Whiskey for peace was not
          the price the expedition was prepared to pay, nor was it diplomacy on the level of
          virtue expected by 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>. And hard on this demand
          came a call from 
          <name type="person" key="Little Thief">Little Thief</name>for a delegation led by the
          trader 
          <name type="person" key="Farfonge">Fairfong</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Labiche, François">François Labiche</name>to make peace with
          the 
          <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Pawnee.html" rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Pawnee Indians">Pawnees</name>
                  </ref>. When this request was flatly rejected, all talk ended in sullen silence.</p>
               <p>Uncertain of their next move and fearing that the whole conference might dissolve in
          confusion, the captains decided that gifts, medals, and certificates of good behavior
          might appease the Indians. Parcels of tobacco, beads, and face paint were quickly
          distributed. Medals and certificates went to warriors like 
          <name type="person" key="Big Ax (NeeSworunja)">Big Axe</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Black Cat (Necasawa)">Black Cat</name>. But those
          well-intentioned items sparked fresh misunderstanding. When the explorers had prepared
          bundles of trade goods and medals for chiefs who had not attended the August 3
          gathering, they had not realized the approximate equality of status between 
          <name type="person" key="Little Thief">Little Thief</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Big Horse">Big Horse</name>. The 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Missouri Indians">Missouri</name>chief had been sent a
          medal of lesser grade, and he now required one fitting his position. No sooner had that
          been accomplished than there was trouble in the ranks of the warriors. These men had
          expected substantial gifts and had received pieces of printed paper instead. No matter
          that the document proclaimed each Indian a "friend and ally" of the United States. One
          plainly disgusted warrior named 
          <name type="person" key="Big Blue Eyes (Stargrahunja)">Big Blue Eyes</name>made it clear
          what he wanted and abruptly handed back the certificate. Some moments later the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Oto Indians">Oto</name>had second thoughts and asked
          that it be returned. Angered at what seemed a lack of respect for official documents, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>refused and "rebuked them very
          roughly for having in object goods and not peace with their neighbors." Those pointed
          words may have been an accurate estimate of 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Oto Indians">Oto</name>and 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Missouri Indians">Missouri</name>priorities, but they
          were hardly salve for bruised feelings. 
          <name type="person" key="Little Thief">Little Thief</name>finally put the matter to rest
          and asked that 
          <name type="person" key="Big Blue Eyes (Stargrahunja)">Big Blue Eyes</name>be restored
          to the expedition's good graces. Not so quick to forgive, the explorers handed the paper
          to 
          <name type="person" key="Little Thief">Little Thief</name>, saying that he could present
          it to the offending warrior.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>had expected the Indians' quick
          acceptance of American policies. All the gifts and military show were aimed at producing
          that result. On the other hand, the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Oto Indians">Otos</name>and 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Missouri Indians">Missouris</name>imagined wonderful
          giveaways of valuable goods from what seemed an endless supply on the keelboat. 
          <name type="person" key="Little Thief">Little Thief</name>and the other chiefs knew that
          their influence was in decline as 
          <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html" rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref>and upriver villagers garnered a steadily larger share of the trade. Each
          expected too much from the other, and the day seemed to be ending in squabble and petty
          dispute. Trying to conclude the conference on a positive note, the explorers initiated a
          second round of gifts. Whiskey, keelboat curiosities like the ever impressive magnet and
          telescope, and an airgun show ended the council. Or at least 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>thought that the gathering was
          finished. Discontented with skimpy presents, many Indians remained in camp asking for
          whiskey and trade items. What had been planned as an impressive day of solemn talk and
          American power tailed off in misunderstanding and confusion. 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>were not about to alter either
          their goals or their tactics, but what happened in the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Oto Indians">Oto</name>-
          <name type="native_nation" key="Missouri Indians">Missouri</name>talks should have been
          a warning of difficulties ahead.
          <ref target="n0148" n="48"/>
               </p>
               <p>The meetings with the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Oto Indians">Oto</name>and 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Missouri Indians">Missouri</name>Indians were the first
          tests of the expedition's diplomatic skill. They were also a time to learn patience in
          the face of those who found the explorers' proposals either incomprehensible or
          confusing. Those August councils produced mixed results. 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>might announce American sovereignty
          and assert that trade contacts were established, that sites were marked for future
          posts, and that intertribal peace was being promoted. The Corps of Discovery might be
          learning to live with the Indians. But a closer look makes those assertions appear less
          substantial. The 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Oto Indians">Otos</name>and their neighbors wanted
          trade. With what nation and under whose flag mattered not at all. Promises of peace with
          nearby Indians, no matter how honestly made, bound no one. As the expedition made its
          way up the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>and into 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Yankton">Yankton</name>
                  <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html" rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref>territory, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>could realistically claim little
          success. They were now entering a plains world infinitely more complex than any they had
          encountered on the lower river.</p>
               <p>On August 27, as the expedition passed the mouth of the 
          <name type="place" key="James (Jacque) River (S. Dak.)">James River</name>, an Indian
          boy swam out to hail one of the pirogues. When the Americans pulled their boats on
          shore, two more Indian youths appeared. These Indians—two 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Yankton">Yanktons</name>and an 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Omaha</name>—told 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>that there was a large 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Yankton">Yankton</name>camp not far up
          the 
          <name type="place" key="James (Jacque) River (S. Dak.)">James</name>. Eager to talk with
          these Indians, the captains sent 
          <name type="person" key="Dorion, Pierre, Sr.">Pierre Dorion</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Sergeant Nathaniel Pryor</name>to the 
          <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html" rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref>village. Toward evening 
          <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Pryor</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Dorion, Pierre, Sr.">Dorion</name>reached the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Yankton">Yankton</name>camp and received
          an enthusiastic welcome. Following tradition, the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Yankton">Yanktons</name>wanted to carry 
          <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Pryor</name>into camp on a buffalo robe.
          It was to be more than a ride; it was a sign of honor and distinction. But the sergeant
          hastily declined, explaining that he was not the owner of the great boat now on the
          river. The 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Yankton">Yanktons</name>were not to be
          denied, however, and 
          <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Pryor</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Dorion, Pierre, Sr.">Dorion</name>were treated to a feast of
          fat dog, yet another sign of special attention.
          <ref target="n0149" n="49"/>
               </p>
               <p>The warm greeting extended to 
          <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Pryor</name>mirrored the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Yankton">Yankton's</name>eagerness to
          talk with 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>. All of this was genuine
          hospitality and something more. What lay behind the offered buffalo robe procession and
          dog dinner were 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Yankton">Yankton</name>concerns about
          their own role in a rapidly changing plains world. The 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Yankton">Yanktons</name>did trade to the
          east with North West Company posts and had occasional visits from 
          <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>merchants, but they needed a
          place in some dependable commercial system. They also needed protection from their more
          aggressive neighbors the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Tetons</name>. When 
          <name type="person" key="Dorion, Pierre, Sr.">Dorion</name>, now joined by his son 
          <name type="person" key="Dorion, Pierre, Jr.">Pierre</name>, and 
          <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Pryor</name>brought the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Yankton">Yankton</name>delegation to the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>shore opposite 
          <name type="place" key="Calumet Bluff (Nebr.)">Calumet Bluff</name>, both the Indians
          and the explorers anticipated a successful meeting.</p>
               <p>The morning of August 30 found the Corps of Discovery camped at 
          <name type="place" key="Calumet Bluff (Nebr.)">Calumet Bluff</name>on the west side of
          the river at the site of today's 
          <name type="place" key="Gavins Point Dam">Gavins Point Dam</name>. As the sun burned off
          an early fog, the explorers busied themselves with council preparations. What had been
          done for the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Oto Indians">Otos</name>and 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Missouri Indians">Missouris</name>was now readied for
          the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Yankton">Yanktons</name>. Even before
          breakfast, some inquisitive Yanktons swam the river to watch the mysterious doings of
          the bearded strangers. At 9:00 
          <hi rend="smallcaps">A.M.</hi>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>were ready to begin their first
          conference with the 
          <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html" rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref>. While the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Oto Indians">Oto</name>and 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Missouri Indians">Missouri</name>meetings were important
          as first forays in frontier diplomacy, the explorers knew that talks with any 
          <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html" rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref>group would be of lasting significance. If the American fur trade empire was to
          move from the realm of 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name>imagination to commercial
          reality, 
          <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html" rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref>cooperation and participation were essential. Knowing all that, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>dispatched a pirogue across the
          river to begin the proceedings.</p>
               <p>If the stakes were high for American diplomacy in the new West, they were equally
          high for the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Yankton">Yanktons</name>. Chiefs like 
          <name type="person" key="Weuche (and similar spellings) (La Librator)">Weuche</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="White Crane (Martoree, Mot, thouge)">White Crane</name>made
          that plain as they entered the precincts of 
          <name type="place" key="Calumet Bluff (Nebr.)">Calumet Bluff</name>in high ceremony. The
          whole 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Yankton">Yankton</name>delegation was
          preceded by four musicians, singing and playing as they paraded through the camp. That
          sense of drama was heightened when the captains ordered the bow swivel gun on the
          keelboat fired. Ritual payments of tobacco were made to the musicians; the conferees
          shook hands and then sat down to hear 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>present the American proposals.
          His speech, translated by 
          <name type="person" key="Dorion, Pierre, Sr.">Pierre Dorion, Sr.</name>, lasted until
          late in the afternoon. The expedition's records do not contain a full text of the
          speech, but some clues in 
          <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway's</name>journal suggest that it focused on
          peace with the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Oto Indians">Otos</name>and 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Missouri Indians">Missouris</name>and on arranging a
          major delegation of chiefs from several 
          <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html" rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref>bands. Probably, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>proclaimed American sovereignty
          and promised reliable trade from 
          <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>. When the speech ended, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>handed out medals to five of the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Yankton">Yankton</name>chiefs. 
          <name type="person" key="Weuche (and similar spellings) (La Librator)">Weuche</name>,
          sometimes known as 
          <name type="person" key="Weuche (and similar spellings) (La Librator)">La
          Liberator</name>or the 
          <name type="person" key="Weuche (and similar spellings) (La Librator)">Handshake</name>,
          was pronounced first chief and given a red-laced coat, military cocked hat, and American
          flag. The Indians retreated to the shade of some cottonwoods and divided the
          presents.</p>
               <p>The 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>expedition came to the northern
          plains as outsiders, but that night the explorers became part of a prairie community. In
          the late afternoon they provided beads as prizes when 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Yankton">Yankton</name>boys showed their
          skill with bow and arrow. At dark a crackling fire was built in the center of camp. Into
          the firelight came men in gaudy paint to dance and sing of their great feats in battle
          and the chase. Music came from a drum whose deerskin head was a gift from 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>. While drummers beat out a
          powerful rhythm, other Indians kept time with deer hoof rattles. Later, 
          <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>recalled the vivid sights and sounds
          of that 
          <name type="place" key="Calumet Bluff (Nebr.)">Calumet Bluff</name>spectacle. "It always
          began with a houp and hollow and ended with the same, and in the intervales one of the
          warriors at a time would rise with his weapon and speak of what he had done in his day
          and what warlike actions he had done. This they call merit. They would confess how many
          horses they had Stole." Perhaps instructed by 
          <name type="person" key="Dorion, Pierre, Sr.">Dorion</name>and his son, members of the
          expedition threw the dancers gifts of tobacco, knives, and hawks bells. For the Corps of
          Discovery, this would be a night to remember when times were harder and there was less
          to celebrate.
          <ref target="n0150" n="50"/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>were beginning to learn that the
          protocol of Indian diplomacy required time for chiefs and elders to hammer out replies
          to any proposal. But 
          <name type="person" key="Weuche (and similar spellings) (La Librator)">Weuche</name>and
          his fellow 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Yankton">Yanktons</name>had no desire to
          keep the Americans waiting. Very early on the morning of August 31, the Indian
          delegation returned with their answers. That there were several responses and not one
          common reply from the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Yankton">Yanktons</name>was another part
          of 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>education in native political
          realities. 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Weuche (and similar spellings) (La Librator)">
          Weuche</name>wasted no time revealing what was uppermost in his mind. Reliable trade
          connections were essential for the survival of the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Yankton">Yanktons</name>. The chief
          reported that he and his warriors lacked both firearms and ammunition. Their women and
          children were destitute. Weuche wanted immediate relief, a request he thought not
          unreasonable in view of the riches of the keelboat. As an alternative, the chief
          suggested that his warriors be permitted to stop the next trade boat from 
          <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>and help themselves to
          whatever was necessary.</p>
               <p>But economics was not the only item on 
          <name type="person" key="Weuche (and similar spellings) (La Librator)">
          Weuche's</name>agenda. As an astute plains politician, he quickly recognized that close
          ties to the new father would both protect and enhance the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Yankton">Yanktons'</name>influence. 
          <name type="person" key="Weuche (and similar spellings) (La Librator)">
          Weuche</name>cleverly offered his services to organize a large delegation from many
          bands the following spring. While not denying that men like 
          <name type="person" key="Dorion, Pierre, Sr.">Pierre Dorion</name>and his son would be
          useful in that effort, the chief made it clear that ultimate success hinged on his good
          offices. And as for intertribal peace, 
          <name type="person" key="Weuche (and similar spellings) (La Librator)">
          Weuche</name>again suggested that affairs be left in his hands. Explaining that other
          Indians "would hear him better," the chief assured 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>that he could be trusted as a
          faithful intermediary. Finally, 
          <name type="person" key="Weuche (and similar spellings) (La Librator)">
          Weuche</name>brought his comments full circle by returning to the trade issue. This time
          the chief took careful note of the international nature of the plains economy. 
          <name type="person" key="Weuche (and similar spellings) (La Librator)">
          Weuche</name>reported that he had already held English and Spanish medals. But, he
          pointedly complained, the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Yankton">Yanktons</name>needed more than
          bits of bronze and silver to fend off poverty. At this point, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>may well have become worried by
          constant references to trade goods. They had already chastised one 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Oto Indians">Oto</name>for paying undue attention to
          knives and beads. If the friendly 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Yankton">Yanktons</name>thought the
          expedition was really a trading venture, then less hospitable Indians farther upriver
          might stop and plunder the Americans. At the end of 
          <name type="person" key="Weuche (and similar spellings) (La Librator)">
          Weuche's</name>talk and before the other chiefs began to speak, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>again attempted to explain the
          nature of their mission. He insisted that the explorers were not traders but had come
          only to open the road for others. He assured the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Yankton">Yanktons</name>that honest
          traders with quality goods were not far behind. But the concept of exploration as a
          national undertaking had no precedent in tribal life. A keelboat filled with what seemed
          an endless store of goods only served to confuse the question.</p>
               <p>Although the nature and purpose of the expedition was no clearer in 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Yankton">Yankton</name>minds, other
          chiefs like 
          <name type="person" key="White Crane (Martoree, Mot, thouge)">White Crane</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="The Half Man">Half Man</name>needed to be heard. Their replies
          generally followed a common pattern. All agreed that trade and peace were worthy
          objectives. Of all the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Yankton">Yanktons</name>who spoke during
          the day, none offered more important advice than 
          <name type="person" key="The Half Man">Half Man</name>. The chief made the expected
          promises, declaring his interest in peace with the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Oto Indians">Otos</name>and a desire to see the great 
          <name type="place" key="Washington D.C.">Washington</name>chief. But at the end of his
          remarks, 
          <name type="person" key="The Half Man">Half Man</name>added a prophetic warning. "I
          fear," he said, "those nations above will not open their ears, and you cannot I fear
          open them."
          <ref target="n0151" n="51"/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="The Half Man">Half Man's</name>dark words were hard to take
          seriously in an atmosphere of friendship and productive negotiation. The day ended with
          yet another show of airgun firepower and keelboat curiosities. Gifts of corn and tobacco
          to the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Yankton">Yanktons</name>seemed to seal
          agreements while 
          <name type="person" key="Dorion, Pierre, Sr.">Dorion's</name>plans to remain with them
          augured well for the organization of delegations. On the surface, at least, the council
          was a grand success. Here were 
          <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html" rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref>headmen and warriors who welcomed the Americans and gladly joined the new trade
          system. The expedition's diplomacy appeared to have come of age. To that achievement was
          added the collection of important ethnographic information.
          <ref target="n0152" n="52"/>Just as significant, the expedition had enjoyed good
          relations with a powerful people. Worries about "the nations above" were easily
          discounted in the glow of proceedings at 
          <name type="place" key="Calumet Bluff (Nebr.)">Calumet Bluff</name>. 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>were so confident of continued
          success in dealing with the 
          <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html" rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref>that they did not think twice about leaving behind the only skilled interpreter.
          That the expedition's fortunes were about to slide into a morass of angry words and
          hostile gestures seemed remote. For now there were new plains sights to capture the
          explorers' attention. Again finding the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>channel, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>moved deeper into an Indian world
          that would both baffle and challenge the Corps of Discovery.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="section">
            <head rend="center">Abbreviations</head>
            <p>B A E       Bureau of American Ethnology</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">Field Notes.</hi>      Osgood, Ernest, S., ed. 
        <hi rend="italic">The Field Notes of 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain William Clark</name>, 1803–1805.</hi>New
        Haven: Yale University Press, 1964.</p>
            <p>Gass, 
        <hi rend="italic">Journal.</hi>      
        <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass, Patrick</name>. 
        <hi rend="italic">A Journal of the Voyages and Travels of a Corps of Discovery.</hi>Edited
        by David McKeehan. 1807. Reprint, with preface by Earle R. Forrest. Minneapolis: Ross and
        Haines, 1958.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, 
        <hi rend="italic">Journal.</hi>      Quaife, Milo M., ed. 
        <hi rend="italic">The Journals of 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Meriwether Lewis</name>and Sergeant 
        <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">John Ordway</name>.</hi>Madison: Historical Society
        of Wisconsin, 1916.</p>
            <p>Thw.       Thwaites, Reuben G., ed. 
        <hi rend="italic">The Original Journals of the 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>Expedition.</hi>8 vols. 
        <name type="place" key="New York">New York</name>: Dodd, Mead &amp; Co., 1904–1905.</p>
            <p>Whitehouse, 
        <hi rend="italic">Journal.</hi>      "The Journal of Private 
        <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Joseph Whitehouse</name>." In Thw.
        7:29–190.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="notes" type="notes">
            <head rend="center">Notes</head>
            <note xml:id="n0101" n="1">Donald Jackson, 
        <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Thomas Jefferson</name>and the Stony
        Mountains: Exploring the West from 
        <name type="place" key="Monticello (Va.)">Monticello</name>
               </hi>(Urbana: University of
        Illinois Press, 1981), pp. 25–26.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0102" n="2">
               <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>to 
        <name type="person" key="Barton, Benjamin Smith">Benjamin Smith Barton</name>, February
        27, 1803; 
        <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>to 
        <name type="person" key="Wistar, Caspar">Caspar Wistar</name>, February 28, 1803; 
        <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>to 
        <name type="person" key="Rush, Benjamin">Benjamin Rush</name>, February 28, 1803, Donald
        Jackson, ed., 
        <hi rend="italic">The Letters of the 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>Expedition with Related Documents,
        1783–1854,</hi>2d ed., 2 vols. (Urbana: University of Illinois Press, 1978),
        1:16–19.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0103" n="3">
               <name type="person" key="Gallatin, Albert">Albert Gallatin</name>to 
        <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, April 13, 1803, ibid.
        1:32–34. This judgment must be modified if it can be determined that 
        <name type="person" key="Gallatin, Albert">Gallatin</name>had a major role in formulating
        some of the Indian questions 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark</name>copied in a long list
        sometime early in 1804. See 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, "List of Questions," ibid.
        1:157–61.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0104" n="4">
               <name type="person" key="Lincoln, Levi">Levi Lincoln</name>to 
        <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, April 17, 1803, ibdi.
        1:35.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0105" n="5">
               <name type="person" key="Rush, Benjamin">Benjamin Rush</name>, 
        <hi rend="italic">Medical Inquiries and Observations</hi>(
        <name type="place" key="Philadelphia, Pa.">Philadelphia</name>: Thomas Dobson, 1794), pp.
        9–77. See also Stephen J. Kunitz, "
        <name type="person" key="Rush, Benjamin">Benjamin Rush</name>on Savagism and Progress," 
        <hi rend="italic">Ethnohistory</hi>17 (1970):31–42.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0106" n="6">
               <name type="person" key="Rush, Benjamin">Rush</name>, "Questions to 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Merryweather Lewis</name>before he went up the
        
        <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, May 17, 1803," Jackson, ed., 
        <hi rend="italic">Letters,</hi>1:50. This list was passed to 
        <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>in a letter from 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>dated May 29, 1803, ibid.
        1:52.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0107" n="7">
               <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, "Message to
        Congress—Confidential, January 18, 1803," ibid. 1:10–13; 
        <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>to 
        <name type="person" key="Michaux, André">André Michaeu</name>, [sic], April 30, 1793,
        ibid. 2:669–72, especially p. 670 where the language is clearly influential for the
        instructions to 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0108" n="8">
               <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, "Instructions to 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, June 20, 1803," ibid. 1:62–63. 
        <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name>particular concern for
        Indian languages added a document to the instructions. He had printed for the expedition's
        use blank vocabulary sheets listing common English words with spaces for Indian
        equivalents. See Thw. 7:408–9.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0109" n="9">
               <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, "Instructions to 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>," 1:62.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0110" n="10">
               <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>to 
        <name type="person" key="Adams, John">John Adams</name>, June 11, 1812, Lester J. Cappon,
        ed., 
        <hi rend="italic">The 
        <name type="person" key="Adams, John">Adams</name>-
        <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>Letters,</hi>2 vols. (Chapel
        Hill: University of North Carolina Press, 1959), 2:307.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0111" n="11">
               <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, "Instructions to 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>," 1:63.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0112" n="12">Ibid. 1:64. Jeffersonian Indian policy, as distinct from the
        theories used to rationalize that policy, is skillfully analyzed in Reginald Horsman, 
        <hi rend="italic">Expansion and American Indian Policy, 1783–1812</hi>(East Lansing:
        Michigan State University Press, 1967), chap. 7. 
        <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name>own concise statement of
        federal goals can be found in February 27, 1803, letter to 
        <name type="person" key="Harrison, William Henry">William Henry Harrison</name>, 
        <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>Papers, Library of
        Congress.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0113" n="13">
               <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>to 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, January 22, 1804, Jackson, ed., 
        <hi rend="italic">Letters,</hi>1:65–66.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0114" n="14">Charles Royster, 
        <hi rend="italic">A Revolutionary People at War</hi>(Chapel Hill: University of North
        Carolina Press, 1979), p. 93.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0115" n="15">
               <name type="person" key="Lincoln, Levi">Lincoln</name>to 
        <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, April 17, 1803, Jackson,
        ed., 
        <hi rend="italic">Letters,</hi>1:35.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0116" n="16">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, "Estimate of Expenses," ibid.
        1:9.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0117" n="17">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, "List of Requirements," ibid.
        1:72–75.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0118" n="18">
               <name type="person" key="Whelan, Israel">Israel Whelan</name>, "Recapitulation of
        Purchases by The Purveyor for 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name>," ibid. 1:94.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0119" n="19">
               <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>to 
        <name type="person" key="Croghan, George">George Croghan</name>, May 2, 1804, ibid.
        1:178.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0120" n="20">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>to 
        <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, December 28, 1803, ibid.
        1:161–62.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0121" n="21">
               <hi rend="italic">Field Notes,</hi>p. 16.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0122" n="22">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>to 
        <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, December 28, 1803, Jackson,
        ed., 
        <hi rend="italic">Letters,</hi>1:154.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0123" n="23">Ibid. 1:155.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0124" n="24">
               <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">James Mackay</name>, "Journal," in A. P. Nasatir,
        ed., 
        <hi rend="italic">Before 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>: Documents Illustrating the History
        of the 
        <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, 1785–1804,</hi>2 vols. (
        <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>: 
        <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>Historical Documents Foundation,
        1952), 2:493–94.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0125" n="25">
               <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">James Mackay</name>, "Notes on Indian Tribes,"
        Voorhis Collection, box 4, Missouri Historical Society, 
        <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0126" n="26">
               <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>to 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, November 16, 1803, Jackson, ed.,
        
        <hi rend="italic">Letters,</hi>1:138–39. 
        <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>did not send direct quotations
        from the journal but a summary of the major points in 
        <name type="person" key="Truteau, Jean Baptiste">Jean Baptiste
        Truteau's</name>"Description of the Upper 
        <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>" and his "State of the Indian
        Nations." See Nasatir, ed., 
        <hi rend="italic">Before 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>,</hi>2:376–85. In his January 22,
        1804, letter to 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, 
        <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>enclosed what he described as
        a full translation of the 
        <name type="person" key="Truteau, Jean Baptiste">Truteau</name>journal.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0127" n="27">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>to 
        <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, December 28, 1803, Jackson,
        ed., 
        <hi rend="italic">Letters,</hi>1:148. The English version of 
        <name type="person" key="Soulard, Antoine">Soulard's</name>map is in Gary E. Moulton, ed.,
        
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas of the 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>Expedition</hi>(Lincoln: University
        of Nebraska Press, 1983), plate 4. The French version is in Sara J. Tucker and Wayne C.
        Temple, comps., 
        <hi rend="italic">Atlas: Indian Villages of the 
        <name type="place" key="Illinois">Illinois</name>Country</hi>(Springfield: Illinois State
        Museum, 1942, 1975), plate 77. The Spanish rendering is in Carl I. Wheat, 
        <hi rend="italic">Mapping the Trans
        <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">mississippi</name>West,</hi>5 vols. (San
        Francisco: Institute of Historical Cartography, 1958–62), 1: plate 235a. Valuable notes on
        the 
        <name type="person" key="Soulard, Antoine">Soulard</name>map are in John L. Allen, 
        <hi rend="italic">Passage through the Garden: 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>and the Image of the American
        Northwest</hi>(Urbana: University of Illinois Press, 1975, pp. 148–49; Aubrey Diller, "A
        New Map of the 
        <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>drawn in 1795," 
        <hi rend="italic">Imago Mundi</hi>12 (1955):175–80; Wheat, 
        <hi rend="italic">Mapping the Trans
        <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">mississippi</name>West,</hi>1:157–60.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0128" n="28">Allen, 
        <hi rend="italic">Passage through the Garden,</hi>pp. 141–42 and fig. 23.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0129" n="29">W. Raymond Wood, "The 
        <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">John Evans</name>1796–97 Map of the 
        <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri River</name>," 
        <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="place" key="Great Plains">Great Plains</name>Quarterly</hi>1 (1981):39–53;
        quoted, 39.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0130" n="30">
               <hi rend="italic">Fields Notes,</hi>pp. 35–36; Thw. 6:270–77.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0131" n="31">Thw. 1:16.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0132" n="32">
               <hi rend="italic">Field Notes,</hi>p. 21.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0133" n="33">
               <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>to 
        <name type="person" key="Patterson, Robert">Robert Patterson</name>, March 2, 1803,
        Jackson, ed., 
        <hi rend="italic">Letters,</hi>1:21.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0134" n="34">Thw. 1:29.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0135" n="35">
               <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, 
        <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi>p. 85; Thw. 1:46–47.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0136" n="36">Thw. 1:86. Indian history and culture for this part of the
        river is ably treated in R. David Edmunds, 
        <hi rend="italic">The 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Oto Indians">Otoe</name>-
        <name type="native_nation" key="Missouri Indians">Missouria</name>People</hi>(Phoenix:
        Indian Tribal Series, 1976); G. Hubert Smith, "Notes on Omaha Ethnohistory, 1763–1820," 
        <hi rend="italic">Plains Anthropologist</hi>18 (1973):257–70; William Whitman, 
        <hi rend="italic">The Oto,</hi>Columbia University Contributions to Anthropology, 28 (New
        York, 1937):1–32.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0137" n="37">
               <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name>, 
        <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi>p. 26; Thw. 1:88–89.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0138" n="38">Roy E. Appleman, 
        <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>: Historic Places Associated with
        Their Transcontinental Exploration</hi>(Washington, D.C: National Park Service, 1975), pp.
        336–37; 
        <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, 
        <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi>p. 102; Thw. 1:92–94.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0139" n="39">
               <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, 
        <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi>p. 104; Thw. 1:96.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0140" n="40">Ibid. 1:97.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0141" n="41">"
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>to the 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Oto Indians">Oto Indians</name>," Jackson, ed., 
        <hi rend="italic">Letters,</hi>1:203–8.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0142" n="42">
               <hi rend="italic">Field Notes,</hi>p. 8.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0143" n="43">Thw. 1:36–37.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0144" n="44">
               <hi rend="italic">Field Notes,</hi>p. 95; 
        <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name>, 
        <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi>p. 30; 
        <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, 
        <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi>p. 104; Thw. 1:97–99; 
        <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse</name>, 
        <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi>p. 48.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0145" n="45">Smith, "Notes on 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Omaha</name>Ethnohistory," pp. 264–69; Thw.
        1:102, 106, 109–10.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0146" n="46">Ibid. 1:111.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0147" n="47">Ibid. 1:112; 
        <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse</name>, 
        <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi>p. 50.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0148" n="48">
               <hi rend="italic">Field Notes,</hi>pp. 109–10; Thw. 1:112–14.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0149" n="49">Ibid. 1:126, 128.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0150" n="50">
               <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name>, 
        <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi>p. 37; 
        <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, 
        <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi>pp. 119–20; Thw. 1:131.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0151" n="51">
               <hi rend="italic">Field Notes,</hi>pp. 125–26; 
        <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, 
        <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi>pp. 121–23; Thw. 1:131.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0152" n="52">Although the expedition's attention at 
        <name type="place" key="Calumet Bluff (Nebr.)">Calumet Bluff</name>was focused on
        questions of diplomacy and progress upriver, 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark</name>did record valuable data
        about 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Yankton">Yankton</name>life. 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>noted 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>dress, weapons, and musical
        instruments. He filled in a vocabulary form and wrote a long description of the important
        warrior societies that gave shape to the lives of 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>males. From 
        <name type="person" key="Dorion, Pierre, Sr.">Pierre Dorion</name>, 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>obtained a useful list of the 
        <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>bands. See Thw.
        1:129–33.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.ronda.01.00" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.ronda.01.00" type="contents"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.ronda.01.02" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>