<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.sup.lavender.01.10">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Way to the Western Sea</title>
            <title type="sub">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>across the Continent</title>
            <title type="sub" level="a">Chapter 10</title>
            <author>David Lavender</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2005</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic
        Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Way to the Western Sea</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">Chapter 10</title>
               <author>David Lavender</author>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>2001</date>
               <idno type="ISBN">0-8032-8003-3</idno>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Supplements</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Texts</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-11-09</date>
            <date>2005-04-20</date>
            <name>Becky Potter</name>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Split into chapters Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-04-12</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="ten" type="chapter">
            <head rend="center">TEN. Forty Below—and Far to Go</head>
            <div type="section">
               <p>On forty different sunrises during December, January, and February (plus two more in
          March), temperature readings at 
          <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name>sank below zero. The
          most frigid day, though not by much, was December 17: 45°F below at sunrise and 28°
          below at 4:00 P.M. All sunrise temperatures from January 5, 1805, through January 15
          were –10° or lower; –48°, – 38°, – 36°. The average for the three-month period was four
          degrees above zero. For comparison: during the thirty-year span from 1951 through 1980,
          the average temperature for the same months in the same general area was 12.3° above
          zero—roughly twenty degrees below freezing. Even granting the likelihood that the
          Corps's thermometers were less precise than modern ones, the winter at 
          <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name>was remarkably chilly.
          <ref target="n1001" n="1"/>
               </p>
               <p>Double suns shone in the southern sky. One night the moon wore halos and bars.
          Moisture in the air occasionally froze into a floating murk that resembled fog. When
          breezes were gentle—not often—frost collected in deep rinds on the barren limbs of the
          trees. Then a rising wind would shake the boughs and the frost crystals would fall like
          snow from a bright blue sky. Sometimes one of the cottonwoods 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>had described as full of water
          would explode with a boom like a cannon shot. Gales roared with discouraging frequency,
          sweeping the plains bare except for ridges of drifted snow that lay like welts across
          the earth.</p>
               <p>On December 7, 
          <name type="person" key="Big White (Sheheke)">Big White</name>galloped to the fort,
          shouting and pointing. Shaggy buffalo, seeking relief from the chill of a violent
          northwest wind, were streaming off the plains and down the slopes of the river trench
          into the timber-filled bottomlands. Village hunters were gathering for the kill, but
          would hold back until the whites joined them.</p>
               <p>During the next bitter week 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>took turns leading detachments of
          the Corps into the numbing cold to join the slaughter. Afoot, they watched enviously as
          mounted Indians armed with bows and arrows surrounded a number of buffalo and eased them
          out of the trees onto the terraces or into clearings where their excited horses could
          maneuver. Each rider chose a quarry, ran his horse up beside the ponderously galloping
          beast, and with his powerful bow drove an arrow all but out of sight into its flesh. The
          
          <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>killed about twenty that
          first day, twice as many as the whites, hunting among the trees, brought down with their
          rifles. Three that members of the Corps felled were shot within sight of the fort. One
          of the trio, a cow, leaped off the bank onto the ice, broke through, and died in the
          "vacancy" as 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>expressed it. Somehow the men got a
          rope braided out of elk hide around the animal, dragged her to the boat landing, and
          butchered her there. She was pregnant. Cutting the fetus free, the whites gave it to the
          wives of the interpreters who cooked and ate it with zest.
          <ref target="n1002" n="2"/>
               </p>
               <p>Of the ten buffalo the whites killed, they were able to butcher and lug back to the
          fort only five before darkness fell. Wolves and Indians claimed the other five. To
          increase the speed of retrieval—the buffalo were drifting farther away from the fort—the
          captains bought one packhorse and rented three from the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>. Even so, they did not
          recover nearly as many animals as the hunters killed. The below-zero cold made quick
          butchering impossible, and predators devoured whatever was left unattended for long. To
          protect some of the spoils 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name>and then 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark</name>, on separate occasions and
          accompanied by a few men, shivered out the darkness beside the inert mounds of
          flesh.</p>
               <p>Casualties among the enlisted men were high—frosted feet, hands, faces, and in 
          <name type="person" key="York">York's</name>case a nipped penis, presumably incurred
          while he was relieving himself. But there was no telling when buffalo would come as
          close again, and so the Corps stayed stubbornly with the hunt until December 12, when
          the sunrise temperature was – 38°F. The hunters still out were called back, and for the
          next few days the men ventured away from the fort only to gather firewood on their
          hand-drawn sleds. Their great dislike was sentry duty on the rooftop, even though turns
          were limited to half an hour each during the coldest weather.</p>
               <p>As temperatures rose, the buffalo drifted back to their grazing on the high plains.
          The men resumed cutting timber and building a wall of massive pickets across what had
          been the open end of the fort. Crowds of 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>came by to visit, often
          making nuisances of themselves by pilfering small articles and importuning the captains
          to exchange trade goods for corn. This presented 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>with a dilemma. The merchandise in
          the storerooms had to be used as good-will offerings for Indians as far away as the 
          <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>. Yet if the buffalo stayed away
          the Corps would need the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>' dried vegetables as a
          source of food. How could they get the provisions without jeopardizing their own
          future?</p>
               <p>An unnamed entrepreneur devised a solution. Why not let 
          <name type="person" key="Bratton, William E.">William Bratton</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Willard, Alexander">Alexander Willard</name>, who knew
          something of blacksmithing, and 
          <name type="person" key="Shields, John">John Shields</name>, who was both a blacksmith
          and an expert gunsmith, offer to repair and/or sharpen the relatively few metal objects
          the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>had collected from British
          traders over the years—hoes, skinning knives, kettles, and occasional fire-arms—in
          exchange for agreed-on measures of corn and dried vegetables? The idea took hold. 
          <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Sergeant Gass</name>supervised the building of a
          covered pit in which wood could be reduced to charcoal; on the day before Christmas the
          blacksmiths set up the forge and bellows, which until then had been seldom used.
          <ref target="n1003" n="3"/>The Indians thronged around open-mouthed. Magic!</p>
               <p>Work did not begin on Christmas, however. The 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>were asked to stay their
          distance, since that was a great "medicine day" for the whites, though if any religious
          activity did take place, that fact, too, goes unrecorded. (There is no indication that
          any group worship of any kind was ever held during the course of the expedition.)
          Shortly before sunrise, the enlisted men and the discharged French who were living in a
          nearby hut woke the captains with volleys of rifle shots. A flag was raised, the swivels
          boomed, and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>passed out rum that was gulped down
          before breakfast. There was a special feast—bread baked from a limited supply of flour,
          pies made of dried apples, pepper for spicing the steaks, and more rum. One of the rooms
          was cleared for dancing, 
          <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Cruzatte</name>tuned his fiddle, and the
          frolic began. Bored after a time, a few of the men went hunting. By nine in the evening
          everyone was ready for bed, as tired as if they had been working all day.
          <ref target="n1004" n="4"/>On New Year's Day, 1805, there was another celebration. At
          the request of the chiefs of 
          <name type="place" key="Mitutanka (Matootonha) village">Matootonha</name>and with the
          captains' permssion, 
          <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name>led sixteen men
          across the river ice to the Indian village. They took with them "a fiddle &amp; a
          Tambereen &amp; a Sounden Horn"—a bugle. They fired a rifle salute outside the village,
          were invited in, and fired another volley in the plaza. The townspeople were enthralled
          by their dancing, as were all Indians they met. One of the Frenchmen jigged while
          standing on his hands.</p>
               <p>Not wanting to put a damper on the fun, the captains stayed at the fort, but when
          word arrived of an altercation, 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>went up with 
          <name type="person" key="York">York</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Jusseaume, René">Jessaume</name>, and an unnamed soldier.
          Whatever the problem, it was over when he arrived, and the merriment was going strong. 
          <name type="person" key="York">York</name>added to it with a solo performance that drew
          resounding applause. At sunset the whites returned to the fort except six who asked for
          and were granted permission to stay the night. Those six learned, among other things,
          that during cold weather each 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>family stabled its best
          horses in its lodge, in stalls prepared to the left of the tunnellike entrance. For food
          the animals gnawed the bark off cottonwood limbs that were thrown to them.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Black Cat (Posecopsahe)">Black Cat</name>, who had spent the
          day with 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and the other half of the
          expedition at the fort, thought it would be fine if his people at 
          <name type="place" key="Ruptáre (Rooptahee) village">Rooptahee</name>could see the
          whites perform. 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>agreed, and the remainder of the
          enlisted men enjoyed their boisterous turn on January 2.
          <ref target="n1005" n="5"/>
               </p>
               <p>Shortly after New Year's, the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>of 
          <name type="place" key="Mitutanka (Matootonha) village">Matootonha</name>held a
          celebration of their own. The whites referred to it as the Buffalo Calling Dance. To the
          Indians it was the Red Stick Ceremony.
          <ref target="n1006" n="6"/>Like most Indian rituals, the Red Stick gathering was
          designed to fill a need, in this case the luring back of the buffalo that had wandered
          far away, leaving the Indians short of food.</p>
               <p>Basically the performance was a symbolic dramatization of a myth too involved to be
          summarized here. First, twelve old men esteemed for their wisdom carried twelve red
          boards, representing buffalo, into the lodge of a man who, prompted by dreams, had
          volunteered to hold the ritual and provide the necessary foods. The boards were arranged
          like pickets in a straight line from the central fireplace to the rear wall. Criers went
          through the village announcing that the four-day ritual was about to begin. Old men came
          to the lodge and seated themselves inside, at the left of the entrance. Several young
          men and their wives gathered to the right.</p>
               <p>The wives were clad only in buffalo robes draped loosely around their bodies. The
          idea was to lure the old men to have intercourse with them. 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, who obtained his information from
          Corps members who participated in the ceremony, felt the affair had been designed by the
          ancient ones for their own benefit. The Indians' intent was different. They believed
          wisdom and power could be transmitted from old men to young through the medium of
          women.</p>
               <p>After such preliminaries as feasting and smoking had been completed, one of the
          ancients simulated intercourse with a small doll dressed like a female. The act launched
          the ceremony. Each young husband said to his wife, "Help me become fortunate. Walk with
          my father," by which he meant an elder of a different clan from his. If the ancient one
          chosen by the youth was agreeable, the pair went outside, the woman clutching the
          elder's medicine bundle for strength. Apparently the coupling took place in the open
          air, in the dead of winter, with the woman's robe as a bed.</p>
               <p>If the elder turned out to be impotent, the young people felt disgraced. The
          embarrassment could be remedied, but only to an extent, by a simulation of the essential
          act—or by choosing a substitute. The Corps's enlisted men were eagerly sought, for all
          whites, at that time and place, were considered to possess great wisdom, for how else
          could they create such wonders as guns, magnifying glasses, cloth, and shimmering blue
          beads? "We sent a man to this Medisen dance last night," 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>wrote on January 5, "they gave him
          4 girls all this to cause the buffalow to Come near." His observation skipped a step,
          however. The buffalo came because the red-stick symbols, having certified the ceremony,
          transmitted the message to the herd: let them approach so one more necessary cycle of
          life could be completed, an honor to the sacrificial buffalo as well as to the people
          the animals saved by nourishing them.</p>
               <p>Four days after the conclusion of the ceremony, the buffalo did indeed return.
          Temperatures skidded fearfully. 
          <name type="person" key="Laroque, François-Antoine">Laroque</name>, writing letters in a
          lodge in one of the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name>villages, reported, "The
          ink freezes in my pen, though I sit so close to the fire as I can without burning my
          leg." The sunrise reading at 
          <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name>on January 10 was forty
          below.
          <ref target="n1007" n="7"/>Again a high wind roared out of the northwest, and again
          herds of gaunt buffalo, this time accompanied by many elk, streamed into the
          bottomlands.</p>
               <p>Whites and Indians poured out for the hunt. And again there were casualties. Shortly
          after sunrise on the day the thermometer dropped to forty below, a 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>boy aged about
          thirteen—actually he had been taken prisoner during a battle and then adopted by a 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>family—appeared at the
          fort's new gate. He had been out hunting with his adoptive father the day before. Seeing
          how the cold was getting to the lad, the older man told him to seek the shelter of the
          fort. Dark caught him trudging through the snow. Breaking off some branches and scraping
          together some dead leaves, he lay down on them, protected only by his small buffalo
          robe, light leggings of antelope skin, and moccasins.</p>
               <p>When he limped into the fort the next day, his feet were frozen. The captains thawed
          them in cold water, but soon it was obvious the toes could not be saved. First "they" (
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>probably, since he was generally
          regarded as the camp doctor) plucked off the dead tissue. When the infection spread,
          they "sawed" off the members, perhaps stanching the flow of blood with a hot iron. There
          was no anesthetic, of course, and inasmuch as the expedition's inventory mentions no
          surgical saw, one doesn't like to think what sort of instrument was used. "Our
          captains," 
          <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>reported, "took the greatest care of
          him possible." But recovery was slow and he had to stay at the fort until February 23,
          when his father arrived with a sleigh to take him home.
          <ref target="n1008" n="8"/>
               </p>
               <p>As a contrast: another Indian who spent the same forty-below night in the bottomlands
          without shelter reached the fort uninjured, prompting 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>to write, "Customs &amp; the habits
          of these people has anured [them] to bare more Cold than I thought it possible for man
          to endure." Equally impressive, he thought, was the solicitude of the entire village for
          the two temporarily lost people. The boy had not been born into the tribe and the man
          was a person of no distinction, yet all 
          <name type="place" key="Mitutanka (Matootonha) village">Matootonha</name>was anxious
          about their safety.
          <ref target="n1009" n="9"/>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>The poor meat picked up during the January hunts, most of it lean elk fortified by an
          occasional thin deer, did little to replenish the Corps's larder. Fortunately the
          Indians' desire for ironware remained insatiable. The blacksmiths cut into four-inch
          squares an old sheet-iron stove the expeditions' cooks had burned out during the trip
          upriver, and exchanged each piece for seven or eight gallons of corn; the buyer then
          fashioned his acquisition into iron arrow points or hide scrapers, infinitely better
          than similar implements made of stone. Another fast-selling item was iron war hatchets
          fashioned for the buyers out of iron obtained—the journals don't say where. In any
          event, the Corps stayed mostly on a vegetarian diet while entertaining the first 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name>chiefs to visit the fort.
          During the same period the captains refused 
          <name type="person" key="Laroque, François-Antoine">Laroque's</name>request to accompany
          the party to the 
          <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>—why should a U.S. expedition help
          a Canadian fur company scout out the resources of the land? And, most arduously, the
          crew tried to chop the three boats free from ice that had encased them to the gunwales
          and was threatening to crush them.
          <ref target="n1010" n="10"/>
               </p>
               <p>Vegetarianism did not suit for long men who were expending great amounts of energy in
          a bitter climate. Accordingly 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>set out on February 4 to find
          enough buffalo to quiet the grumblings of their stomachs. He took with him, according to
          
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, who was to attend to the
          journal during 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>absence, sixteen members of the
          Corps and two of the Frenchmen who were living in the hut near the fort. The group
          traveled down the valley with their equipment in two homemade sleighs, each pulled by a
          horse. Overflow was loaded on a third animal. One of the horses was a gray mare followed
          by a young colt; another had been borrowed from 
          <name type="person" key="Laroque, François-Antoine">Laroque's</name>clerk, 
          <name type="person" key="McKenzie, Charles">Charles McKenzie</name>.
          <ref target="n1011" n="11"/>
               </p>
               <p>Hard going. In places the river had, on occasion, thawed enough to send a sheet of
          water across the ice downstream. The surface had then frozen again, creating a trap of
          sorts. 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>broke through once, soaked his
          moccasins and leggings, and afterwards blistered his feet walking on ice that held him,
          just barely, but was rough and uneven, demanding great care to prevent slipping. During
          the first forty-four miles of travel the crew killed enough buffalo so that after the
          carcasses had been boned and the fat meat cut away from the lean, they were able to send
          the three horses laden with food to the fort and still keep enough to provision
          themselves.</p>
               <p>On they went, pulling the sleighs by hand. Having no way to transport the meat they
          obtained during the rest of the journey, they put it, after butchering, into log cribs
          tight enough to fend off wolves, ravens, and magpies. The last cache they built was
          hidden in the trees near the mouth of the 
          <name type="place" key="Heart (Ches-che-tar and similar spellings) River">Heart
          River</name>, where 
          <name type="place" key="Bismark, N. Dak.">Bismarck</name>, 
          <name type="place" key="North Dakota">North Dakota</name>, stands today. Wearily then
          they turned around, planning, once they reached their destination, to send a fresh party
          after the cached beef. On the last day, February 12, they walked thirty miles, sometimes
          on rippling ice and sometimes short-cutting across timbered points where the snow lay
          nearly knee-deep. They arrived, 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>said, "fatigued."</p>
               <p>On the 14th, 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name>, recently recovered from
          being bled and purged for pleurisy, headed downstream with the two sleighs, the three
          horses, and the frisky colt. Three men went with him, 
          <name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">Robert Frazer</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Goodrich, Silas">Silas Goodrich</name>, and the discharged 
          <name type="person" key="Newman, John">John Newman</name>, who was working hard to be
          reinstated as a member of the Corps of Discovery. Toward evening, after they had
          traveled some two dozen miles, a hundred and six 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>(literally) came yammering
          down on them. A few of the attackers cut the two horses out of the sleighs and dashed
          away with them. (
          <name type="person" key="McKenzie, Charles">McKenzie's</name>would have to be paid for,
          adding that mite to the total cost of the expedition.) The whites grimly held onto the
          frightened, plunging mare. The attackers also stripped the Americans of two knives and a
          tomahawk, but then, apparently fearing that the whites were about to shoot, returned the
          tomahawk.</p>
               <p>A strange standoff. The Americans wisely held their fire, perhaps at 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard's</name>barked advice, and it
          was not the Indians' way to risk lives unnecessarily no matter how the odds favored
          them. They'd added to their reputation by taking two horses from these whites who were
          continually bragging about their country's power; they could count that coup
          dramatically for years to come. Enough! Away they raced, whooping triumphantly.
          Unwilling to expose themselves in a forlorn camp, the whites, the mare, and the colt
          trudged back through the darkness to the fort, which they reached at two in the
          morning.</p>
               <p>Those damnable 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>! 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>sent messengers to 
          <name type="place" key="Mitutanka (Matootonha) village">Matootonha</name>: come help us
          pursue our mutual enemy. 
          <name type="person" key="Big White (Sheheke)">Big White</name>and a lesser chief
          responded immediately with a few men, "Some [armed] with Bows and arrows," 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>wrote, "Some with Spears &amp;
          Battle axes, 2 with fuzees"—outdated muskets; hunters were out on the plains with the
          good guns, 
          <name type="person" key="Big White (Sheheke)">Big White</name>explained. About twenty
          volunteers from the fort joined in. The rest stayed behind to keep an eye on the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Assiniboine Indians">Assiniboins</name>who were roving
          about the neighborhood, to gather firewood, and chip away at the icebound boats.</p>
               <p>The only trace of the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>the avengers found were some
          cast-off moccasins, horse tracks, and the galling remnants of one of 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>caches, which the brigands had
          rifled of meat and burned. But the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>had missed the lowest one,
          which 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>found intact. Realizing at last
          that there was no chance of overtaking the quarry, he cooled off and turned his party to
          hunting. After they had bagged thirty-six deer and fourteen elk they hitched the gray
          mare to a sleigh loaded with six hundred pounds of meat. They piled a ton more, poor
          quality, winter-lean stuff, on the other, and with sixteen men pulling on its ropes,
          returned to 
          <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name>. They arrived about
          dark on February 21.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>Ten days before that, the makings of one of the West's better-known legends received
          a major boost toward immortality, 
          <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau's</name>
                  <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">child-wife</name>, went into labor. The husband was
          off with the hunters, and 
          <name type="person" key="Jusseaume, René">René Jessaume's</name>spouse, aided
          conversationally by 
          <name type="person" key="Jusseaume, René">René</name>, was acting as midwife. As the
          pains grew more excruciating (Indian women don't always drop babies as easily as buffalo
          drop calves), either the midwife or 
          <name type="person" key="Jusseaume, René">Jessaume</name>offered the suggestion that
          powdered rattles from a rattlesnake, swallowed with water, would hurry things along.
          Indeed? And how did one obtain rattlesnake rattles in the dead of winter? 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Lewis</name>, perhaps: he was always
          collecting natural history specimens.</p>
               <p>Sure enough, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>did have snake rattles. He
          handed 
          <name type="person" key="Jusseaume, René">Jessaume</name>two "rings." Ten minutes after
          the dose was administered, the baby was born and given, on the father's return, perhaps
          the most common of French-Canadian Christian names, 
          <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Jean Baptiste">Jean Baptiste</name>.
          <ref target="n1012" n="12"/>(A supposition, offered without firm evidence: what if 
          <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name>, recalling the
          Catholic rituals of his boyhood, had asked 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>to be the infant's godfather? Would
          that help explain 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>warm regard for the family and
          his wish to raise 
          <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Jean Baptiste</name>"as my own child"? 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, by contrast, considered 
          <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name>of no worth except as
          an interpreter; 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>was also indifferent toward the
          child.)
          <ref target="n1013" n="13"/>
               </p>
               <p>The last days of February were marked by a run of fine weather: the sunrise
          temperature on the 22d was eight degrees above zero, and from then until well into
          March, afternoon readings were thirty-two degrees or higher. The men put their clothes
          and bedding out to air, and as the mercury rose, so did the pace of preparations for the
          coming summer.</p>
               <p>For more than a month the crew had been struggling intermittently and fruitlessly to
          free the two pirogues and the keelboat from the ice. Initially the captains had feared
          the accumulation would crush them. The ice was three feet thick, with lenses of water
          caught between the layers that frustrated both chopping and picking. Later, as warming
          days turned the surface of the ice soggy, apprehension shifted. When the spring breakup
          occurred, immense floes would sweep down the river, battering the boats to pieces on
          their way.</p>
               <p>Efforts redoubled, beginning February 22. Using iron-pointed levers and ropes of elk
          hide, the crew managed to crack both pirogues free. After smoothing out a road for log
          rollers, they hauled the pair ashore and up beside the pickets of the fort. The keelboat
          proved more stubborn. While Indians crowded about to watch, the straining workers broke
          the rope again and again, until at last they doubled the cord, dug in, and succeeded.
          <ref target="n1014" n="14"/>
               </p>
               <p>Even before the boats had been brought ashore, the captains had revised their
          transportation logistics. As a result of their experiences with the shoaling 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>the previous fall and of talks
          with the Indians, they decided the keelboat would be a handicap on the upper river.
          Consequently they determined to send it downstream. 
          <name type="person" key="Warfington, Richard">Corporal Richard
          Warfington's</name>soldiers, who had wrestled the white pirogue upstream, would act as
          crew and fight off the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>if that proved necessary.
          Those of the red pirogue's erstwhile French boatmen who remained in the vicinity would
          go along as passengers, as would the discharged and disgraced 
          <name type="person" key="Reed, Moses B.">Reed</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Newman, John">Newman</name>; though 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>recognized 
          <name type="person" key="Newman, John">Newman's</name>efforts at rehabilitation, he
          sternly refused to reinstate him. The returning craft would also carry two dozen crates
          of specimens and a bundle of reports for 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>.</p>
               <p>The two pirogues, both more maneuverable and of shallower draft than the keelboat,
          would be used for completing the ascent of the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>. They were not roomy enough,
          however, to hold the thirty-three persons and the one dog of what would become known as
          the permanent party, plus, of course, their baggage. At the end of the month,
          accordingly, part of the fort's garrison was sent upstream to find cottonwood trees big
          enough for making dugouts—six long, narrow affairs, unstable but capable of being sailed
          when the wind was right. The trees the scouts found were awkwardly located some six
          miles up the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>and another mile and a half from
          its banks.
          <ref target="n1015" n="15"/>Carrying the finished dugouts to the stream would be
          difficult, but no matter. Pushing to the 
          <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>was the consuming thought right
          then.</p>
               <p>Concurrently with the tree hunters' departure, 
          <name type="person" key="Gravelines, Joseph">Joseph Gravelines</name>, two Frenchmen,
          and two 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name>Indians arrived at the
          fort. From them 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>learned, with renewed anger, that
          the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>who had attacked 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name>and his meat gatherers two
          weeks earlier—one hundred and six of them by 
          <name type="person" key="Gravelines, Joseph">Gravelines's</name>count—had stopped at the
          
          <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name>towns on their way
          downstream and had boasted of their deeds. This annoyed the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Rees</name>, as the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name>were often called, who
          were out of sorts with the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>, anyway. For stories had
          reached the river Indians that 
          <name type="person" key="Cameron, Murdoch">Murdock Cameron</name>a British trader on the
          
          <name type="place" key="Minnesota River">St. Peter's</name>, was selling guns to the
          belligerent tribe. 
          <name type="person" key="Cameron, Murdoch">Cameron</name>had supposed the buyers would
          use the weapons against their old enemy, the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Chippewa Indians">Chippewa</name>, who had recently
          killed three of his men. But the feeling of power brought by the guns had led several
          bands of the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>to vow an attack on the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name>for entering into an
          alliance with the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>. During the battling the
          Corps of Discovery was to be annihilated for engineering the disruption. Only 
          <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo</name>, who
          had helped restrain the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">Bois Brulé</name>
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Tetons</name>during the September
          confrontation with the explorers, was refusing to join the projected assault.
          <ref target="n1016" n="16"/>
               </p>
               <p>This information was counterbalanced, in the captains' estimation, by a letter from 
          <name type="person" key="Tabeau, Pierre-Antoine">Antoine Tabeau</name>that 
          <name type="person" key="Gravelines, Joseph">Gravelines</name>delivered. Frightened by
          the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>threat, the trader wrote, the
          
          <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name>wanted to cement their
          tentative alliance with the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>and 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatasa Indians">Hidatsas</name>by moving north to live
          close to the upper river Indians. Would the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>and 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name>be agreeable?</p>
               <p>Delighted, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>conveyed the message to both
          tribes. With some reserve the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>and 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name>chiefs suggested that a
          proper 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name>delegation be sent up the
          
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>to talk things over. Still, it
          looked as though the Grand Plan for breaking the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux's</name>grip on the river was going
          to work. Using the Frenchmen who had arrived with 
          <name type="person" key="Gravelines, Joseph">Gravelines</name>as couriers, the captains
          sent a letter back to 
          <name type="person" key="Tabeau, Pierre-Antoine">Tabeau</name>, urging him to press for
          the conference. As for 
          <name type="person" key="Gravelines, Joseph">Gravelines</name>, he stayed at 
          <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name>. The captains, who
          considered the trader to be, in 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>words, "an honest discrete man
          and an excellent boat-man," had hired him to pilot the keelboat down the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, picking up as many 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name>chiefs along the way as
          would consent to come aboard. He would also collect whatever 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Yankton">Yankton Sioux</name>, 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Omahas</name>, 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Oto Indians">Otos</name>, and 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Missouri Indians">Missouri</name>
                  <name type="person" key="Dorion, Pierre, Sr.">Pierre Dorion</name>had managed to gather
          during the winter. (No 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>or 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name>would agree to join the
          excursion for fear of the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Tetons</name>.) After landing in 
          <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Gravelines, Joseph">Gravelines</name>would help escort the red
          dignitaries to 
          <name type="place" key="Washington D. C.">Washington</name>.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="place" key="Washington D. C.">Washington</name>! Although 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>thoughts kept veering toward the 
          <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>, they could not leave until they
          had finished putting into orderly shape for 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name>eyes the staggering number
          of specimens, maps, and detailed reports they had been working over since their
          departure from 
          <name type="place" key="Camp Dubois (Camp Wood, River Dubois) (Ill.)">Camp
          Wood</name>ten months before.</p>
               <p>They had collected enough objects to equip a small museum—sixty-seven specimens of
          soil, salts, and minerals; sixty examples of plants, including one supposed to be a
          sovereign remedy for the bites of rattlesnakes and rabid wolves; the hides of many
          animals, some stuffed and several unknown to Americans of the time; four live magpies, a
          live sharp-tailed grouse, and a live prairie dog, probably the one they had driven from
          its burrow farther downstream with kegs of water; a variety of embalmed insects; and
          many Indian curiosities. All this had to be annotated, packaged, and labeled.
          <ref target="n1017" n="17"/>
               </p>
               <p>The annotations were essentially rewritten field notes about materials collected
          under severe limitation. Neither man was a trained scientist. 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>crash courses prior to his
          departure from 
          <name type="place" key="Washington D. C.">Washington</name>had taught him how to focus
          his inquiries in different disciplines, but not much else. Both, however, were
          conscientious observers, each with a particular talent. 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>was more adept at eliciting
          information from Indians and at illustrating his written descriptions with rough-hewn
          but accurate drawings. 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>had an unusually sharp eye for
          the details of flora and fauna, and a trenchant pen for conveying the essence of his
          studies.</p>
               <p>To the physical objects they sent downstream on the keelboat they added voluminous
          reports on the climate, topography, river drainage systems, soil fertility, and Indian
          cultures of all Upper 
          <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name>Territory. Because they had been
          locked inside the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri River</name>trench, except for climbs
          to occasional viewpoints, they'd had to extend their observations by questioning Indians
          through interpreters and by interviewing such knowledgeable traders as 
          <name type="person" key="Tabeau, Pierre-Antoine">Antoine Tabeau</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Heney, Hugh">Hugh Heney</name>of the North West Company, the
          latter of whom had joined 
          <name type="person" key="Laroque, François-Antoine">Laroque</name>at the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name>villages in December.</p>
               <p>The geographic material they had collected they organized into two documents with
          similar titles. One, a discourse prepared by 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, described the streams that
          discharged into the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>—their length, navigability,
          sources, and the appearance of the lands through which they flowed. He called his
          compilation "A Summary View of Rivers and Creeks." 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>supplemented that essay with four
          arithmetic tables that gave the distances from one stream mouth to the next one
          upstream, an estimate of each tributary's length, and a record of latitudes taken here
          and there by the captains during the upriver journey. He called these tables "A Summary
          View of Rivers, Creeks, and Remarkable Places," the last term referring, in the main, to
          large islands and the site of both deserted and occupied Indian villages. Both summaries
          ended with guesswork, based on Indian information, about the country that lay west of
          the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>.
          <ref target="n1018" n="18"/>
               </p>
               <p>Their data on the territory's native inhabitants were contained in what 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>entitled "Estimate of Eastern
          Indians," eastern because it dealt with tribes living on the inland side of the 
          <name type="place" key="Continental Divide">Continental Divide</name>. When including
          the "Estimate" in a special message to Congress on February 19, 1806, 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>retitled it "A Statistical
          View of the Indian Nations Inhabiting the Territory of Louisiana and the Countries
          Adjacent to its Northern and Western Boundaries." The "Estimate," like the "Summaries,"
          was based largely on hearsay, as the captains frankly admitted. Even so, it contained
          more information about Upper Louisiana than anyone else in the United States could
          muster, and it would give would-be traders a basis for planning.</p>
               <p>The last point was important. Although 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>had told 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>to hunt out knowledge for its
          own sake, the president had not overlooked pragmatic goals. The dichotomy is clearly
          revealed in the captains' handling of Indian studies. Before leaving 
          <name type="place" key="Washingtonton D. C.">Washington</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>had been advised to collect
          information about such things as Indian pulse rates, menstrual cycles, funeral customs,
          medical practices, and religious observances. At the same time he was to record anything
          that might be helpful in establishing and maintaining commercial contacts. Quickly
          realizing the impossibility of ferreting out extensive anthropological detail during the
          limited time they could spend with most tribes, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>had concentrated their search on
          matters that would primarily interest traders—language, the home territories of the
          different tribes, the peoples with whom they were at peace or war, the potential value
          of their commerce, and, for the government, the possibility of relocating important
          tribes near federal trading posts in the event the Indian Bureau decided such
          interference with private enterprise was advisable.</p>
               <p>For example, consider the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name>, who were called 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Minitaris</name>in the "Estimate."
          According to 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, the tribe often left their domed
          houses to range along both banks of the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>up to and beyond the mouth of the
          
          <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone</name>. The area abounded in
          beaver. The 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name>did not hunt the
          valuable fur-bearing animals, however, because the chase was difficult and they could
          get the supplies they needed by bartering horses and vegetables with the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Assiniboine Indians">Assiniboins</name>, 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Crow Indians">Crows</name>, 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Cheyenne Indians">Cheyennes</name>—and from the
          Canadians. Private traders would like to know such things. And the government would like
          to know that the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name>probably could be
          prevailed on to relocate their villages near the mouth of the 
          <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone</name>if a federal trading post
          were established there. Such a move might be necessary, for 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>had heard, through 
          <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name>, rumors to the
          effect that the North West Company was planning to build a post at the mouth of the 
          <name type="place" key="Knife River">Knife</name>.</p>
               <p>And the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>. Their many bands, named and
          located in the "Estimate," roamed a huge area. Of these bands the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Tetons</name>were "the vilest
          miscreants of the savage race," a remark that overlooked 
          <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black
          Buffalo's</name>perhaps temporary coolness toward joining the projected war against the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>and the Americans. The 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Tetons'</name>trade, the captains
          said, might be of value if those Indians were reduced to order by armed intervention.
          And that, too, was something every trader in 
          <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>would read with interest. An
          inevitable question arises: How did 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>themselves evaluate this
          territorial acquisition about which they had written so much? In his journal 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>had noted such unfavorable factors
          as growing alkalinity in certain creeks and bordering ground. Both had read in the
          diaries of their predecessors' remarks about sterility and semiaridity. They had
          experienced the harsh, desiccating winds that blew almost constantly across the High
          Plains. They had endured the crushing cold of a plains winter. But were they pessimistic
          about the area's adaptability to white settlement? The answer has to be a firm
          negative.</p>
               <p>A recurrent phrase in 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>upriver journal is "butifull
          prospect," which is not a term he would have applied to views that struck him as
          unfavorable to human occupation. 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>is more specific. In a letter he
          wrote his mother just before leaving 
          <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name>, he grows almost
          ecstatic.
          <ref target="n1019" n="19"/>The 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, "so far as we have yet
          ascended, waters one of the fairest portions of the globe." He had heard the area was
          "barren, steril, and sandy." Not so. A fertile soil of loam sustained a luxuriant growth
          of grass on which game abounded. The only lack was timber, and that was not the result
          of adverse climate or inadequate soil, but of raging grass fires the Indians kindled
          either carelessly at their camps or set deliberately, partly for excitement and partly
          to control the movement of game. For that matter, the Corps had started some towering
          blazes, too, to attract the attention of tribes they wanted to contact, a matter the
          letter did not mention.</p>
               <p>(
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>challenging remark about the
          treeless nature of the plains, incidentally, has stout defenders. In spite of relatively
          light precipitation trees can be grown there, as many a farmer has discovered. The 
          <name type="place" key="Nebraska National Forest (Nebr.)">Nebraska National
          Forest</name>in the western sandhills of that state, which was planted as a calculated
          experiment flourished as soon as grass fires were controlled.
          <ref target="n1020" n="20"/>No major lumber company has sought to exploit the area,
          however.)</p>
               <p>At this late date it is hard to know to what extent 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>saw the plains through
          preconditioned eyes. The American West was supposed to be fertile. America's advancing
          frontier, and hence a great part of the young nation's strength, depended on that axiom.
          <ref target="n1021" n="21"/>
                  <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>knew of the treeless
          expanses in the continent's interior, but, less aware than 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>of fire's ravages, he suggested
          that the soil out there was not too poor, but 
          <hi rend="italic">too rich</hi>for trees, thus turning the average pioneer's
          conventional wisdom upside down. Both 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark</name>, children of
          agriculturists, had absorbed the faith of an expansive agrarian society without
          question. The multitudes of grass-eating animals the Corps subsisted on proved that
          nutritious growth existed, and the herds were said to become more numerous as one
          pressed on west from the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>-
          <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name>villages—settlements
          which were, after all, based on agriculture. Though the captains had not yet laid eyes
          on the valley of the 
          <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone River</name>, it, too, was
          reputed to be another terrestrial paradise. Why doubt? The best was yet to be.</p>
               <p>The key that locked these data together was a map of a highly conjectural West that 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>drew during the long nights at 
          <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name>. Its base was the 
          <name type="person" key="King, Nicholas">King</name>-
          <name type="person" key="Arrowsmith, Aaron">Arrowsmith</name>chart he had studied at 
          <name type="place" key="Camp Dubois (Camp Wood, River Dubois) (Ill.)">Camp
          Wood</name>when first estimating distances and potential routes to the 
          <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>. On that foundation he
          superimposed such new information and corrections as 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and he had gleaned from talks
          with Indians and with every trader they had met during their upstream journey.</p>
               <p>First, 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>filled in the largely blank areas
          between the upper 
          <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name>and the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, drawing his facts from 
          <name type="person" key="Heney, Hugh">Hugh Heney</name>, once a partner of 
          <name type="person" key="Loisel, Régis">Regis Loisel's</name>but more recently an
          employee of the North West Company of 
          <name type="place" key="Canada">Canada</name>. That done, 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>turned his attention to the lower
          and middle 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri's</name>major tributaries—the 
          <name type="place" key="Osage (Osage) River">Osage</name>, 
          <name type="place" key="Kansas (Decaugh, Kaw) River">Kansas</name>, 
          <name type="place" key="Platte River (Nebr.)">Platte</name>, 
          <name type="place" key="Niobrara (Quicurre, Rapid) River">Niobrara</name>, and 
          <name type="place" key="Cheyenne River">Cheyenne</name>rivers. In all cases he showed
          the streams heading too far west. Most were represented as rising in the 
          <name type="place" key="Black Hills">Black Hills</name>of present 
          <name type="place" key="South Dakota">South Dakota</name>, a range that 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>showed as extending much farther
          north and south than is the case. Contributing to his errors was 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>miscalculation of the
          longitude of the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>villages—99°24'45". The
          correct position is 101°27'. David 
          <name type="person" key="Thompson, John B.">Thompson</name>of the North West company had
          been roughly ninety miles closer to the truth half a dozen years earlier, although the
          captains, convinced of the superiority of their methods, boasted to 
          <name type="person" key="Laroque, François-Antoine">Laroque</name>that they had
          corrected his colleague's figures.
          <ref target="n1022" n="22"/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>primary challenge, of course, was
          learning as much as possible about the country they—and after them the pioneer merchants
          of the United States—would need to know in order to reach the Orient-facing harbors of
          the 
          <name type="place" key="Pacific Coast">Pacific Coast</name>. In this instance their
          informants were the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>and 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name>. Fortunately the early
          hostility of the latter tribe thawed; for the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name>, the captors of 
          <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name>, were accustomed to range as far
          west as the 
          <name type="place" key="Continental Divide">Continental Divide</name>during their
          horse-stealing raids against the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Snake</name>Indians. There is no
          evidence, incidentally, that the young 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Snake</name>woman, 
          <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name>, contributed in any way to the
          production of the map.</p>
               <p>The obstacles to accurate mapping were prodigious.
          <ref target="n1023" n="23"/>The Indians had no compasses. They indicated directions by
          pointing more or less along the lines followed by the sun at different seasons of the
          year. This resulted in a certain fuzziness for a geographer hoping to move from one
          distant point to another along a zigzagging course. The Indians, moreover, did not
          measure distances in miles, but in "sleeps" or "suns." The ground they covered during
          one "sun" depended on the pace of their horses. The Corps, however, hoped to journey as
          far as the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri's</name>headwaters by boat. Correlating
          the two standards was tentatively done, to say the least. In addition, the Indians had
          scant notions of navigability, so that their descriptions of streams as they appeared to
          a man on horseback were hardly definitive for boats. Plus this: on their war excursions
          against the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Snakes</name>, the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="HIdatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name>avoided the rough breaks
          south of the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>and struck directly across the
          plains. As a result they had not even seen the river for long distances. Finally, there
          were the usual frustrations of grasping information that passed through several mouths—a
          
          <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name>warrior to 
          <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name>to 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name>or 
          <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Cruzatte</name>, and thence to the
          interrogator.</p>
               <p>The Indians could draw rough maps, however, either on hide or on smoothed patches of
          earth, using an awl or a twig to scratch out river courses and adding little heaps of
          sand to indicate mountains. Directions as well as topography emerged with fair accuracy
          on such charts (if communication came through accurately), but distances remained
          elusive. Perhaps the best way to show the differences between what the captains
          anticipated and what they found will be to outline the expectations portrayed on the map
          and then let reality emerge in the narrative as it progresses.</p>
               <p>First, the 
          <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone River</name>
                  </hi>. 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>had picked up glimmerings of the
          stream from the journals and cartographic speculations of their predecessors, 
          <name type="person" key="Truteau, Jean Baptiste">Jean Baptiste Truteau</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">James Mackay</name>, and 
          <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">John Evans</name>. During their talks with
          the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>chief 
          <name type="person" key="Big White (Sheheke)">Big White</name>and with various 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name>, the 
          <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone</name>and its major tributaries,
          such as the 
          <name type="place" key="Bighorn (Ar-sar-ta) River">Bighorn</name>, emerged with fair
          correctness. But somehow they got the notion that the river rose in the 
          <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rockies</name>near the spot where "the
          Spaniards reside." Hardly, especially when one considers the nature of the lofty peaks
          that intervene between the 
          <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone's</name>farthest headwaters and
          those of the "Spanish" streams, presumably the 
          <name type="place" key="Platte River (Nebr.)">Platte</name>, 
          <name type="place" key="Rio Grande">Rio Grande</name>, and 
          <name type="place" key="Colorado River">Colorado</name>. However, awareness of the 
          <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone</name>did enable the captains to
          get rid of the 
          <name type="place" key="Little Missouri (E-mâh-tark',-Ah'-zhah) River">Lesser
          Missisourie</name>of the 
          <name type="person" key="King, Nicholas">King</name>-
          <name type="person" key="Arrowsmith, Aaron">Arrowsmith</name>chart (it became today's
          relatively insignificant 
          <name type="place" key="Little Missouri (E-mâh-tark',-Ah'-zhah) River">Little
          Missouri</name>), and with that out of the way they were able to accommodate a main 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>bending far to the south in
          western 
          <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>.</p>
               <p>They also visualized the 
          <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone</name>as boiling down out of
          rough, heavily timbered country into "one of the fairest portions of 
          <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name>, a country not yet hunted and
          abounding in animals of the fur kind." Now, that was information that would cause a stir
          in 
          <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>. (It also stirred young 
          <name type="person" key="Laroque, François-Antoine">François Laroque</name>, who, after
          being denied permission to accompany the Corps to the 
          <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>, set out with a party of 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Crow Indians">Crow Indians</name>to look over the 
          <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone</name>region for the North West
          Company. On the trip 
          <name type="person" key="Laroque, François-Antoine">Laroque</name>did hear of the Great
          Falls of the 
          <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone</name>, but he did not reach as
          high as today's 
          <name type="place" key="Yellowstone National Park">Yellowstone National Park</name>.)
          Inasmuch as 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>had advised 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>to keep an eye on the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>southern tributaries—he had been
          thinking of ways to reach Spanish 
          <name type="place" key="New Mexico">New Mexico</name>—
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>promised him, when writing in
          April 1806, that the Corps would explore the 
          <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone</name>on its return from the 
          <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>. This is significant, for it shows
          they had already learned that a short trip east from 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Three Forks of the">Three Forks</name>over what
          is now 
          <name type="place" key="Bozeman Pass">Bozeman Pass</name>would bring them into the
          lovely valleys of the upper 
          <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone</name>near today's 
          <name type="place" key="Livingston, Mont.">Livingston</name>. Fur traders would relish
          that knowledge, too.
          <ref target="n1024" n="24"/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">The 
          <name type="place" key="White Earth (Ok-hah-Âh-zhâh) River">White Earth
          River</name>
                  </hi>. The stream, its name a translation of the Indian 
          <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="place" key="White Earth (Ok-hah-Âh-zhâh) River">Ok-hah, Ah-zhah</name>
                  </hi>, was said to debouch into the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>from the north, three miles below
          and opposite to the mouth of the 
          <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone</name>. Supposedly the source of
          the 
          <name type="place" key="White Earth (Ok-hah-Âh-zhâh) River">White Earth</name>lay far to
          the north, near the south fork of the 
          <name type="place" key="Saskatchewan">Saskatchewan</name>. If so and if 
          <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name>Territory was held to embrace every
          tributary of the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, this would thrust a barrier
          across Canadian expansion to the west and, as 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>wrote triumphantly, would give
          American fur traders a good run at the fabled beaver regions of 
          <name type="place" key="Athabasca">Athabasca</name>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">The 
          <name type="place"
                           key="Milk (Ah-mâh-tâh, ru-shush-sher, River Which Scolds at All Others) River">Milk
          River</name>
                  </hi>. The Indians called it 
          <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="place"
                           key="Milk (Ah-mâh-tâh, ru-shush-sher, River Which Scolds at All Others) River">
            Ah-mah-tah, ru-shush-sher</name>
                  </hi>, or "
          <name type="place"
                        key="Milk (Ah-mâh-tâh, ru-shush-sher, River Which Scolds at All Others) River">The River
          that Scolds at All Others</name>." 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>believed that it, too, might give
          access to the 
          <name type="place" key="Saskatchewan">Saskatchewan</name>. According to their
          understanding of Indian information, it was the last major northern tributary of the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>. Encountering it would mean they
          were well on their way to the thunderous 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">Great Falls of the
          Missouri</name>, a natural phenomenon that both awed and fascinated their Indian
          informants.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">The 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">Great Falls</name>
                  </hi>. The
          roar of this "most tremendious cataract" reputedly could be heard for miles. The river
          rushed so fast, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>reported in his "Summary View of
          Rivers and Creeks," that on reaching the brink of the precipice it shot out so far that
          there was space, at the bottom, "for several persons to pass abrest underneath the
          torrent, from bank to bank, without wetting their feet." Passing around the cataract was
          no problem. A half-mile portage along the level plain on the north side of the river
          would bring the Corps to the spot where the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>"assumes it's usual appearance,
          being perfectle navigable."</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">The 
          <name type="place" key="Sun (Mah-pah-pah,-ah-zhah, Medicine) River">Sun
          River</name>
                  </hi>. The Indians called this stream the 
          <name type="place" key="Sun (Mah-pah-pah,-ah-zhah, Medicine) River">Medicine</name>. It
          enters the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>from the west, and according to
          the Indians (insofar as the captains understood them) it rose in the 
          <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky Mountains</name>opposite to a
          west-flowing stream that presumably was a tributary of the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>. But the 
          <name type="place" key="Sun (Mah-pah-pah,-ah-zhah, Medicine) River">Medicine</name>was
          reported to be too swift and shallow to be navigated. Besides, the captains had been
          ordered to explore the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>to its headwaters. Accordingly
          they spent little time trying to unravel the confusing details that clustered around the
          natives' descriptions of the small stream.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Three Forks of the">Three Forks</name>
                  </hi>. Before the captains reached the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">Great Falls</name>they would
          notice that the trough of the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>bent from its westward course to
          the southwest. It would maintain that direction through several parallel ridges. A
          little more than a hundred miles beyond the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">Great Falls</name>, as the
          explorers computed the distance, the stream would divide into three forks. The western
          one would lead to a fifteen-mile portage across the 
          <name type="place" key="Continental Divide">Continental Divide</name>.</p>
               <p>The 
          <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="place" key="Continental Divide">Continental Divide</name>
                  </hi>looked on 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>map much as it looked on the 
          <name type="person" key="King, Nicholas">King</name>-
          <name type="person" key="Arrowsmith, Aaron">Arrowsmith</name>—the westernmost of four
          north-south ridges that rose rather mildly out of gentle valleys or perhaps out of a
          slightly elevated plain. 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>even retained the mythological
          names of some of the divide's peaks—the King, the Heart, and so on. The western base of
          this easily crossed divide, the Indians asserted, was washed by a large river that ran
          from south to north. Farther than that the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name>had never been. The
          captains were confident, however, that this river was the hypothecated south fork of the
          
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>. After flowing through plains
          almost as level as those bordering most of the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, the fork would enter the main 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>. The journey from the divide to
          the 
          <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>should be little more than three
          hundred miles. With that notion firmly in mind, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>assured 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>that the Corps could easily
          reach the ocean and return to the headwaters of the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>or perhaps even to the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>towns before winter set in.
          <ref target="n1025" n="25"/>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>By March 20, 1805, the six pirogues designed to take the place of the keelboat had
          been completed. 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>took enough men upstream to lug the
          new craft a mile and a half to the river and then float them amid chunks of broken ice
          to the fort, where they were carefully caulked. During their labors the explorers were
          amazed by a kind of Indian hunting totally new to them. Buffalo trying to cross the
          stream at breakup time were often marooned on big cakes of floating ice. Seeing one
          approach, a hunter or two would take off to intercept it, jumping dexterously from floe
          to floe until they reached the cake the buffalo occupied. Rendered harmless by its
          insecure footing, the shaggy beast received its death wound almost without a struggle.
          The hunters then paddled the icy hearse ashore.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="McKenzie, Charles">Charles McKenzie's</name>journal supplies an
          additional item. During the winter many buffalo had died upstream. They, too, floated
          down, on the floes or among them. Young Indians skipped from cake to cake with ropes to
          haul the nauseating creatures ashore, for when "the flesh is a greenish hue ... and so
          ripe, so tender, that very little boiling is necessary—the stench is intolerable—yet the
          soup they make from it . . . is reckoned delicious."
          <ref target="n1026" n="26"/>
               </p>
               <p>By April 6 the river was clear of ice, and the boats were ready to start both
          upstream and down to their separate destinations. The men, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>wrote, were "in good health
          [except for the usual venereal complaints] and excellent sperits, zealously attached to
          the enterprise, and anxious to proceed."
          <ref target="n1027" n="27"/>But there was a last-minute delay. A messenger crossed the
          river, probably in an Indian bullboat, and reported that the entire 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name>nation, or so the
          captains understood, was coming north to build new towns nearby.</p>
               <p>Promptly 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>dispatched an interpreter over to
          meet the throng. It turned out there were ten 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name>, the delegation the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>and 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name>had requested to come
          upstream to smoke in amity while discussing the proposed relocation of the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name>towns. The interpreter
          also passed on a letter from 
          <name type="person" key="Tabeau, Pierre-Antoine">Tabeau</name>that stated that three 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>chiefs (probably not 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Tetons</name>) and some 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name>had listened to his
          blandishments and would board the keelboat when it passed the villages on its way to 
          <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>. 
          <name type="person" key="Tabeau, Pierre-Antoine">Tabeau</name>asked permission to join
          the party with four hands and three thousand pounds of fur.
          <ref target="n1028" n="28"/>
               </p>
               <p>Good omens. The captains' diplomacy was showing firm signs of moving ahead, and the
          keelboat would be well protected if any band of truculent 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>tried to interfere. In high
          spirits the little fleet of two pirogues and six small "canoes" pushed off at 4:00 p.m.
          on April 7. 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, who by then was definitely
          keeping a journal, eyed the procession proudly. "This little fleet altho' not quite so
          rispectable as those of Columbus or 
          <name type="place" key="Cook, James">Capt. Cook</name>, were still viewed by us with as
          much pleasure as those deservedly famous adventurers beheld their's." 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, less given to introspection, used
          his journal to call the roll of those aboard (not counting himself and 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>): Sergeants 
          <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Nathaniel Pryor</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">John Ordway</name>, and 
          <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Patrick Gass</name>. Privates 
          <name type="person" key="Bratton, William E.">William Bratton</name>. 
          <name type="person" key="Collins, John">John Collins</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Colter, John">John Colter</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Pierre Cruzatte</name>. 
          <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Joseph Field</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">Reuben Field</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">Robert Frazer</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Gibson, George">George Gibson</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Goodrich, Silas">Silas Goodrich</name>. 
          <name type="person" key="Hall, Hugh">Hugh Hall</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Howard, Thomas P.">Thomas Howard</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Labiche, François">François Labiche</name>, Baptiste 
          <name type="person" key="Lepage, Jean Baptiste">Lepage</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="McNeal, Hugh">Hugh McNeal</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Potts, John">John Potts</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">George Shannon</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Shields, John">John Shields</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Thompson, John B.">John Thompson</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Werner, William">William Werner</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Joseph Whitehouse</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Willard, Alexander">Alexander Willard</name>. 
          <name type="person" key="Windsor, Richard">Richard Windsor</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Weiser, Peter">Peter Wiser</name>. Interpreters 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">George Drouillard</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Toussaint Charbonneau</name>. 
          <name type="person" key="York">York</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name>, and her two-month-old infant, 
          <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Jean Baptiste">Baptiste</name>. And 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>should have added the dog 
          <name type="person" key="Seaman">Seaman</name>, who ate as much as any one of the
          men.</p>
               <p>A mixed bag and far to go. But by that time all who were capable of looking ahead had
          been thoroughly tested both individually and as a unit, except for 
          <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Lepage, Jean Baptiste">Lepage</name>, both added at 
          <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name>. Probably the others
          would have echoed 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>statement to 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, "With such men I have
          every thing to hope and but little to fear." Most of the crew (there's no telling about 
          <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name>) might even have agreed with 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>statement in his journal, "I
          could but esteem this moment of departure among the most happy of my life," though
          whether or not they would return "was for experiment yet to determine."
          <ref target="n1029" n="29"/>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="notes" type="notes">
            <head rend="center">Notes</head>
            <div type="section">
               <note xml:id="n1001" n="1">Temperature readings: 
          <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>, III, 852–55. 
          <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>prints a low of -45° for
          December 17, 1804; a photostatic copy of the actual tables (Large, 7) shows the low for
          the day to be -43°. Averages were calculated by Large, 6–10.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1002" n="2">
                  <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>in Quaife, 169. For the hunts:
          ibid., 169–71; 1, 235–37; Biddle, 122–24.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1003" n="3">
                  <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>in Quaife, 174. 
          <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>, 138: "The blacksmith has
          become one of our greatest resources for procuring grain."</note>
               <note xml:id="n1004" n="4">Moulton, 
          <hi rend="italic">Journals</hi>, III, 211. 
          <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse</name>(in Thwaites VII),
          72.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1005" n="5">The New Year celebrations: 1, 242–44; Moulton, 
          <hi rend="italic">Journals</hi>, III, 266–67; 
          <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>in Quaife, 174–75; 
          <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name>, 79–80.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1006" n="6">Bowers, 315–19. I, 245. Jackson, 
          <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, II, 538. 
          <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>, 131–32. 
          <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>put part of the description of
          the buffalo ceremony in Latin to avoid offending the sensibilities of his readers. A
          translation can be found in Marx, 21–22.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1007" n="7">Wood and Thiessen, 148.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1008" n="8">Chuinard, 267–69. Cutright, 
          <hi rend="italic">Pioneering Naturalists</hi>, 114. Moulton, 
          <hi rend="italic">Journals</hi>, III, 271–72. 
          <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>in Quaife, 176. 
          <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse</name>, VII, 74, says the boy
          was abandoned when he fell behind, and his father expected to find only a corpse on
          returning to seek his son. A few days later 
          <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse</name>froze his own feet when
          spending a night in the open.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1009" n="9">
                  <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>, 133.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1010" n="10">Tomahawks: Russell, 284–86. Boat problems: Moulton, 
          <hi rend="italic">Journals</hi>, III, 284–303, and for rejection of 
          <name type="person" key="Laroque, François-Antoine">Laroque</name>, entry for January
          31, 1805.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1011" n="11">The hunt can be followed in 
          <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>in Quaife, 179; Moulton, 
          <hi rend="italic">Journals</hi>, III, 285–300. The fact that 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>wrote his entries in the journal
          
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>had been keeping is a bit of
          evidence that although 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>had been writing up field notes,
          he had not maintained the diary 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>had requested. (Moulton, 
          <hi rend="italic">Journals</hi>, III, 285n.)</note>
               <note xml:id="n1012" n="12">I, 261. Moulton, 
          <hi rend="italic">Journals</hi>, III, 291.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1013" n="13">Jackson, 
          <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, 315–16, 369.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1014" n="14">Moulton, 
          <hi rend="italic">Journals</hi>, III, 301–4. 
          <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>in Quaife, 183–84.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1015" n="15">I, 275–76.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1016" n="16">Ibid., 285–86. 
          <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>in Quaife, 187–89.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1017" n="17">Jackson, 
          <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, 231–42.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1018" n="18">VI, 29–55. 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>tables are in ibid., 60ff., and
          have been reproduced in Allen, 228–31.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1019" n="19">Jackson, 
          <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, 222–25.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1020" n="20">Stewart, 127–33.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1021" n="21">Smith, chapter 11.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1022" n="22">
                  <name type="person" key="Laroque, François-Antoine">Laroque</name>in Wood and Thiessen,
          151.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1023" n="23">The procedures employed in producing the 1805 map are
          summarized in Allen, 226–51; DeVoto, 
          <hi rend="italic">Course</hi>, 464–69; Wheat, II, 32–39. The map itself is reproduced
          (use your magnifying glass!) in both Wheat and in Allen, 231–39.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1024" n="24">Ibid., 234. Data concerning 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>notions of rivers they would meet
          on the way West comes principally from 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>"Summary View of Rivers and
          Creeks" in VI, 29–55.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1025" n="25">Jackson, 
          <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, 234.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1026" n="26">I, 278–79. 
          <name type="person" key="McKenzie, Charles">McKenzie</name>in Wood and Thiessen,
          239.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1027" n="27">I, 281.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1028" n="28">
                  <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>in Quaife, 189–90. I, 285–86.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1029" n="29">I, 285.</note>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.lavender.01.09" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.lavender.01.00" type="contents"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.lavender.01.11" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
