<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.lc.lavender.01.app1">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Way to the Western Sea</title>
            <title type="sub">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>across the Continent</title>
            <title type="sub" level="a">Appendix 1</title>
            <author>David Lavender</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2005</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic
        Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Way to the Western Sea</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">Appendix I</title>
               <author>David Lavender</author>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>2001</date>
               <idno type="ISBN">0-8032-8003-3</idno>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-11-09</date>
            <date>2005-04-20</date>
            <name>Becky Potter</name>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Split into chapters Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-04-12</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="appendix.1" type="chapter">
            <head rend="center">APPENDIX I. 
        <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name>Instructions to 
        <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>
            </head>
            <div type="section">
               <p>T
          <hi rend="italic">o 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name>, esquire, Captain of
          the 1st regiment of infantry of the United States of America</hi>: Your situation as
          Secretary of the President of the United States has made you acquainted with the objects
          of my confidential message of Jan. 18, 1803, to the legislature. you have seen the act
          they passed, which, tho' expressed in general terms, was meant to sanction those
          objects, and you are appointed to carry them into execution.</p>
               <p>Instruments for ascertaining by celestial observations the geography of the country
          thro' which you will pass, have already been provided. light articles for barter, &amp;
          presents among the Indians, arms for your attendants, say for from 10 to 12 men, boats,
          tents, &amp; other travelling apparatus, with ammunition, medicine, surgical instruments
          &amp; provisions you will have prepared with such aids as the Secretary at War can yield
          in his department; &amp; from him also you will recieve authority to engage among our
          troops, by voluntary agreement, the number of attendants above mentioned, over whom you,
          as their commanding officer are invested with all the powers the laws give in such a
          case.</p>
               <p>As your movements while within the limits of the U. S. will be better directed by
          occasional communications, adapted to circumstances as they arise, they will not be
          noticed here. what follows will respect your proceedings after your departure from the
          U. S.</p>
               <p>Your mission has been communicated to the Ministers here from 
          <name type="place" key="France">France</name>, 
          <name type="place" key="Spain">Spain</name>&amp; 
          <name type="place" key="England">Great Britain</name>, and through them to their
          governments: and such assurances given them as to it's objects as we trust will satisfy
          them. the country of 
          <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name>having been ceded by 
          <name type="place" key="Spain">Spain</name>to 
          <name type="place" key="France">France</name>, the passport you have from the Minister
          of 
          <name type="place" key="France">France</name>, the representative of the present
          sovereign of the country, will be a protection with all it's subjects: And that from the
          Minister of 
          <name type="place" key="England">England</name>will entitle you to the friendly aid of
          any traders of that allegiance with whom you may happen to meet.</p>
               <p>The object of your mission is to explore the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri RIver">Missouri river</name>, &amp; such principal
          stream of it, as, by it's course &amp; communication with the waters of the 
          <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific Ocean</name>, may offer the most direct
          &amp; practicable water communication across this continent, for the purposes of
          commerce.</p>
               <p>Beginning at the mouth of the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, you will take observations of
          latitude &amp; longitude, at all remarkable points on the river, &amp; especially at the
          mouths of rivers, at rapids, at islands &amp; other places &amp; objects distinguished
          by such natural marks &amp; characters of a durable kind, as that they may with
          certainty be recognized hereafter. the courses of the river between these points of
          observation may be supplied by the compass, the log-line &amp; by time, corrected by the
          observations themselves. the variations of the compass too, in different places, should
          be noticed.</p>
               <p>The interesting points of portage between the heads of the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>&amp; the water offering the best
          communication with the 
          <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific Ocean</name>should also be fixed by
          observation, &amp; the course of that water to the ocean, in the same manner as that of
          the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>.</p>
               <p>Your observations are to be taken with great pains &amp; accuracy, to be entered
          distinctly, &amp; intelligibly for others as well as yourself, to comprehend all the
          elements necessary, with the aid of the usual tables, to fix the latitude and longitude
          of the places at which they were taken, &amp; are to be rendered to the war office, for
          the purpose of having the calculations made concurrently by proper persons within the U.
          S. several copies of these, as well as your other notes, should be made at leisure times
          &amp; put into the care of the most trustworthy of your attendants, to guard by
          multiplying them, against the accidental losses to which they will be exposed. a further
          guard would be that one of these copies be written on the paper of the birch, as less
          liable to injury from damp than common paper.</p>
               <p>The commerce which may be carried on with the people inhabiting the line you will
          pursue, renders a knolege of these people important. you will therefore endeavor to make
          yourself acquainted, as far as a diligent pursuit of your journey shall admit, 
          <list type="simple">
                     <item>with the names of the nations &amp; their numbers;</item>
                     <item>     the extent &amp; limits of their possessions;</item>
                     <item>     their relations with other tribes or nations;</item>
                     <item>     their language, traditions, monuments;</item>
                     <item>     their ordinary occupations in agriculture, fishing,
            hunting, war, arts, &amp; the implements for these;</item>
                     <item>     their food, clothing, &amp; domestic
            accomodations;</item>
                     <item>     the diseases prevalent among them, &amp; the remedies
            they use;</item>
                     <item>     moral &amp; physical circumstances which distinguish
            them from the tribes we know;</item>
                     <item>     peculiarities in their laws, customs &amp;
            dispositions;</item>
                     <item>     and articles of commerce they may need or furnish,
            &amp; to what extent.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>And considering the interest which every nation has in extending &amp; strengthening
          the authority of reason &amp; justice among the people around them, it will be useful to
          acquire what knolege you can of the state of morality, religion &amp; information among
          them, as it may better enable those who endeavor to civilize &amp; instruct them, to
          adapt their measures to the existing notions &amp; practises of those on whom they are
          to operate.</p>
               <p>Other object worthy of notice will be 
          <list type="simple">
                     <item>the soil &amp; face of the country, it's growth &amp; vegetable productions;
            especially those not of the U. S.</item>
                     <item>the animals of the country generally, &amp; especially those not known in the U.
            S.</item>
                     <item>the remains and accounts of any which may deemed rare or extinct;</item>
                     <item>the mineral productions of every kind; but more particularly metals, limestone,
            pit coal &amp; salpetre; salines &amp; mineral waters, noting the temperature of the
            last, &amp; such circumstances as may indicate their character.</item>
                     <item>Volcanic appearances.</item>
                     <item>climate as characterized by the thermometer, by the proportion of rainy, cloudy
            &amp; clear days, by lightening, hail, snow, ice, by the access &amp; recess of frost,
            by the winds prevailing at different seasons, the dates at which particular plants put
            forth or lose their flowers, or leaf, times of appearance of particular birds,
            reptiles or insects.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Altho' your route will be along the channel of the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, yet you will endeavor to inform
          yourself, by inquiry, of the character &amp; extent of the country watered by it's
          branches, &amp; especially on it's southern side. the North river or Rio Bravo which
          runs into the 
          <name type="place" key="Gulf of Mexico">gulph of Mexico</name>, and the North river, or 
          <name type="place" key="Colorado River">Rio colorado</name>, which runs into the 
          <name type="place" key="Gulf of California">gulph of California</name>, are understood
          to be the principal streams heading opposite to the waters of the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, and running Southwardly.
          whether the dividing grounds between the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>&amp; them are mountains or
          flatlands, what are their distance from the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, the character of the
          intermediate country, &amp; the people inhabiting it, are worthy of particular enquiry.
          The Northern waters of the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>are less to be enquired after,
          because they have been ascertained to a considerable degree, and are still in a course
          of ascertainment by English traders &amp; travellers. but if you can learn anything
          certain of the most Northern source of the 
          <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Missisipi</name>, &amp; of it's position
          relative to the lake of the woods, it will be interesting to us. some account too of the
          path of the Canadian traders from the 
          <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Missisipi</name>, at the mouth of the
          Ouisconsin river, to where it strikes the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>and of the soil &amp; rivers in
          it's course, is desireable.</p>
               <p>In all your intercourse with the natives treat them in the most friendly &amp;
          conciliatory manner which their own conduct will admit; allay all jealousies as to the
          object of your journey, satisfy them of it's innocence, make them acquainted with the
          position, extent, character, peaceable &amp; commercial dispositions of the U. S. of our
          wish to be neighborly, friendly &amp; useful to them, &amp; of our dispositions to a
          commercial intercourse with them; confer with them on the points most convenient as
          mutual emporiums, &amp; the articles of most desireable interchange for them &amp; us.
          if a few of their influential chiefs, within practicable distance, wish to visit us,
          arrange such a visit with them, and furnish them with authority to call on our officers,
          on their entering the U. S. to have them conveyed to this place at public expence. if
          any of them should wish to have some of their young people brought up with us, &amp;
          taught such arts as may be useful to them, we will receive, instruct &amp; take care of
          them. such a mission, whether of influential chiefs, or of young people, would give some
          security to your own party. carry with you some matter of the kinepox, inform those of
          them with whom you may be of it' efficacy as a preservative from the small-pox; and
          instruct &amp; incourage them in the use of it. this may be especially done wherever you
          winter.</p>
               <p>As it is impossible for us to foresee in what manner you will be recieved by those
          people, whether with hospitality or hostility, so is it impossible to prescribe the
          exact degree of perseverance with which you are to pursue your journey. we value too
          much the lives of citizens to offer them to probably destruction. your numbers will be
          sufficient to secure you against the unauthorised opposition of individuals, or of small
          parties: but if a superior force, authorised or not authorised, by a nation, should be
          arrayed against your further passage, &amp; inflexibly determined to arrest it, you must
          decline it's further pursuit, and return. in the loss of yourselves, we should lose also
          the information you will have acquired. by returning safely with that, you may enable us
          to renew the essay with better calculated means. to your own discretion therefore must
          be left the degree of danger you may risk, &amp; the point at which you should decline,
          only saying we wish you to err on the side of your safety, &amp; bring back your party
          safe, even if it be with less information.</p>
               <p>As far up the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>as the white settlements extend,
          an intercourse will probably be found to exist between them and the Spanish posts at 
          <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>, opposite 
          <name type="place" key="Cahokia, Ill.">Cahokia</name>, or 
          <name type="place" key="Saint Genevieve, Mo.">Ste. Genevieve</name>opposite 
          <name type="place" key="Kaskaskia, Ill.">Kaskaskia</name>. from still farther up the
          river, the traders may furnish a conveyance for letters. beyond that you may perhaps be
          able to engage Indians to bring letters for the government to 
          <name type="place" key="Cahokia, Ill.">Cahokia</name>or 
          <name type="place" key="Kaskaskia, Ill.">Kaskaskia</name>, on promising that they shall
          there receive such special compensation as you shall have stipulated with them. avail
          yourself of these means to communicate to us, at seasonable intervals, a copy of your
          journal, notes &amp; observations of every kind, putting into cypher whatever might do
          injury if betrayed.</p>
               <p>Should you reach the 
          <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific ocean</name>[One full line scratched out,
          indecipherable.—Thwaites.] inform yourself of the circumstances which may decide whether
          the furs of those parts may not be collected as advantageously at the head of the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>(convenient as is supposed to the
          waters of the 
          <name type="place" key="Colorado River">Colorado</name>&amp; 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Oregon or Columbia</name>) as at 
          <name type="place" key="Nootka Sound">Nootka sound</name>or any other point of that
          coast; &amp; that trade be consequently conducted through the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>&amp; U. S. more beneficially
          than by the circumnavigation now practised.</p>
               <p>On your arrival on that coast endeavor to learn if there be any port within your
          reach frequented by the sea-vessels of any nation, and to send two of your trusty people
          back by sea, in such way as shall appear practicable, with a copy of your notes. and
          should you be of opinion that the return of your party by the way they went will be
          eminently dangerous, then ship the whole, &amp; return by sea by way of 
          <name type="place" key="Cape Horn">Cape Horn</name>or the 
          <name type="place" key="Cape of Good Hope">Cape of good Hope</name>, as you shall be
          able. as you will be without money, clothes or provisions, you must endeavor to use the
          credit of the U. S. to obtain them; for which purpose open letters of credit shall be
          furnished you authorising you to draw on the Executive of the U. S. or any of its
          officers in any part of the world, on which drafts can be disposed of, and to apply with
          our recommendations to the Consuls, agents, merchants, or citizens of any nation with
          which we have intercourse, assuring them in our name that any aids they may furnish you,
          shall honorably repaid, and on demand. Our consuls Thomas Howes at Batavia in Java,
          William Buchanan on the isles of 
          <name type="place" key="France">France</name>and Bourbon, &amp; John Elmslie at the Cape
          of good hope will be able to supply your necessities by draughts on us.</p>
               <p>Should you find it safe to return by the way you go, after sending two of your party
          round by sea, or with your whole party, if no conveyance by sea can be found, do so;
          making such observations on your return as may serve to supply, correct or confirm those
          made on your outward journey.</p>
               <p>In re-entering the U. S. and reaching a place of safety, discharge any of your
          attendants who may desire &amp; deserve it, procuring for them immediate paiment of all
          arrears of pay &amp; cloathing which may have incurred since their departure; &amp;
          assure them that they shall be recommended to the liberality of the legislature for the
          grant of a soldier's portion of land each, as proposed in my message to Congress &amp;
          repair yourself with your papers to the seat of government.</p>
               <p>To provide, on the accident of your death, against anarchy, dispersion &amp; the
          consequent danger to your party, and total failure of the enterprise, you are hereby
          authorised, by any instrument signed &amp; written in your hand, to name the person
          among them who shall succeed to the command on your decease, &amp; by like instruments
          to change the nomination from time to time, as further experience of the characters
          accompanying you shall point out superior fitness; and all the powers &amp; authorities
          given to yourself are, in the event of your death, transferred to &amp; vested in the
          successor so named, with further power to him, &amp; his successors in like manner to
          name each his successor, who, on the death of his predecessor, shall be invested with
          all the powers &amp; authorities given to yourself.</p>
               <p>Given under my hand at the city of 
          <name type="place" key="Washington D. C.">Washington</name>, this 20th day of June
          1803</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="right">
                     <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Th. Jefferson</name>
                     <lb/>Pr. U S. of America</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.lavender.01.20" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.lavender.01.00" type="contents"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.lavender.01.app2" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>