<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.sup.lavender.01.11">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Way to the Western Sea</title>
            <title type="sub">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>across the Continent</title>
            <title type="sub" level="a">Chapter 11</title>
            <author>David Lavender</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2005</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic
        Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Way to the Western Sea</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">Chapter 11</title>
               <author>David Lavender</author>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>2001</date>
               <idno type="ISBN">0-8032-8003-3</idno>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Supplements</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Texts</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-11-09</date>
            <date>2005-04-20</date>
            <name>Becky Potter</name>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Split into chapters Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-04-12</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="eleven" type="chapter">
            <head rend="center">ELEVEN. Hazards by Water</head>
            <div type="section">
               <p>The white pirogue, smaller but more stable than the red, was the queen of the little
          fleet. In her lockers the captains stored their astronomical instruments, several casks
          of gunpowder, medicines, their best trade goods, their journals, and other valuable
          papers. For safety's sake, the three privates of the expedition who could not swim were
          assigned as oarsmen to this "flagship." (The boat's full complement of rowers was six.)
          Also riding in the white pirogue were 
          <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name>and her 
          <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Jean Baptiste">two-month-old baby</name>, her
          husband, 
          <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Toussaint Charbonneau</name>, the
          hunter-interpreter 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">George Drouillard</name>, and captains 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark</name>.
          <ref target="n1101" n="1"/>
               </p>
               <p>The close association continued at night, when the captains sought shelter with 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name>, and his family in a
          movable leather tepee. It was made of several expertly tanned buffalo hides sewed
          together in such fashion that they formed a tall cone when draped around a dozen
          ten-foot-long lodge poles.
          <ref target="n1102" n="2"/>Presumably the poles were also carried in the boat, for
          suitable slim, straight timbers were not always easy to find along the river's edge.</p>
               <p>Generally speaking, Indian women set up their families' lodges after each move, but
          it would have been unduly time-consuming for 
          <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name>to have struggled alone with the
          awkward tent each morning and evening. Since it is difficult to imagine 
          <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name>losing face, in his
          own estimation, by lending her a hand, conjecture veers to 
          <name type="person" key="York">York</name>. The black slave (
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>always referred to him as "
          <name type="person" key="York">my servant</name>") was enormously strong, fat, amiable,
          and trained by long experience in the ways of wilderness housekeeping. Probably 
          <name type="person" key="York">York</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name>also cooked for the occupants of the
          tepee. 
          <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name>, who was an expert
          at making boudins, a sausage encased in somewhat cleansed buffalo intestines, may have
          helped prepare other dishes as well.</p>
               <p>During the first week of travel, the expedition traversed the crinkled, miles-long
          curve called the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Bend of the">Great Bend of the
          Missouri</name>. There the 
          <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name>-bound river gave up its
          eastern course and struck south. For the boatmen, passing the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Bend of the">Great Bend</name>meant they
          were at last heading due west toward the setting sun, the 
          <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>. Spirits were high, and the spring
          weather smiled in accord. Gray disintegrating heaps of ice, pushed onto the banks and
          sandbars during the breakup, were the only remaining signs of winter. The trees in the
          bottomlands were beginning to bud; flowers spangled the greening plains, where flocks of
          geese fed on the new grass. Their square sails raised whenever the winds favored, the
          two pirogues and the six cranky new dugouts covered the ninety-three miles to the mouth
          of the 
          <name type="place" key="Little Missouri (E-mâh-tark',-Ah'-zhah) River">Little
          Missouri</name>in slightly more than four days.
          <ref target="n1103" n="3"/>
               </p>
               <p>Paradise did have flaws. Riverside bluffs were occasionally obscured by mephitic
          smoke rising from seams of lignite coal set to smoldering years before either by
          spontaneous combustion or by grass fires—the source, probably, of tales told by
          French-Canadians of volcanoes in the mysterious West. (Years later, the surveyor
          Ferdinand Hayden declared, "The sulphurous smell which issues from these fires is
          exceedingly offensive.") Other disagreeable odors rose from scattered piles of decaying
          buffalo carcasses; the animals had drowned when the spring-softened ice gave way under
          them, and afterwards had been deposited on exposed shores by the high water of spring. A
          more familiar discomfort appeared on April 9, the year's first "musquetor." By the next
          day the pests were troublesome, and would stay that way for months to come.</p>
               <p>Food was limited, at first, to parched corn and jerky. The men craved fresh meat, but
          
          <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name>and 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Assiniboine Indians">Assiniboin</name>hunters had
          frightened the game out of the river valley within two or three days' ride of the
          villages. The animals the Corps finally did see were too winter-lean to be acceptable,
          except for their tongues. Another substitute was the flesh of the beaver they shot or
          trapped; a single long, flat tail provided, when broiled, a feast for two hungry
          persons. They killed geese now and then, and also helped themselves to the eggs in
          whatever nests they found. To their surprise, most of the goose nests they spotted were
          high in lofty cottonwood trees. 
          <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name>showed them how to find caches of
          unfamiliar but edible roots that gophers stored near piles of driftwood. Meanwhile,
          buffalo calves were growing and were fat, even if their mothers weren't. So buffalo veal
          became, for a time, a mainstay of the thirty-two adult travelers and of 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>
                  <name type="person" key="Seaman">big, black Newfoundland dog</name>.</p>
               <p>As the days passed, the violence of the north and northwest winds increased. Sudden
          squalls added to the problem. Early in the afternoon of April 13, while 
          <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Toussaint Charbonneau</name>was at the
          tiller of the white pirogue and the boat was bounding easily over high, opaque waves
          where the river was several hundred yards wide, an unexpected gust lashed obliquely
          across the water. The boat listed dangerously. 
          <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name>froze. 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>yelled for 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name>to take the tiller and for
          the other crew members to drop the sails. The boat staggered upright, undamaged. "This
          accedent," 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>admitted in his journal, "was
          very near costing us dear." But he did not shift any of the pirogue's valuable cargo to
          other boats or make any changes in the crew's assignments.</p>
               <p>Perhaps he thought there would be no use in doing so. The six long, narrow dugouts,
          invariably called "canoes" in the journals, were particularly vulnerable to the
          unremitting force of the wind. This was especially true when the fleet had to turn some
          long, exposed point. Slapped hard by the waves, the unstable craft and, more than once,
          the pirogues shipped water. If the wetting was serious, the cargo had to be unloaded and
          spread out to dry.</p>
               <p>Sometimes the travelers could buck adverse winds by breaking out the tow ropes and
          dragging the craft ahead. At other times, perhaps for a few hours and on occasions for
          an entire day, they could not move at all. At such times they tried to find a cove where
          they could tie the dugouts to the shore and anchor the pirogues in front of them as
          breakwaters. The gales blew sand off the bars in streamers like smoke. "We are compelled
          to eat, drink, and breath it very freely," 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>wrote, to which 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>added, "The party complain much of
          the Sand in their eyes." In time the inflammations grew serious enough that 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>dug into the medicine chest and
          concocted an eyewash of white vitriol and sugar of lead (zinc sulphate and lead
          acetate). Meanwhile 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>fretted that "the winds of this
          country . . . have become a serious obstruction to our progress onward."
          <ref target="n1104" n="4"/>
               </p>
               <p>Wind or not, the captains never forgot that one of their main assignments was to
          learn what they could of the land and its wildlife. 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>was the one who spent the most
          time afoot on this assignment. Head bent against the gales, he wandered along the broad
          trails the buffalo had trampled into the earth and noted admiringly the exactness with
          which the shaggy beasts had worked out the most efficient routes from one point to
          another. He climbed the bluffs on both sides of the river to learn how plants, birds,
          and animals had adapted to the varied environments. He detected the difference in the
          habitats preferred by mule deer and white-tailed deer. He marveled at the way wolves
          would cut one antelope out of a herd and then spell each other as they ran the
          fleet-footed prey to exhaustion. He listened intently to bird calls so that he could
          render the sounds phonetically on paper. When he came across unfamiliar plants he tested
          them with his tongue, nose, and fingertips in order to be able to convey the most
          accurate description possible—descriptions often hundreds of words long and composed by
          the dwindling light of the evening's campfire. Unfortunately he never published a
          scientific paper on his findings and so later naturalists, acting in full honesty, often
          received credit for bringing to the world's attention bits of lore that 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name>had first portrayed.
          <ref target="n1105" n="5"/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>contributed fully. Sometimes he
          left spare accounts of things he had seen. More often he told 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>about the discoveries he had
          made during one of his own strenuous hikes and let his friend handle the paperwork. 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>main job was cartography. As he
          had done on the way up the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>to the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>villages, he kept careful
          compass records of the river's many turnings and of mileages between prominent points,
          as computed by dead reckoning. He then transferred the data onto separate sheets of
          paper, as he had done the previous year. Limited though the strip maps were to the
          river's immediate environs, they nevertheless could be used to check, in part, the
          accuracy of the big, conjectural map of the West he had drawn at 
          <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name>during the winter,
          relying mainly on information collected from the Indians and then transferred to the
          basic 
          <name type="person" key="King, Nicholas">King</name>-
          <name type="person" key="Arrowsmith, Aaron">Arrowsmith</name>map they were carrying with
          them.
          <ref target="n1106" n="6"/>
               </p>
               <p>Results excited the captains. The 
          <name type="place" key="Little Missouri (E-mâh-tark',-Ah'-zhah) River">Little
          Missouri</name>came in from the south and the 
          <name type="place" key="White Earth (Ok-hah-Âh-zhâh) River">White Earth River</name>from
          the north, as the Indians had said they would. The Indians had also said, or so the
          captains had understood, that the White Earth was navigable almost as far north as 
          <name type="place" key="Canada">Canada's</name>South 
          <name type="place" key="Saskatchewan River">Saskatchewan River</name>, as portrayed on
          their 
          <name type="person" key="King, Nicholas">King</name>-
          <name type="person" key="Arrowsmith, Aaron">Arrowsmith</name>chart. If so, the 
          <name type="place" key="White Earth (Ok-hah-Âh-zhâh) River">White Earth</name>could be
          used for tapping the great fur country of the Canadian Northwest. Buoyed by that hope,
          they walked beside the tributary for about four miles. It should not have struck them as
          prepossessing. Its low, steep banks were stained white with patches of alkali; its bed, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>wrote, "seems composed of mud
          altogether." Swollen by spring runoff, it was about sixty yards wide. Later settlers,
          seeing the stream at a drier season, would name it 
          <name type="place" key="White Earth (Ok-hah-Âh-zhâh) River">Little Muddy Creek</name>.
          But 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>wanted it as a highway for American
          commerce, and they wrote about it with the ink of hope, a strange aberration for two
          normally competent observers.
          <ref target="n1107" n="7"/>
               </p>
               <p>Three or four miles above the mouth of the 
          <name type="place" key="White Earth (Ok-hah-Âh-zhâh) River">White Earth</name>, another
          tributary of special interest to 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>entered the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>. This one came from the south
          and was truly majestic. The 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name>called it 
          <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Mee, Ah-zhah</name>. As noted earlier, it was
          not unknown to white men. French-Canadian voyageurs and traders of the original Missouri
          Fur Company had been calling it 
          <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Roche Jaune</name>for more than a decade.
          Roche Jaune, the River of Yellow Rock, or 
          <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone</name>. The name is inexplicable,
          for there is no indication that any of the whites who wrote about it had yet heard of,
          let alone seen, the vivid yellow walls of the river's upper canyon. Nevertheless, the
          stream, labeled 
          <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone</name>through some strange
          coincidence, appears strongly on 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>conjectural map, where it reaches
          much too far south across lands barely rippled by mountains.</p>
               <p>Such a stream merited actual examination, not guesswork. During their winter with the
          
          <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>, the captains had laid
          plans to explore it on their return journey to the States. Before then, however, they
          wanted to determine the geographic coordinates of its mouth for the sake of 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>strip maps. When contrary winds
          pinned the fleet against the banks of the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>decided to speed matters by
          going ahead on foot, accompanied by 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, and the brothers 
          <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph and Reubin">Joseph and Reuben Field</name>. After
          taking his readings, he would wait for the boats to follow when they could.</p>
               <p>The quartet climbed to the top of the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri's</name>southern bluffs and struck
          overland toward what they assumed would be the junction—if Indian descriptions were
          correct. Elation filled them. There it was, strong and beautiful, curling lazily through
          a wide, fertile plain streaked with magnificent stands of trees, their new leaves
          glistening in the sunlight. Then and there 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>decided, with the sense of
          wonder that is one of his most appealing characteristics, to camp on the 
          <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone's</name>banks, amid vast herds of
          wildlife, and enjoy the pristine scene before taking his observations.</p>
               <p>The next day 
          <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Joseph Field</name>explored the river upstream
          as far as he could walk and return before dark. Meanwhile the others roamed the area
          around the junction, thinking, inaccurately, that no other white men had seen this
          unspoiled Eden.
          <ref target="n1108" n="8"/>They picked out a site where a United States government
          trading post might be located in competition to the British, if the newly amalgamated
          Hudson's Bay and North West companies sought to take over the fur business of this
          lovely section of 
          <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name>Territory. (Though no government post
          was ever built at the junction, a series of commercial ones eventually were.)</p>
               <p>They could not get over the amounts of wildlife. "The whole country was covered with
          herds of buffaloe, Elk &amp; Antelopes ... so gentle we pass near them without appearing
          to excite any alarm, and when we attract their attention they approach more nearly to
          see what we are." 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>was so exhilarated that when the
          quartet rejoined the boats close to the confluence that evening, he ordered "a dram to
          each person; this soon produced the fiddle, and they spent the evening with much
          hilarity, singing and dancing, and seemed perfectly to forget their past toils, as they
          appeared regardless of those yet to come."
          <ref target="n1109" n="9"/>
               </p>
               <p>Did 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>ever sing and dance during
          lighthearted moments? The journals never mention such levity, and probably the captains'
          sense of what was fitting—that inevitable gap between officers and enlisted men—held
          them back. But surely their hearts sang. To be here, to open for their countrymen such a
          gate as this! And they still had close to two thousand miles to go. What more remained
          for them to find!</p>
               <p>On they labored, the river making S-curves ahead of them like a slow-traveling
          bullsnake. Past thick strata of coal, some of it burned dark red by old fires. Into a
          spell of frigid weather: ice on the water buckets, a dervish dance of snowflakes that
          whitened the ground and led 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>to exclaim that it was a "verry
          extraordenarey climate, to behold trees Green &amp; flowers spred on the plain &amp;
          Snow an inch deep."
          <ref target="n1110" n="10"/>But it was a fine country for all of that. The broad
          bottomlands were filled with more timber than the explorers had seen since passing the
          hundredth meridian. And the game was fattening—ducks, swans, buffalo, antelope, elk,
          beaver. "It is now only amusement," 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>said, "for 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. C</name>and myself to kill as much meat
          as the party can consum." But except for grizzly bears they killed no more than they
          needed, and they restrained the men as well. Their superiors in 
          <name type="place" key="Washington D. C.">Washington</name>would read such remarks with
          interest, for any army detachment ordered to penetrate the West would have to live off
          the land.
          <ref target="n1111" n="11"/>
               </p>
               <p>On May 8 they reached, sooner than they had expected, a large tributary flowing into
          the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>from the north. Since the Indians
          had said there was only one such stream beyond the 
          <name type="place" key="White Earth (Ok-hah-Âh-zhâh) River">White Earth River</name>(or
          so the captains had understood), this must be it. Not liking the Indian name, which
          translated as "
          <name type="place"
                        key="Milk (Ah-mâh-tâh, ru-shush-sher, River Which Scolds at All Others) River">The River
          That Scolds at All Others</name>," they rechristened it 
          <name type="place"
                        key="Milk (Ah-mâh-tâh, ru-shush-sher, River Which Scolds at All Others) River">
          Milk</name>because it was "about the colour of a cup of tea with the admixture of a
          tablespoonful of milk." The persistence of hope: if the 
          <name type="place" key="White Earth (Ok-hah-Âh-zhâh) River">White Earth</name>did not
          "furnish a predictable and advantageous communication with the Saskashiwan river," this
          one might.</p>
               <p>On and on, into adventures the captains, to whom safety was a prime requisite,
          probably would have been glad to skip—their feud with grizzly bears and, simultaneously,
          additional mishaps with the white pirogue.</p>
               <p>Bears! The trader 
          <name type="person" key="Vallé, Jean">Jean Vallé</name>, whom the Corps of Discovery had
          met far downstream, below the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name>, had spoken of the huge
          beasts with almost tremulous awe. The 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>and 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name>were frankly terrified.
          Before hunting a grizzly, the Indians painted their bodies as if they were going to war.
          If a kill resulted, they cherished the creature's curved black talons, each more than
          four inches long, as fully as they did an enemy's scalp.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>was supercilious about the
          tales. After all, the natives had nothing better to hunt with than bows, arrows, and
          notoriously wretched trade muskets. A skilled white, equipped with one of the new
          Harpers Ferry rifles, should have no trouble. The fact that the bears were carrion
          eaters, leaving their huge tracks in profusion around the heaps of drowned, decaying
          buffalo corpses, may have added to his scorn without his being aware of it.</p>
               <p>His first encounter did little to change his mind. While walking along the shore
          early in the morning of April 29, a companion and he ran across "two brown or yellow
          bears." (At first the explorers called the bears white, as their informants had. A
          strange error. The massive beasts are not white. However, the tips of their yellowish
          reddish, or even almost black hair are lighter than the basic strands, so that in
          certain lights they do appear grizzled. 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>later spoke of "grisly bears," 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>of "Grisley bears." Grizzly ... or
          perhaps "grisly," in the sense of "terrifying, ghastly"?)
          <ref target="n1112" n="12"/>The two hunters each picked a target that April morning and
          each accurately fired the single ball in his rifle. One bear fled. The other performed
          as the Indians had predicted; it charged. It was hurt, however, and the hunters were
          able to reload and bring it down. It was half-grown, a mere three hundred pounds, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>estimated. He admitted that it
          had been much more "furious" than an ordinary black or brown bear would have been, but
          he still believed that grizzlies "are by no means as formidable or dangerous as they
          have been represented."</p>
               <p>A week later, 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name>spotted a full-grown one,
          "turrible looking," standing in the water. Probably it was fishing; the stroke of a
          grizzly's front paw is lightning fast. Taking careful aim, each man fired, reloaded,
          fired again for a total of ten shots. Perhaps because the animal did not sense from
          which direction the attack was coming, it did not charge but swam with a tremendous
          roaring half the distance across the river to a sandbar. There it died. Some of the
          party dragged the body back with a boat. It measured eight feet seven and a half inches
          from the tip of its nose to the extremity of its hind feet. 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>thought it might weigh five hundred
          pounds; 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, six hundred. An autopsy showed
          that five balls had gone through its lungs; five more had lodged in other parts of its
          body. Its heart was as large as that of a large ox; its maw, ten times the size of an
          ordinary black bear's, was filled with flesh and fish. Its fat, rendered out for future
          use in cooking, as was that of most bears killed later on, yielded a small cask of
          oil.</p>
               <p>The experience, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>said, left half the party
          content to live and let live. "Others however seem keen for action." One of the
          unconverted was 
          <name type="person" key="Bratton, William E.">William Bratton</name>. He was suffering
          with boils—that scourge had broken out again—and was given permission to seek relief by
          turning his oar over to someone else and walking along the shore. Late in the afternoon
          he "came running up to the boats with loud cries and every symptom of terror and
          distress." While alone, he had shot a grizzly dead center, whereupon the enraged beast
          had pursued him half a mile, but, slowed by its wound, had not quite overtaken him.</p>
               <p>No bear could get away with 
          <hi rend="italic">that</hi>. 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and seven men tracked the animal
          by its blood and found it had dug itself a kind of nest two feet deep, into which it had
          curled. They poured a volley into it. By the time it had expired, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>was converted. "I . . . had
          rather fight two Indians than one bear." A figure of speech: he had never fought an
          Indian. But he had seen grizzlies die, and their fierce farewell to life, he confessed,
          "intimidated" him.</p>
               <p>Nor was that the end of the Corps's education in the ways of bears. On May 14, the
          six men oaring the two rear dugouts spotted a grizzly snoozing in an open spot and
          decided to bag it. They crept up behind a little mound until they were within forty
          paces. Four fired; two held off, in case of emergency. The bear charged and two more
          shots banged out. One bullet broke the animal's shoulder but scarcely slowed it. The
          terrified men scattered, hunting cover where they could reload. This did not mean just
          levering another shell into the firing chamber. As National Park Ranger Dan Murphy, who
          knows muzzleloaders, has put it, "Get out powder, measure, and pour into barrel. Get out
          greased patch and ball, put patch on barrel. Put ball on top of it. Draw rammer, ram
          ball home. Return rammer. Open frizzen. Get out powder again, pour small amount into
          frizzen pan. Close frizzen. Fire. Repeat."
          <ref target="n1113" n="13"/>
               </p>
               <p>Each shot seemed simply to direct the bear toward the shooter. Two men, hotly
          pursued, flung guns and shot pouches aside, and jumped over a twenty-foot bank into the
          river. The bear jumped after them and was about to close on one when a man on top of the
          bluff shot the grizzly (grisly?) and killed it. Thoroughly subdued, the sextet made
          their way to camp and there found that their act had been topped, unbelievable though it
          seems, by another of 
          <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Toussaint
          Charbonneau's</name>misadventures with the white pirogue.</p>
               <p>Both 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>had gone ashore that afternoon,
          leaving the boat and its irreplaceable cargo in charge of 
          <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Pierre Cruzatte</name>. A shift in the wind
          was favorable; up went the sails. Distracted by something, 
          <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Cruzatte</name>turned the helm over to 
          <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name>. History repeated. A
          squall jerked the brace of the square sail out of the hands of the man attending it. 
          <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name>lost his grip on the
          tiller. The boat rolled onto its side and would have turned full turtle if its motion
          had not been checked by an awning that had been erected earlier to shield the boatmen
          from the sun. While 
          <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name>was "crying aloud to
          his god for mercy," 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, watching aghast from the
          shore, tore off his coat before realizing he would almost surely drown if he tried to
          swim to the rescue through three hundred yards of high waves.</p>
               <p>Brandishing his rifle and howling like the squall itself, 
          <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Cruzatte</name>brought 
          <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name>to his senses. The
          men in the boat threw their weight against the high tide. The pirogue ponderously
          righted, filled with water to within an inch of its gunwales. Bailing and rowing
          frantically, the crew got it ashore. All this while 
          <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name>, sitting up to her waist in water
          and presumably holding her child in one arm, reached out and with "fortitude and
          resolution caught and preserved most of the light articles which were washed overboard"
          (
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>words).
          <ref target="n1114" n="14"/>
               </p>
               <p>Two narrow escapes in a single day. The bear might well have killed one or more men.
          The loss of the white pirogue could have ended the expedition altogether. As the
          soldiers put up a makeshift camp before spreading the baggage out to dry, the captains
          decided "to console ourselves and cheer the sperits of our men and accordingly took a
          drink of grog and gave each man a gill." As a more permanent memento they named the
          little side creek near the site "
          <name type="place" key="Snow (Brown Bear Defeated) Creek">Brown Bear Defeated
          Creek</name>."</p>
               <p>They spent two increasingly precious days drying out the pirogue's cargo. The main
          losses turned out to be a disturbing amount of medicine, some gunpowder, and several
          cooking utensils. On the 17th they took off again, hauling the boats against the wind by
          tow lines. As usual, they went to bed that night without extinguishing their campfires.
          Long after those in the leather tepee had fallen asleep, the guard roused them. A big
          dead tree had caught fire and was about to topple onto the lodge. Hastily its occupants
          moved the tepee about fifty yards away, whereupon the tree crashed. "A few minutes later
          we should have been crushed to attoms" (
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>). But they had not escaped
          entirely. Wind-dashed sparks severely damaged the leather lodge and set piles of
          driftwood afire, which "much harassed" the party and resulted in naming the nearby side
          stream, on 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>strip map, "
          <name type="place" key="Seven Blackfoot (Burnt Lodge, Rattlesnake) Creek">Burnt Lodge
          Creek</name>."</p>
               <p>One more naming. May 29. All but the sentry were asleep. A huge buffalo bull swam
          across the river, bumped into the white pirogue, and heaved itself over the stern. From
          there the heavy-shouldered beast charged into the camp, its big hooves thundering within
          inches of some of the sleeping men. Alarmed by the yells of the sentry, the bull swerved
          directly toward the hard-used tepee. The dog 
          <name type="person" key="Seaman">Seaman's</name>furious barking drove it aside and
          shortly the pandemonium subsided. At daylight the Corps discovered that the bull had
          broken, during its climb across the pirogue, the stock of one of the swivel guns, part
          of the rudder's mechanism, and 
          <name type="person" key="York">York's</name>rifle. "it appears," 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>wrote, "that the white perogue,
          which contains our most valuable stores is attended by some evil gennii." The closest
          creek was named "
          <name type="place" key="Dog (Bull) Creek (Mont.)">Bull Creek</name>."</p>
               <p>And a postscript. May 30. Not long after leaving 
          <name type="place" key="Dog (Bull) Creek (Mont.)">Bull Creek</name>, the fleet passed
          the mangled, horribly odorous remnants of at least a hundred buffalo that the men
          decided had recently been stampeded over the cliffs above by Indians. 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>expatiated on the procedure. A
          fleet-footed decoy disguised in a buffalo hide placed himself between a herd and "a
          precipice proper for the purpose"—a phrase to remember. Other Indians who had quietly
          surrounded the herd on all but the cliff side suddenly leaped upright and frightened the
          animals into flight. The decoy guided them to the brink of the precipice, then stepped
          nimbly aside and over the animals went, a waterfall of flesh.</p>
               <p>Though buffalo 
          <hi rend="italic">pishkins</hi>(a 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfoot</name>word) certainly
          occurred, modern archeologists who have clambered about the site described by 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and mapped by 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>doubt that those particular
          precipices were "proper for the purpose." They can be approached only across a long span
          of steep, ragged ground not conducive to a headlong stampede. According to the doubters,
          the putrid heap on the bank was composed of animals that had perished by falling through
          the spring-weakened ice and had later been deposited by high water, as had other
          collections of dead buffalo the Corps had noticed farther downstream. Maybe so. But at
          least one documented killing took place there, among the enormous number of overfed
          wolves that had collected around the corpses. They paid so little attention to 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>as he walked among them that he was
          able to step up beside one and, as an experiment, thrust his espontoon (more generally
          spelled "spontoon," which is a short pike equipped with a steel point) through its rib
          cage into its heart. With these many items in mind, the captains named the next stream
          they came to "
          <name type="place" key="Arrow Creek (Slaughter River)">Slaughter Creek</name>," a
          designation settlers later changed to 
          <name type="place" key="Arrow Creek (Slaughter River)">Arrow Creek</name>.
          <ref target="n1115" n="15"/>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>During the latter part of this month of namings, the land grew markedly more arid.
          The sides of the river trench were more broken, and the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>itself, murderous with sawyers,
          grew still more crooked. Most side channels were either dry or contained trickles of
          water so impregnated with alkali as to be scarcely potable. Springs of the sort common
          in the eastern United States were rare, and dews almost never occurred. A snow flurry
          early in May and a shower on May 18 were the only precipitation the Corps encountered
          during seven weeks after leaving the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>towns.</p>
               <p>Except for a few scraggly pines and patches of low, ground-hugging juniper that
          appeared near the tops of the steep bluffs north of the river, the principal growth on
          the hillsides consisted of different varieties of sagebrush, saltbush, and prickly pear
          cactus, all of them typical of arid lands. A useless country, 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>implied: "[It] may with propriety I
          think be termed the Deserts of America for I do not think it can ever be settled." Even
          that persistent romantic, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name>, spoke of "a desert,
          barren country," and rejoiced in the cottonwoods of the bottomlands, whose "appearances
          were quite reviving after the drairy country through which we have been passing."
          <ref target="n1116" n="16"/>
               </p>
               <p>The 
          <name type="place" key="Musselshell (Mah-tush,-ah-zhah, Shell) River">Musselshell
          River</name>, whose mouth they visited on May 20, aroused no particular comment. The
          name came via translation from the Indians, who long before had noticed the huge number
          of fossilized mollusc shells in the vicinity. The circumstance suggested an ancient
          inland sea, as that amateur paleontologist, 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Thomas Jefferson</name>, and some of his
          friends in the American Philosophical Society might have realized. But 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, pressed for time, did not pause
          to look for fossils.</p>
               <p>What really interested them right then were the distant, isolated ranges of high,
          snow-streaked mountains that rose out of the plains both north and south of the river. A
          puzzle. According to the captains' calculations, based on their well-worn 
          <name type="person" key="King, Nicholas">King</name>-
          <name type="person" key="Arrowsmith, Aaron">Arrowsmith</name>map as amended according to
          Indian information, they were still far from the 
          <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky Mountains</name>. The Indians, moreover,
          had not mentioned these islands in the sky, or at least neither 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>nor 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>had picked up any such statements.
          In an effort to explain the solitary massifs, the captains decided the mysterious peaks
          had to be a northward extension of the 
          <name type="place" key="Black Hills">Black Hills</name>, whose length they had already
          greatly exaggerated. This new conjecture was also wrong, but it was comforting, for it
          put an otherwise inexplicable phenomenon into context.
          <ref target="n1117" n="17"/>
               </p>
               <p>Another surprise (for it, too, had not been mentioned during the winter's interviews
          with the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name>) was a clear, handsome
          stream that entered the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>about two and a half miles above 
          <name type="place" key="Arrow Creek (Slaughter River)">Slaughter Creek</name>. After
          hiking up it for several miles, 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>"thought proper to call it 
          <name type="place" key="Judith River">Judieth's River</name>," after 
          <name type="person" key="Hancock, Julia">Julia (Judy) Hancock</name>. 
          <name type="person" key="Hancock, Julia">Julia</name>was then a child of thirteen and
          one hesitates to think that 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>was already contemplating marrying
          her, as he did when she was sixteen, or that 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>supposed he would. Nevertheless
          this gesture toward the fair sex, the first of its kind among scores of namings,
          impressed 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>romantic bent, as we shall
          shortly see.</p>
               <p>By the latter part of May the Corps was traversing, with infinite labor, a wildly
          beautiful stretch of the river known today as the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Breaks of the">Breaks of the Missouri</name>and
          still a fantasyland in spite of being partially mutilated by the huge 
          <name type="place" key="Fort Peck Reservoir">Fort Peck Reservoir</name>. In a section
          the explorers called the Stone Walls, the multihued bluffs were banded with a thick
          stratum of almost horizontal white sandstone. In places this band was seamed
          perpendicularly by intrusive dikes of dark brown volcanic porphyry. Erosion of the
          softer material around the dikes had left the jointed rock standing as trim as walls,
          only a few feet thick and often scores of feet tall, of "workmanship so perfect . . .
          that I should have thought that Nature had attempted to rival the human art of masonry"
          (
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>). Elsewhere water draining off
          the land back of the steep bluffs had worn the white sandstone "into a thousand
          grotesque figures . . . collumns of various sculptures both grooved and plain . . . some
          collumns standing and almost entire with their pedestels and capitals . . . some lying
          prostrate and broken." Pyramids, organ pipes, spires, niches, alcoves—scores of scenes
          of "visionary inchantment."</p>
               <p>Fittingly enough, this entrancing region was inhabited by large numbers of Rocky
          Mountainbighorn sheep. As early as April 29, some members of the Corps had glimpsed a
          few of the creatures skipping gracefully over rocky hillsides that looked too
          precipitous for any hoofed animal to cross. At that time the explorers had been unable
          to obtain specimens. In the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Breaks of the">Breaks</name>, however, the sheep
          became common, and on May 25 three members of the party shot three animals. 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>described them and their
          massive, circular, laminated horns in admirable, even practical detail: "I have no doubt
          of [the horns'] elegance and usefullness in hair combs, and [they] might probably answer
          as maney valuable purposes to civilized man, as [they do] to the native Indians, who
          form their water cups, spoons, and platters of it," as well as fancy, transparent, and
          elastic bows. The animals were perhaps too lovely for their own good; the Audubon
          subspecies of the bighorn, which was the one 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>described, became much sought
          after by hunters and is now extinct.
          <ref target="n1118" n="18"/>
               </p>
               <p>The Corps worked their way past these visionary enchantments at heavy physical cost.
          Although the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>was about as wide as ever, it had
          grown shallower and swifter. Near the mouths of side streams were jumbles of rocks that
          had been washed into the main river by occasional flash floods. The only way to surmount
          the dancing rapids that resulted—and also to buck the wind with its flying clouds of
          powdery sand—was to tow the boats. Sometimes the men struggled ahead in icy water up to
          their chests. Sometimes they hobbled, in their homemade leather moccasins, through
          cactus and over sharp stones fallen from the cliffs. The year's first sustained rain,
          which fell on May 29 and 30, made matters worse by turning the clay soil into a slippery
          goo so tenacious they had to fight their way ahead on bare feet.</p>
               <p>If an elk-hide rope stretched out and broke in the swift water, the boat involved was
          apt to swing sideways to the current and drift downstream. If it then struck a rock, it
          was likely to overturn unless salvaged first by the nimble work of the pursuing boatmen.
          In bad places, accordingly, the human draft horses observed great caution. In spite of
          that, the only hemp rope in the outfit, and the one reserved for the white pirogue,
          snapped. Heeling around, the craft barely touched a boulder and almost upset before
          crewmen could leap aboard and put it to rights. 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>was disgusted: "I fear her evil
          gennii will play so many pranks with her that she will go to the bottom one of these
          days."</p>
               <p>In his mind her days were already numbered. Risks were growing so great he planned to
          transfer her cargo to the collapsible iron boat he had designed in Washington and had
          ordered specially built at 
          <name type="place" key="Harpers Ferry, W. Va.">Harpers Ferry</name>. With that in mind,
          he killed six elk on June 2, intending to use their skins for covering his invention.
          That same day a grizzly pursued 
          <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name>, who managed to dive
          into a dense copse and hide while 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name>killed the beast with a
          shot in the head. So there was much to think about on June 2, but at twilight all was
          driven from the explorers' minds by what looked like a shocking geographic betrayal.</p>
               <p>Up ahead, where the bluffs on the south lost some of their height and the bottomlands
          widened, the river split into two branches of approximately equal size. Impossible. The
          only major northern tributary the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name>had told 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>about was The River That Scolds at
          All Others. The Corps had passed that stream, after renaming it the 
          <name type="place"
                        key="Milk (Ah-mâh-tâh, ru-shush-sher, River Which Scolds at All Others) River">
          Milk</name>, nearly four weeks before. Moreover: the sole tributary the Indians had
          mentioned as entering the main river from the south was the 
          <name type="place" key="Musselshell (Mah-tush,-ah-zhah, Shell) River">
          Musselshell</name>. They had not talked of the 
          <name type="place" key="Judith River">Judith</name>. Only of the 
          <name type="place" key="Musselshell (Mah-tush,-ah-zhah, Shell) River">
          Musselshell</name>, which was unmistakably behind them. Yet here were two streams. One
          had to be the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri's</name>. One had to be a branch,
          perhaps the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>north fork, as shown on the 
          <name type="person" key="King, Nicholas">King</name>-
          <name type="person" key="Arrowsmith, Aaron">Arrowsmith</name>map. Which was which? Why
          hadn't the Indians warned them?</p>
               <p>It was essential they learn immediately. For if they chose wrong and ended up
          stranded far from the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>headwaters, there would not be
          time to come back and try again, even if the discouraged soldiers were willing to make a
          second effort. Choose now. Choose right. Or the Corps of Discovery was finished.</p>
               <p>The next morning they moved camp directly below the junction, on the north side of
          the main river. While canoe and land parties made preliminary investigations of both
          streams, the captains scrambled to the top of the wedge of land separating the branches.
          This led to the discovery that a pretty little creek sliced through the wedge to enter
          the north fork a few miles above the junction. Because of that creek's bordering hills,
          they could not get a view of the course the north branch followed. But they did have a
          magnificent panorama of what lay to the south and southwest. First came the looming,
          snow-streaked peaks known today as the 
          <name type="place" key="Highwood (South) Mountains">Highwoods</name>. Beyond and
          somewhat to the west of the isolated 
          <name type="place" key="Highwood (South) Mountains">Highwoods</name>another stretch of
          peaks extended dimly a little west of north until their snowy summits disappeared
          beneath the horizon. The first ridge of the 
          <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rockies</name>at last! Or so 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>supposed.</p>
               <p>With the supposition came, like a flash of sunlight, a possible solution to the
          problem of identities. The 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name>had said that after
          issuing from the easternmost ridge of the 
          <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rockies</name>, the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>flowed northeast a hundred or
          more miles, passing a thunderous waterfall before veering fully east to pick up the 
          <name type="place" key="Musselshell (Mah-tush,-ah-zhah, Shell) River">
          Musselshell</name>, 
          <name type="place"
                        key="Milk (Ah-mâh-tâh, ru-shush-sher, River Which Scolds at All Others) River">The River
          That Scolds</name>, and the 
          <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone</name>.
          <ref target="n1119" n="19"/>The windings of the south fork and the gentle undulations
          of the land rolling out from the skirts of the peaks prevented the captains from tracing
          the course of the river far enough to know beyond doubt that it was the stream of which
          the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name>had spoken—the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, whose headwaters they had been
          ordered to find as a prelude to reaching the 
          <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>. Yet what else could it be?</p>
               <p>Well, there was that troublesome junction, that extra stream, just behind their
          heels. Why hadn't the Indians mentioned it? What was it?</p>
               <p>Probably 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>offered the explanation. During the
          spring, after talking about geography with the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name>(also known as the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Big Bellies</name>), he had drawn on
          his conjectural map of the West a dotted line labeled "The War Path of the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Big Bellies</name>." This was the route
          the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name>warriors used in reaching
          the horse-rich 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Snake</name>and 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Flathead</name>Indians of the 
          <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rockies</name>. The fast-traveling raiders
          disdained the labor and slowness of boats. Instead, they rode directly across the
          plains, well south of the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, until they intersected the
          river at the awesome landmark 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>had labeled "Falls" on his map. The
          worrisome river junction lay well north of the war path. Quite possibly the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name>had neither seen nor
          heard of the junction. So of course they had said nothing about it.
          <ref target="n1120" n="20"/>
               </p>
               <p>Back to camp 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>went, satisfied with their
          conjectures. And there they found that the enlisted men had developed a contrary logic
          of their own. For well over two thousand miles they had been following a notoriously
          turbid river whose bottom was thick with silt and whose surface had a heavy, undulant
          motion. The northern branch retained those characteristics. The southern was so
          transparent it was possible to see flat stones and gravel in its bottom. Its surface was
          swift, sleek, and sparkly. How could a stream that looked like crystal be the famed Big
          Muddy?</p>
               <p>This was a military expedition and the captains could have ordered, without
          explanation, the contingent to go where the officers chose. But to start the men along a
          route they clearly believed might be disastrous would destroy the high morale that had
          been a major element in the expedition's success so far. Consequently, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>replied patiently to the demurrers,
          pointing out that streams recently emerged from the mountains—and that description
          certainly 
          <hi rend="italic">seemed</hi>to fit the south fork—retained their clear, dancing
          appearance for several miles. By contrast, the north fork, which by measurement had
          turned out to be smaller than the south, was so laden with silt that it must have flowed
          a long distance through the plains. Perhaps it did not reach as far west as the
          mountains at all. If that were true, how could the expedition reach the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>by following it? Besides, what of
          all the things the Indians had said?</p>
               <p>The men weren't satisfied by these arguments. Nor were the scouts who had been sent
          out that morning any help. The depth of both the south and north river troughs and the
          rolling nature of the plains had kept them from developing any firm information about
          the rivers' distant courses. Clearly a broader reconnaisance was needed.</p>
               <p>In the end it was arranged that 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Sergeant Gass</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name>, the 
          <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph and Reubin">Field brothers</name>, and 
          <name type="person" key="York">York</name>would follow the south fork until they were
          sure of its trend. Meanwhile 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>would go up the north fork with 
          <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Sergeant Pryor</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Shields, John">Shields</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Windsor, Richard">Windsor</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Cruzatte</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name>, and 
          <name type="person" key="Lepage, Jean Baptiste">Lepage</name>. The seventeen men who
          stayed in camp under 
          <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Sergeant Ordway</name>would hunt, both for food
          and for deer and elk hides the Corps could sew into clothing and use for covering the
          iron boat frame. In particular, they all needed moccasins for feet torn and bruised by
          towing the boats barefooted over miles of stones and thorns. And all of them were still
          cheerful. No, it would not have done to shake morale such as that by arbitrarily
          ignoring the men's opinions.</p>
               <p>The new reconnaisance was conducted during a miserable period of mixed rain and snow.
          <ref target="n1121" n="21"/>
                  <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>party was the luckier in that
          they were able to stay dry in an abandoned Indian tepee during their first night out.
          There was probably considerable kidding of 
          <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph and Reubin">Joseph Field</name>, who escaped a
          grizzly's charge by the thinnest of margins. The next day the scouts got even, in their
          own minds, by slaying three huge bears and dining on part of one. And all the while the
          river trench kept pulling them southwest. The 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>for sure, 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>announced, though the others still
          had reservations. Turning around the next day, the little party made a forced march back
          to the junction, carrying with them, as raw material for more clothing, the hides of
          seven deer they killed along the way.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>trip was more arduous. At
          times thirst and wind-whipped rain drove his group off the plains into the bottom of the
          north fork. Not for long, however. The valley was narrow; in many places steep ridges
          dropped into the water. To get around such places they would either angle across the
          faces of the bluffs or clamber back to the plains. At night they sought shelter in
          thickets of riverbank willows. The brush broke the wind but did little to turn the
          rain.</p>
               <p>By June 6 (the day 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>returned to the junction), 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>felt confident the fork he was
          following angled too far north of west to strike the landmarks the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name>had said lay along the
          true 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>. To make doubly sure, he sent 
          <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Pryor</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Windsor, Richard">Windsor</name>ahead to a distant hill to take
          additional sightings. While waiting for them, he and the others constructed two small
          rafts. Floating down the river would be easier than walking either along its banks or
          atop the wind-swept, ravine-creased plains. Or so they assumed. When 
          <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Pryor</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Windsor, Richard">Windsor</name>returned about noon with word
          that the river continued north of west, they loaded their rafts for the return journey.
          The flimsy contraptions bucked and tilted. After soaking the elkskins they were taking
          to camp and almost losing their guns, they abandoned the effort, to spend another
          "disagreeable and wrestless night" without shelter.</p>
               <p>The next day they tried to negotiate the faces of bluffs they had crossed readily on
          the way upstream. This time, however, the soaked ground was as slippery as bear oil. One
          pass turned out to be especially dangerous. (By "pass" 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>meant a narrow, horizontal ledge
          and not a low saddle between hills.) When he tried to walk along it, his feet flew out
          from under him "and but for a quick and fortunated recovery by means of my espontoon I
          should been precipitated into the river down a craggy pricipice about ninety feet."
          (Shades of the knife thrust that had saved him from a disastrous fall near the Tavern, a
          short time after the expedition had started up the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>!) Behind him 
          <name type="person" key="Windsor, Richard">Windsor</name>landed belly down on the same
          slippery ledge, his right arm and right leg dangling into space. Calmly 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>coaxed the frightened soldier
          ahead to safety and then ordered the others to backtrack, descend the bluff, and wade
          around its base in ice-cold water breast deep. 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Windsor, Richard">Windsor</name>soon joined them, and they
          walked dourly through mud, water, and wet brush until, like 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>party, they found shelter in an
          old Indian lodge.</p>
               <p>At about ten o'clock the next morning, June 8, the sun broke through the clouds.
          Listening to the songs of an almost incredible number of birds, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>felt his spirits soaring. He had
          found a new river, and it needed a name. 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>had used Judith for a river he
          fancied, so 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>decided to lay claim to this one
          and call it 
          <name type="place" key="Marias River">Maria's River</name>in honor of 
          <name type="person" key="Wood, Maria">Maria Wood</name>, a cousin of his. Its turbulent
          and muddy water, he admitted, "illy comported with the pure celestial virtues and
          amiable qualifications of that lovely fair one." It was a noble river, nevertheless,
          passing through a rich, picturesque landscape where magnificent animals abounded. More
          important, it opened the way to a valuable fur country (that fantasy again!). 
          <name type="person" key="Wood, Maria">Maria</name>. 
          <name type="person" key="Wood, Maria">Maria</name>. But 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name>, unlike 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark</name>with his 
          <name type="person" key="Hancock, Julia">Judy</name>, never did marry her or anyone
          else.</p>
               <p>Having compared notes, the captains announced their decision for the shallow,
          swift-flowing south fork. To gain manpower for handling the boats in the difficult
          current, they decided to leave the red pirogue hidden in a stand of thick cottonwood
          timber on an island near the junction. Part of its cargo, together with the heaviest
          material in the white pirogue and in the dugouts, would be cached in a slender-necked,
          deep, bulbous pit dug into a dry spot well back from the river. Whatever essentials the
          red boat had carried would be distributed as evenly as possible among the remaining
          craft.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>carefully explained to a meeting
          of the men the evidence prompting the choice. The soldiers agreed to go wherever they
          were taken, but they were still not satisfied. With 
          <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Cruzatte</name>, the best riverman in the
          group, acting as their spokesman, they politely listed once more their reasons for
          favoring the familiar-looking north fork. To placate them once again, the captains
          agreed that 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and a small group of scouts
          would go up the south fork ahead of the main party to determine whether the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">Great Falls of the
          Missouri</name>did indeed lie up that branch. If they did not find the cataract within a
          reasonable distance, they would return and halt the boats before the error became
          irremediable.</p>
               <p>That weight off their minds, the soldiers, most of whom had spent the day dressing
          skins for clothing, "passed the evening dancing singing &amp;c and were extreemly
          cheerful." 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, though, was feeling unwell.
          Nervous stomach? Possibly. He seldom suffered from such an ailment, but this day the
          expedition was standing on the threshhold of what could be its most serious crisis to
          date. Anyway, he purged himself with a dose of salts and told his diary that the action
          brought him relief.</p>
               <p>His was not the only ailment. 
          <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name>, normally active and helpful, awoke
          wan and listless in the leather tent the morning after 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>purge. It was not a good time
          to drag. Both captains were absorbed in trying to bring order to the major adjustments
          facing the party. Rain-wet baggage had to be spread out and dried. The earth from the
          six-foot-deep cache had been placed on skins, lugged away, and scattered where it would
          not be noticed by passing Indians. Now the cache itself had to be lined with sticks and
          grass so the materials placed in it would stay dry. Items to be stored were segregated
          from those that would go. The former included bundles of furs, kegs of pork, hulled
          corn, powder and lead for bullets, traps, and all but the most essential
          tools—altogether about half a ton of material, 
          <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Sergeant Gass</name>estimated.
          <ref target="n1122" n="22"/>
               </p>
               <p>Because the blacksmiths worked up to the last minute putting the necessary tools into
          shape and repairing firearms, including 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>airgun, a second, smaller
          cache had to be prepared for the forge and bellows. A duplicate store of powder and lead
          also went into the second pit, so that if Indians found and rifled one cache, the other
          might remain to fortify the explorers on their return journey. Meanwhile the big red
          pirogue had to be inched into its island hiding place and covered with boughs.</p>
               <p>At some point during the hurly-burly, 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>noticed that 
          <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name>was suffering from more than an
          ordinary indisposition. Severe pains in the lower abdomen. Lips dry and feverish.
          Opening his razor-sharp lancet, he slit into a vein on the inside of her elbow. After
          letting as much blood flow as he deemed wise, he applied a tourniquet. The process
          probably terrified the young mother, even though she must have heard about and perhaps
          have seen the operation performed on male members of the expedition. But she had
          complete confidence in 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, which may be why he rather than 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>did the bloodletting.
          <ref target="n1123" n="23"/>
               </p>
               <p>All the principals in the performance were in the leather tepee that night, June 10.
          As 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>listened to 
          <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name>stir when the baby whimpered, he
          must have thought, before dropping asleep, how deeply they would depend on her when they
          met some of her horse-owning tribespeople up the river, as surely they would. As surely
          they 
          <hi rend="italic">had</hi>to. But he was too tired to worry for long. After all, didn't
          the nation's best physicians consider bleeding a sovereign remedy?</p>
               <p>The next morning, after a concerned glance at the pallid young woman, he shouldered
          his pack and started up the south fork with 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Gibson, George">Gibson</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Goodrich, Silas">Goodrich</name>, and 
          <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Joseph Field</name>to prove in fact what he
          already knew from logic: here was the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="notes" type="notes">
            <head rend="center">Notes</head>
            <div type="section">
               <note xml:id="n1101" n="1">I, 301.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1102" n="2">I, 285.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1103" n="3">
                  <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name>to the 
          <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone River</name>: I, 283–347; 
          <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>in Quaife, 190–203; Moulton, 
          <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>, plates 32–35 and 55–56.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1104" n="4">Quotations about wind and sand: I, 333–34. About eyewash: II,
          22.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1105" n="5">Cutright's "Summary of Discoveries" at the end of each
          chapter in 
          <hi rend="italic">Pioneering Naturalists</hi>makes 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>achievements in this field easy
          to follow. For the 
          <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>section of the trail, sec also L. 
          <name type="person" key="Thompson, John B.">Thompson</name>, 6–19.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1106" n="6">Moulton, 
          <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>, as in note 3 above. Heckrotte, 20.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1107" n="7">Allen, 253–54, 259–60.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1108" n="8">
                  <name type="person" key="Ménard, Pierre">Pierre Ménard</name>, a French-Canadian
          resident of the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>-
          <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name>towns, reputedly went to
          the 
          <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone</name>and perhaps up it some
          distance before 1800. What little information he brought back was collected by 
          <name type="person" key="Truteau, Jean Baptiste">Jean Baptiste Truteau</name>of the
          original Missouri Fur Company. Copies of part of 
          <name type="person" key="Truteau, Jean Baptiste">Truteau's</name>data were sent to 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, who forwarded the material
          to 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>. One assumes the lines about 
          <name type="person" key="Ménard, Pierre">Ménard</name>on the 
          <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone</name>were not included, or 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>would have been less positive
          about his being the first white man to see that river. For odds and ends on the problem,
          see Nasatir, 
          <hi rend="italic">Before 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>
                  </hi>, II, 381; Wood and Thiessen,
          30–45; Jackson, Letters, 138–39; Brown, 15; Saindon, 4–10. For 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>on the 
          <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone</name>: I, 335–36; 
          <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>in Quaife, 201–2.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1109" n="9">I, 338.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1110" n="10">I, 361, 345.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1111" n="11">
                  <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone</name>to the 
          <name type="place" key="Marias River">Marias</name>: I, 348, II, 112; 
          <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>, 171–211; Moulton, 
          <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>, plates 34–41, 43, 57–61.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1112" n="12">Cutright, 
          <hi rend="italic">Pioneering Naturalists</hi>, 142.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1113" n="13">I, 372. Murphy, unpaged, under date May 11, 1805.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1114" n="14">I, 25. Moutlon, 
          <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>, plates 50, 58. The incident of the nearly swamped boat is
          used by some scholars to explain 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>missing journals. He had been
          keeping a daily record, the argument runs, but did not feel the material was well enough
          polished to send to 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>with the other items that
          left 
          <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name>on the keelboat. He
          hoped to refine the journals and dispatch them to 
          <name type="place" key="Washington D. C.">Washington</name>aboard a pirougue scheduled
          to go downstream from the headwaters of the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>. In the meantime he substituted 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>jourrnal, though 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>also was embarrassed by his work's
          lack of polish. According to this theory, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>journals were stored in the
          white progue and were among the few articles lost during the mishap of May 14. Neither 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>nor he mentioned the loss, however,
          which seems strange—if it happened. Immediately after the upset 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>began copying into his often-sparse
          record 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>long scientific discourses, as
          if duplicate copies would guarantee that a similar loss would not occur in the future.
          For fuller discussions of this largely bootless argument, see Jackson, "Advice," and
          Cutright, 
          <hi rend="italic">History of the Journals</hi>.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1115" n="15">II, 91, VII, 95. 
          <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>in Quaife, 221. 
          <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name>, 110. The alternate explanation,
          drowned buffalo, is in Wood, "
          <name type="place" key="Arrow Creek (Slaughter River)">Slaughter River</name>."</note>
               <note xml:id="n1116" n="16">II, 80, 84, 88.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1117" n="17">II, 67. Allen, 265–66. Some of the isolated peaks the
          captains noticed were the 
          <name type="place" key="Little Rocky (North) Mountains">Little Rockies</name>and 
          <name type="place" key="Bears Paw (North) Mountains">Bear Paws</name>to the north and
          the 
          <name type="place" key="Judith (South) Mountains">Judiths</name>, 
          <name type="place" key="Moccasin Mountains">Moccasins</name>, 
          <name type="place" key="Highwood (South) Mountains">Highwoods</name>, and 
          <name type="place" key="Little Belt Mountains">Little</name>and 
          <name type="place" key="Big Belt Mountains">Big Belts</name>to the south.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1118" n="18">L. 
          <name type="person" key="Thompson, John B.">Thompson</name>, 10.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1119" n="19">Allen, 246–52. Ibid., 136, gives a reproduction of 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>mileage chart.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1120" n="20">II, 136. Allen 273n. Moulton, 
          <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>, plates 32a, b, c.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1121" n="21">The stay at the 
          <name type="place" key="Marias River">Marias</name>: I, 112–46; 
          <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>, 212–24; 
          <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>in Quaife, 224–30; Allen,
          268–78.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1122" n="22">II, 136–37. 
          <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>in Quaife, 227–29. 
          <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name>, 115. 
          <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse</name>in VII, 98.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1123" n="23">II, 140. Cutright, "Barks and Saltpeter."</note>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.lavender.01.10" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.lavender.01.00" type="contents"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.lavender.01.12" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
