<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.sup.ronda.01.03">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> among the Indians</title>
            <title type="sub" level="a">3. The <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> Interlude</title>
            <title type="sub"/>
            <author>James P. Ronda</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2005</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               
               
               
               
               
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title level="m" type="main">
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> among the Indians</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">3. The <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> Interlude</title>
               <author xml:id="" n="">James P. Ronda</author>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1984</date>
               <idno type="ISBN">0-8032-8990-1</idno>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
              <term>Texts</term>
            </keywords>
           <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Books</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-11-01</date>
            <date>2005-02-01</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>File splitting Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="ch3" type="chapter" n="3">
            <quote>
               <lg type="linegroup">
                  <l>"Durtey, Kind, pore, and extravigent"</l>
               </lg>
               <bibl>—<name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark</name>, 1804</bibl>
            </quote>
            <div type="section">
               <p>
The <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name> encounter had no quick ending and escaping its tangles proved no easy task. When the expedition resumed its progress up the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri River</name> on September 29, <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo</name> was on board the keelboat while the <name type="person" key="Partisan">Partisan</name> was waiting in the wings. Standing on a sandbar, the <name type="person" key="Partisan">Partisan</name> and two of his warriors demanded transportation as far as the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> villages. When the captains refused, <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo</name> suggested that a carrot or two of tobacco and a ferry ride from one bank to the other might placate the <name type="person" key="Partisan">Partisan</name>. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> wearily complied, hoping this would be the last <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name> request.</p>
               <p>
The expedition's attention was now turned to the first signs of the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name>. At the mouth of <name type="place" key="Chantier Creek">No Timber Creek</name>, known today as <name type="place" key="Chantier Creek">Chantier Creek</name>, the Americans found an abandoned <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> settlement. Described by <name type="person" key="Truteau, Jean Baptiste">Truteau</name> in the mid-1790s the village had been occupied until the end of the century. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> wrote that nothing remained of the village "but the mound which surrounds the town." <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, who always had an eye for simple but revealing detail, noted remains of cornfields in rich bottomland around the empty village.<ref target="n0301" n="1"/> In subsequent days the expedition would see more abandoned towns, all mute testimony to the many years of <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> migration along the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>.</p>
               <p>
On the following day, September 30, some of the last scenes in the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name> drama were played out. With <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo</name> still on board, the explorers brought their flotilla to a sandbar opposite a <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> encampment. As the men ate breakfast, the captains talked with several warriors. The Indians were told about the "bad treatment" the expedition had suffered at the hands of the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name> bands lower down the river and were warned not to try the same. Those brave words were carefully matched by a generous amount of tobacco, and the American party moved on without incident. In the afternoon the wind picked up and the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> suddenly became a choppy lake. Rocking dangerously, the keelboat seemed ready to founder. <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo</name>, fearing for his life, pleaded to be put ashore. Perhaps relieved to be free of their Indian passenger, the captains gave the chief some gifts and "advised him to keep his men away."<ref target="n0302" n="2"/>
               </p>
               <p>
In early October, as the weather turned cold and windy, the expedition encountered even more traces of the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name>. On the first of the month, they found another abandoned townsite, a fortified island settlement of substantial size. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> described the ruins as "only a mound circular walls 3 or 4 feet high."<ref target="n0303" n="3"/> But <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> found more than <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> remains around the <name type="place" key="Cheyenne River">Cheyenne River</name>; they also found <name type="person" key="Vallé, Jean">Jean Vallé</name>, an independent trader. The Frenchman was engaged in the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> trade and had a small supply of goods for that purpose. <name type="person" key="Vallé, Jean">Vallé</name> gave the captains an important bit of information about Upper <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> trade patterns when he reported that many of the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> were currently at the <name type="place"
                        key="Grand (We-tar-hoo and similar spellings) River (S. Dak.)">Grand River</name>
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> villages.<ref target="n0304" n="4"/>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> would soon learn much more about that <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name>-<ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> connection, and disrupting it became one of the captains' leading diplomatic objectives.</p>
               <p>
Knowing that they would soon be with the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> did not allay the ever present dread of <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name> ambush. October 2 proved to be a day filled with alarms and fear of the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref>. Suspecting a surprise attack, "We prepared our selves for action which we expected every moment." Action seemed at hand early in the afternoon when a large <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name> band appeared on a hill overlooking the north bank of the river. One of the warriors came down to the bank and fired his gun into the air. Certain that the attack was upon them, the expedition prepared to defend itself. <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse</name> later wrote, "we were determined to fight or dye." But that firm resolve was unnecessary as the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name> party, whose intentions were never clear, left as quickly as it had appeared.<ref target="n0305" n="5"/>
                  <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> warriors would not again menace the explorers until they wintered with the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Mandan.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>
                  </ref>.</p>
               <p>
As the expedition continued up the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, there were more signs of the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name>. On October 4, the captains saw the island village of <name type="place" key="Lahocatt village">Lahoocatt</name>, a fortified town of some seventeen earth lodges. <name type="place" key="Lahocatt village">Lahoocatt</name> had been occupied by an <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> tribe that <name type="person" key="Tabeau, Pierre-Antoine">Tabeau</name> called the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Laocatas</name>. About 1797 they had abandoned <name type="place" key="Lahocatt village">Lahoocatt</name> and moved north to join the larger body of <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> at the <name type="place"
                        key="Grand (We-tar-hoo and similar spellings) River (S. Dak.)">Grand River</name> villages.<ref target="n0306" n="6"/> At the end of the first week of October, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> saw even more abandoned villages around the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Moreau (Sur-war-kar-ne) River (S. Dak.)">Moreau River</name>. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> noted a substantial settlement of "about 80 neet lodges covered with earth and picketed around." A brief examination of the site turned up bullboats, mats, and baskets. Three different kinds of squash were still growing in the untended village fields.<ref target="n0307" n="7"/> The following day, October 7, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> walked up the <name type="place" key="Moreau (Sur-war-kar-ne) River (S. Dak.)">Moreau River</name> bank about a mile to yet another vacant <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> town, this one consisting of some sixty lodges. Occupied as late as the previous winter, the village was strewn with mats, baskets, and bullboats.<ref target="n0308" n="8"/>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>
Earth lodges, fortifications, and extensive fields of corn, beans, and squash were all signs of the culture of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> Valley villagers. The <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name>, or Star-rah-he as they called themselves, were the first of the northern plains villagers encountered by the expedition.<ref target="n0309" n="9"/> Virtually all European visitors to the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> noted the linguistic affinity between the <name type="place" key="Platte River (Nebr.)">Platte River</name>
                  <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Pawnee.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Pawnee Indians">Pawnees</name>
                  </ref> and the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name>. <name type="person" key="Tabeau, Pierre-Antoine">Tabeau</name> observed, "The <name type="native_nation" key="Pawnee Indians, Loup or Skiri">Loups</name> and all the different <name type="native_nation" key="Pawnee Indians">Panis</name> now on the <name type="place" key="Platte River (Nebr.)">River Platte</name>, made, undoubtedly with the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Ricaras</name> but one nation which time and circumstance have, without doubt insensibly divided." <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> agreed. The <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name>, they wrote, "are the remains of ten large tribes of <name type="native_nation" key="Pawnee Indians">Panias</name>."<ref target="n0310" n="10"/> The <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> met by the expedition were descendants of people who came out of what later anthropologists called the Central Plains Tradition. These people built nearly square lodges with rounded corners in what is now western <name type="place" key="Iowa">Iowa</name>, <name type="place" key="Kansas">Kansas</name> north of the <name type="place" key="Arkansas River">Arkansas River</name> drainage, and east and south-central <name type="place" key="Nebraska">Nebraska</name>. Since the tradition is associated with the Caddoan language family, they were probably the predecessors of the historic <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Pawnee.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Pawnee Indians">Pawnees</name>
                  </ref> and <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name>.</p>
               <p>
Sometime after A.D. 1400 these proto-<name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> began moving north out of the central plains into the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Big Bend of the">Big Bend</name> region of the Upper <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>. This migration may have been occasioned by severe droughts on the central plains. As the proto-<name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> entered the Upper <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, they settled in territory claimed by the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Mandan.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>
                  </ref>. Early relations between the two peoples were generally peaceful. Indeed, housing styles of the Central Plains Tradition influenced <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> earth lodge construction. But by the middle-1400s, as the northern <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Mandan.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>
                  </ref> began to reoccupy the <name type="place" key="Bad (Teton) River (S. Dak.)">Bad</name>-<name type="place" key="Cheyenne River">Cheyenne</name> region, conflict erupted. One sign of conflict was the rise of fortified <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> villages.<ref target="n0311" n="11"/> Meeting stiff resistance, the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Mandan.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>
                  </ref> gradually withdrew during the 1450–1650 period, leaving the Upper <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> south of the <name type="place" key="North Dakota">North Dakota</name> border open for <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> occupation. After the mid-sixteenth century and until the historic era, <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> sites in the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Big Bend of the">Big Bend</name> and <name type="place" key="Bad (Teton) River (S. Dak.)">Bad</name>-<name type="place" key="Cheyenne River">Cheyenne</name> regions were unfortified, a fact suggesting that fear of <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> attack had considerably diminished. But that fairly peaceful interlude was shattered in the eighteenth century when the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> migration to the northern plains and increased tension with the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> villagers once again caused <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> villages to be protected with enclosing ditches and palisades. As <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> were to learn, the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> were entering a time of trouble—trouble not to be made any less by the presence of outsiders with unpredictable behavior and uncertain motives.<ref target="n0312" n="12"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Characteristic of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> village life-style was the compact settlement with dome-shaped earth lodges, gardens, and nearby fields. <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name>, <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>, and <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> towns were all located around the mouths of major western tributaries of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri River</name>. The <name type="place" key="Bad (Teton) River (S. Dak.)">Bad</name>, <name type="place" key="Cheyenne River">Cheyenne</name>, <name type="place" key="Moreau (Sur-war-kar-ne) River (S. Dak.)">Moreau</name>, and <name type="place"
                        key="Grand (We-tar-hoo and similar spellings) River (S. Dak.)">Grand Rivers</name> were the foci of <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> occupation in the historic period. Several related ecological factors determined the location of Indian villages. The rivers provided fresh water while the valleys offered a source of firewood. In addition, the east-west position of the valleys acted as natural highways guiding western tribes such as the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref>, <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Cheyenne.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Cheyenne Indians">Cheyennes</name>
                  </ref>, and Kiowas to the agricultural towns.<ref target="n0313" n="13"/>
               </p>
               <p>
By the time <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> reached the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> in 1804, the villages were again fortified with ditches and palisades. The first extensive description of <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> defenses of the kind seen by the captains comes from <name type="person" key="Truteau, Jean Baptiste">Truteau's</name> 1795 journal. He noted that <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> villages were ringed by palisdes five feet high and reinforced with earth. The palisades were made of stout willow or cottonwood poles "as thick as one's leg, resting on the crosspieces and very close together." Against the palisades was an earth embankment at least two feet thick. "In this way," he wrote, "the height of the poles would prevent the scaling of the fort by the enemy, while the well-packed earth protects those within from their balls and arrows."<ref target="n0314" n="14"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Before the outbreak of smallpox in the 1780s, there were numerous <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> villages, each containing upwards of thirty-five earth lodges. By the advent of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> settlements clustered around the <name type="place" key="Cheyenne River">Cheyenne</name>, <name type="place" key="Moreau (Sur-war-kar-ne) River (S. Dak.)">Moreau</name>, and <name type="place"
                        key="Grand (We-tar-hoo and similar spellings) River (S. Dak.)">Grand</name> rivers had grown to accommodate refugees from war and disease. The captains noticed recently abandoned towns of sixty loges; each of three villages visited during their interlude with the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> had at least that number. The lodges were scattered in no apparent pattern, a deviation from the arrangement of them in rough lanes that recent anthropologists have identified as part of the Middle Missouri Tradition. When <name type="person" key="Brackenridge, H. M.">Henry Brackenridge</name> visited the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> towns in 1811, he found the lodges built so close to each other that it was easy for a newcomer to become lost quickly. There was no central plaza, as in <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> towns, although the large medicine lodge did provide some spatial focus.<ref target="n0315" n="15"/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> earth lodges were the first of that distinctive housing described by the expedition. The circular design of the domestic earth lodge can be traced back to what is known as the Central Plains Tradition. The essential features of the historic earth lodge included a fire pit at the center of the floor, four primary posts to hold up the superstructure, a smoke hole in the roof, and a tunnel-like entrance. The average <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> lodge was about fifteen feet high and thirty feet in diameter. Replacing dirt washed away from the frame was an important task for women after every rain.<ref target="n0316" n="16"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Although many European visitors to the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> towns attempted to describe the construction of earth lodges, few could bring the practiced eye of a carpenter to the subject as did <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Patrick Gass</name>.<ref target="n0317" n="17"/> On October 10, 1804, <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name> and several other members of the expedition went to the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> village at <name type="place" key="Ashley Island">Ashley Island</name>. While there, the sergeant took time to study earth lodges and their construction. <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass's</name> description remains the best firsthand account of <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> housing.</p>
               <p>
                  <quote>
In a circle of a size suited to the dimensions of the intended lodge, they set up 16 forked posts five or six feet high, and lay poles from one fork to another. Against these poles they lean other poles, slanting from the ground, and extending about four inches above the cross poles: these are to recieve the ends of the upper poles, that support the roof. They next set up four large forks, fifteen feet high, and about ten feet apart, in the middle of the area; and poles or beams between these. The roof poles are then laid on extending from the lower poles across the beams which rest on the middle forks, of such a length as to leave a hole at the top for a chimney. The whole is then covered with willow branches, except the chimney and hole below to pass through. On the willow branches they lay grass and lastly clay. At the hole below they build a pen about four feet wide and projecting ten feet from the hut; and hang a buffalo skin at the entrance of the hut for a door.<ref target="n0318" n="18"/>
                  </quote>
               </p>
               <p>
The earth lodge towns and their sedentary populations were possible because the villagers developed a complex strategy to wrest a living from the Upper <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> valley. Outsiders who visited the region in the summer months did not experience the demands placed on Indians for survival in the northern plains environment. Those demands included a climate of extremes from winters of—44°F to summer of +116°F and an average yearly rainfall of no more than sixteen inches. This rigorous climate yielded a frost-free growing season of no more than one hundred days a year.<ref target="n0319" n="19"/> Temperature, rainfall, and seasonal flooding meant agricultural uncertainties for Upper <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> farmers. Despite these problems, <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> farming was productive enough to sustain village life and produce a substantial surplus for trade.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> agriculture centered on the production of several food crops and at least one ceremonial plant. <hi rend="italic">Zea mays,</hi> the wild cereal grass, was the foundation crop for all Upper <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> farmers. Edwin Denig, an American Fur Company official at <name type="place" key="Fort Union (N. Dak.)">Fort Union</name> in the mid-nineteenth century, reported the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> corn "seldom exceeds two and a half or three feet in height." Denig noted that each cornstalk contained only a few ears with kernels "small, hard, and covered with a thicker shell than that raised in warmer climates."<ref target="n0320" n="20"/> Although corn was the essential staple for diet and trade, other crops were cultivated by <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> farmers. Beans were planted in the corn hills so that their vines could climb the stalks. Some of those bean seeds were collected by the captains and sent to <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, who in April 1807 planted them. He reported them "very forward" in progress by April 18. On the first of May of the same year, <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> planted some <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> corn at <name type="place" key="Monticello (Va.)">Monticello</name> and observed later that the plants produced ears suitable for roasting about a week after those coming from more familiar maize varieties.<ref target="n0321" n="21"/> Corn and beans, the two sister crops, were joined by a third, squash. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> recorded in his journal that the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> raised three kinds of squash.<ref target="n0322" n="22"/> Like <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> farmers, <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> women boiled some of the squash for immediate use while slicing and drying most of the crop for winter consumption.<ref target="n0323" n="23"/>
               </p>
               <p>
The <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> also grew pumpkins, watermelons, and tobacco. The tobacco attracted much of the expedition's attention. Both <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Patrick Gass</name> quickly recognized that the Indian tobacco (<hi rend="italic">Nicotiana quadrivalis</hi>) was something quite different from the Chesapeake varieties. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, always interested in precise botanical descriptions, observed that <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> tobacco grew about three feet high, was planted in hills, and was harvested in late summer. The captain found smoking this tobacco "very pleasant." Gass agreed about the pipe qualities of the blend but added that it was less suited for chewing.<ref target="n0324" n="24"/>
               </p>
               <p>
The land used by <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> farmers was held by family groups as corporate property. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> reported, "They claim no land except that on which their villages stand and the fields which they cultivate." The fields were generally plots of about one or one-and-a-half acres. Each family's land was carefully marked with brush and pole fences. Apparently, there were two kinds of <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> farm lands seen by the expedition and by later visitors. Very close to the villages were fenced garden plots. As trade demands for increased production mounted, fields up to a mile away from the village center were cleared. Planting began in April or May, depending on weather and ground conditions, and harvest of the major corn crop was in early August.<ref target="n0325" n="25"/>
               </p>
               <p>
As in many other American Indian tribes, <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> women did the farming. Europeans, accustomed to seeing men in the fields, consistently misunderstood the native division of labor and labeled Indian women "squaw drudges." <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> was not immune to that cultural blindness and insisted that <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> women "do the drugery as Common amongst Savages." <name type="person" key="Tabeau, Pierre-Antoine">Tabeau</name> went further and charged that village women were virtual slaves to tyrannical husbands.<ref target="n0326" n="26"/> What <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, <name type="person" key="Tabeau, Pierre-Antoine">Tabeau</name>, and other Europeans did not understand was the seasonal nature of woman's work, their companionship in the shared labor, the elevated ritual status of <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> women because of their role as earth mothers, and the substantial demands made on men in trade, war, and hunting. <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> women farmed, using two simple but effective tools. Hoes or digging sticks were made from the shoulder blades of buffalo or deer. These scapular hoes were used to break ground and keep weeds from overgrowing the plots. A second implement was a rake fashioned by binding reeds to a long handle. Despite the uncertainties of climate and flooding, <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> agriculture was very productive. As late as 1853, <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> farmers grew five thousand bushels of corn for sale outside the villages.<ref target="n0327" n="27"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Agriculture was the foundation of the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> economy, but hunting buffalo and other game animals was also important. When the corn crop failed, as it did in the summer of 1803 because of severe flooding, many <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> left the <name type="place" key="Moreau (Sur-war-kar-ne) River (S. Dak.)">Moreau</name> and <name type="place"
                        key="Grand (We-tar-hoo and similar spellings) River (S. Dak.)">Grand River</name> villages to hunt on the plains. Hunting was far more than an expedient in hard times. The extended winter buffalo hunt was a necessary part of the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras'</name> food supply. In October or November, hunting parties would leave the river villages in search of the herds. The mounted hunters carried skin tepees with them as they traveled far from the villages. Because of the close relationship between the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> and the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref>, village hunters sometimes spent the winter alongside the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref>. The <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> buffalo hunt was, at least until the mid-nineteenth century, strictly regulated by warriors especially selected for the occasion. Those warriors would arrange the placement of hunters and give signals for the rush to kill the animals. Their buffalo hunting was sometimes limited by interference from the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref>. Anxious to remain the prime suppliers of hides and meat to the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name>, <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name> bands blockaded the villages and kept hunters away from the herds. This happened in October 1803 and was further evidence of <name type="person" key="Tabeau, Pierre-Antoine">Tabeau's</name> observation that the buffalo was "a very uncertain resource" for the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name>.<ref target="n0328" n="28"/>
               </p>
               <p>
As <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> neared the <name type="place"
                        key="Grand (We-tar-hoo and similar spellings) River (S. Dak.)">Grand River</name> villages, they slowly learned about two aspects of <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> life that would shape their relations with the Indians. <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> politics might be best characterized as chaotic factionalism—a maze of interlocking lineage, village, and band loyalties complicated by the consequences of devastating epidemics. Just as <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had to thread their way through <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">Brulé</name>
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name> politics, so would they have to cope with men like <name type="person" key="Lighting Crow (Kakawissassa)">Kakawissassa</name>, <name type="person" key="Raven Man (Kakawita)">Kakawita</name>, <name type="place" key="Hay (Pocasse)">Pocasse</name>, and <name type="person" key="Eagles Feather (Piaheto)">Piahito</name>. But with the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> encounter still fresh in their minds, it was a second dimension of <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> life that commanded more of the captains' attention. During the troubled days at the <name type="place" key="Bad (Teton) River (S. Dak.)">Bad River</name>, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had heard about the complex web of trade that bound Upper <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> villagers and many western nomads together in an intricate system of cooperation, exchange, and intimidation. The importance of that system would be brought home to the explorers with considerable force during their interlude with the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name>.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> farmers were part of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> Trade System. Their towns were the locale's focal points for the system while the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> villages on the <name type="place" key="Knife River">Knife River</name> served as the upper exchange centers. The villagers were engaged in supplying the agricultural needs of the nomads. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> aptly described the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> farmers as the "gardners for the Soues."<ref target="n0329" n="29"/> They grew corn, raised horses, and processed hides in return for a wide variety of merchandise and foodstuffs brought by their western and southwestern customers. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> listed among those customers the <name type="native_nation" key="Arapaho Indians">Arapahos</name>, <name type="native_nation" key="Comanche Indians">Comanches</name>, <name type="native_nation" key="Kiowa Indians">Kiowas</name>, <name type="native_nation" key="Osage Indians">Osages</name>, and <name type="native_nation" key="Tawehash Indians">Tawehashs</name>. But the most important customers of the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> were the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Cheyenne.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Cheyenne Indians">Cheyennes</name>
                  </ref> and the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref>.<ref target="n0330" n="30"/> The <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras'</name> dealings with these two tribes were quite different, and those differences played a central role in expedition-Indian relations.</p>
               <p>
The often-troubled relationship between the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> villages and <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name>
                  <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> bands was an uneasy symbiosis. From a <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name> perspective, some sort of control had to be maintained over the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name>. As <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name> population expanded west of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, reliable sources of food had to be found. Both <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo</name> and the <name type="person" key="Partisan">Partisan</name> made plain to the captains the long-term <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> interest in controlling the flow of manufactured goods upriver to the village farmers. The overriding <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> need was for the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras'</name> food products and horses. Just how strong that need was can be seen in a preexpedition incident involving <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo</name> and his family. Sometime around 1800, one of <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo's</name> brothers paid a visit to the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> town at <name type="place" key="Ashley Island">Ashley Island</name>. <name type="person" key="Raven Man (Kakawita)">Kakawita</name>, <name type="person" key="Tabeau, Pierre-Antoine">Tabeau's</name> host, evidently had a grudge against the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">Brulé</name> man. When he killed <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo's</name> brother, the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">Brulé</name> chief took revenge on five or six <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> and a larger conflict seemed imminent. But as the August trading time approached and <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> corn ripened, all thoughts of warfare disappeared.<ref target="n0331" n="31"/> For the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref>, corn was more important than blood. That August, as in every other late summer and early fall, <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> bands flocked to the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> towns, bringing meat, fat, and hides from the plains and European-manufactured goods from the Dakota Rendezvous.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, like other non-Indian observers, consistently misunderstood the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name>-<ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> connection. Already disposed to cast the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Tetons</name> as "that lawless, savage, and rapacious race," the captains viewed the relationship as one of colonial exploitation. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> believed that this economic link meant <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> political domination of the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name>. As he explained, the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Tetons</name> maintained "great influence over the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Rickeres</name>, poison[ed] their minds and [kept] them in perpetial dread." To the captains, <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> villagers seemed helpless victims of <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> aggression. In both their written records and in their diplomacy, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> argued that a disruption of the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name>-<ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> alliance would free the village farmers from tyranny and might force <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name> bands to accept American trade terms. The explorers, who had only limited experience with the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name>, were not alone in believing that the villagers were an oppressed people. The trader <name type="person" key="Tabeau, Pierre-Antoine">Tabeau</name> insisted that the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> functioned as "a certain kind of serf" for the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="person" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref>. He declared that the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> were so fully dominated by the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="person" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> that they were even compelled to buy their bows and arrows from the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Tetons</name>.<ref target="n0332" n="32"/>
               </p>
               <p>
But this harsh view of <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name>-<ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> relations was not shared by the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> themselves. They saw many advantages in the connection not quickly evident to outsiders. The economic advantages included a source of manufactured goods, especially guns, and a reliable market for corn and horses. <name type="person" key="Tabeau, Pierre-Antoine">Tabeau</name> and the captains tended to overstate the violence and intimidation present in <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name>-<ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> dealings. There was, in fact, far more cooperation in times of war and friendship in times of peace. Much of the tension <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> were to encounter between the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> and <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Mandan.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>
                  </ref> was based on raids carried out by joint <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name>-<ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> war parties against the <name type="place" key="Knife River">Knife River</name>
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> villages. Among the objects sent back from <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name> was a buffalo robe painting of one such raid in 1797.<ref target="n0333" n="33"/> The <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> knew well the military power of the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Tetons</name>, but they also knew how important their corn was to <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> survival. <name type="person" key="Truteau, Jean Baptiste">Truteau</name> was close to the mark when he wrote in 1795 that "the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Ricaras</name> and this <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> nation live together peacefully. The former recieve them in order to obtain guns, clothes, hats, kettles, clothes, etc., which are given them in exchange for their horses. They humor them through fear and to inevitably overpower them."<ref target="n0334" n="34"/>
               </p>
               <p>
The captains themselves ran into the determination of the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> to continue their <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> connection. When the expedition stopped at the <name type="place"
                        key="Grand (We-tar-hoo and similar spellings) River (S. Dak.)">Grand River</name> villages on the return journey, the explorer-diplomats tried in vain to convince the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> chiefs to sever <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> ties. Several chiefs, who grasped the Upper <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> balance of trade and power better than the neophyte Americans, replied that they "must trade with the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sieoux</name> one more time to get guns and powder; that they had no guns or powder and more horses than they had use for, [and] after they got guns and powder . . . they would never again have any thing to do with them."<ref target="n0335" n="35"/> The captains had been put off in the best traditions of international diplomacy; once again their desire to rearrange traditional patterns of Indian behavior was thwarted.</p>
               <p>
If the captains and the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> had very different perceptions of the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref>, both parties agreed that the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Cheyenne.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Cheyenne Indians">Cheyennes</name>
                  </ref> were far more acceptable and less troublesome customers. The <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Cheyenne.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Cheyenne Indians">Cheyennes</name>
                  </ref>, who had abandoned farming in the eastern prairie valleys to become a plains people, depended heavily on the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> for foodstuffs and tobacco. Each summer many <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Cheyenne.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Cheyenne Indians">Cheyennes</name>
                  </ref> journeyed to the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> villages to trade and renew old friendships. Some advance groups came in mid-June while larger parties arrived in mid-July. Some remained with the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> well into the fall months, as <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> discovered. <name type="native_nation" key="Cheyenne Indians">Cheyenne</name> traders brought to the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> a wide variety of perishable meat products as well as exquisite skin clothing made by their women. The <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> especially valued "shirts of antelope skin, ornamented and worked with different colored quills of the porcupine." In addition to meat and fancy clothing, the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Cheyenne.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Chyenne Indians">Cheyennes</name>
                  </ref> also brought flour made from pounded prairie apples. Much of what they offered might be classed as luxury goods, but there was one <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Cheyenne.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Cheyenne River">Cheyenne</name>
                  </ref> commodity that <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> middlemen were very anxious to possess. <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Cheyenne.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Cheyenne Indians">Cheyenne</name>
                  </ref> horses were essential to fill out herds in preparation for trading with the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref>. The <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> wanted <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Cheyenne.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Cheyenne Indians">Cheyenne</name>
                  </ref> horses so badly that they were willing to trade precious guns, powder, and shot for them. During the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> period, the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> were prepared to trade one gun, one hundred rounds of ammunition, and a knife for one horse. The result of this trade, however, was that <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref>-<ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Cheyenne.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Cheyenne Indians">Cheyenne</name>
                  </ref> relations were often tense because the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name> bands resented seeing <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> corn in <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Cheyenne.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Cheyenne Indians">Cheyenne</name>
                  </ref> mouths and English trade guns in <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Cheyenne.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Cheyenne Indians">Cheyenne</name>
                  </ref> hands."<ref target="n0336" n="36"/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, arriving at the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> villages in October, did not see the festive trading days of August and September. Some fifteen to sixteen hundred people had thronged the trade fair, described by <name type="person" key="Tabeau, Pierre-Antoine">Tabeau</name> as "this great gathering of different nations." Although there was always the threat of violence, especially between the competitive <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> and <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Cheyenne.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Cheyenne Indians">Cheyennes</name>
                  </ref>, the trading days were better occasions to make bargains and visit old friends. "Times are lively," noted Edwin Denig, "feasting and dancing goes on constantly, both in the village and camp—horse racing, gambling in many ways. Bucks and belles dressed in their best and tricked out in all the gaudy colors of cloth, paints, and porcupine quills may be seen mingled in the dance or exchanging their professions of love in more solitary places. The old men smoke and eat without intermission. The middle aged exchange horses and other property. The soldiers gamble. And the young warriors spend both day and night in attempts at seduction of the young women in both camps. Strange scenes are witnessed here, much that would be interesting, much more that would be indescribable."<ref target="n0337" n="37"/> Although the captains had not experienced those scenes, they surely had to face the consequences of those trading days. The alliances and friendships forged during the trade fairs would shape the responses of the Indians to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> diplomacy in the days to come.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> saw little of the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras'</name> ritual life during their brief October stay. Had they come earlier, they might have witnessed the impressive blessing-of-the-corn ceremony done to ensure an abundant harvest. Tabeau, who saw the three-day celebration, wrote that "everything breathes gaiety at this festival." An elaborate altar was set up in the lodge of the principal village chief. That altar was festooned with large gourds, arrows decorated to look like corn stalks, green branches, and dried meat. Empty baskets and scapular hoes were placed before the altar to symbolize the hope for a bountiful harvest. Crowns of plaited straw were to ward off insects and green branches were offerings to the moon and stars to gain good weather. To honor their role in agriculture, women arrayed in their best clothing sat near the center posts of the lodge. Having missed this ritual, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> could not comment on it, nor on the many beliefs and rites surrounding the buffalo. Although the captains and their men spent considerable time visiting the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name>, no journalist in the expedition took note of the private altars and painted buffalo skulls present in every earth lodge. Nor did the explorers set down <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> ideas about the many spirits in their universe and the central force, "the Master of Life."<ref target="n0338" n="38"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Because the expedition's members usually seemed aware of Indian architecture and village design, it is even more surprising that no journal contains any reference to the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> medicine lodge. This ritual lodge was often the largest earth structure in the village. Located near the center of the village, it shared some construction features with domestic lodges: four primary interior posts, a central fire pit, and a walled entrance passage. The lodge measured some fifty or sixty feet in diameter and, unlike the circular domestic lodges, was octagonal in shape. Inside the medicine lodge and opposite the entrance was a low platform or altar for ritual offerings.<ref target="n0339" n="39"/>
               </p>
               <p>
If <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> were oblivious to the ritual ties that bound <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> life together, they were very aware of the powerful force that threatened to unravel it. Beginning in the 1780s, smallpox epidemics swept through the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> trench, wreaking terrible havoc on all Indians. In the period before the epidemics, the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> numbered perhaps twenty thousand to thirty thousand persons.<ref target="n0340" n="40"/> They belonged to many bands and lived in dozens of villages along the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>. The general western pandemic of 1780–81 killed perhaps seventy-five percent of the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> population, causing the abandonment of many villages and the amalgamation of numerous political groups. When <name type="person" key="Truteau, Jean Baptiste">Truteau</name> visited the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> in 1795, he was told that there had already been three epidemics, reducing thirty-two villages to a mere handful.<ref target="n0341" n="41"/> That wave of disease was followed in 1801–1802 by another one. <name type="native_nation" key="Tabeau, Pierre-Antoine">Tabeau</name>, writing about the 1803–1804 period, reported that "of the eighteen fairly large villages, situated upon the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> at some distance from each other, the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Ricaras</name> are reduced to three very mediocre ones." Although <name type="person" key="Tabeau, Pierre-Antoine">Tabeau</name> recognized the role of war in this dramatic population decline, he was emphatic in arguing that smallpox "unexpectedly made this terrible ravage among them." <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> were only recording the obvious when they blandly noted that the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> were "much reduced" from previous numbers.<ref target="n0342" n="42"/>
               </p>
               <p>
For the history of expedition-Indian relations, the impact of the epidemics was most clearly seen in <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> politics. Although there is little evidence that the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> developed political integration beyond the village level before the 1780–81 pandemic, the waves of disease so shattered the ranks of chiefs, elders, bundle holders, and important women as to make future intervillage leadership highly unlikely. As their numbers dropped and survivors from many different villages and lineages clustered into what amounted to refugee towns, intense factionalism flared between dozens of once powerful chiefs and warriors. Just as <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> have to confront <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name>
                  <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> internal politics, now they would have to deal with the domestic rivalries present in the three <name type="place"
                        key="Grand (We-tar-hoo and similar spellings) River (S. Dak.)">Grand River</name> settlements.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Truteau, Jean Baptiste">Truteau</name> was the first non-Indian to analyze <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> factional politics. The French trader recognized that the villages he knew around the <name type="place" key="Cheyenne River">Cheyenne River</name> in 1795 were filled with the survivors of earlier epidemics. The chiefs were constantly engaged in "differences of opinion and wrangles for authority." <name type="person" key="Truteau, Jean Baptiste">Truteau</name> bealived that this factionalism, or "jealousy" as he termed it, was "the sole cause of their discord and their divisions." He reported that these factional controversies were sufficiently intense to cause some <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> to move north to the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> region while others drifted south to live with the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Pawnee.html"
                       rend="box">Pawnees</ref>.<ref target="n0343" n="43"/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Tabeau, Pierre-Antoine">Tabeau</name>, who spent much more time with the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> than either <name type="person" key="Truteau, Jean Baptiste">Truteau</name> or the captains, added much valuable detail to <name type="person" key="Truteau, Jean Baptiste">Truteau's</name> concept of factionalism bred by disease. <name type="person" key="Tabeau, Jean Baptiste">Tabeau</name> had firsthand experience with the rivalries between Indian leaders. When he arrived among the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name>, he became the object of much bickering between the <name type="place" key="Ashley Island">Ashley Island</name> village's civil chief <name type="person" key="Lighting Crow (Kakawissassa)">Kakawissassa</name> and a war chief named <name type="person" key="Raven Man (Kakawita)">Kakawita</name>. Both men wanted the honor and prestige of having <name type="person" key="Tabeau, Pierre-Antoine">Tabeau</name> as a house guest. But the argument went well beyond hospitality. Whoever played host to the trader would reap considerable influence in village life. For <name type="person" key="Raven Man (Kakawita)">Kakawita</name>, leader of a small village recently come to <name type="place" key="Ashley Island">Ashley Island</name>, snaring <name type="person" key="Tabeau, Pierre-Antoine">Tabeau</name> meant economic advantage and increased power. The Frenchman had another lesson in <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> factionalism when in August 1803 he attempted to convene a grand council to discuss trade arrangements. Knowing how many <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> males were designated as chiefs, the trader carefully invited forty-two of the leading men. To his surprise, he was berated for neglecting so many others. As <name type="person" key="Tabeau, Pierre-Antoine">Tabeau</name> aptly put it, the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> towns were filled with "captains without companies."<ref target="n0344" n="44"/> Dialect differences, old rivalries, important families weakened by disease, and leaders without followers all made <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> politics treacherous ground for any outsider.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>
At the time <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> visited them, the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> were living in three large villages on the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> near the mouth of the <name type="place"
                        key="Grand (We-tar-hoo and similar spellings) River (S. Dak.)">Grand River</name>. These villages were founded sometime in the late 1790s after the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> abandoned their <name type="place" key="North Dakota">North Dakota</name> settlements.<ref target="n0345" n="45"/> The first <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> village encountered by the expedition was <name type="place" key="Sawa-haini village">Sawa-haini</name>, which consisted of about sixty earth lodges on <name type="place" key="Ashley Island">Ashley Island</name> in the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri River</name>. The island was fully cultivated, with corn and tobacco especially evident. Both <name type="person" key="Tabeau, Pierre-Antoine">Tabeau</name> and the captains reported that <name type="person" key="Lighting Crow (Kakawissassa)">Kakawissassa, or the Crow at Rest</name>, was the leading civil chief in <name type="place" key="Sawa-haini village">Sawa-haini</name>. However, during the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> period his authority was challenged by <name type="person" key="Raven Man (Kakawita)">Kakawita, or Man Crow</name>, war chief of the small village of <name type="place" key="Narhkarica village">Narhkarica</name> recently come to <name type="place" key="Sawa-haini village">Sawa-haini</name>. When the captains returned in 1806, <name type="person" key="Lighting Crow (Kakawissassa)">Kakawissassa</name> told them he had given his chief's medal to yet another <name type="place" key="Sawa-haini village">Sawa-haini</name> chief, a man named <name type="person" key="Grey Eyes">Grey Eyes</name>. People living on the island, along with those at the second village, were known to the captains as <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name>-proper in order to distinguish them from the ethnically diverse <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> of the third town. That second village was upriver a short distance from <name type="place" key="Sawa-haini village">Sawa-haini</name>. Part of what archaeologists call the <name type="place" key="Leavenworth site">Leavenworth Site</name> (39C09), <name type="place" key="Rhtarahe village">Rhtarahe</name> was the lower of the two villages to share this location. <name type="place" key="Rhtarahe village">Rhtarahe</name> had about sixty to seventy lodges. <name type="native_nation" key="Hay (Pocasse)">Pocasse or Hay</name> was the leading civil chief. <name type="place" key="Cottonwood Creek (S. Dak.)">Cottonwood Creek</name> separated the earth lodges of <name type="place" key="Rhtarahe village">Rhtarahe</name> from those of <name type="place" key="Waho-erha village">Waho-erha</name>. European visitors to the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> recognized that <name type="place" key="Waho-erha village">Waho-erha</name> was different from the other villages in both language and ethnic mix. Answering a query from <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Nicholas Biddle</name> in 1810, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> reported that <name type="place" key="Waho-erha village">Waho-erha</name> was composed of nine different tribes who had not been involved in recent (1790s) troubles with the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Mandan.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>
                  </ref> as had the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name>-proper. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> noted, "A difference in pronounciation and some difference of language may be discovered between them and the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> proper."<ref target="n0346" n="46"/>
                  <name type="person" key="Tabeau, Pierre-Antoine">Tabeau</name>, who had more experience with the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name>, agreed with <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> observation. The French trader characterized the differing <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> accents and inflections as "the tower of Babel." The leading civil chief in <name type="place" key="Waho-erha village">Waho-erha</name> was <name type="person" key="Eagles Feather (Piaheto)">Piahito, or Hawk's Feather</name>. Unlike the <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name>, who developed an intervillage council in the 1780s, factionalism and old suspicions kept the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> bands divided. Each village would face the American visitors alone.<ref target="n0347" n="47"/>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>
On October 8, 1804, as the Corps of Discovery passed the mouth of the <name type="place"
                        key="Grand (We-tar-hoo and similar spellings) River (S. Dak.)">Grand River</name>, two of the explorers cam upon the <name type="place" key="Ashley Island">Ashley Island</name> village of <name type="place" key="Sawa-haini village">Sawa-haini</name>. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> described the three-mile-long island as "covered with fields, where those people raise their corn, tobacco, beans etc." As the flotilla passed the island, many <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> lined the banks to gawk at the strangers. The men were dressed in buffalo robes, leggings, and moccasins while the women wore fringed antelope dresses. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> noted that most of the warriors were well armed with northwest trade guns.<ref target="n0348" n="48"/> On a sandbar opposite the village were more <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> sightseers and a French trader. While <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> led most of the party to a campsite beyond the island, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and several crewmen in a pirogue went to talk with the trader. The captains had been told in <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> that they might meet one "<name type="person" key="Tabeau, Pierre-Antoine">Mr. Tebeaux</name>," who could give the explorers "much information in relation to that country."<ref target="n0349" n="49"/> The Frenchman on shore was <name type="person" key="Tabeau, Pierre-Antoine">Tabeau's</name> fellow trader, <name type="person" key="Gravelines, Joseph">Joseph Gravelines</name>. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> described him as "a man well versed in the language of this nation [who] gave us some information relitive to the Country, nation etc."<ref target="n0350" n="50"/> Both <name type="person" key="Gravelines, Joseph">Gravelines</name> and <name type="person" key="Tabeau, Pierre-Antoine">Tabeau</name> spoke the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> and <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> languages, skills much in demand for the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> talks. Later in the evening <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, <name type="person" key="Gravelines, Joseph">Gravelines</name>, and some of the party went to <name type="place" key="Sawa-haini village">Sawa-haini</name> carrying tobacco for a get-acquainted smoke. Heartened by that event and reassured by <name type="person" key="Gravelines, Joseph">Gravelines</name> and <name type="person" key="Tabeau, Pierre-Antoine">Tabeau</name> that the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> were "all friendly and glad to see us," the captains prepared for serious diplomacy the next day.<ref target="n0351" n="51"/>
               </p>
               <p>
At camp during that first evening among the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name>, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> may well have discussed American diplomatic goals as applied to the <name type="place"
                        key="Grand (We-tar-hoo and similar spellings) River (S. Dak.)">Grand River</name> villagers. The captains surely did not accept <name type="person" key="Truteau, Jean Baptiste">Truteau's</name> claim that the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> were "the key to the passages which we must traverse to reach all the nations higher up the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>."<ref target="n0352" n="52"/> That distinction was reserved for the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name>
                  <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref>. Nonetheless, the explorer-diplomats did not underestimate the importance of the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> both as military allies of the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> and as potential American trading partners. They knew from their <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> contacts that the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> had harrassed traders and often blocked their access upriver to the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Mandan.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>
                  </ref>. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> was honestly concerned about the reception the expedition would receive when he wrote that the Americans were prepared for war or peace with the villagers. <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> had not given the explorers the kind of precise instructions for the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> negotiations as he had for dealings with the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name>
                  <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref>. However, the general observations in the president's instructions to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and the recent experiences with the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Tetons</name> served to clarify what the expedition hoped to achieve while at the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> villages. On one level these objectives were the same as pursued since the beginning of the voyage. The captains were to assert United States sovereignty over Louisiana Purchase lands. Military parades and airgun displays were put on to make Indians stand in awe of American power. As they had done with other tribes, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> planned to distribute medals and uniforms to chiefs ready to support American authority. Old rivalries were to be forgotten and peace was to obtain among all the tribes. Such a peace was a prerequisite for another cornerstone of American policy: the promotion of trade with American merchants. Although the captains knew from <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> informants and from conversations with <name type="person" key="Tabeau, Pierre-Antoine">Tabeau</name> and <name type="person" key="Gravelines, Joseph">Gravelines</name> that the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> could not supply beaver pelts, the market for goods to replace those of English manufacture was great.<ref target="n0353" n="53"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Sovereignty, client chiefs, and trade were all important subjects for discussion with the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> chiefs. But if the events of the interlude with the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> proved any test, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had other things on their minds as well. Those other concerns focused on the complex relations between the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name>
                  <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref>, the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name>, and the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Mandan.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>
                  </ref> and <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name>. The explorers only gradually sensed how intricate those relations were. As they began talks with the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name>, the captains perceived the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Tetons</name> as ferocious enemies to undercut, the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> as unwilling dupes of the rapacius <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref>, and the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Mandan.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>
                  </ref> and <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name> as a force of unknown dimensions. With a naive optimism typical of so much Euro-American frontier diplomacy, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> believed they could easily reshape Upper <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> realities to fit their expectations. The <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> were to be weaned away from dependence on the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Tetons</name>. An American-inspired alliance of all Upper <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> villagers might further weaken the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref>. On the night before the negotiations began, those goals seemed within reach. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> knew from <name type="person" key="Tabeau, Pierre-Antoine">Tabeau</name> and <name type="person" key="Gravelines, Joseph">Gravelines</name> that <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> moves had been underway in the past six months to lessen tensions with the <name type="place" key="Knife River">Knife River</name> peoples. But the captains also knew that the Laocata band of <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> had done all it could to sabotage an <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name>-<name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> peace. The Laocata action was a reminder that the violent events of the 1790s were not forgotten. Weakening the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name>-<ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> connection and promoting peace among all the Upper <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> villagers seemed a rational and beneficial policy to both the captains and their trader allies.<ref target="n0354" n="54"/> To the surprise of the explorer-diplomats, virtually all Indian parties proved resistant to change and suspicious of American motives.</p>
               <p>
During the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name> face-off it had been evident that <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">Brulé</name> politicians like <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo</name> and the <name type="person" key="Partisan">Partisan</name> had a clear concept of <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name> interests and the personal stature to make decisions promoting those interests. In the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> political world of "captains without companies," it proved more difficult to articulate a policy toward non-Indian outsiders. Civil chiefs, leading warriors, elders, and important families found their authority fragmented and open to challenge in the troubled times after the epidemics. Having the remnants of several bands living in one village made for political tensions unknown in <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> life before disease forced such amalgamation. This state of affairs would remain unchanged for years. When the Astorians were among the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> in 1811, some village chiefs attempted to block the progress of that expedition unless substantial gifts were offered. This decision was openly opposed by several elders who urged the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> to "behave well towards white people," arguing that "the advantages they derived by intercourse with them" far outweighed any danger.<ref target="n0355" n="55"/> In the fall of 1804, village chiefs like <name type="person" key="Lighting Crow (Kakawissassa)">Kakawissassa</name> and <name type="person" key="Eagles Feather (Piaheto)">Piahito</name> had considerable influence, but their power to determine and enforce policies was limited by cultural attitudes toward leadership as well as by the presence of refugee bands who did not accept decisions made by others. Chiefs, leading families, and ordinary <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> saw little reason to exchange valuable and reliable dealings with the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name>
                  <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> for the uncertainties of <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> trade and <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> friendship. Village chiefs would be polite to the white strangers and might even make some promises, but the real <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> interest was to have the Americans move on with the least disruption to the old ways of war and trade.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> hoped to begin talks with the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> on October 9. Invitations had been sent by way of <name type="person" key="Gravelines, Joseph">Gravelines</name> and <name type="person" key="Tabeau, Pierre-Antoine">Tabeau</name> to <name type="person" key="Lighting Crow (Kakawissassa)">Kakawissassa</name>, <name type="place" key="Hay (Pocasse)">Pocasse</name>, and <name type="person" key="Eagles Feather (Piaheto)">Piahito</name>. A flag pole had been raised at the expedition's camp and some preparations were underway to begin the now-familiar display of military pomp and hardware. Sometime before noon the three chiefs appeared and the obligatory smoking began. The visual impact of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> diplomacy required good weather for marching, shooting, and distributing gifts. When it became plain that this Tuesday would be windy, rainy, and cold, all agreed to postpone discussions until the following day. The <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> and Americans spent the rest of the day visiting each other. During those visits, <name type="person" key="York">York</name> proved to be the greatest attraction, as he would be on subsequent days. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> wrote that the villagers were "much astonished at my black Servent, who did not lose the opportunity of displaying his powers, strength etc."<ref target="n0356" n="56"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Clear weather the next day seemed promising for a council session. After breakfast with <name type="person" key="Tabeau, Pierre-Antoine">Tabeau</name> and <name type="person" key="Gravelines, Joseph">Gravelines</name>, the captains made all the necessary preparations for the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras'</name> arrival. After the flag was raised and many of the men donned dress uniforms, the camp was ready to greet its Indian visitors. By midmorning <name type="person" key="Lighting Crow (Kakawissassa)">Kakawissassa</name> and several leading men from <name type="place" key="Sawa-haini village">Sawa-haini</name> had arrived. But to the captains' dismay, delegations from the two other villages were conspicuously absent. That absence was a clear indication of the tension between the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> towns. <name type="place" key="Hay (Pocasse)">Pocasse</name>, <name type="person" key="Eagles Feather (Piaheto)">Piahito</name>, and their respective village councils were fearful that <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> might make <name type="person" key="Lighting Crow (Kakawissassa)">Kakawissassa</name> the "grand chief." Such an action would upset the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> balance of power and possibly had no precedent in <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> history. The captains, having learned something about internal Indian politics while among the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Tetons</name>, recognized the source of the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras'</name> concern. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> observed, "We have every reason to believe that a gellousy exists between the Villages for fear of our making the first chief from the lower village." But recognizing the problem did not mean that <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> were willing to alter their decision to make <name type="person" key="Lighting Crow (Kakawissassa)">Kakawissassa</name> the first or grand chief. At noon, increasingly concerned over the delay and worried that the talks might crumble, the captains asked <name type="person" key="Gravelines, Joseph">Gravelines</name> to go over to the villages and again invite <name type="place" key="Hay (Pocasse)">Pocasse</name> and <name type="person" key="Eagles Feather (Piaheto)">Piahito</name> to the council.<ref target="n0357" n="57"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Early in the afternoon the two reluctant chiefs and several principal men arrived at the expedition's camp. After smoking the required pipe, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> stood and "read a speech to them giving them good counsel." This prepared talk, interpreted to the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> by <name type="person" key="Gravelines, Joseph">Gravelines</name>, was probably the same one delivered to other tribes from the beginning of the voyage. As the captains told the Otos, "the great chief of the Seventeen great nations of America, impelled by his parental regard for his newly adopted children on the troubled waters, has sent us out to clear the road, remove every obstruction, and make it the road of peace between himself and his red children residing there."<ref target="n0358" n="58"/> The speech stressed the now-familiar themes of federal Indian policy in the early Trans-<name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name> West. The acceptance of United States sovereignty, peace between the tribes, and trade with American merchants would be rewarded by the protection and favor of the great chief of the seventeen fires.</p>
               <p>
As <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> was slowly reading his speech, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> attention was seized by something in the audience that put a new urgency to the negotiations: the presence of two <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name>
                  <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref>, one of whom <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> recognized from the troubled days at the <name type="place" key="Bad (Teton) River (S. Dak.)">Bad River</name>. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> was certain that the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> were there to thwart the progress of the expedition and retain some measure of control over <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> affairs. If the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name> ambassadors succeeded in playing on the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras'</name> fears, especially those of <name type="place" key="Hay (Pocasse)">Pocasse</name> and <name type="person" key="Eagles Feather (Piaheto)">Piahito</name>, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> might have to face a second Upper <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> Indian confrontation.<ref target="n0359" n="59"/>
               </p>
               <p>
With <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> talk finished, the display of military firepower and the all-important distribution of gifts began. As if to put an exclamation point to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> presentation, three shots were fired from the bow swivel gun on the keelboat. The captains may have hoped the two <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> would be reminded of how close those guns had come to firing on their warriors just a few days before. When the smoke cleared, out came gift bale number fifteen, marked and prepared for the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras'</name> use months before in <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>. The bale contained a bewildering array of goods, all representing what the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> might obtain by trading directly with <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> merchants. There was a pound of vermilion paint for the warriors, three pewter looking glasses for young girls, and over four hundred needles for <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> women. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> laid out their country store of merchandise, ranging from cloth, beads, combs, razors, and rolls of wire to nine pairs of scissors, knives, tomahawks, and even six Jew's harps. For the chiefs there were military coats, cocked hats, medals, and American flags. Notably absent from the gifts was any alcohol. The <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> made it plain to all European visitors that the drink was unwelcome. As they explained to <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, those whites who gave Indians alcohol were not friends but were simply interested in seeing natives act the fool.<ref target="n0360" n="60"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Knowing that there was "gellousy" among the three <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> villages over whose chief was to be afforded highest honors, the captains might have exercised some caution in handing out uniforms and medals and in naming chiefs to certain ranks. But Euro-American practice had always been to designate one Indian as the principal chief, whether that particular group sanctioned such a position or not. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> were not about to break with tradition, even if it caused more tension within <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> politics and made <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> efforts at sowing discord easier. <name type="person" key="Lighting Crow (Kakawissassa)">Kakawissassa</name> of <name type="place" key="Sawa-haini village">Saw-haini</name> was named "grand chief" with the appropriate medal, while <name type="person" key="Hay (Pocasse)">Pocasse</name> and <name type="person" key="Eagles Feather (Piaheto)">Piahito</name> were offered medals of lesser grades. At the same time, perhaps to soothe bruised pride, other goods were given to each chief in equal measure. To signal the end of the conference, the airgun was brought out and fired. <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> observed that the chiefs "appeared to be astonished at the sight of it and the execution it would do." As was their custom, the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> chiefs told <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> that an answer, or rather three answers, to the American speech would come the next day. This was neither an attempt to deceive the explorers nor a ploy to draw out the negotiations. Rather, it was an acceptance of the fact that all decisions were the result of a consensus reached by elders in a village council. Since there was no <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> tribal council, each village would present a separate reply. The presence of <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name> representatives and the naming of <name type="person" key="Lighting Crow (Kakawissassa)">Kakawissassa</name> as leading chief only complicated the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras'</name> task of responding to the American views.<ref target="n0361" n="61"/>
               </p>
               <p>
With the talks over, <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> and one other expedition member went to visit <name type="place" key="Rhtarahe village">Rhtarahe</name> while <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name> took a party to sample food and hospitality at <name type="place" key="Sawa-haini village">Sawa-haini</name>. That afternoon of sightseeing and friendly talk produced some valuable information about <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> life as well as scenes of comic proportion. <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway's</name> congenial stay in <name type="place" key="Rhtarahe village">Rhtarahe</name> gave the sergeant and his companion a chance to sample the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> diet. Welcomed into <name type="place" key="Hay (Pocasse)">Pocasse's</name> lodge, the Americans sat on woven mats and were served by the chief's wife. They were brought a bowl of beans and corn, the staple of <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> fare. Following that dish, three different but unnamed Indian foods were offered to the Americans. "We ate some of each," wrote <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, "and found very good." If he was fascinated with Indian menus, the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> were equally intrigued by the looks and manners of the explorers. <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> wrote later that those Indians "were very friendly to us and seemed to be desirous to talk with us and scarcely kept their eyes off us."<ref target="n0362" n="62"/> Usually a keen observer of the common things in native life, <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> strangely neglected to record anything about the interior furnishings of the earth lodge. In fact, no journalist in the expedition took note of lodge interiors.</p>
               <p>
While <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> was tasting <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> cooking, <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass's</name> party made its way to <name type="place" key="Ashley Island">Ashley Island</name>. If <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> failed to examine lodge furnishings, <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name> did not neglect details of exterior construction. His careful description, quoted earlier, is the best surviving account of <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> housing. He offered an earth lodge portrait that squares with archaeological studies done at the two upper villages.<ref target="n0363" n="63"/> But it was <name type="person" key="York">York</name> who proved the center of attraction that afternoon. The <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> were both attracted to and terrified by his blackness. Having never seen a black man, they were quite unsure if <name type="person" key="York">York</name> was a man, a beast, or a strange and powerful spirit being. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> later explained that <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> who had seen whites but not blacks thought <name type="person" key="York">York</name> "something strange &amp; from his very large size more vicious than whites." On the other hand, those <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> who had seen neither whites nor blacks were convinced that all members of the expedition, regardless of color, were possessed with extraordinary powers. <name type="person" key="York">York</name> thoroughly enjoyed his newfound celebrity status and had already "made himself more turribal" than the captains wished.<ref target="n0364" n="64"/> That afternoon <name type="person" key="York">York</name> and hordes of <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> children had chased each other, the black man bellowing at them that he was a wild bear caught and tamed by <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain Clark</name>. What may have worried the captains in this playful sport was <name type="person" key="York">York's</name> boast that he ate human flesh. The <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> practiced ritual cannibalism of their fallen enemies, but that was a far cry from consuming village youth.<ref target="n0365" n="65"/> With <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> chiefs embroiled in factional disputes and <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name> agents ready to use those tensions against the expedition, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> did not need rumors drifting through the earth lodges that the Americans kept a great he-bear ready to eat Indian children.</p>
               <p>
Some of the captains' fears about <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> reactions evaporated the next morning. Toward noon, <name type="person" key="Lighting Crow (Kakawissassa)">Kakawissassa</name> arrived at the expedition's camp. In accordance with the notion of reciprocity in gift giving, the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> leader brought baskets of corn, beans, and dried squash. While those provisions were surely appreciated, <name type="person" key="Lighting Crow (Kakawissassa)">Kakawissassa's</name> reply to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> speech was even more welcome.</p>
               <p>
The chief's speech contained three important elements. First, there was the immediate question of <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> influence on the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras'</name> behavior toward the expedition. The two <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name> emissaries had certainly argued for some direct action against the explorers. Although the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> were not known as great warriors, in the years after <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> they would be very effective in blocking American access up the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>. But <name type="person" key="Lighting Crow (Kakawissassa)">Kakawissassa</name> made it plain at the beginning that the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras'</name> weapons would not be turned against the explorers. "Can you think," declared the chief, "any one dare put their hands on your rope of your boat. No! not one dare." Proclaiming the road open, <name type="person" key="Lighting Crow (Kakawissassa)">Kakawissassa</name> turned to his second point. In reply to the call for intertribal peace, the chief asked the captains to "speak good words" to the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Mandan.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>
                  </ref> on behalf of the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name>. Seeing two of their diplomatic goals seemingly accepted without opposition or argument, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> must have been pleased when the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> chief expressed an interest in becoming part of the <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> trade system. Although <name type="person" key="Lighting Crow (Kakawissassa)">Kakawissassa</name> lamented the fact that beaver pelts were not available for <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> women to process, he promised a good supply of buffalo robes. More important, he promised to aid American traders in entering <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Cheyenne.html"
                       rend="box">Cheyenne</ref> and <name type="native_nation" key="Arapaho Indians">Arapaho</name> markets.<ref target="n0366" n="66"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Taken at face value, what <name type="person" key="Lighting Crow (Kakawissassa)">Kakawissassa</name> told <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> promised a real victory for American policy and the expedition's negotiating skill. After the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name> troubles, the captains needed such a victory. But <name type="person" key="Lighting Crow (Kakawissassa)">Kakawissassa's</name> speech was actually much more and much less than it appeared to be. That the captains accepted it literally only suggests how innocent they were of Indian realities. On the issue of <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref>-inspired attempts to forcibly detain the expedition, <name type="person" key="Lighting Crow (Kakawissassa)">Kakawissassa</name> was forth-right in saying that <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name> advice had been rejected. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> took this to signal a weakening of the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name>-<ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> alliance. But postexpedition events did not bear out the captains' optimistic evaluation. The <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> were not about to abandon their <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> trade connection for an uncertain link with <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>. American merchants, interested in beaver, could not take the place of <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> middlemen as both suppliers of manufactured goods and customers for <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> corn and horses. <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> life was based on the production of agricultural surpluses that would have little place in an American fur trade. That the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> did not envision severing the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> alliance was to be made painfully clear in 1807, when both <name type="person" key="Lisa, Manuel">Manuel Lisa</name> and <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Nathaniel Pryor</name> encountered hostility from <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name>-<ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> forces.</p>
               <p>
The <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> peace overture, an integral part of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Indian diplomacy, also was not quite what the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> speaker made it out to be. Despite their best efforts during the talks with the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> and later during the winter at <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name>, the captains found the old <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name>-<name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> tensions not easily overcome. The peace policy, actually part of a larger anti-<ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> thrust, was doomed to failure by both <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name> military power and persistent villager rivalries. In 1810, an <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name>-<name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> alliance would field several war parties against the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref>, but those joint ventures would be short-lived. More important, the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name> bands engaged in massive economic retaliation against <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> towns, ensuring the demise of any villager alliance.<ref target="n0367" n="67"/> It may be that the willingness of the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> to allow <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> to pass unimpeded was an abberation. In the years after the expedition, as <name type="person" key="Lisa, Manuel">Manuel Lisa</name> brought the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> into the American trading orbit, the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> assumed the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Tetons'</name> old hostile role. Fearing that <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> power was increasing by the <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> connection while their fortunes declined, the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> successfully blockaded the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>. Certainly American agents and merchants like the Chouteaus and <name type="person" key="Ashley, William">William H. Ashley</name> found the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> to be implacable foes. Only gradually did American diplomats learn that flowery speeches and a few gifts could not easily transform Indian loyalties.</p>
               <p>
But the nuances of <name type="person" key="Lighting Crow (Kakawissassa)">Kakawissassa's</name> speech eluded <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, and early in the afternoon, believing they had achieved their goals, the captains ordered the expedition a short distance upriver to a camp closer to the twin villages of <name type="place" key="Rhtarahe village">Rhtarahe</name> and <name type="place" key="Waho-erha village">Waho-erha</name>. With <name type="person" key="Lighting Crow (Kakawissassa)">Kakawissassa</name> and one of his nephews on board the keelboat, the explorers made their way toward the upper villages. <name type="person" key="Hay (Pocasse)">Pocasse</name> joined the boat party and late in the afternoon the whole group landed at a sandbar just below <name type="place" key="Rhtarahe village">Rhtarahe</name>. They were greeted by knots of curious villagers anxious to catch a glimpse of the strangers. The whole scene was made more colorful by several American flags snapping in the river breeze. The captains paused for a moment to take a sextant reading, something the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> were certain was just one more piece of the explorers' spiritual magic, and then walked up to <name type="place" key="Rhtarahe village">Rhtarahe</name> with <name type="person" key="Hay (Pocasse)">Pocasse</name>. The chief made <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> a gift of corn and beans while others in the party ate <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> porridge and bread. After staying some time at <name type="place" key="Rhtarahe village">Rhtarahe</name> "talking on various subjects," the Americans paid a brief visit to <name type="place" key="Waho-erha village">Waho-erha</name> and its chief, <name type="person" key="Eagles Feather (Piaheto)">Piahito</name>. There, too, the explorers enjoyed Indian food and hospitality. Promises were exchanged about talks the next day, and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> judged the situation that evening as "all tranquillity."<ref target="n0368" n="68"/>
               </p>
               <p>
October 12 was the last full day the expedition spent among the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name>; nothing happened to shake the captains' confidence that they had convinced village chiefs to accept American policies. Yet, had the explorers listened more carefully to speeches made by <name type="place" key="Hay (Pocasse)">Pocasse</name> and <name type="person" key="Eagles Feather (Piaheto)">Piahito</name>, they might have been less certain of their victory. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, and <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name>, in the company of interpreters, spent the morning listening to the chiefs' speeches while <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway's</name> boat parties did some small-scale trading.<ref target="n0369" n="69"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Those final talks began with the captains reminding the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> of "the magnitude and power of our country." <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> confidently recorded that those words "pleased and astonished them verry much."<ref target="n0370" n="70"/> The speech delivered by <name type="person" key="Hay (Pocasse)">Pocasse</name> contained much that the explorers wanted to hear. <name type="person" key="Hay (Pocasse)">Pocasse</name> reaffirmed the obvious: the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> planned no hostile action against the expedition. He declared his interest in a <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> peace and also expressed some desire to visit with <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>. At the end of the talk, almost as an afterthought, <name type="person" key="Hay (Pocasse)">Pocasse</name> suggested yet another doubt about severing the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> connection. With the exposed location of the villages and the temporary nature of American forces, what guarantees of safety did the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> have against retaliation by the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Tetons</name>? <name type="person" key="Hay (Pocasse)">Pocasse</name> put it simply: "After you set out, many nations in the open plains may come to make war against us, we wish you to stop their guns and prevent it if possible."<ref target="n0371" n="71"/>
               </p>
               <p>
The doubts and fears expressed by <name type="person" key="Hay (Pocasse)">Pocasse</name> were amplified when <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> met with <name type="person" key="Eagles Feather (Piaheto)">Piahito</name>. This <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> chief gave the captains a quick lesson in Upper <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> power politics. The people of <name type="place" key="Waho-erha village">Waho-erha</name> were distinct in language and past history from the other villages. <name type="place" key="Waho-erha village">Waho-erha</name> had not taken part in the recent and still smoldering <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>-<name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> war. <name type="person" key="Eagles Feather (Piaheto)">Piahito</name> was very skeptical that wounds still fresh couuld be quickly healed by some of the expedition's diplomatic salve. Had they more fully understood what <name type="person" key="Eagles Feather (Piaheto)">Piahito</name> had to say, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> might have sensed how formidable a task it would be to rearrange traditional alliances and cure old hurts.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Eagles Feather (Piaheto)">Piahito</name> opened his remarks by bluntly saying he would believe a <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>-<name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> peace only when he saw it with his own eyes. As much as he doubted <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> intentions, he also questioned <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> motives, declaring that the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name> "has not a good heart." If <name type="person" key="Eagles Feather (Piaheto)">Piahito</name> offered the captains some healthy skepticism about intertribal relations, he also presented an equally realistic appraisal of intra-<name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> affairs. <name type="person" key="Eagles Feather (Piaheto)">Piahito</name> said he always followed the lead of <name type="person" key="Lighting Crow (Kakawissassa)">Kakawissassa</name> and <name type="person" key="Hay (Pocasse)">Pocasse</name> and that they would watch over <name type="place" key="Waho-erha village">Waho-erha</name> while he went up to the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Mandan.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>
                  </ref>. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> wanted their message to be accepted by the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> leadership, and <name type="person" key="Eagles Feather (Piaheto)">Piahito</name> reassured the explorers that at least <name type="person" key="Lighting Crow (Kakawissassa)">Kakawissassa</name> and <name type="person" key="Hay (Pocasse)">Pocasse</name> "believe your words." But the <name type="place" key="Waho-erha village">Waho-erha</name> chief also seemed to issue a veiled warning about a unity of <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> views more apparent than real. "Maybe we will not tell the truth" was hardly the strong statement of approval the captains wanted from the chief. <name type="person" key="Eagles Feather (Piaheto)">Piahito</name> again stressed his concern about a trip to the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Mandan.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>
                  </ref>. What would an alliance with the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Mandan.html"
                       rend="box">Mandan Indians<name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians"/>
                  </ref> mean, how might the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> react, and what possible benefits wouuld the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> gain from such a move? As the formal talks ended and one of the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> chiefs agreed to go with the captains to the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Mandan.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>
                  </ref>, all those doubts and questions were unresolved.<ref target="n0372" n="72"/>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>
If official relations with the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> were troubled by some unsettling issues, unofficial and personal affairs with <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> women went on quite satisfactorily. For the first time since leaving <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>, the young men of the expedition had ample time and opportunity for sexual contacts with Indian women. Those liaisons must be understood from both sides of the cultural divide. To ignore them here and later would be to deny the humanity of the expedition and to turn a blind eye on much of the historical record.</p>
               <p>
Sexual experiences, like all intimate encounters, may mean very different things to persons of dissimilar cultures. The <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras'</name> perception of sexual intercourse and the role of women in the act differed markedly from that of the expedition's males. First, it must be said that the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name>, like their <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> neighbors, placed a very high value on women. They were the principal agriculturists, and that economic position meant ritual prominence as well. Women were neither the drudges nor the pawns of <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> men so often portrayed in the records of white visitors.<ref target="n0373" n="73"/> Further, <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> matrilineal society did not place as much importance on exclusive sexual relations with male spouses. As one <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> told <name type="person" key="Truteau, Jean Baptiste">Truteau</name>, "When a man dies he cannot carry women with him to the regions of the dead; and . . . they who quarrel, fight, and kill each other about the possession of a woman, are fools or mad-men."<ref target="n0374" n="74"/> That young <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> women were anxious for sexual encounters with non-Indians was noted by virtually every visitor. As John Bradbury put it, "Travelers who have been acquainted with savages, have remarked that they are either very liberal of their women to strangers, or extremely jealous. In this species of liberality no nation can be exceeded by the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name>, who flocked down every evening with their wives, sisters, and daughters, each anxious to meet with a market for them."<ref target="n0375" n="75"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Interest in sex with strangers was based on three distinct cultural sanctions. The <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> villagers were eager to obtain European goods, and having sexual relations with traders meant receiving those objects in payment for favors. Ironware, paint, blue beads, and cloth were all part of the exchange. <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> women demanded and got high prices for their services. As Bradbury testified, "I observed several instances wherein the squaw was consulted by her husband as to the <hi rend="italic">quantum sufficit</hi> of price, a mark of consideration which, from some knowledge of Indians, and the estimation in which their women are held, I had not expected."<ref target="n0376" n="76"/> But having sexual relations with a trader provided more than a supply of scarce luxury goods. Because they were central figures in the staple food trade with other tribes, <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> women hoped to forge commercial links with white merchants. Sex, as <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> were to discover at <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name>, was an important way to seal a business arrangement.</p>
               <p>
Sex with visitors was also an integral part of northern plains hospitality. When Bradbury visited an <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> lodge, he found that the welcome included not only a bed but a "bedfellow."<ref target="n0377" n="77"/> As the captains learned during the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name> confrontation, to reject such offers was to court misunderstanding and suspicion. If intercourse with non-Indian males strengthened trade ties and expressed traditional hospitality, it also signified something far more complex in northern plains life. The <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> and their neighbors, both villagers and nomads alike, perceived sexual contact as a means of transferring spiritual power from one person to another. The <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> buffalo-calling ceremony was only the most spectacular example of this belief. In that ritual, women had intercourse with elderly men, taking the seminal skill of old hunters and passing it on to their husbands. Sex became a kind of conduit for power. In the same way, <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> women sought sex with Europeans as a way to pass the strength and skill of the outsiders on to their mates. As John Ewers has written, the "concept of the transmission of power through sexual intercourse seemed to have played a part in the eagerness of <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> women to cohabit with white men in the early days of the fur trade."<ref target="n0378" n="78"/>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> understood the sense of awe when he wrote, "The Indians believed that these traders were the most powerful persons in the nation."<ref target="n0379" n="79"/> Sex was a means to appropriate that power and place it at their disposal.</p>
               <p>
There is little doubt that the men of the expedition found <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> women attractive. They surely did not agree with <name type="person" key="Tabeau, Pierre-Antoine">Tabeau's</name> charge that <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> females were "the most ugly and have the advantages of surpassing all the others in slovenliness." One who disagreed was <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name>. Writing that the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> were "the most cleanly Indians I have ever seen on this voyage," the sergeant added that village women were "handsome" and "the best looking Indians I have ever seen." <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> agreed, noting that "some of their women are very handsome and clean." Even <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, who characterized the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> as "pore and Durtey," recalled to <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Nicholas Biddle</name> that the "<name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Ricara</name> women [were] better looking than the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref>."<ref target="n0380" n="80"/>
               </p>
               <p>
In the notebook journals of the expedition, there are only the most oblique references to sexual contact with <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> women. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> claimed that <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> overtures were rejected while the expedition was at the villages but implied that once the party departed on October 12 it was quite a different story. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> recorded that on the evening of the 12th two young women were sent by an <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> man "and persisted in their civilities." In his plainest statement about intimate relations with the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> written while the expedition was in progress, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> noted that the women were "very fond of carressing our men." <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> was less reticent when he answered questions for <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Nicholas Biddle</name> in 1810. He frankly admitted that the men "by means of interpreters found no difficulty in getting women." He believed that <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> women were "lecherous" and engaged in sexual adventures "without the husband's knowledge." However, in the same note to <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> reported that "the husbands etc. [gave] wives and sisters to strangers."<ref target="n0381" n="81"/> Other travelers observed that <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> women usually initiatied sexual encounters, and there seems to be little doubt that the men in the expedition accepted the offers.</p>
               <p>
The only fully documented case of this involved <name type="person" key="York">York</name>. In the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras'</name> eyes, <name type="person" key="York">York</name> was the central attraction of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> expedition. Airguns, gifts, and strange doings with a sextant all paled in significance before <name type="person" key="York">York</name>. The black man fascinated Indian adults and terrified their children. <name type="person" key="York">York's</name> blackness was viewed by the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> as a sign of special spiritual power, and they appropriately named him "the big Medison." To have sexual contact with <name type="person" key="York">York</name> was to get in touch with what seemed awesome spirit forces. On one occasion an <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> man invited <name type="person" key="York">York</name> to his lodge, offered him his wife, and guarded the entrance during the act. When a member of the expedition came looking for <name type="person" key="York">York</name>, "the master of the house would not let him in before the affair was finished."<ref target="n0382" n="82"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Perhaps the most telling comment on the sexual desires of visitors among the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> came in a conversation that <name type="person" key="Brackenridge, H. M.">Henry M. Brackenridge</name> reported having with a village chief: " 'I was wondering,' said he, 'whether you white people have any women amongst you.' I assured him in the affirmative. 'Then,' said he, 'why is it that your people are so fond of our women, one might suppose they had never seen any before?' "<ref target="n0383" n="83"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Early in the afternoon of October 12, with the talks completed and one of the village chiefs on board, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> left the <name type="place"
                        key="Grand (We-tar-hoo and similar spellings) River (S. Dak.)">Grand River</name> settlements. It was a festive departure, with "the fiddle playing and the horns sounding." The days that followed were filled with small incidents that added to the sum of Indian-expedition relations. One of those revealing events took place on October 14 when <name type="person" key="Newman, John">Private John Newman</name> was sentenced to corporal punishment for "mutinous expression." <name type="person" key="Newman, John">Newman's</name> whipping "allarmed the Indian chief very much." Virtually all native American cultures rejected public physical punishment of either children or adults, believing that confomrity to social norms might be better achieved by more subtle group pressure. As the expedition moved toward its <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> wintering quarters, there was time to record additional bits of ethnographic data. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> noted an <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> stone monument surrounded by votive offerings. At another time <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> and the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> chief walked along the shore as the Indian recounted "a number of their traditions about turtles, snakes, etc. and the power of a particular rock or cove on the next river which informs of every thing." Sadly for the ethnographic record, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> believed that "none of those I think worth mentioning."<ref target="n0384" n="84"/>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>
As <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> headed toward the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> villages, they left behind with the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> a strange set of impressions. Although the villagers had been acquainted with whites for some time, they had never seen such a large group of visitors. The intentions and behavior of the captains, their technology, and the presence of <name type="person" key="York">York</name> all produced a vivid folklore. <name type="person" key="Tabeau, Pierre-Antoine">Tabeau</name>, who dutifully recorded some of the tales, found himself in "a bad scrape by treating them as ridiculous." <name type="person" key="Raven Man (Kakawita)">Kakawita</name>, <name type="person" key="Tabeau, Pierre-Antoine">Tabeau's</name> leading <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> informant, reported what was widely believed among the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> about the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> expedition. In their opinion, the explorers were on a special vision quest and had met "obstacles perhaps invincible" on their journey. One of those obstacles was reputed to be an awesome beast without a mouth who ate by "breathing the smoke of the meat through the nose." Even more terrible, related the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> storytellers, was "a troop of Amazons who kill all their male children, pulverize their genitals and conceive again by the injection of the powder obtained." Just how the expedition overcame those monsters is not part of the surviving record. What finally impressed the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> were the objects carried by the expedition. The sextant, the magnet, and phosphorous were talked about as evidence of the captains' spirit powers. And, of course, there was <name type="person" key="York">York</name>. As <name type="person" key="Tabeau, Pierre-Antoine">Tabeau</name> wrote, "The most marvelous was, though, a large fine man, black as a bear who spoke and acted as one."<ref target="n0385" n="85"/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> party carried away from their time with the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> many personal memories of the sort not readily committed to the pages of diaries or official reports. There can be no doubt that after the tense days with the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Tetons</name>, the relaxed hospitality of the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> was a welcome change. It remained for <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> to record his impressions of the <name type="place"
                        key="Grand (We-tar-hoo and similar spellings) River (S. Dak.)">Grand River</name> villagers. Of the people, he wrote, "They appear to be peaceful, their men tall and perpotiend, women Small and industerous." Recalling their hospitality, he described the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> as "Durtey, Kind, pore and extravigent." <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> expressive word <hi rend="italic">extravigent</hi> was his way of drawing attention to the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras'</name> generosity with food and favors. Pleased to give gifts, the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> took "what was offered with great pleasure."<ref target="n0386" n="86"/>
               </p>
               <p>
There was much about <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> culture that the captains either did not understand or did not see. Politics, sacred bundles, band organization, and the yearly round of ritual and ceremony all eluded the explorers. What the expedition's journalists did record was the exterior of <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> life—an exterior of substantial earth lodges, well-tended fields, and friendly people. American frontiersmen, who valued a secure house and good crops, found much to admire during their time with the Star-rah-he.

</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="section">
            <head rend="center">Abbreviations</head>
            <p>
B A E       Bureau of American Ethnology</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">Field Notes.</hi>        Osgood, Ernest, S., ed. <hi rend="italic">The Field Notes of <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain William Clark</name>, 1803–1805.</hi> New Haven: Yale University Press, 1964.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal.</hi>        <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass, Patrick</name>. <hi rend="italic">A Journal of the Voyages and Travels of a Corps of Discovery.</hi> Edited by <name type="person" key="McKeehan, David">David McKeehan</name>. 1807. Reprint, with preface by Earle R. Forrest. Minneapolis: Ross and Haines, 1958.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal.</hi>        Quaife, Milo M., ed. <hi rend="italic">The Journals of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Meriwether Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Sergeant John Ordway</name>.</hi> Madison: Historical Society of Wisconsin, 1916.</p>
            <p>
Thw.       Thwaites, Reuben G., ed. <hi rend="italic">The Original Journals of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition.</hi> 8 vols. New York: Dodd, Mead &amp; Co., 1904–1905.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal.</hi>        "The Journal of <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Private Joseph Whitehouse</name>." In Thw. 7:29–190.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="notes" type="notes">
            <head rend="center">Notes</head>
            <note xml:id="n0301" n="1">
               <name type="person" key="Truteau, Jean Baptiste">Truteau</name>, "Description," 2:378–79; Thw. 1:172; <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> p. 142.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0302" n="2">Thw. 1:174.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0303" n="3">
               <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> p. 144; Thw. 1:175. The <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> villages seen on September 29 and October 1, 1804, were evidently part of what archaeologists call the <name type="person" key="Black Widow site">Black Widow Site</name> (39ST25 and 39ST50) in present-day <name type="place" key="Stanley County, S. Dak.">Stanley County</name>, <name type="place" key="South Dakota">South Dakota</name>. See Donald J. Lehmer and David T. Jones, <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> Archaeology: The <name type="place" key="Bad (Teton) River (S. Dak.)">Bad River</name> Phase,</hi> Smithsonian Institution River Basin Surveys Publications in Salvage Archaeology, no. 7 (Washington, D.C., 1968), p. 83.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0304" n="4">
               <hi rend="italic">Field Notes,</hi> p. 153; Thw. 1:175.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0305" n="5">
               <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> pp. 57–58; Thw. 1:177–78; <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> p. 66.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0306" n="6">Abel, ed., <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="person" key="Tabeau, Pierre-Antoine">Tabeau's</name> Narrative,</hi> pp. 125, 127–28: Lehmer and Jones, <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> Archaeology,</hi> p. 93; Thw. 1:179.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0307" n="7">
               <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> p. 59; Lehmer and Jones, <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> Archaeology,</hi> p. 93; <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> p. 147; Thw. 1:181.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0308" n="8">Lehmer and Jones, <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> Archaeology,</hi> p. 94; <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> p. 148; Thw. 1:182.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0309" n="9">Both <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> (Thw. 6:88) and John Bradbury, <hi rend="italic">Travels in the Interior of America</hi> (Liverpool: Smith and Galway, 1817), p. 111, note Star-rah-he as the "primitive" name of the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name>. Douglas R. Parks, "Bands and Villages of the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Pawnee Indians">Pawnee</name>," <hi rend="italic">Nebraska History</hi> 60 (1979): 224, finds that AxtaRAhi, the <name type="native_nation" key="Pawnee Indians">Pawnee</name> word for the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name>, was probably the name of the largest band. See also Abel, ed., <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="person" key="Tabeau, Pierre-Antoine">Tabeau's</name> Narrative,</hi> pp. 124–25.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0310" n="10">Ibid., pp. 125–26; Thw. 6:89.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0311" n="11">Roger T. Grange, Jr., "An Archaeological View of Pawnee Origins," <hi rend="italic">Nebraska History</hi> 60 (1979):134–60, especially p. 144; Donald J. Lehmer, <hi rend="italic">Introduction to Middle Missouri Archaeology,</hi> United States Department of the Interior, National Park Service, Anthropological Papers, no. 1 (Washington, D.C., 1971), pp. 124–28.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0312" n="12">Lehmer, <hi rend="italic">Middle Missouri Archaeology,</hi> chaps. 4–5; Lehmer and Jones, <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> Archaeology,</hi> pp. 82–83; Roy W. Meyer, <hi rend="italic">The Village Indians of the Upper <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>: The <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>, <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name>, and <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name>
               </hi> (Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1977), pp. 7–8.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0313" n="13">Lehmer, <hi rend="italic">Middle Missouri Archaeology,</hi> p. 172.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0314" n="14">
               <name type="person" key="Truteau, Jean Baptiste">Truteau</name>, "Journal," 1:295–96.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0315" n="15">
               <name type="person" key="Brackenridge, H. M.">Henry M. Brackenridge</name>, <hi rend="italic">View of <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name>; Together with a Journal of a Voyage up the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri River</name>, in 1811</hi> (Pittsburgh: Cramer, Spear, and Eichbaum, 1814), p. 248; Bradbury, <hi rend="italic">Travels,</hi> p. 110; Lehmer, <hi rend="italic">Middle Missouri Archaeology,</hi> p. 141.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0316" n="16">Richard A. Krause, <hi rend="italic">The <name type="place" key="Leavenworth site">Leavenworth Site</name>: Archaeology of an Historic <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> Community,</hi> University of Kansas Publications in Anthropology, no. 3 (Lawrence, 1972), pp. 23–40; Lehmer, <hi rend="italic">Middle Missouri Archaeology,</hi> pp. 106, 136–39.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0317" n="17">Among the best descriptions of <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> earth lodges are those in Abel, ed., <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="person" key="Tabeau, Pierre-Antoine">Tabeau's</name> Narrative,</hi> pp. 146–47, and <name type="person" key="Brackenridge, H. M.">Brackenridge</name>, <hi rend="italic">Views of <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name>,</hi> p. 248.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0318" n="18">
               <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> pp. 60–61.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0319" n="19">Waldo, R. Wedel, <hi rend="italic">Archaeological Materials from the Vicinity of <name type="place" key="Mobridge, S. Dak.">Mobridge</name>, <name type="place" key="South Dakota">South Dakota</name>,</hi> Smithsonian Institution, BAE Bulletin no. 157, <hi rend="italic">Anthropological Papers,</hi> no. 45 (Washington, D.C., 1955), p. 75.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0320" n="20">Edwin T. Denig, <hi rend="italic">Five Indian Tribes of the Upper <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>: <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>, <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arickaras</name>, <name type="native_nation" key="Assiniboine Indians">Assiniboines</name>, <name type="native_nation" key="Cree Indians">Crees</name>, <name type="native_nation" key="Crow Indians">Crows</name>,</hi> ed. John C. Ewers (Norman: University of Oklahoma Press, 1961), pp. 44–45.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0321" n="21">Edwin M. Betts, ed., <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Thomas Jefferson's</name> Garden Book, 1766–1824</hi> (<name type="place" key="Philadelphia, Pa.">Philadelphia</name>: American Philosophical Society, 1944), pp. 334, 339.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0322" n="22">Thw. 1:181.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0323" n="23">Gilbert L. Wilson, <hi rend="italic">Agriculture of the <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> Indians: An Indian Interpretation,</hi> University of Minnesota Studies in the Social Sciences, no. 9 (Minneapolis, 1917), pp. 68–81.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0324" n="24">
               <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> p. 61. A thorough discussion of <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> plants is in Cutright, <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>: Pioneering Naturalists,</hi> pp. 97–99.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0325" n="25">
               <name type="person" key="Brackenridge, H. M.">Brackenridge</name>, <hi rend="italic">Views of <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name>,</hi> p. 248; Denig, <hi rend="italic">Five Tribes,</hi> pp. 44–45.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0326" n="26">Abel, ed., <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="person" key="Tabeau, Pierre-Antoine">Tabeau's</name> Narrative,</hi> pp. 148–49. Thw. 1:188.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0327" n="27">Abel, ed., <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="person" key="Tabeau, Pierre-Antoine">Tabeau's</name> Narrative,</hi> p. 149; Denig, <hi rend="italic">Five Tribes,</hi> p. 46.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0328" n="28">Abel, ed., <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="person" key="Tabeau, Pierre-Antoine">Tabeau's</name> Narrative,</hi> pp. 74, 132, 149; <name type="person" key="Brackenridge, H. M.">Brackenridge</name>, <hi rend="italic">Views of <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name>,</hi> p. 255; Denig, <hi rend="italic">Five Tribes,</hi> pp. 48, 61.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0329" n="29">Thw. 6:89.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0330" n="30">Ibid. 1:190.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0331" n="31">Abel, ed., <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="person" key="Tabeau, Pierre-Antoine">Tabeau's</name> Narrative,</hi> pp. 130–31.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0332" n="32">Ibid.; Thw. 1:189.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0333" n="33">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> to <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, April 7, 1805, Jackson, ed., <hi rend="italic">Letters,</hi> 1:235–36.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0334" n="34">
               <name type="person" key="Truteau, Jean Baptiste">Truteau</name>, "Journal," 1:310.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0335" n="35">Thw. 5:356.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0336" n="36">Abel, ed., <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="person" key="Tabeau, Pierre-Antoine">Tabeau's</name> Narrative,</hi> pp. 151–52, 158; <name type="person" key="Brackenridge, H. M.">Brackenridge</name>, <hi rend="italic">Views of <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name>,</hi> p. 251; Joseph Jablow, <hi rend="italic">The <name type="native_nation" key="Cheyenne Indians">Cheyenne</name> in Plains Indian Trade Relations, 1795–1840</hi> (Seattle: University of Washington Press, 1950), pp. 51–58; Thw. 5:356, 6:89.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0337" n="37">Abel, ed., <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="person" key="Tabeau, Pierre-Antoine">Tabeau's</name> Narrative,</hi> p. 162; Denig, <hi rend="italic">Five Tribes,</hi> p. 47.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0338" n="38">Abel, ed., <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="person" key="Tabeau, Pierre-Antoine">Tabeau's</name> Narrative,</hi> pp. 190–92, 216–17; <name type="person" key="Brackenridge, H. M.">Brackenridge</name>, <hi rend="italic">Views of <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name>,</hi> pp. 256-57; Bradbury, <hi rend="italic">Travels,</hi> p. 165.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0339" n="39">Bradbury, <hi rend="italic">Travels,</hi> pp. 165–66; Lehmer, <hi rend="italic">Middle Missouri Archaeology,</hi> pp. 139–40, figures 86, 87.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0340" n="40">Preston Holder, <hi rend="italic">The Hoe and the Horse on the Plains: A Study of Cultural Development among North American Indians</hi> (Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1970), p. 30; George E. Hyde, "The Mystery of the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name>," <hi rend="italic">North Dakota History</hi> 18 (1951): 204. Donald J. Lehmer quoted in W. Raymond Wood, "Northern Plains Village Cultures: Internal Stability and External Relationships," <hi rend="italic">Journal of Anthropological Research</hi> 30 (1974): 9, offers a much lower pre-epidemic population estimate of 9,000 <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> in a total village population of 25,000.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0341" n="41">Lehmer and Jones, <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> Archaeology,</hi> pp. 90–92; <name type="person" key="Truteau, Jean Baptiste">Truteau</name>, "Journal," 1:299.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0342" n="42">Abel, ed., <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="person" key="Tabeau, Pierre-Antoine">Tabeau's</name> Narrative,</hi> pp. 123–24; Donald J. Lehmer, "Epidemics among the Indians of the Upper <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>," in <hi rend="italic">Selected Writings of Donald J. Lehmer,</hi> ed. W. Raymond Wood (Lincoln, Nebr.: J &amp; L Reprint Co., 1977), pp. 105–11; Thw. 6:89.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0343" n="43">
               <name type="person" key="Truteau, Jean Baptiste">Truteau</name>, "Journal," 1:299–303.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0344" n="44">Abel, ed., <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="person" key="Tabeau, Pierre-Antoine">Tabeau's</name> Narrative,</hi> pp. 123–24, 129–37; Holder, <hi rend="italic">The Hoe and the Horse,</hi> pp. 131–33.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0345" n="45">"<name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name> Notes," 2:537; Lehmer and Jones, <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> Archaeology,</hi> p. 93; Prince Maximilian reporting a conversation with <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Toussaint Charbonneau</name>, in Reuben G. Thwaites, ed., <hi rend="italic">Early Western Travels,</hi> 32 vols. (Cleveland: Arthur H. Clark Co., 1904–1906), 23:229–30.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0346" n="46">"<name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name> Notes," 2:537.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0347" n="47">Abel, ed., <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="person" key="Tabeau, Pierre-Antoine">Tabeau's</name> Narrative,</hi> p. 125; Hyde, "Mystery of the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name>," pp. 52–53; Parks, "<name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Pawnee Indians">Pawnee</name> Bands," p. 218; Moulton, ed., <hi rend="italic">Atlas,</hi> plate 10; Wood, "Evans Map," p. 47.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0348" n="48">Thw. 1:189.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0349" n="49">Ibid. 6:270.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0350" n="50">Ibid. 1:183–84.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0351" n="51">
               <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> pp. 148–49.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0352" n="52">
               <name type="person" key="Truteau, Jean Baptiste">Truteau</name>, "Journal," 1:296.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0353" n="53">Horsman, <hi rend="italic">Expansion and American Indian Policy,</hi> pp. 104–14; Abel, ed., <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="person" key="Tabeau, Pierre-Antoine">Tabeau's</name> Narrative,</hi> pp. 162–63; Thw. 1:184.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0354" n="54">Abel, ed., <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="person" key="Tabeau, Pierre-Antoine">Tabeau's</name> Narrative,</hi> pp. 127–34, 204.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0355" n="55">Bradbury, <hi rend="italic">Travels,</hi> pp. 110, 122.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0356" n="56">
               <hi rend="italic">Field Notes,</hi> p. 158; <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> p. 149; Thw. 1:185.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0357" n="57">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> do not make it clear why they decided to appoint <name type="person" key="Lighting Crow (Kakawissassa)">Kakawissassa</name> as First Chief. Nor is it plain why someone from <name type="place" key="Sawa-haini village">Sawa-haini</name> should take precedence over a chief from any of the other villages. Since <name type="person" key="Tabeau, Pierre-Antoine">Tabeau</name> and <name type="person" key="Gravelines, Joseph">Gravelines</name> had close ties to <name type="person" key="Raven Man (Kakawita)">Kakawita</name> and <name type="person" key="Lighting Crow (Kakawissassa)">Kakawissassa</name>, it is possible that the Frenchmen influenced the decision.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0358" n="58">"<name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> to the <name type="native_nation" key="Oto Indians">Oto Indians</name>," Jackson, ed., <hi rend="italic">Letters,</hi> 1:205.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0359" n="59">
               <hi rend="italic">Field Notes,</hi> p. 158. The presence of the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Tetons</name> is mentioned in no other expedition journal.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0360" n="60">Abel, ed., <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="person" key="Tabeau, Pierre-Antoine">Tabeau's</name> Narrative,</hi> p. 171; Thw. 1:199, 6:151.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0361" n="61">
               <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> pp. 150–51; Thw. 1:185–86.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0362" n="62">
               <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> pp. 150–51.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0363" n="63">
               <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> pp. 60–61; Krause, <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="place" key="Leavenworth site">Leavenworth Site</name>,</hi> pp. 23–40.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0364" n="64">Thw. 1:185–86.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0365" n="65">
               <hi rend="italic">Field Notes,</hi> p. 158; Holder, <hi rend="italic">The Hoe and the Horse,</hi> pp. 47–48.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0366" n="66">Thw. 7:303.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0367" n="67">White, "The Winning of the West," p. 332.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0368" n="68">
               <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> p. 62; <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> p. 151; Thw. 1:186–87.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0369" n="69">
               <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> pp. 62-63; <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> pp. 151–52.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0370" n="70">Thw. 1:188.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0371" n="71">Ibid. 7:303–4.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0372" n="72">"<name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name> Notes," 2:537; Thw. 7:304–5.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0373" n="73">Holder, <hi rend="italic">The Hoe and the Horse,</hi> p. 58.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0374" n="74">
               <name type="person" key="Truteau, Jean Baptiste">Truteau</name>, "Journal," 1:258, 300.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0375" n="75">Bradbury, <hi rend="italic">Travels,</hi> pp. 124–25.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0376" n="76">Ibid.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0377" n="77">Ibid., p. 169; Thw. 1:189.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0378" n="78">George Catlin, <hi rend="italic">O-Kee-Pa: A Religious Ceremony and other Customs of the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>,</hi> ed. John C. Ewers (New Haven: Yale University Press, 1967), p. 8; Alice B. Kehoe, "The Function of Ceremonial Sexual Intercourse among the Northern Plains Indians," <hi rend="italic">Plains Anthropologist</hi> 15 (1970):99–103.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0379" n="79">Thw. 7:370.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0380" n="80">
               <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> pp. 62–63; Abel, ed., <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="person" key="Tabeau, Pierre-Antoine">Tabeau's</name> Narrative,</hi> p. 174; Thw. 1:186; "<name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name> Notes," 2:537.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0381" n="81">Ibid. 2:503; Thw. 1:189, 194.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0382" n="82">"<name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name> Notes," 2:503; <hi rend="italic">Field Notes,</hi> p. 158.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0383" n="83">
               <name type="person" key="Brackenridge, H. M.">Brackenridge</name>, <hi rend="italic">Views of <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name>,</hi> p. 258.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0384" n="84">
               <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> p. 152; Thw. 1:193, 197.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0385" n="85">Abel, ed., <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="person" key="Tabeau, Pierre-Antoine">Tabeau's</name> Narrative,</hi> pp. 200–1.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0386" n="86">Thw. 1:188.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.ronda.01.02" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.ronda.01.00" type="contents"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.ronda.01.04" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
