<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.sup.lavender.01.14">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Way to the Western Sea</title>
            <title type="sub">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
        <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>across the Continent</title>
            <title type="sub" level="a">Chapter 14</title>
            <author>David Lavender</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2005</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic
        Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Way to the Western Sea</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">Chapter 14</title>
               <author>David Lavender</author>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>2001</date>
               <idno type="ISBN">0-8032-8003-3</idno>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Supplements</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Texts</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-11-09</date>
            <date>2005-04-20</date>
            <name>Becky Potter</name>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Split into chapters Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-04-12</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="fourteen" type="chapter">
            <head rend="center">FOURTEEN. Hunger</head>
            <div type="section">
               <p>"every thing," 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark</name>wrote about the meeting of
          the boat crews with the horse Indians, "appears to astonish those people. the appearance
          of the men, their arms, the canoes, the Clothing my 
          <name type="person" key="York">black servent</name>&amp; the Segassity of 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt Lewis's</name>
                  <name type="person" key="Seaman">Dog</name>." Sagacity? Did 
          <name type="person" key="Seaman">Seaman</name>extend a paw to shake hands? Plunge into
          the river to bring back sticks that had been thrown for him? In any event, as the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name>crowded around,
          staring, 
          <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name>added to the confusion by
          recognizing a young woman who had been captured with her during the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name>attack at 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Three Forks of the">Three Forks</name>. Unlike 
          <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau's</name>wife, that captive
          had escaped and made her way home—a considerable feat, it would appear from today's
          viewpoint, for a child ten or twelve years old. The reunion, 
          <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Nicholas Biddle</name>remarked after hearing 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>tale, "had in it something
          peculiarly touching."
          <ref target="n1401" n="1"/>
               </p>
               <p>As soon as the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name>could lay hold of the
          newly arrived captain, they led him to one of their easily erected brush wickiups. Long
          ago, outsiders had taken to defining the builders of those wickiups with a sinuous
          motion of hand and arm: "people of the woven houses." Or so the theory goes. But the
          motion might also be taken to represent a serpent's progress. 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Snake</name>Indians—and, by
          association, the great 
          <name type="place"
                        key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Fork Columbia) River">
          Snake River</name>that wound through part of their territory. 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark's</name>suggestion that the term
          derived from the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni's</name>skill in taming
          serpents is not widely accepted.
          <ref target="n1402" n="2"/>
               </p>
               <p>Be that as it may, the Indians took him inside and seated him, as a sign of honor, on
          a white buffalo robe. All those in attendance took off their moccasins. The ceremonial
          pipe passed back and forth, and 
          <name type="person" key="Cameahwait">Cameahwait</name>decorated the captain's shaggy
          hair with six pieces of "pearl," or bits of seashell. That indirect evidence of trade
          routes to the 
          <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>was exciting.</p>
               <p>Because 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name>was off hunting—there were
          many people to feed—
          <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name>were summoned to help
          translate. It was an awkward procedure. One of the captains spoke in English to the
          boatman 
          <name type="person" key="Labiche, François">Labiche</name>. He put the remarks into
          French for 
          <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name>, who passed them
          along in 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name>to his wife. She
          translated them into 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name>for 
          <name type="person" key="Cameahwait">Cameahwait</name>. As the talks began, recognition
          came to her again, this time like a blow. The chief was her brother! Inexpressibly
          agitated, she threw her blanket over his head (a sign, perhaps, of their sibling bond)
          and burst into tears. After the two had wept together for a time, the ceremony resumed,
          "but her new situation seemed to overpower her, and she was frequently interrupted by
          tears."
          <ref target="n1403" n="3"/>
               </p>
               <p>This preliminary introduction completed, the whites invited all the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name>in the vicinity to a
          small-scale replica of the formal councils they had held the preceding year with the
          tribes they had encountered along the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>. Like its predecessors the
          meeting took place under an awning made from a sail. It may be assumed that 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name>, back with the other
          hunters after bagging four deer and an antelope, passed on 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>remarks in hand and body
          language, for he'd had ample practice at other gatherings. Because the Indians' main
          home was not on American soil—at least not yet—
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>did not address them as children
          of the great father. He did, however, point out that the Corps was an official arm of
          the United States government and was traveling to the 
          <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>in search of a good route for
          bringing American merchandise into the interior. Since no commerce could be developed
          until after the explorers had returned home, it behooved the Indians to speed the
          explorers along their way by furnishing horses and a guide. The time to start was now,
          by helping the expedition get its baggage across the divide.</p>
               <p>Very interesting, 
          <name type="person" key="Cameahwait">Cameahwait</name>replied, "with his ferce eyes and
          lank jaws grown meager for the want of food. . . . `If we had guns, we could then live
          in the country of buffaloe and eat as our enemies do and not be compelled to hide
          ourselves in these mountains and live on roots and berries as the bears do.'" But before
          he could furnish horses, he would have to return to his village and prevail on the
          people there to help.
          <ref target="n1404" n="4"/>
               </p>
               <p>It was a risky outlook, but for the time being the Americans had to be satisfied with
          it. They wound up the meeting by distributing the usual medals and gifts. 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>fired his airgun—great medicine,
          that!—and the entire group of Indians at the camp (the number is uncertain; it could
          have been as low as sixteen) was feasted on hulled corn supplemented by the antelope the
          hunters had brought in. On their part, the thirty-two expedition members and the dog
          made short shrift of the four deer.</p>
               <p>The talk of trade led to more talk about routes. The Indians the captains questioned
          agreed with 
          <name type="person" key="Cameahwait">Cameahwait</name>. Men could not pierce the fearful
          gorges that led toward the sea. If they tried they would starve, for there was no game
          in those terrible wastes. Though 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>remained unconvinced—what of those
          shells in 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>hair?—the statements were so
          positive they agreed they had better look things over before they jumped.</p>
               <p>They planned carefully. 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, whose sore feet and legs had
          healed, would lead eleven men equipped with boat-building tools down the river until he
          found trees from which dugouts could be hewn. If timber proved unavailable or if the
          river really was unnavigable, he would investigate possibilities by land. 
          <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name>would go with him as far as the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name>village. There they
          would make sure that the Indians, whom 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>regarded as capricious and
          undependable, returned promptly with men who, so 
          <name type="person" key="Cameahwait">Cameahwait</name>promised, would be willing to sell
          horses. In the interim 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>was to supervise the making of
          pack saddles and the rearranging of the baggage into parcels suitable for horse
          transport.
          <ref target="n1405" n="5"/>
               </p>
               <p>The next morning 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether</name>indulged in a bit of
          aggressive salesmanship. 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>needed a few horses immediately for
          carrying his party's boat-building tools and enough supplies for an extended stay of
          construction work, if such developed. 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>hunters needed one or two so
          they could range far to find game enough for those who stayed behind. So after the
          Indians had collected their mounts, he drew from one of the bales of trade goods a cloth
          coat, some gay hankerchiefs, a pair of leggings, and a knife, the whole worth, back in 
          <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>, about twenty American
          dollars. How many horses, he asked the watching, yearning riders, would one or more of
          them give for the collection? After strenuous bargaining, he got three. He turned two
          over to 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, the other to 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name>. Inspired by the success,
          some of the men (whether of 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>group or 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>is not stated) obtained, for
          private use, a fourth in exchange for a worn shirt, a pair of old leggings, and a knife.
          Nor was that all. As 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>eleven men were hiking toward the
          pass, the mounted Indians in file beside them, they met a 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name>riding one mule and
          leading another. The fellow was so shocked at seeing the white captain traveling on foot
          that he promptly gave him one mule and added a Spanish saddle. 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>repaid the generosity with a
          waistcoat. At lunchtime he also broke into his party's supply of corn and pork to feed
          the Indians, for they had no food with them, their hunters having failed to find game
          along the way.
          <ref target="n1406" n="6"/>
               </p>
               <p>Back at the camp beside the forks of the 
          <name type="place" key="Bevaerhead (Jefferson) River">Jefferson</name>/
          <name type="place" key="Beaverhead (Jefferson) River">Beaverhead River</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>somberly estimated the number of
          pack saddles he should have his men make. Twenty, he decided. They produced the
          necessary boards by sawing off the blades of the dugout oars and by breaking up wooden
          packing boxes after transferring their contents into specially prepared rawhide sacks.
          He softened other pieces of leather in water so they could be cut into thongs for taking
          the place of nails in the construction and into straps for the saddle riggings.</p>
               <p>He began his work on August 18, 1805, his thirty-first birthday. It was not a happy
          occasion for him. As far as the journals show, he had not reminded 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name>, or anyone else of the
          event. Probably it is not possible now to understand fully why the anniversary triggered
          
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>all-too-easily-induced
          melancholia. Certain guesses can be offered, however. As an army officer, he could not
          build up unstrained relationships with enlisted men, and so 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>departure this particular day may
          have left him feeling very lonesome, there in the subarctic zones just below the top of
          the remote 
          <name type="place" key="Continental Divide">Continental Divide</name>. He was,
          furthermore, very ambitious and hence susceptible to fears of failure. With winter just
          ahead, if there was no way through the mountains his great enterprise might collapse.
          Yet when he unburdened himself in his journal—a trip journal, not a personal diary—none
          of these considerations surfaced. Instead he sounded like a very moody, very
          introspective, very youthful thirty-one. Which he was.</p>
               <p>He had been indolent, he wrote. He had not improved his mind as much as he might
          have. He had "as yet done but little, very little indeed, to further the hapiness of the
          human race or to advance the information of the succeeding generation." In the future,
          he vowed, he "would live for 
          <hi rend="italic">mankind</hi>as I have heretofore lived for 
          <hi rend="italic">myself</hi>."
          <ref target="n1407" n="7"/>
               </p>
               <p>Considering what he was doing for country and mankind, the self-flagellation was
          hardly deserved. Yet it may have helped stir him into filling, during the next several
          days, page after page of his journal with ethnographic observations about the hitherto
          unknown 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name>, or 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Snake</name>, tribe. It was the sort
          of analysis that 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>wanted and that more than
          one "succeeding generation" of anthropologists would find very useful.</p>
               <p>The words poured out: family relationships in the tribe, the status of women as he
          saw it, the characteristics of the people as a whole, foods, dress, weapons, diseases.
          For the most part his observations were accurate, concise, and objective. At times he
          added personal reactions. By using nothing more than the sharp tip of a deer or elk
          horn, he noted, a warrior could chip an arrowhead out of flint "with a quickness and
          neatness that is really astonishing." A necklace of grizzly bear claws marked its wearer
          as a celebrity, for first he had to slay the animal, and that deed "with the means they
          have . . . must really be a serious undertaking."</p>
               <p>For practical reasons he was interested in sexual customs. Women and children
          outnumbered men in the village beyond the divide at least three to one. Most of the
          women were married—polygamy was acceptable—but, as in other tribes, marital ties did not
          forbid liaisons with outsiders if the husband consented, which, for a trifle, he
          generally did. Aware of the impossibility of imposing restraint on the Corps's young
          men, "whom some months abstanence have made very polite to those tawney damsels," 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>contented himself, for the
          record, with urging discretion.</p>
               <p>He also made inquiry through 
          <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name>as to whether the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name>were subject to
          venereal complaints. Some were infected, he learned, and the victims often died. The
          knowledge apparently did not increase his worry about his soldiers or about what they
          might bring to the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name>. However, it did lead
          him, as a matter of scientific interest, to speculate that if a tribe as isolated as the
          
          <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name>suffered from the
          disorders, sexual diseases were probably endemic to America and not imported from
          Europe, as was generally believed. He was probably right. Syphilis may well have been
          carried from the New World to the old by Columbus's sailors.
          <ref target="n1408" n="8"/>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>Twenty pack saddles, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>soon realized, were not going to
          be enough for transporting the Corps's equipment over the hill. Shrunken though his
          supplies seemed, they would have to be pared still more. Finding a distant place for a
          cache and making sure the four Indians at camp were not watching, he had some of his men
          dig a hole. Into it went the natural history specimens he had collected between 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">Great Falls</name>and the
          divide, as well as every gaudy coat, every carrot of tobacco, and every bar of lead he
          thought the expedition could spare. The next problem was the dugouts. He did not want
          the Indians breaking them up for fuel, for they would be needed if the Corps returned
          this way from the ocean, or from whatever obstacle chanced to turn them hack.
          Accordingly, he filled the boats with rocks and sank them in a pond near the forks.</p>
               <p>Shortly thereafter, on August 22, 
          <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name>, and 
          <name type="person" key="Cameahwait">Cameahwait</name>returned with about fifty warriors
          accompanied by their families and many horses. The sight jarred 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>. So large a group probably
          signified that the salmon run had dwindled away and that as soon as other groups of 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name>and perhaps some 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Flatheads</name>arrived to build up
          their strength, the combined parties would move down the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>on their dangerous trek to the
          buffalo grounds. With them, almost beyond doubt, would go some of the horses he had been
          counting on.</p>
               <p>Hoping that food might keep the Indians amiable while he dickered, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>sent 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name>out with the expedition's
          lone animal to find as much game as possible. All the hunter got was a single fawn.
          Breaking into the expedition's reserves, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>had the cooks boil up huge
          kettlefuls of corn and beans. The Indians enjoyed the unfamiliar fare, but it did not
          incline them to part with horses on the eve of their vital hunt. During a long
          bargaining session, the captain succeeded in obtaining only five of the twenty or more
          animals he needed.
          <ref target="n1409" n="9"/>
               </p>
               <p>The only solution was to go to the village, where horses not required for the hunt
          should be available. To make the trip he would load the heaviest material on the five
          head he had purchased, add 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard's</name>mount and other animals
          he could rent, and hire porters to lug along, on foot, whatever the Corps's crewmen,
          burdened with their personal baggage, could not handle. Unfortunately the porters—women,
          because the men refused even to listen to such a proposal—would not go unless the entire
          group they were with also returned to the village.</p>
               <p>To keep hunger from upsetting his plans, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>had his men prepare a brush drag
          of the sort that had served the expedition well on some of the tributary streams of the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>. With the contraption he and his
          crew, helped by a few Indians, swept 528 big trout out of the sunny pools below the
          forks. The Indians' conduct during the operation won 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>admiration. They were orderly;
          they did not crowd or grab. Short of culinary articles of their own, the women borrowed
          knives and kettles from the whites, and, after the meal, scrupulously returned them.
          <ref target="n1410" n="10"/>
               </p>
               <p>Geniality did not reduce stubbornness, however. When 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>sought the next morning, August
          23, to start the mixed group toward the divide, 
          <name type="person" key="Cameahwait">Cameahwait</name>balked. More Indians, he said,
          would soon be passing through on their way to the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>and he wanted to talk to them.
          Reluctantly, for he could do nothing else, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>complied, and then turned the
          delay to his advantage the next day by purchasing three more horses and a mule from the
          newcomers. Two rented animals and the mount 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name>had been using brought the
          total number of available packhorses to twelve. (
          <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussiant">Charbonneau</name>, using knickknacks 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>had given him, had bought a
          riding horse for 
          <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name>and her baby, and a friendly Indian,
          conscious of the needs of dignity, had loaned 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>a mount, but those animals were
          not for packing.) Determined to wait no longer, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, at noon on the 24th, pressed
          ahead with his cavalcade—mounted Indians milling along beside the string of plodding
          packhorses, porters, and overburdened crew members.
          <ref target="n1411" n="11"/>
               </p>
               <p>All this put 
          <name type="person" key="Cameahwait">Cameahwait</name>in an untenable position.
          Government of the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name>, as with most tribes,
          was by consensus, and he retained his position as principal chief only to the extent
          that the members of the band respected his judgment. But which way should he lean now?
          He did not wish to alienate these whites of whom his sister spoke with great favor. They
          had shared their food with his hungry people. They had promised that if the expedition
          succeeded, traders would soon bring in firearms and other goods that would enable the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name>to hold up their heads
          again. Yet 
          <name type="person" key="Cameahwait">Cameahwait</name>understood his band's
          possessiveness about their horses, the only wealth they had. They had lost many to the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Atsina Indians">Pahkees</name>not long before, and that
          made them doubly jealous of the rest. Finally, many of his starving tribesmen were
          losing patience, saying angrily that it was time they were off on their annual hunt.
          What obligation commanded that they keep on riding back and forth over the pass for the
          sake of strangers?</p>
               <p>Unutterably badgered, 
          <name type="person" key="Cameahwait">Cameahwait</name>capitulated and secretly sent
          messengers ahead to the village, asking the people there to catch their horses and ride
          over the divide, ready for the hunt. Learning of the defection, 
          <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name>told 
          <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name>of it. Not realizing
          the seriousness, her husband did not tell 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>of it until the procession had
          halted for lunch just short of the divide. The captain was appalled. The moment the
          villagers arrived, the people he was with would swing around. He would lose the horses
          he had rented and the services of the women porters. Worse, his hope of acquiring more
          pack animals for following 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>to whatever trail he had decided on
          would evaporate.</p>
               <p>Summoning 
          <name type="person" key="Cameahwait">Cameahwait</name>and the two lesser chiefs who
          accompanied him, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>upbraided them. Did their
          promises mean nothing? Did they expect that white men would come to them with trade
          goods if they did not keep faith and help the expedition reach its goal?</p>
               <p>Squirming, the lesser chiefs shifted full blame onto 
          <name type="person" key="Cameahwait">Cameahwait</name>. For a long moment he stood
          silent. The hunger. His honor. And a chance to get firearms. The latter considerations
          triumphed and he sent a runner to the village, countermanding his order. But as the
          group neared the Indian encampment the following day (August 26) he asked 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>to help him save face by firing
          a set of volleys. The salute would impress his people and make them aware of the power
          of guns—a power that his decision about returning would bring to them, if the white men
          kept their promise.
          <ref target="n1412" n="12"/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>agreed, of course. He had saved
          the expedition by maneuvering it through a more critical situation than is generally
          recognized today. True, he had many horses still to buy, but at least he now had a
          chance. How important that opportunity had become he learned when he met 
          <name type="person" key="Colter, John">John Colter</name>in the village with a message
          from 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>and discovered what lay ahead.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>The reader will remember that 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>and his potential boat builders,
          accompanied by 
          <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name>, and 
          <name type="person" key="Cameahwait">Cameahwait's</name>first group of Indians, had left
          the American camp near the forks of 
          <name type="place" key="Beaverhead (Jefferson) River">the Beaverhead</name>early in the
          morning of August 19. With their heaviest goods carried by a couple of packhorses, they
          were able to travel fast. According to 
          <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Sergeant Gass's</name>estimate, they covered
          thirty-six miles that day, including a crossing of 
          <name type="place" key="Lemhi Pass">Lemhi pass</name>. Another few miles brought them to
          the Indians' main camp, which had been moved a short distance upstream since 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>visit. There the whites paused
          in the band's sole remaining leather tepee for a few hours of ceremony and talk. With 
          <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name>, and an unnamed French boatman
          acting as conduits for the conversation, 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>cleared off a patch of ground and
          pressed 
          <name type="person" key="Cameahwait">Cameahwait</name>to draw a specific map of the
          supposedly impassable river he had talked about only in generalities so far.
          <ref target="n1413" n="13"/>
               </p>
               <p>After scratching a line in the earth with a knife blade—that was the river, torn by
          rocks into froth—the chief heaped up mounds of sand to represent mountains dropping
          steeply into the water, leaving no banks that men or horses could travel. Impassable, he
          insisted again. For the time being 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>accepted the statement. But what of
          the seashells and pieces of Spanish horse equipment he had noticed in the camp? Was it
          possible, he asked, that they came along trails running southwest of the river?</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Cameahwait">Cameahwait</name>sent for an old man who had once
          lived several days' travel in that direction. The fellow talked grimly of vast expanses
          of hostile desert broken only occasionally by canyoned rivers. Scholars now surmise he
          was talking of the bleak 
          <name type="place" key="Snake River Plain">Snake River plains</name>of southern 
          <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>, but 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, unfamiliar with the Southwest and
          confused by fuzzy translations, supposed the fellow was trying to tell him of the
          approaches to the 
          <name type="place" key="California, Gulf of">Gulf of California</name>. For an
          expedition seeking the mouth of the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>, that route would not do.</p>
               <p>Next 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>asked about trails northwest of the
          supposedly impassable river. He'd heard of one, 
          <name type="person" key="Cameahwait">Cameahwait</name>replied. It was said 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Pierced Nose Indians</name>—the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Percé</name>—used it to reach the
          buffalo. But it was a very bad trail, without game, broken and rocky and heavily
          timbered. If snow came early, it would be fatal.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>was elated. If Indians could get
          through with women and children, the expedition could. Yet a string of packhorses could
          be troublesome: rounding the animals up every morning, packing and unpacking them every
          day, risking sore feet and accidents at critical times. Perhaps he had better evaluate
          the river, after all. Like 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, he still did not believe that
          Indians unaccustomed to boats knew how to estimate fast water.</p>
               <p>When he asked about a guide, 
          <name type="person" key="Cameahwait">Cameahwait</name>produced a man the explorers took
          to calling 
          <name type="person" key="Old Toby">Old Toby</name>, a designation belied by the
          endurance and agility he showed during the next several weeks. By three in the
          afternoon, only a few hours after the scouts had reached the village, the party was on
          its way, 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>riding his gift mule and the rest
          walking, their equipment on the two packhorses. (Presumably 
          <name type="person" key="Old Toby">Toby</name>rode his own horse.) While daylight
          lasted, they followed the 
          <name type="place" key="Lemhi (East Fork Lewis's) River">Lemhi</name>north, downstream.
          The next morning they reached a big river gliding hard and strong out of the southwest.
          Surely this new stream was the South Fork of the 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>, which the captains, following
          dotted lines on 
          <name type="person" key="King, Nicholas">Nicholas King's</name>conjectural map of 1803,
          had postulated as far back as 
          <name type="place" key="Camp Dubois (Camp Wood, River Dubois) (Ill.)">Camp
          Wood</name>near 
          <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>. Later, acting on the basis
          of 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name>information, they had
          refined the fork into a long stream running due north along the western base of the 
          <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rockies</name>until it finally swung west to
          join the main 
          <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>near the coast. Because 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name>had been the first
          white man to see the headwater streams of the fork, 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>named it 
          <name type="place"
                        key="Salmon (Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">Lewis's
          River</name>. Today it is called the main fork of the 
          <name type="place"
                        key="Salmon (Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">
          Salmon</name>. The beautifully located, river-girt, mountain-cupped town of 
          <name type="place" key="Salmon, Idaho">Salmon</name>now stands at the stream's junction
          with the 
          <name type="place" key="Lemhi (East Fork Lewis's) River">Lemhi</name>.</p>
               <p>As the explorers pressed down the 
          <name type="place"
                        key="Salmon (Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">
          Salmon</name>, still flowing northward, the difficulties of travel increased. In places
          the knees of great mountains, patched with evergreens high up and scaled with sagebrush
          lower down, pressed so close to the water that the way-farers had to climb far up the
          steep hillsides to skirt the obstructions. Unaware of whites in their country, the few
          Indians they met were terrified at seeing them, but after 
          <name type="person" key="Old Toby">Toby's</name>voice had reassured them, they either
          gave the whites or sold them, at trifles, some of the salmon and cakes of berries they
          had. It was a welcome generosity, for the country was indeed devoid of game.</p>
               <p>On the 22d, after passing a tributary that 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>did not name but that is now called
          the 
          <name type="place" key="North Fork Salmon River (Fish Creek)">North Fork of the
          Salmon</name>, the river bent sharply west. Travel grew worse. Again and again the men
          and the two packhorses had to labor over the steep promontories that ribbed the narrow
          canyon bottom, where white water boomed and thrashed. On the 23d the horses were blocked
          completely. Yet 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>still wanted to believe that canoes
          could be taken through if the ladings were portaged around the bad places and the craft
          were lowered through the heavy water with cords. So he told eight of the men to remain
          at the stopping place while he, 
          <name type="person" key="Old Toby">Toby</name>, and three of the soldiers went ahead on
          foot to learn whether his thin hope was tenable.</p>
               <p>The going was rough—teetering slabs of talus at the base of the cliffs, strong
          currents slamming against the far walls of the tight bends, water "foaming &amp; roreing
          thro the rocks in every direction." To complete the whites' education, 
          <name type="person" key="Old Toby">Toby</name>led them along an Indian path that climbed
          six miles up a side stream (today's 
          <name type="place" key="Squaw Creek (Idaho)">Squaw Creek</name>) to a stupendous view of
          "the hollers [hollows] of the river for 20 miles." From that vantage point, as 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>put matters dryly, 
          <name type="person" key="Old Toby">Toby</name>"pointed out the dificulties."</p>
               <p>Back they went to the place where the others were camped. There 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>tore a page out of his notebook and
          wrote a letter to 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>. He was willing to make a stab
          at the river under certain conditions: let half the party follow the stream while the
          other half hunted on the mountains above, coming down now and then to help and change
          places with the river crews. But the ferocity of the river was such that perhaps the
          Corps ought to risk the starvation trail used by the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Pierced Nose Indians</name>. 
          <name type="person" key="Old Toby">Old Toby</name>had been there as a youth and believed
          he could find it again.</p>
               <p>This note, and a horse, 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>entrusted to 
          <name type="person" key="Colter, John">John Colter</name>for delivery to 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>at the main 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name>village. 
          <name type="person" key="Old Toby">Toby</name>went with 
          <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name>so that 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>could talk to him through
          interpreters, for 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>of course had been relying on sign
          language, which he knew only imperfectly from observing 
          <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name>at work. The others
          followed slowly, depending for food on the Indians and camping finally beside the 
          <name type="place" key="Lemhi (East Fork Lewis's) River">Lemhi</name>, a few miles above
          its junction with the 
          <name type="place"
                        key="Salmon (Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">
          Salmon</name>. No use going farther, for the main party would soon be coming down the
          tributary. Wishing they had a little red meat to eat, the men began making pack saddles
          for the horses they supposed 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>was buying.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>After brief talks with 
          <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Old Toby">Toby</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>agreed they should take the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Percé</name>trail. This meant,
          ideally, a riding horse for each of the thirty-one adults in the party plus another two
          dozen or so for packing, some of which could be used for food in case of an emergency.
          Since 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>and he, traveling separately, had
          brought only fifteen or so across 
          <name type="place" key="Lemhi Pass">Lemhi Pass</name>to the village, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>was going to have to steel
          himself for a lot of drawn-out dickering. Accordingly he asked 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, by messenger, for help. Leaving
          his party's baggage downstream with two men to guard it, 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>and the rest of his group responded
          promptly.</p>
               <p>Realizing their bargaining strength, those 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name>who were willing to
          sell jacked prices higher and higher, and then happily gambled away their profits,
          "content," in 
          <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway's</name>words, "to let the world go as it
          may." Soon the Indians were asking for guns and ammunition as well as for knives and
          clothing. At that the whites balked. The twenty-nine horses they now owned—good animals
          but sore-backed because of the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshonis'</name>crude saddles—would
          have to do. The captains, 
          <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name>, and a few others could ride, but
          most would have to walk, yanking the stubborn pack animals along by their improvised
          halters. At least hunting had improved, and the Corps was able to start out with a
          little venison to supplement their diet of fish.
          <ref target="n1414" n="14"/>
               </p>
               <p>The morning of August 30 was a time of swirling color and confusion, the whites
          loading their fractious animals to go north, the Indians readying their gear for the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>hunt. At that point 
          <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name>definitely cast her lot with the
          Americans. Perhaps she did not even question her obligation to stay with the husband who
          had purchased her and who had no intention of leaving the expedition. It is likely, too,
          that she preferred the ways of the whites and the security they provided. 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>quite possibly was already calling
          her "
          <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Janey</name>" and her son "
          <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Jean Baptiste">Pomp</name>," as he did later on.
          <ref target="n1415" n="15"/>(His use of the nicknames is not to be taken as evidence of
          the secret, unrequited grand passion between soldier and Indian maid that aficionados of
          the latter like to dwell dreamily on. But it does indicate an easygoing relationship
          that could have appealed to the girl-mother who previously had known little but
          abuse.)</p>
               <p>No journal keeper mentions her decision. 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>was absorbed in the turmoil of
          departure, to which the private affairs of the interpreter and his wife were peripheral
          indeed. As for 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, he had ceased making, on
          August 26, journal entries of any sort. Melancholia again? Or, as is more probable, did
          he fall silent in order to lighten his load of duties? 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, to be sure, had asked that
          both captains (and other expedition members) keep diaries. But the president was not
          after different viewpoints; he simply wanted to increase the odds that at least one
          diary would survive. To those in the field, the duplication must have been onerous at
          times. 
          <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse</name>often copied each other
          word for word. And was it really necessary, the captains perhaps asked each other, for
          both to stay up to all hours writing under dim candlelight about the same things?
          Couldn't they take turns?</p>
               <p>That in effect is what they did. Though 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>continued with his voluminous
          field notes, he made no more journal entries, except for three short periods when 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>was away on various errands, until
          January 1, 1806. At that time 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>resumed his diary—and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>ceased his. And so, for the period
          to January 1, we must rely on 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>for a record of each day's
          traverse, and on Sergeants 
          <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Private Joseph Whitehouse</name>.</p>
               <p>These tell us that after picking up 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>baggage the cavalcade continued
          down the right bank of the 
          <name type="place"
                        key="Salmon (Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">
          Salmon</name>, across talus piles that bruised the horses' feet and ankles and then up
          today's 
          <name type="place" key="Boyle Creek">Boyle Creek</name>to a bit of flat land big enough
          to hold a night's camp and provide grazing for the horses. There the men ate their last
          sparse ration of venison and topped off the meal with locally grown berries. This
          shortage of food may be what prompted the six Indians who had accompanied them this far
          to turn back, so that 
          <name type="person" key="Old Toby">Old Toby</name>and one of his sons were the only 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name>who remained. Having
          fewer mouths to feed could not have displeased either the captains or the hunters.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Old Toby">Toby</name>was leading them over a shortcut of sorts,
          scrambling up steep hills, dipping into creek valleys, and threading increasing amounts
          of timber as elevation increased. That evening, September 1, they camped on the 
          <name type="place" key="North Fork Salmon River (Fish Creek)">North Fork of the
          Salmon</name>, six miles above its confluence with the main river—close enough that
          three men were able to hike down to an Indian camp 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>party had passed during their
          exploratory venture and return with twenty-five pounds of dried salmon.</p>
               <p>Real trouble began the next day. They had to cut passage through thickets of
          evergreens, both standing and fallen. They dragged their reluctant horses through deep
          bogs the men named the 
          <name type="place" key="Dismal Swamp">Dismal Swamp</name>. While they were clambering up
          rocky hillsides to escape the narrowing defile through which the creek poured, several
          horses slipped and fell. Some tumbled down the slope and, burdened by their packs, could
          not regain their feet. The men had to slide down to them, remove the loads, urge them
          back onto the trail, and then carry the baggage up for repacking. One animal gave out so
          completely they had to abandon it and its load. Except for a few "pheasants" (grouse),
          the hunters brought in nothing fresh to eat. Ravenous, the crew wanted to kill a horse.
          The captains turned instead to their shrinking supply of pork. Live animals were
          precious.
          <ref target="n1416" n="16"/>
               </p>
               <p>September 3 was the worst day. Two men took the horse 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>had been riding back to rescue
          the animal that had been left behind. They salvaged it by putting its load on 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>stallion and letting it limp
          back behind them. Then more uphill, more downhill, more trail cutting, more horses
          falling—"horrid bad going," said 
          <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse</name>, to which 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>added his amen: "some of the worst
          roads that a horse ever passed." Gloomily he went on, "We met with a great misfortune,
          in haveing our last Themometer broken, by accident." If the instrument had been sound,
          it would have set a new low for the season. A rain that had been falling most of the
          afternoon turned, after dark, to snow. Later the skies cleared, the stars leaped out
          like a spray of icy points, and everything that was wet froze hard. "Slept wet and
          hungry and cold," 
          <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse</name>complained. But at least
          the discoverers had crossed the humpbacked ridge, seven thousand feet in elevation, that
          divides the waters of 
          <name type="place"
                        key="Salmon (Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">Lewis's
          River</name>from those of the stream 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>later named 
          <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">Clark's River</name>. It
          is the 
          <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">
          Bitterroot</name>today.</p>
               <p>After working their way down 
          <name type="place" key="Camp Creek (Ravalli County, Mont.">Camp Creek</name>, the Corps
          came into a lovely vale holding thirty-three tepees—about four hundred men, women, and
          children. They were 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Flatheads</name>, short, stocky,
          light-hued members of the widespread 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Salish</name>people. Since 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Flatheads</name>did not deform their
          children's skulls, as the coastal Indians did, the reason for the name is unknown,
          although various theories have been offered.
          <ref target="n1417" n="17"/>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>had first heard of them from the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name>, who said they dwelt
          beside a big stream flowing north along the western base of the 
          <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rockies</name>, and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>had located them in that position
          on his 1805 map. But here, on the scene, a bit of geography suddenly straightened itself
          out. There was not one north-flowing river at the base of the mountains, as they had
          thought the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name>had said, but two,
          separated by the divide they had just crossed—
          <name type="place"
                        key="Salmon (Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">Lewis's
          River</name>, which they'd seen bend west toward the 
          <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>, and 
          <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">Clark's River</name>.
          Whether 
          <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">Clark's River (the
          Bitterroot</name>) also reached the ocean, no one on the spot could tell them.</p>
               <p>The 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Flatheads</name>were anxious to climb
          the hill the Americans had just descended. That way they could strike east across the 
          <name type="place" key="Continental Divide">Continental Divide</name>at what is now 
          <name type="place" key="Gibbon Pass">Gibbon Pass</name>and follow the 
          <name type="place" key="Big Hole (Sensable, Wisdom) River">Wisdom (Big Hole)
          River</name>to the forks of the 
          <name type="place" key="Beaverhead (Jefferson) River">Jefferson</name>, where 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>dugouts had run into trouble a
          month earlier. The Corps, on its part, was just as anxious to reach the trail of the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Pierced Nose Indians</name>.
          Nevertheless, the prospect of profitable horse trading kept the groups together for a
          day and a half. In that time the captains purchased at least eleven sound, clean-limbed
          animals (or perhaps thirteen; accounts aren't clear) and traded off seven of their
          injured mounts for the same number of healthy ones. Three of the acquisitions were mares
          followed by unweaned colts.</p>
               <p>When the explorers continued through cold rains down the 
          <name type="place" key="Bitterroot Valley">Bitterroot Valley</name>, they had
          approximately forty good horses in their remuda. Though hunger still pinched them much
          of the time, they were feeling more confident about the future than they had for several
          days past. Perhaps 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>was feeling better about
          himself, too, for he had taken advantage of slow spells in the bargaining to make notes
          on some of the new tribe's salient characteristics and to compile a partial vocabulary
          for 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>to use in his studies of
          comparative languages.</p>
               <p>The 
          <name type="place" key="Lolo Trail">Lolo Trail</name>, the name later given to the 
          <name type="place" key="Lolo Trail">Nez Percé Trail</name>, followed a creek that ran
          sparkling out of the mountains to join the 
          <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead)River">Bitterroot</name>. The
          captains halted there to give 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>time to take celestial
          observations, for the hunters to gather meat—they did not have much luck—and for the
          other men to repair their moccasins. While most of the horses grazed, 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Old Toby">Toby</name>rode down 
          <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Clark's, Flathead) River">Clark's River</name>to its
          
          <name type="place"
                        key="Clark Fork (Clark's, East Fork Clark's, Flathead) River">East
          Fork</name>(today's 
          <name type="place" key="Missoula, Mont.">Missoula</name>) to look over the country. More
          geography fell into place. According to 
          <name type="person" key="Old Toby">Toby</name>, travelers could veer up the 
          <name type="place"
                        key="Clark Fork (Clark's, East Fork Clark's, Flathead) River">East
          Fork's</name>left-hand branch to an easy pass over the 
          <name type="place" key="Continental Divide">Continental Divide</name>. The pass opened
          onto an east-flowing stream the captains had already named 
          <name type="place" key="Dearborn River">Dearborn</name>; it entered the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>close to the 
          <name type="place" key="Gates of the Rocky Mountain">Gates of the Mountain</name>. The
          traverse took four days, 
          <name type="person" key="Old Toby">Toby</name>declared.
          <ref target="n1418" n="18"/>The Corps had been on the road fifty-two days.</p>
               <p>The 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name>had told them about this
          crossing and about a similar one from the head of the 
          <name type="place" key="Sun (Mah-pah-pah,-ah-zhah, Medicine) River">Medicine</name>. The
          captains had not understood the talk clearly. Besides, they had needed horses and the
          only place they could be sure of finding them (it had been said) was among 
          <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea's</name>people near the headwaters of the 
          <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>. So they had followed the long
          hairpin curve—south, southwest, and north—that at the time had seemed the most
          dependable way. On their return journey, they could check this amazing shortcut, for
          they seem never to have doubted that they would return home by land—and not by sea, as 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>had said they might.</p>
               <p>They started up the 
          <name type="place" key="Lolo Trail">Lolo Trail</name>in midafternoon, September 11.
          Straightway they ran into portents. Fresh, unseasonable snow cloaked the high peaks of
          the 
          <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Snow) Mountains">Bitterroot Mountains</name>. A hard
          frost whitened the grass when they awoke on the morning of the twelfth. Later that same
          day they encountered pine trees from which starving Indians had peeled the bark in
          order, 
          <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name>said, to be able to eat the moist
          fibers of the bark's inner layers.
          <ref target="n1419" n="19"/>
               </p>
               <p>On the thirteenth they crossed a relatively low divide to headwater creeks that would
          soon unite to form a river later travelers would know as the 
          <name type="place" key="Lochsa (Upper Kooskooskee) River">Lochsa</name>, a 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Flathead</name>word meaning "rough
          water." Though they were unaware of it as yet, their guide, 
          <name type="person" key="Old Toby">Toby</name>, had been confused by paths the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Flatheads</name>used to reach good
          fishing places along the upper part of the river. The main trail followed the ridge
          tops, but he was whipping his horse down rain-slippery hills into tangles of fallen
          timber. On the night of the fourteenth, much fatigued and ravenously hungry, the
          explorers experimented with some of the gummy portable soup 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>had packed away in lead
          canisters long before in 
          <name type="place" key="Philadelphia, Pa.">Philadelphia</name>. Not liking it, they
          killed one of their colts for supper.</p>
               <p>The next day they floundered along the riverbank until 
          <name type="person" key="Old Toby">Toby</name>realized his mistake: they should be on
          the top of the giant hogback that formed the northern border of the 
          <name type="place" key="Lochsa (Upper Kooskooskee) River">Lochsa's</name>profound
          canyon. To get there they climbed four thousand feet up a precipitous side ridge—tight
          zigzags, rocks that cut the horses' ankles, loose, gravelly soil, and piles of jackstraw
          trees that had been felled by fire and wind. Among the horses that lost their footing
          and rolled down the hill was one that carried 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>field desk. Although the desk was
          irretrievably smashed, the horses survived. Dark had closed in when they reached the
          top. No water there. But they were able to melt enough snow for thinning the portable
          soup. With colt bones added for flavor, it tasted better.</p>
               <p>Try to visualize that narrow, gigantic ridge winding between a series of knobby peaks
          overlooking a seemingly endless wilderness of deep, winding, heavily forested troughs.
          Rough saddles separate knob from knob, so that the travelers were constantly dropping
          down only to have to toil despairingly up again. In a few places the dim trail cut along
          the steep sides of the ridge to reach water. But eventually the long string, made up of
          forty or so horses and an unknown number of hikers, had to seek out the top again, to
          resume slogging from knob to wearying knob.</p>
               <p>On the morning of the sixteenth they awoke on a side hill "astonished" to find their
          beds under six inches of snow, its whiteness dulled by thick fog. In order to find the
          trail, 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>walked along, head bent, leading
          his horse. Snow shaken from the weighted branches soaked them all, until, in 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>words, he was "as wet and as cold
          in every part as I ever was in my life, indeed I was at one time fearfull my feet would
          freeze in the thin Mockirsons which I wore." Those who had cloth tore it up to wrap
          their feet. 
          <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name>? The baby? No one says.</p>
               <p>The low point came when 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>fired at a deer and heard the
          hammer click uselessly because of a loose flint—or so he wrote. 
          <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse</name>says the gun fired but the
          shooter missed.
          <ref target="n1420" n="20"/>As morale sagged in the afternoon, 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>hurried ahead with one man along
          the side of the ridge. On reaching water near a sheltering copse of balsam, he built
          huge fires to warm the others when they came up, numb and downcast. That night they
          killed a second colt, ate half of it as a side dish for portable soup, and kept the rest
          for the next day's breakfast.</p>
               <p>They had to turn the horses loose that night to graze. In the morning the hungry
          animals were badly scattered, partly because the mare whose colt had just been butchered
          had gone back along the trail looking for it. The delay caused by gathering the animals
          and excessive slipperiness resulting from melted snow held the cavalcade to a meager
          ten-mile advance. At suppertime they butchered the last colt, and again saved half. The
          skimpy supper left the thirty-five adults almost as voracious as if they hadn't eaten.
          In desperation the captains decided 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>should press ahead the next morning
          with six men (but without 
          <name type="person" key="Old Toby">Toby</name>for some unexplained reason) and try to
          find food to send back.
          <ref target="n1421" n="21"/>
               </p>
               <p>After twenty miles of rocky, up-and-down riding, the advance party climbed a knob
          later named 
          <name type="place" key="Sherman Peak">Sherman Peak</name>. Far ahead the rumpled forest
          at last leveled off. Broad, tan openings broke the black look of the spiked trees.
          Surely there would be game there, and perhaps Indians to lend help. But the plains were
          still forty or more rugged miles away, and that involved going without food until late
          in the morning of the nineteenth, when they spotted a stray Indian horse. It was not
          fat, and 
          <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>had been emphatic about
          respecting Indian rights. But the men begged hard, and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>consented. After eating a hearty
          breakfast, they left the rest of the meat for those who followed. Sustained by that one
          meal, they reached 
          <name type="place" key="Weippe Prairie">Weippe Prairie</name>late the next morning,
          September 20.</p>
               <p>Three Indian boys, seeing the seven strangers riding toward them among the widely
          spaced ponderosa pines, dived into the tall grass to hide. Dismounting, 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>gave his gun and horse to one of
          the men to hold and searched through the grass until he found two of the youngsters
          curled up and trembling like rabbits. Reassuring them with a piece of ribbon, he and his
          companions followed the excited pair to a village of about thirty lodges made of mats
          woven of withes. Here the newcomers were surrounded by scores of apprehensive women and
          children and a few old men. The chief and most of the braves, 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>learned through signs, were away on
          a war excursion. They told him, as nearly as he could understand the word, that they
          were 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Cho-pun-nish</name>. They were a
          likely people, he thought, of a somewhat darker complexion than the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Flatheads</name>. The men were portly,
          the women small but "handsome featured." He noticed their ornaments: white shells, blue
          beads, and brass rings. Some were worn in their noses. For these native people were
          indeed of the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Pierced Nose tribe</name>, the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Percé</name>, later its
          pronunciation anglicized, unfortunately, into "nezz purse."</p>
               <p>The mobile village had been located on the prairie because this was the best place
          and season for harvesting the bulbous roots of the camas lily—women's work. Mounds of
          roots stood here and there on the prairie and in the village. Close by were pit ovens
          for drying the vegetables so they could be pounded into flour for making soup or bread.
          When the new arrivals asked for food, the Indians plied them with dried salmon, raw
          camas roots, cooked roots, and bread of camas flour. Although the whites ate copiously,
          they wanted more solid food, both for themselves and for 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>expectant group. Sending
          hunters out for deer, 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>rode to a neighboring village, for
          he understood it might be near a navigable river. The town was not on a river, however,
          and he had no luck finding meat. Neither did the hunters. But again they were fed
          generously on fish and roots.</p>
               <p>All seven were miserably sick during the night, the result, they thought, of
          overloading their hunger-weakened stomachs with unfamiliar food. Nevertheless, the men
          went hunting again in the morning, while 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>delved for information. Obligingly
          the principal chief of the town drew a map for him. Half a day's march away, on an
          island in the river 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>wanted to see, was the fishing camp
          of an influential person whose name the captain translated as 
          <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">Twisted Hair</name>. A little
          distance below 
          <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">Twisted Hair's</name>camp, his
          river and another came together. A little farther on, more streams added their water to
          the flow. After a distance of many sleeps, this big river broke through the mountains,
          creating in its passage a huge waterfall. Below the fall some white men lived, a remark
          the captain recorded without comment. He had heard a similar rumor way back among the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name>.
          <ref target="n1422" n="22"/>
               </p>
               <p>The hunters returned in the afternoon, still empty-handed. So roots and dried salmon
          would have to do for both his men and 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>. 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>bought as much as the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Percé</name>would sell for the
          knickknacks he had in his pockets. Loading the food onto a packhorse, he entrusted it to
          
          <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">Reuben Field</name>for delivery. Still feeling
          miserable ("I am verry sick to day," he wrote, "and puke which relive me"), he set out
          for 
          <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">Twisted Hair's</name>river camp to
          double-check the information he had received. After a long ride through the dark with an
          Indian guide hired for a red handkerchief, the explorers reached the top of a line of
          tall bluffs bounding a large stream. After inching cautiously downward, they located the
          camp shortly before midnight and were made welcome. Sick and weary though he was, 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>went through the requisite
          ceremonies, explained the American purpose as well as his knowledge of sign language
          allowed, and after bestowing a medal on the chief—"A Chearfull man of about 65 with
          apparent siencerity"—he tumbled into bed at about one in the morning.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>Far back on the 
          <name type="place" key="Lolo Trail">Lolo Trail</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>picked up his pen and resumed
          his journal writing. It was a doleful tale. The twenty-eight people with him were
          showing signs of malnutrition, perhaps even of scurvy—cramps, thin diarrhea, skin
          rashes.
          <ref target="n1423" n="23"/>Weakness, the difficulties of the trail, and constant
          trouble with the horses kept them to a snail's pace, even though they wanted to hurry.
          On September 18, the day 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>party pushed ahead, they rode
          eighteen waterless miles, coming after dark to the head of a ravine down which they were
          able to lead the horses to a spring. After drinking deep and dining on a bit of soup,
          bear oil, and a few tallow candles, the wayfarers lay down beside approximately forty
          horses and managed to pass the night "on this Sidling Mountain."</p>
               <p>The next day the rough ridge trail led them to the top of 
          <name type="place" key="Sherman Peak">Sherman Peak</name>. There they, like 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, looked out to the distant prairie
          "with inexpressible joy." A little farther on, the narrow trail slanted high across the
          face of an almost perpendicular slope. There 
          <name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">Robert Frazer's</name>horse, loaded with two
          boxes of powder and ball, fell a hundred yards down the hill (200 feet, 
          <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>; 100 feet, 
          <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse</name>) and crashed into the
          brushy creek bottom.
          <ref target="n1424" n="24"/>Amazingly, the men were able to salvage both the ammunition
          and the horse, "the most wonderfull escape," 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>said, that he had ever seen.</p>
               <p>Another wonderful experience was finding, the next day, the slaughtered horse 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>advance party had left for them.
          That sustained them for thirty more hours, when they were able to put together a meal of
          a bit of horse meat, three grouse, one coyote, and some crayfish taken from the stream
          beside which they camped.</p>
               <p>It is a measure of 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, perhaps, that throughout this
          time the entries in his trip journal stayed as voluminous as ever—much longer than 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>. He devoted pages to
          distinguishing between the eight varieties of evergreens they passed and describing new
          birds they saw: a black-and-white jay (Canadian jay), and three varieties of grouse. As
          altitude dropped and the temperature warmed, he noted the changes these factors brought
          to the vegetation. But after they had met 
          <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">Reuben Field</name>toward noon on September 22,
          had devoured the food he brought, and had gone on to make camp beside the nearest 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Percé</name>village, he wrote one
          flowery sentence about "the pleasure I now felt in having tryumphed over the 
          <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">rockey Mountains</name>," and then laid down
          his pen. With one three-day exception (November 29 through December 1) he did not make
          another journal entry until the new year.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, limping from the effects of a
          fall from a horse he had borrowed from 
          <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">Twisted Hair</name>, rejoined the
          party that same evening. He bore glad tidings. No more rocky trails. No more horses to
          struggle with. They were within fifteen miles of a branch of the river that would carry
          them to the ocean.</p>
               <p>He also warned them against eating too much. Wasted breath. Those were starving men.
          During a day's layover, while the captains held the usual council and handed out gifts,
          including an American flag for the grand chief who was absent, they absorbed as much
          dried salmon and camas root as they could hold. The next morning nearly everyone was
          violently ill. They blamed the ailment on their radical change of diet. The experience
          of later explorers and fur trappers tends to confirm the belief.
          <ref target="n1425" n="25"/>In spite of the extreme unpleasantness of the affliction,
          however, the captains determined to press on: they had no time to lose building canoes,
          reaching the ocean, and establishing winter quarters.</p>
               <p>It was a ghastly march, attended by crowds of Indians. "
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name>," 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>wrote, "scercely able to ride on a
          jentle horse which was furnished by the Chief, Several men So unwell that they were
          Compelled to lie on the Side of the road for some time others obliged to be put on
          horses." The hunters 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>had left at 
          <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">Twisted Hair's</name>camp—they were
          sick, too—had killed only two deer, and so the temptation to eat salmon and camas root
          continued. 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>handed out every type of medicine
          the expedition had: 
          <name type="person" key="Rush, Benjamin">Rush's</name>thunderbolts, salts, and "Tarter 
          <hi rend="italic">emetic</hi>." On they dragged through heavily forested country and
          down beside 
          <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">Twisted Hair's</name>river (the 
          <name type="place" key="North Fork Clearwater (Chopunnish) River">north fork of the
          Clearwater</name>) to the main fork, or, as the captains called it, the 
          <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Kooskooskee</name>. On
          September 26, they managed to cross the main stream and set up what they named 
          <name type="place" key="Canoe Camp (Idaho)">Canoe Camp</name>in a likely grove opposite
          the mouth of the north fork.</p>
               <p>They stayed there eleven days. Considering their circumstances, they wrought
          mightily. When the hunters proved unable to bring in enough deer, they ate a horse. That
          finished, they turned reluctantly to fish and roots, the latter of which "filled us [the
          two captains] so full of wind, that we were Scercely able to Breathe all night."
          Despairing, some of the crew followed the example of the French rivermen and began
          buying and eating fat Indian dogs.
          <ref target="n1426" n="26"/>
               </p>
               <p>At 
          <name type="place" key="Canoe Camp (Idaho)">Canoe Camp</name>the crew was divided into
          five groups. With axes hardly big enough for the work, they began hacking away at five
          huge trees, probably red cedar though heavy ponderosa pine was more common in the area,
          from which they hoped to fashion five river-worthy boats. Once the trees were down, they
          saved labor by building fires along the tops, Indian fashion, and then scraped out the
          ashes and charred wood with their chisels and adzes.</p>
               <p>They dried and repacked their possessions. They branded and cut the forelocks off
          their thirty-eight surviving horses so the animals could be easily recognized, and
          entrusted them to 
          <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">Twisted Hair</name>to watch until
          they returned. They cached their saddles and some powder during the dark of the night.
          There were four big canoes—no journal keeper reported their length, width, or depth—and
          one small one designed to run ahead of the others and check the state of the water. They
          planned on thirty-seven passengers: the original thirty-three, which included 
          <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea's</name>infant, plus 
          <name type="person" key="Old Toby">Toby</name>and his son, and 
          <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">Twisted Hair</name>and a fellow
          chieftan, 
          <name type="place" key="Tetoharsky">Tetoharsky</name>. The latter two had agreed to come
          along as interpreters while the travelers were still in 
          <name type="place" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Percé</name>country. And then there was 
          <name type="person" key="Seaman">Seaman</name>.</p>
               <p>On the night of October 6, 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>fell ill again. No matter. 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>was even more debilitated. So it
          fell to 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, the next morning, to supervise
          the hurly-burly of breaking camp, loading the canoes, and lashing in the bundles, for
          they knew rough water foamed ahead. Finally, toward noon, uncertain of their own
          strengths and certainly uncertain about their new boats, they swung into the current.
          For the first time since leaving the junction of the 
          <name type="place" key="Ohio River">Ohio</name>and the 
          <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name>, 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark</name>were going with the flow of
          a river instead of against it.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="notes" type="notes">
            <head rend="center">Notes</head>
            <div type="section">
               <note xml:id="n1401" n="1">
                  <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>, II, 334.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1402" n="2">Hodge, II, 557. Jackson, 
          <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, II, 554.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1403" n="3">
                  <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>, II, 334.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1404" n="4">II, 361–63. 
          <name type="person" key="Cameahwait">Cameahwait's</name>remark, "If we had guns ..." is
          in II, 380.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1405" n="5">II, 364.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1406" n="6">DeVoto, 
          <hi rend="italic">Journals</hi>, 205–6. 
          <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>in Quaife, 270. 
          <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse</name>in VII, 138.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1407" n="7">
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>self-evaluation: DeVoto, 
          <hi rend="italic">Journals</hi>, 206.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1408" n="8">
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>ethnographic jottings are
          spread throughout II, 372–III, 32 (the material on venereals is on 372–73). DeVoto's
          condensation is in 
          <hi rend="italic">Journals</hi>, 207–27. 
          <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>presents the ethnographic data
          in a single unit, 367–84.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1409" n="9">III, 13.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1410" n="10">IlI, 14. 
          <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>in Quaife, 272.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1411" n="11">III, 28.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1412" n="12">Holding 
          <name type="person" key="Cameahwait">Cameahwait</name>to his promise: III, 35–36; 
          <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>in Quaife, 274. Ronda, 153, who
          persistently faults 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>for not evaluating the Indians
          according to modern ethnological standards, feels the "blast" 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>gave the chief was too
          severe.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1413" n="13">
                  <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>reconnaissance: II, 380–I11, 47; 
          <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>, II, 342–55; Allen, 294–300.
          Peebles, 5–11, attempts a precise definition of trails and a location of each night's
          campsite.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1414" n="14">Horse buying: III, 46–48; 
          <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>in Quaife, 275–76; 
          <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse</name>in VII, 146. It is not
          possible to determine the exact number of horses the expedition had at any one time.
          (Appleman, 372 nn. 115 and 116.)</note>
               <note xml:id="n1415" n="15">Jackson, 
          <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, I, 315–17.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1416" n="16">
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name>to 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Flatheads</name>: III, 50–53; 
          <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>, 382–86; 
          <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name>, 155–56.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1417" n="17">The 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Flatheads</name>, a 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Salish</name>tribe, did not deform
          their skulls, but their tops looked flat compared to the peaked skulls created by other 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Salish</name>and 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookan</name>tribes. (Brandon, 310.)
          Ronda, 155, says the name came from the sign-language designation for the tribe: hands
          pressed against the sides of the head in a flattening motion. See also Hodge under "
          <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Salish</name>."</note>
               <note xml:id="n1418" n="18">III, 58.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1419" n="19">The 
          <name type="place" key="Lolo Trail">Lolo Trail</name>: III, 62–72; 
          <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>in Quaife, 284–87; 
          <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse</name>in VII, 153–58; Peebles,
          17–19; Space, 2–12.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1420" n="20">
                  <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>and the deer: III, 69; 
          <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse</name>in VII, 157.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1421" n="21">From September 18 through 22, 
          <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>and 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>journal entries alternate in
          III, 79–84 and Space, 12–19. 
          <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse</name>in VII, 156–60 and 
          <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>in Quaife, 288–90, supplement 
          <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>. See also Peebles under
          appropriate dates.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1422" n="22">Reaching the 
          <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Percé</name>through the building
          of the canoes: III, 84–98; 
          <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>in Quaife, 290–94; Peebles, 23–26;
          Space, 19–22.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1423" n="23">Chuinard, 320. Mirsky, 318.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1424" n="24">III, 74. 
          <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>in Quaife, 288. 
          <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse</name>in VII, 156.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1425" n="25">Cutright, 
          <hi rend="italic">Pioneering Naturalists</hi>, 218–19.</note>
               <note xml:id="n1426" n="26">
                  <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>in Quaife, 293.</note>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.lavender.01.13" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.lavender.01.00" type="contents"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.lavender.01.15" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
