<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.sup.lavender.01.09">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Way to the Western Sea</title>
            <title type="sub">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> across the Continent</title>
            <title type="sub" level="a">Chapter 9</title>
            <author>David Lavender</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2005</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               
               
               
               
               
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Way to the Western Sea</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">Chapter 9</title>
               <author>David Lavender</author>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>2001</date>
               <idno type="ISBN">0-8032-8003-3</idno>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
              <term>Texts</term>
            </keywords>
           <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
             <term>Books</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-11-09</date>
            <date>2005-04-20</date>
            <name>Becky Potter</name>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Split into chapters Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="nine" type="chapter">
            <head rend="center">NINE. The Grand Plan</head>
            <div type="section">
               <p>
The first <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> village they sighted contained, within its stockade of short pickets, about forty big, dome-shaped, earth-covered habitations, almost exactly like those used by the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name>. It stood atop a bluff about fifty feet high, the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> curling at its base. To land at the narrow beach below the town would give the villagers, if they turned hostile, a strategic advantage no army officer would consider. Nor did the captains want to expose their whole group by advancing in a body. So they moored the boats half a mile downstream. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, suffering from rheumatism, stayed with part of the men at the landing place. Several <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name> stayed there also, watching intently as the white cooks set up a little steel mill and ground parched corn into meal for corn pones—a great improvement, certainly, over rolling, as the Indians did, a round stone back and forth over a flat rock, with the kernels in between.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, meanwhile, accompanied by interpreters <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">George Drouillard</name> and <name type="person" key="Gravelines, Joseph">Joseph Gravelines</name> and a squad of riflemen, hiked with a crowd of <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> men, women, and children to the village. Its name, as <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> later spelled the word phonetically, was <name type="place" key="Mitutanka (Matootonha) village">Matootonha</name>. (Today's archeologists call the site <name type="place" key="Mitutanka (Matootonha) village">Mitutanka</name>.) Its principal chief was <name type="person" key="Big White (Sheheke)">Sheheke</name>. Because <name type="person" key="Big White (Sheheke)">Sheheke</name> was fat and of light complexion, the handful of French-Canadian traders who either lived in the area or visited occasionally from the British posts to the the northeast called him <name type="place" key="Big White (Sheheke)">Le Gros Blanc</name>, or <name type="person" key="Big White (Sheheke)">Big White</name> in English.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Big White">Big White</name> and several other of <name type="place" key="Mitutanka (Matootonha) village">Matootonha's</name> leading men smoked cordially with the visitors—tobacco was an essential prelude to any important meeting—and <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> returned to the boats in high spirits. The Corps should have no trouble setting up a council for all five of the neighborhood towns, only two of them <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>. After that they could settle in for the winter. High time, too, to judge from the flights of geese, swans, cormorants, and 
ducks passing overhead, the wavering Vs of each southbound flock outlined sharply against the pale sky.</p>
               <p>
The next morning both captains visited <name type="place" key="Mitutanka (Matootonha) village">Matootonha</name>. This time they picked up <name type="person" key="Jusseaume, René">René Jessaume</name>, a free trader who had been living with the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name> and their neighbors, the <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name>, for the past fifteen years. English traders who knew <name type="person" key="Jusseaume, René">Jessaume</name> considered him devoid of morals. When <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">John Evans</name>, working for the Spanish in 1796, had ordered him to leave the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> and return to <name type="place" key="Canada">Canada</name>, <name type="person" key="Jusseaume, René">Jessaume</name> had tried to kill him, or so <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name> charged. After talking with <name type="person" key="Jusseaume, René">Jessaume</name> for a time, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> wrote him down as "cunnin, artful, and insonce [insolent]." But the Canadian could speak the Indians' language and understood the power hierarchies in the different villages, attributes that would stand the captains in good stead when the moment came to hand out medals and red coats to the chiefs they formally recognized.<ref target="n0901" n="1"/>
               </p>
               <p>
With <name type="person" key="Jusseaume, René">Jessaume</name> in one of the boats the whites rowed up the sweeping meanders of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> past a second <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> village. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, struggling with the heavy sounds of an unfamiliar tongue, called the village <name type="place" key="Ruptáre (Rooptahee) village">Rooptahee</name>. (Today's archeologists call it <name type="place" key="Ruptáre (Rooptahee) village">Nuptadi</name>.) Not quite as populous as <name type="place" key="Mitutanka (Matootonha) village">Matootonha</name>, <name type="place" key="Ruptáre (Rooptahee) village">Rooptahee</name> lay on the opposite, or northeastern, bank, surrounded on three sides by the coiling river. Upstream from the town, where the brush of 
the flood plain had some years since been cleared away for gardens, the Corps made camp. Nearby they raised a flagpole to mark the site for the big council they had scheduled for the following day, October 28. They had already told the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name> about the meeting. Now they hired three young Indian runners to carry the word, along with carrots of tobacco, to the three <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> villages that dotted the lower mile and a half of the <name type="place" key="Knife River">Knife River</name>, where it ran almost parallel to the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>.</p>
               <p>
(A note on nomenclature, which can be skipped if desired. The first white travelers to visit the five riverside villages in what is now central <name type="place" key="North Dakota">North Dakota</name> lumped them together as the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> towns. The <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name> lived only in the lower two, however. The next village above them—the domed huts stood on a west-side bluff overlooking the confluence of the <name type="place" key="Knife River">Knife</name> and <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> rivers—was the home of a group that the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>, and hence <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, called the Wattasons or sometimes the Ahaharways. Though the Wattasons spoke their own dialect, they were related to the tribe that lived in two villages of earth-covered lodges farther up the <name type="place" key="Knife River">Knife</name>—villages called <name type="place" key="Metaharta (Metehartar) village">Metaharte</name> and <name type="place" key="Big Hidatsa site">Big Hidatsa</name>. The latter was by far the largest town in the area. The <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>, and hence <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> 
and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, called the dwellers in those upper two towns the <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Minitaris</name>. <name type="person" key="Jusseaume, René">Jessaume</name> and his fellow French-Canadians added other names: Souliers (Shoes) for the Wattasons and <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Gros Ventres (Big Bellies)</name> for the <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Minitaris</name>. Today the surviving <name type="place" key="Knife River">Knife River</name> people call themselves <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name>, after the now-vanished village of that name.<ref target="n0902" n="2"/> This account will also use <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> for the tribe, though it means differing from <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> usage.)</p>
               <p>
Odd similarities marked the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>-<name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> council and the one the captains had recently concluded with the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name>. In both instances clouds of sand stirred up by strong winds forced a postponement. Influential representatives from the upper towns of both neighborhoods failed to appear because of deep-seated jealousies. The upriver <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> had not wanted a downriver Indian made head chief over every village. The <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name>, on their part, 
feared the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name> might take precedence in whatever trading arrangements these strangers from the far-off mouth of the river might establish.</p>
               <p>
There were also profound differences, the main one being that the residents of the three <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> towns belonged to the same tribe. The <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name> were different tribes. The <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name> were the more bellicose; their war parties regularly rode far west to attack the Indians who lived in the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky Mountains</name>—a matter of importance to the captains, who needed to refine their understanding of the lands between the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> and the sea. The 
<name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>, by contrast, stayed close to their fields and only fought, they said, to stave off guerrilla strikes by the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name>.</p>
               <p>
Winds howled again on October 29, but <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> did not want to ask for another postponement lest the volatile groups grow impatient and disperse. Accordingly they had the enlisted men set up a canvas enclosure topped with a canvas awning. The swivel guns boomed; the enlisted men paraded. To the tune of the flutterings and cracklings of the canvas, and with <name type="person" key="Jusseaume, René">Jessaume</name> interpreting, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> gave a long speech "Similer," <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> wrote, "to what we had Delivered to the nations below." Bored by it, one aged <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> stirred restlessly and would have left the gathering if some of the others hadn't rebuked him for his rudeness.<ref target="n0903" n="3"/>
               </p>
               <p>
The usual making of chiefs followed. A head man was named for each village and a grand chief for each tribe. <name type="person" key="Black Cat (Posecopsahe)">Black Cat</name> of <name type="place" key="Ruptáre (Rooptahee) village">Rooptahee</name> was declared principal chief of all <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>; Kakoaksis of <name type="place" key="Big Hidatsa site">Big Hidatsa</name>—he was <name type="person" key="Le Borgne (One Eye)">Le Borgne</name> to the French because of his single eye—was put over the <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name>. The ceremony of recognition was something of a rump session, for <name type="person" key="Le Borgne (One Eye)">Le Borgne</name> was off with a war party, and <name type="person" key="Big White (Sheheke)">Big White</name>, named chief of <name type="place" key="Mitutanka (Matootonha) village">Matootonha</name> town, had been 
unable to cross the wind-swept river in his frail boat of buffalo hide and willows. The presents intended for the two had to be entrusted to messengers, and so some of the impact was gone.</p>
               <p>
At the captains' urging, those chiefs who were in attendance consented to smoke with the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> peace delegate whom the Corps had brought upstream as part of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> slowly evolving strategy of opening the river by isolating the obstreperous <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>. <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name>, <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>, and <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> against the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Tetons</name> . . . if old bonds could be turned upside down. The <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> representative played his part so well that <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> rewarded him with a U.S. silver dollar as a medal. The <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name> were more restrained. Though <name type="person" key="Big White (Sheheke)">Big White</name> agreed with <name type="person" key="Black Cat (Posecopsahe)">Black Cat</name> of <name type="place" key="Ruptáre (Rooptahee) village">Rooptahee</name> that peace 
was wonderful and there might be some advantage in visiting <name type="place" key="Washington D. C.">Washington</name>, he added sourly that whenever violence occurred, it was the fault of either the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> or the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name> or of both acting together. In the battles that followed, he said, the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name> slew the enemy as easily as if they were little birds. His people might as well make peace as coast along that way. All in all, it was a lukewarm denouement to a council that had begun with cannon 
fire and parades. But at least the program had been laid before the Indians, and the captains had the rest of the winter in which to improve its luster.</p>
               <p>
A related problem concerned their handling of foreign traders. One of the people who had come to the riverbank to stare at the flotilla as it hove into sight below the villages had been <name type="person" key="McCracken, Hugh">Hugh McCracken</name>, an illiterate Scot recently arrived from a North West Company post on the <name type="native_nation" key="Assiniboine (Ossiniboine) River">Assiniboine River</name>, a hundred and fifty miles to the northeast. His first reaction must have been astonishment: Americans, here where none had ever been before! Louisiana Purchase? He probably had heard nothing about it. On being told, he must have wondered what it meant to him. Would the Americans 
insist, as the Spanish had tried to do, that British fur men would not be allowed to ply their commerce south of the still unmarked border?</p>
               <p>
The captains themselves weren't sure. Under the terms of Jay's Treaty, signed by the United States and <name type="place" key="England">Great Britain</name> in 1794, traders of each nation were allowed to work in the other's territory if they subscribed to regulations applied by the host nation. In the United States this meant that every trader, American or British, 
had to purchase, for a small fee, a government license. But did the generous fur-trade provisos of Jay's Treaty extend to <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name>, which had been acquired <hi rend="italic">after</hi> the signing of that document? As <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> surely knew, many <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> merchants, hoping to keep British competitors out of the huge area, were arguing that the treaty did not apply and therefore the western reaches of the border remained closed, as in Spanish times, to foreign traders. At the time of the Corps's departure from <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> no governmental decision had been reached.</p>
               <p>
Yet how could <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> ask the Indians to acknowledge American jurisdiction without demanding the same recognition from the foreigners who dealt with Indians? (The word "foreigners" of course included such resident French-Canadians as <name type="person" key="Jusseaume, René">René Jessaume</name>, who lived in the villages with their Indian wives and exerted varying degrees of influence over their red neighbors.) So, granted the dilemma, what stance should the captains take, and 
under what authority?</p>
               <p>
They decided, in spite of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> ingrained prejudice against all Britons, to be conciliatory. (One senses <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> calming hand.) When <name type="person" key="McCracken, Hugh">McCracken</name> told them, shortly after the Indian councils ended and he had learned their tenor, that he was about to ride back to his post, they prevailed on him to carry a letter to his superior, <name type="person" key="Chaboillez, Charles">Charles Chaboillez</name>. In the letter they stated they had been dispatched by their government to explore the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> and 
the western part of North America "with a view to the promotion of general science." As proof of the "literary" nature of the project, they enclosed a copy of the passport the British ambassador in <name type="place" key="Washington D. C.">Washington</name> had granted <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> at <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name> request. The Corps expected, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> continued, to remain in the neighborhood of the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name> throughout the winter. There need be no frictions. As individuals "we feel every disposition to cultivate the 
friendship of all well-disposed persons."</p>
               <p>
"Well-disposed." They used the term again when stating it was the policy of the United States to allow "free egress and regress [<name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> words, surely] to all citizens and subjects of foreign powers with which she is in amity." And would <name type="person" key="Chaboillez, Charles">Mr. Chaboillez</name> kindly have those of his men who came to the villages pass on such information as they possessed about the country's geography and natural history?<ref target="n0904" n="4"/>
               </p>
               <p>
It was an adroit letter, not wholly candid. It said nothing about license requirements or the possibility of a complete interdiction of British trade with Indians who lived in American territory. It did establish a precedent of sorts by inviting the Canadians to come on down, an unauthorized step American fur men might well decry. But its very cordiality, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> hoped, might dissuade the British, to whom the Indians were accustomed, from 
stirring up anti-American acts that would jeopardize the expedition's future. Furthermore, the letter put <name type="person" key="Chaboillez, Charles">Chaboillez</name> under an obligation to repay courtesy with courtesy by directing his "well-disposed" traders to tell the American captains what they knew about the Western country and its native inhabitants.</p>
               <p>
On November 2, the captains, freed of their diplomatic chores, selected a site for the fort that would have to shelter and protect about forty-five people during the winter that loomed ahead. The spot they chose lay approximately six river miles below the confluence of the <name type="place" key="Knife River">Knife</name> and the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> and half that distance below the closest village, <name type="place" key="Mitutanka (Matootonha) village">Matootonha</name>, but on the opposite (left) bank. A few score yards back from the site, a bluff rising steeply out of the trees of the bottomland marked the edge of a grassy terrace. Beyond the terrace the bordering hills of the river's broad valley sloped upward to a height of five hundred feet or so. The fort would be built in the shape of a triangle, its apex pointing toward the bluff and its open front facing the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, close to the beach where the keelboat and the two pirogues were moored.</p>
               <p>
Decisions about personnel accompanied the decisions about the fort. A French-Canadian, <name type="person" key="Lepage, Jean Baptiste">Jean Baptiste Lepage</name>, who said he had ventured as far into the wilderness as the <name type="place" key="Black Hills">Black Hills</name>, was hired to replace the discharged <name type="person" key="Newman, John">John Newman</name>. <name type="person" key="Newman, John">Newman</name>, desperately regretting his mutinous flare-up, wanted to be taken back into the Corps. No chance. If the other enlisted men thought discipline was not ironclad, so the captains reasoned, a general unraveling might 
take place that would jeopardize the entire project. <name type="person" key="Newman, John">Newman</name> and <name type="person" key="Reed, Moses B.">Moses Reed</name> could stay out the winter at the fort, but their positions would remain those of common laborers.</p>
               <p>
Though <name type="person" key="Newman, John">Newman</name> and <name type="person" key="Reed, Moses B.">Reed</name> remained with the group, the French crew of the red pirogue did not. To save the cost of their wages and to reduce the number of mouths that would have to be fed during the winter, the captains discharged them shortly after the boats reached the Indian villages. Nor were they allowed to try to race the ice downstream in the red pirogue they had labored with for the past five months; <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had decided it and the white pirogue would be needed when the upstream journey was resumed in the spring. So there the Frenchmen were, totally 
on their own. That was the way employment was handled in those days: pay and transportation ended with the job, as the boatmen had understood when signing up. What they did from then on was up to them.</p>
               <p>
The <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> peace delegate set an example. He and a few lesser <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name> started downstream for the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> towns in either a boat of buffalo hide or a dugout hewn from a cottonwood tree—no journal mentions the craft. Their intent was to seal the recent truces during a ceremonial smoke with the villagers. <name type="person" key="Gravelines, Joseph">Gravelines</name> would follow them in a day or two to guide the arrangements, and an indeterminate number of the French crew decided to accompany him in one or more hurriedly created dugouts. Since <name type="person" key="Gravelines, Joseph">Gravelines</name> is known to have reached the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> towns (<name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> had employed him to escort some <name type="place" key="Washington D. C.">Washington</name>-bound chiefs to <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> the following spring), the 
Frenchmen presumably also reached the villages. If they did not stay there—no records exist—they ran the risk of being caught by either ice or the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>.</p>
               <p>
Those of the French group who did not depart with <name type="person" key="Gravelines, Joseph">Gravelines</name> decided to build a small hut near the fort-to-be and winter among the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>, trapping beaver and enjoying the favors of the complaisant <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> girls. When spring came—well, they would worry then.<ref target="n0905" n="5"/> Perhaps they hoped they would be allowed to catch rides back to <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> aboard the keelboat. Because it was too big for use on the upper river, it would be sent downstream after the ice had broken with specimens and reports for <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">President Jefferson</name>. The craft would be manned on its descent by <name type="person" key="Warfington, Richard">Corporal Warfington's</name> soldiers, erstwhile crewmen of the white pirogue. <name type="person" key="Newman, John">Newman</name> and <name type="person" key="Reed, Moses B.">Reed</name> would also return in the keelboat. Until it left all of them would have plenty of winter work to keep them occupied.</p>
               <p>
Still another decision involved interpreters. <name type="person" key="Jusseaume, René">René Jessaume</name> and his wife and child moved into a tepee beside the site of the fort the day construction started, to be on hand whenever interpreting was needed. The family was followed within twenty-four hours by another resident trader, <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Toussaint Charbonneau</name>, known today to more Americans than any other man of the party except <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark</name>. The reason, it hardly need be said, was his then noticeably pregnant fourteen-or fifteen-year-old Indian wife, <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name>. She, along with another of <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau's</name> women, accompanied him to the embryonic fort. Her name has other spellings: <name type="person" key="Sakagawea">Sacajawea</name> and <name type="person" key="Sakagawea">Sakakawea</name>. The hard <hi rend="italic">g</hi> or the second <hi rend="italic">k</hi> is generally preferred to the <hi rend="italic">j</hi>. Pronunciation is important, according to <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name> aficionados, because the name spelled with a <hi rend="italic">g</hi> or <hi rend="italic">k</hi> and accented on the second syllable is <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> and means "<name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Bird Woman</name>." A soft <hi rend="italic">j</hi> makes it <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name> "Boat Launcher."<ref target="n0906" n="6"/>
               </p>
               <p>
By birth <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name> was a <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name>. In 1800, aged ten, she had been captured by a <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> war party while trying to flee across the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri River</name> at a distant place later called <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Three Forks of the">Three Forks</name>. When she turned nubile, <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name> either bought her or won her from her captor in a gambling game—take your choice, as with the spelling of her name.</p>
               <p>
When the Corps of Discovery reached the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> towns, <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name> was away on a hunting trip. Learning somehow of the council and of the explorers' destination, he realized he owned a profitable bit of merchandise. He hurried to the fort, showed off his wares, and asked for a job as an interpreter. The captains demurred. <name type="person" key="Jusseaume, René">Jessaume</name> was interpreter enough; besides, he spoke some English, while <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name> did not. The trader spluttered back through whoever was translating for him. Listen! This girl—he may well have pushed her ahead right under their noses—was a <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name>. <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name>, understand? Her tribe lived in the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky Mountains</name>. They owned many horses. Horses for carrying baggage across the <name type="place" key="Continental Divide">Continental Divide</name>. The captains would have to have someone who knew their language.</p>
               <p>
Translation, to be sure, would be awkward. But it could be done. <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name> would turn <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name> into <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> for her husband; he would transform it into French for one of the expedition's French half-breeds, <name type="place" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Cruzatte</name>, or <name type="person" key="Labiche, François">Labiche</name>, or even <name type="person" key="Lepage, Jean Baptiste">Jean Baptiste Lepage</name>, whom the captains had just hired. The Frenchman, whoever he was, could then put the words into English for the captains. So <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name> was hired. He would receive the pay; <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name> would do the work. Curiously the journals mention no hesitation over the fact that the teenager would be carrying a newborn infant at least as far as the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rockies</name>.</p>
               <p>
The final decision about personnel had to do with the laying in of food for the first part of the winter—food enough for more than forty people, together with the neighboring Indians, who would expect the whites to share what they had, just as the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name> shared when hunger pinched. It has been estimated that on a single day the crew and associated people could devour an entire buffalo or, in its place, four deer, or one deer and an elk.<ref target="n0907" n="7"/>
                  <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">George Drouillard</name> and six selected but unnamed men were ordered to go downstream in one of the pirogues and bring back as much meat as they could carry. Until they returned, the construction workers would have to depend on whatever corn, dried squash, buffalo steaks, and buffalo tripe the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name> brought them, either as gifts or for barter.</p>
               <p>
The builders pitched tents for shelter and then, racing the cold, set about clearing the area the fort would occupy. The green cottonwoods were heavy—full of water, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> said.<ref target="n0908" n="8"/> Lugging and levering those felled in and close to the clearing was hard enough. The effort grew as distance increased. It took at least four men to bring back one big, trimmed log. The quartet would first roll the timber onto a pair of crosspieces, one near either end. Heaving the cradle and its burden upward, the workers toted it ahead, often chanting to the rhythm of their steps. For help in boosting the log onto the rising walls, they rented a horse from the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name> and rigged up a rope pulley.</p>
               <p>
Each arm of the V-shaped structure was to contain four rooms, each fourteen feet square, seven feet high, and designed to hold a stone fireplace that was used for cooking as well as warmth. The point of the V did not quite close; an opening was left that would let armed men squeeze into a rounded bastion whose loopholes commanded a view of the outer walls of the triangle's sides, each fifty-six feet long. The walls of this bastion were made of contiguous pickets about seven feet tall. In time the enclosure would be roofed in order to provide space for storage.</p>
               <p>
The ceilings of the eight rooms were made of puncheons, which are logs adzed flat on one side. The flat sides, facing up and covered with grass and clay, would form lofts that would be used mostly as dormitories. The outer walls of the lofts projected a little beyond the outside walls of the lower apartments, an overhang designed to add space while discouraging attempts to scale the edifice. The base of the triangular fort, which fronted on the river, eventually was closed off by massive pickets eighteen feet tall and set deep in the ground.</p>
               <p>
The roofs of the structure sloped toward an inner court. In that limited space the men would often show off their jigs and reels to visiting Indians. A sentry regularly paced the walkways on the roof—after all, this was a military establishment, designed in part to impress the land's native inhabitants. After the chinks between the often crooked cottonwood logs had been daubed with clay and sticks, the place became not only draft-proof but "almost Cannon Ball Proof," to borrow the words of a Canadian who visited it late in November. It was named <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name> in honor of the neighboring tribe.</p>
               <p>
It was a lively place. The days during the first part of November stayed above freezing; construction went apace. Many <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name> (but few <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name>) rode by on their way to their hunting camps, or just appeared with their families to see what kind of dwellings white people lived in. They let their horses graze on the good grass in the bottomland while they smoked, ate, and talked as best they could with the always busy whites.</p>
               <p>
On November 12 and again on the 13th, daytime temperatures slipped to fourteen degrees above zero—"naught," as the captains put the figure on their weather charts.<ref target="n0909" n="9"/> Chunks of ice floated down the river; thin lenses of ice rippled along the shoreline. Hastily the men filled one of the storehouses in the bastion with supplies unloaded from the boats. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and a crew then rowed an empty pirogue up the river to gather stones suitable for chimneys. On the way back, the overloaded craft stuck on a sandbar. Over the gunwales the men went, into icy water, to work the boat free. Cold air on wet feet during the rest of the journey resulted in frostbite for some. But, wrote <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Sergeant Ordway</name>, "it hapned they had Some whiskey with them to revive their Spirits."</p>
               <p>
Dwindling food supplies were another worry. Not having heard from <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard's</name> hunters for two weeks, the captains sent a "frenchman" (<name type="person" key="Lepage, Jean Baptiste">Baptiste Lepage</name>?) downstream to look for the missing men. The next day, just as the cooks were dipping into their reserves of salt pork, the searcher reappeared with <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name> and word the hunters were stalled thirty miles below. Drift ice had damaged the prow of the pirogue and rowing was almost impossible. The captains responded by sending back a tow rope and enough tin to sheathe the boat's prow. On November 19 the pirogue returned, laden with the dressed carcasses of thirty-two deer, eleven elk, and five buffalo. Considering the rate at which the party consumed meat, the supply would last about three weeks, yet they cooked up enough the next day to provide a feast for several Indians who heard the good news and appeared with grins of anticipation. They also sent <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Sergeant Pryor</name> to <name type="place" key="Mitutanka (Matootonha) village">Matootonha</name> to swap trade goods for corn that could be used to stretch out the supply.<ref target="n0910" n="10"/>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>
On the day the ice started flowing in the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, <name type="person" key="Black Cat (Posecopsahe)">Black Cat</name>, head man of <name type="place" key="Ruptáre (Rooptahee) village">Rooptahee</name>, brought an <name type="native_nation" key="Assiniboine Indians">Assiniboin</name> chief and seven "men of note" to the fort to meet the captains. Mindful that the <name type="native_nation" key="Assiniboine Indians">Assiniboin</name> tribe ranged mostly on British soil, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> refrained from giving the chief an American medal or an American flag but substituted a length of gold braid plucked from the storehouse's supply of ribbons—or perhaps from his or <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> dress uniform. The gift pleased the fellow, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> wrote afterward—but, he added, the group as a whole was a surly lot, as was to be expected, since they were related to the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>.<ref target="n0911" n="11"/>
               </p>
               <p>
For a few days following the <name type="native_nation" key="Assiniboine Indians">Assiniboin</name> visit, not a <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> appeared at the fort. On the 18th, <name type="person" key="Black Cat (Posecopsahe)">Black Cat</name> arrived with an explanation. The time had been filled with a huge festival to cement trade relations among the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>, <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name>, seventy lodges of visiting <name type="native_nation" key="Assiniboine Indians">Assiniboins</name>, and a few of their associates, the <name type="native_nation" key="Cree Indians">Crees</name>. During the celebration the <name type="native_nation" key="Assiniboine Indians">Assiniboins</name> had publicly mocked the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name> for their friendliness with the Americans. Did the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri 
River</name> Indians suppose they could really get merchandise from southern sources? Hadn't another white man, <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">John Evans</name>, made similar promises eight years ago, only to leave and never return? Stick with us, the <name type="native_nation" key="Assiniboine Indians">Assiniboins</name> said. We and the <name type="native_nation" key="Cree Indians">Crees</name> will buy your vegetables and your horses with our dried meat and leather and with guns and brass kettles and cloth we obtain from the traders in the north. Stay with us, your best suppliers. Or take the consequences.</p>
               <p>
The high-pressure salesmanship upset the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name> so much that they held council to discuss alternatives. Should they retain their <name type="native_nation" key="Assiniboine Indians">Assiniboin</name> connections by turning their backs on the Americans? Or should they risk <name type="native_nation" key="Assiniboine Indians">Assiniboin</name> retaliation by opening their ears to the promises of these energetic men from the south?</p>
               <p>
Though no consensus had been reached at the meetings, it was clear the American program was in trouble.<ref target="n0912" n="12"/> If bullying from nomadic tribes made all the village Indians cower—and how reminiscent of the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>-<name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> situation this was!—the river might end up not only being closed to American trade but also to American use as a main section of the route to the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>.</p>
               <p>
What to do? Lamely the captains told <name type="person" key="Black Cat (Posecopsahe)">Black Cat</name> his people certainly could believe the American promise of bringing a rich trade to the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>. Developing the necessary procedures would take time, but if the Indians were loyal, so would the Great Father be.</p>
               <p>
The talk placated <name type="person" key="Black Cat (Posecopsahe)">Black Cat</name>, who was friendly already. But what of the <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name>, with whom the Corps had had very little contact during the push to complete the fort and provision it with meat? Those chores were finished now except for building a stockade across the open end of the stronghold, and the explorers could return to the murky waters of diplomacy.</p>
               <p>
Treating with the <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name> fell to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>. Off he went on November 25, with <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name> and <name type="person" key="Jusseaume, René">Jessaume</name> as interpreters and six riflemen under <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Sergeant Ordway</name> as a guard. Somehow—journal details are often exasperatingly sparse—they got a pirogue across the ice-choked river. Somewhere <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and the interpreters obtained horses for riding along the snowy, wind-swept terraces to the <name type="place" key="Knife River">Knife River</name> communities. <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway's</name> detail walked; horses 
were expensive even to rent, and with the long journey to the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name> looming ahead, the captains were reluctant to expend the trade goods that were their only currency.</p>
               <p>
Results of the errand were mixed.<ref target="n0913" n="13"/> The party was able to find shelter at the middle <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> village, <name type="place" key="Metaharte (Metehartar) village">Metaharte</name>, partly because that was where <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name> and <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name> had lived before moving to <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name>. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> held productive talks there with <name type="person" key="Black Moccasin (Omp-se-ha-ra)">Black Moccasin</name>, the man <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> and he had recognized a month earlier as the head man of the town. He counciled with chiefs in the other two towns, some of whom seemed reluctant to take his gifts, and he won a bland promise from certain influential warriors not to go to war any more with their accustomed quarry, the <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name> of the mountains.</p>
               <p>
As the weather turned stormy on the 26th and 27th, so did negotiations. One chief, the <name type="person" key="Horned Weasel (Maw-pah'-pir-re-cos-sa-too)">Horned Weasel</name>, declined to see the Americans. And there is no record that <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> tried to contact <name type="person" key="Le Borgne (One Eye)">Le Borgne</name> and other principal men of <name type="place" key="Big Hidatsa site">Big Hidatsa village</name>. What really jarred him were rumors of <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> duplicity. Their conniving was based on tales brought to the villages by Indian travelers: the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name> planned an attack on the <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name> for having entered into an alliance with the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name>. The Americans, the account went on, planned to join the war on the side of the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>. Why else had they built so strong a fort while talking so earnestly of peace? Why else had <name type="person" key="Jusseaume, René">Jessaume</name> and <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name> and their families, one-time residents among the <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name>, moved into the stronghold, if not for the sake of being safe when the battles erupted? And what of that other long-term trader with the <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name>, <name type="person" key="La Franch, Baptiste">Baptiste La France</name>? He had just arrived on the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> with a small party of North West Company men and was popping off with scurrilous 
remarks about the Americans, each time adding that the Britons were the <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas'</name> only true friends. Why would he say such things?</p>
               <p>
The reasons seemed clear to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> interpreters. The <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> villages, located farther down the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> than the <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas'</name>, were in a good geographic position to capture whatever trade began moving up the river from the south. If the <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name> became enemies of the Americans, the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>' chances of taking over the role of middlemen for the new commerce improved in direct proportion. <name type="person" key="La France, Baptiste">Baptiste La France</name>, having sniffed out the way the wind was blowing, was trying to improve the North West Company's standing with the <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name> by joining the anti-American chorus.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> countered vigorously. He prevailed on two, perhaps more, important <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> chiefs and several warriors to return with him through the snow to the fort and with their own eyes and ears measure its friendliness toward all the villages, <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>. (He did not know that at that very moment a small group of <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name> were at <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name>, unable to talk to <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> because, ironically, the interpreters were with <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>.)<ref target="n0914" n="14"/> And <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> had a chance to speak his mind directly to the Nor'Westers. While riding between towns, he bumped first into the clerk, or second-in-command, of the small party, <name type="person" key="McKenzie, Charles">Charles McKenzie</name>. What they talked about is not of record, but <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> stiffness may account for <name type="person" key="McKenzie, Charles">McKenzie's</name> later remark in his journal that the captain was prejudiced against the British. Next <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> encountered, at <name type="person" key="Black Cat (Posecopsahe)">Black Cat's</name> village, the head man himself, <name type="person" key="Laroque, François-Antoine">François-Antoine Laroque</name>. Well educated and affable, Laroque was only twenty. (His birthday was August 18, one day ahead of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>, who was then thirty-one.) He had not yet heard of the Louisiana Purchase. At the time of his departure from his base on the <name type="place" key="Assiniboine (Ossiniboine) River">Assiniboine River</name>, <name type="person" key="McCracken, Hugh">Hugh McCracken</name> had not yet arrived with <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> carefully polite letter to the district manager, <name type="person" key="Chaboillez, Charles">Charles Chaboillez</name>. Even so, Laroque was prepared to be cooperative. He was eager that this, his first major assignment, go well—a hope that depended in part on enlisting <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name> as interpreter. But <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name>, he had learned on reaching the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, was with the Americans, though not actually with <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> right then, for apparently the interpreter had ridden on to the fort while the captain paused to talk to <name type="person" key="Black Cat (Posecopsahe)">Black Cat</name>. It was in the chief's lodge that the Canadian asked to "borrow" <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name> until his commerce was launched. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> agreed and invited the young man to dine at the fort with <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, the <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> chiefs, and him the next evening, November 28. His prejudices, if any, obviously did not blind him to the advantages of amiability.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Laroque, François-Antoine">Laroque</name> missed the date. He waited in <name type="person" key="Black Cat (Posecopsahe)">Black Cat's</name> lodge for <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name> to show up, but it was snowing hard and the interpreter did not appear. So the next day <name type="person" key="Laroque, François-Antoine">Laroque</name> rode down to the fort to collar the fellow. There he walked into a chill that matched the weather's. From some unnamed source the captains had heard that the North West people carried British flags and medals for distribution among the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri River</name> Indians. Crisply <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> told the Canadian to refrain while he was on American soil. The Indians, they added, had been warned to reject any and all tokens of British sovereignty.</p>
               <p>
The nonplussed trader said his party had neither medals nor flags with them and hence no intentions of handing any out. His earnestness restored accord, and he was allowed to borrow <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name>, as arranged earlier, whenever the man's services were not needed by the Americans. With this proviso: the interpreter was not to be asked to translate remarks in any way derogatory to the new owners of <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name> Territory. And then the captains explained what their aims on the upper <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> were. Science and the finding of a usable route to the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>, yes. But there was more—an alliance of the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>, <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name>, and <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> against the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name> that would benefit everyone's trade. For of course British subjects had a treaty right to trade south of the border if they obeyed the same regulations under which Americans operated—no liquor, no following the Indians out to their hunting camps, and so on. In the future, moreover, the United States government might extend its own trading houses up the river in order to make sure the Indians were not gouged by grasping traders from any nation.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Laroque, François-Antoine">Laroque's</name> observations, if any, were not recorded. They would have been interesting, for though he was young he was not naive. After the conversations, he wrote dryly in his journal, "During the time I was there a very grand plan was schemed, but its being realized is more than I can tell, although the Captains say they are well assured it will."<ref target="n0915" n="15"/>
               </p>
               <p>
As <name type="person" key="Laroque, François-Antoine">Laroque</name> and his clerk, <name type="person" key="McKenzie, Charles">Charles McKenzie</name>, would soon learn, there was reason to be skeptical about the plan. The <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name> were not as convinced that joining a U.S.-sponsored alliance would be useful. What seemed to them <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> excessive boasting about the power of the distant Great Father had turned them off. Several chiefs, fearing that there might be harmful medicine in the medals and certificates that were presented to them, had given the symbols away. They felt, too, that the visitors were incompetent, except for the blacksmith and the mender of guns. They wondered why the Americans, who talked about great riches, had not brought more gifts, trade goods, and ammunition with them in their big boats. And if the Americans thought that young <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> warriors would abandon the fighting through which they gained recognition, they were ill informed indeed.</p>
               <p>
One development turned out to be more than gossip. A little after sunrise on November 30, a <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> from <name type="place" key="Mitutanka (Matootonha) village">Matootonha</name> yelled across the river that he had news for the Americans. After a pirogue had battled through the ice to reach him, he apologized; the river by the village was frozen solid and he had supposed it would be frozen here as well. Anyway, he had been sent to tell the captains that a roaming party of <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name>—there was no 
mistaking the emphasis on <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name>
                  </hi>—had surprised five <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name> hunting buffalo on the plains eight leagues to the southwest. The attackers had killed one hunter, wounded two, and made off with nine horses.</p>
               <p>
Here, the captains thought, was a chance to replace words with action. Let a party of volunteers march to <name type="place" key="Mitutanka (Matootonha) village">Matootonha</name>, consult with <name type="person" key="Big White (Sheheke)">Big White</name> and the other chiefs there, and if hostile attack seemed imminent join with warriors from all the villages and engage the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>—those damnable <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>. Though the strategy seems fitted to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> impulsive nature, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> apparently was its originator.<ref target="n0916" n="16"/> And because <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> had only recently returned from the long, snowy, exhausting ride to the <name type="place" key="Knife River">Knife River</name> villages, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> led this foray.</p>
               <p>
Within an hour twenty-three men, including both <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name> and <name type="person" key="Jusseaume, René">Jessaume</name>, had been ferried to the timbered bottomland on the far side of the river. There <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> spread the men out in skirmish formation and advanced, with a good deal of floundering, through thick brush and foot-deep snow toward the terrace bluff. After scrambling up that, they swung across open ground toward the town. The sudden appearance of so large a group in military formation alarmed the Indians. To calm the excited people, <name type="person" key="Big White (Sheheke)">Big White</name> and a delegation of other chiefs wrapped themselves in buffalo robes and walked out to discover what was afoot. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> explained. They wanted to help the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name> chastise the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name> "for taking the blood of our dutifull children."</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Big White (Sheheke)">Big White</name> said the matter needed discussion and invited the soldiers to divide into small groups and make themselves at home in different lodges, resting and eating while the leaders talked. To <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, what followed was total anticlimax. The chiefs insisted the murderers could not be overtaken on the snowy plains; vengeance would have to wait for spring. Recriminations erupted next. A chief called <name type="person" key="Big Man (Oh-he-nar)">Big Man</name> blamed the Americans for the tragedy by saying that the injured party, believing peace had been achieved, had gone onto the plains with a recklessly small group and had paid the price. The <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> might talk peace, but in reality they had always been liars and aggressors.</p>
               <p>
To keep <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> and his grand plan from crumbling then and there, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> drew on all the persuasiveness he possessed. The snowstorm was unfortunate, he said, for the Americans wanted to show tribes everywhere what would happen to those who were foolish enough to harm the Great Father's allies. Also, it was wrong to blame all <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> for the actions of a few. Those few clearly had felt they must follow the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux's</name> bad advice in order to get firearms and ammunition from them. <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name> should understand that kind of pressure. Didn't they have to stay on good terms with the <name type="native_nation" key="Assiniboine Indians">Assiniboins</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Cree Indians">Crees</name> to obtain what those middlemen brought them? But as soon as American goods were flowing up the river and the villagers lived under American protection, the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name> and the <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name> could become independent people at last.<ref target="n0917" n="17"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Had he made his point? He hoped so. The <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name> fed the soldiers liberally and expressed polite thanks for the Americans' concern. Taking as much satisfaction from that as he could, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> gathered his detachment together, paraded them through the village plaza, and then crossed the ice to the other shore. As the cold descended—that night the Corps's thermometer dropped below zero for the first time—they slogged back through brush and drifted snow to the fort. "Verry fatigueing," <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> summed up the experience after passing out extra measures of cheap rum to the men.</p>
               <p>
Fatiguing—and worrisome. Hoping to learn what was really going on down the river, the captains found a messenger who was willing to ride to the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> villages with a letter for <name type="person" key="Tabeau, Pierre-Antoine">Tabeau</name>. What was the situation there—and would the trader please do all he could to hold the grand alliance together?</p>
               <p>
On the personal level there was more warmth. Three days after the fiasco, the father and brother of the man the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name> had slain appeared at the fort with gifts of dried pumpkin and pemmican. The village chiefs might believe privately that the American offer to lead a winter pursuit of the murderers was stupid, but in the minds of the those most concerned, the interest had "produced a grateful respect . . . which pleased us very much."<ref target="n0918" n="18"/>
               </p>
               <p>
And on that note the Corps settled down to the arduous tasks of surviving the present while preparing for the future.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="notes" type="notes">
            <head rend="center">Notes</head>
            <div type="section">
               <note xml:id="n0901" n="1">Osgood, Field Notes, 169. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> omitted his denigration of <name type="person" key="Jusseaume, René">Jessaume</name> in his official journal. <name type="person" key="Henry, Alexander">Alexander Henry</name>, who encountered <name type="person" key="Jusseaume, René">Jessaume</name> in 1806, was also unfavorably impressed. Coues, 333.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0902" n="2">For the names of the tribes and the villages they inhabited—more names than I have given—consult <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> notes to <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name> in Jackson, <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, II, 522, 524–25. See also Hodge under "<name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>," "<name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name>," etc., and Ronda, 67–70. <name type="person" key="Henry, Alexander">Henry</name> gives the locations of the villages in Coues, 322–24. <name type="person" key="Thompson, John B.">Thompson</name>, Narrative, 169n, says the towns were scattered along eleven and a half miles of the riverbank. Perhaps so as the river curved, but the distance from the lowest <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> village, <name type="place" key="Mitutanka (Matootonha) village">Matootonha</name>, to <name type="place" key="Big Hidatsa site">Big Hidatsa</name> could not have been much more than six miles in a direct line by land. The maps in Ronda, 68, and Appleman, 238–39, do not agree with <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> map as reproduced in Moulton, <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>, plates 29 and 61. I have followed <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0903" n="3">I, 210–13.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0904" n="4">Jackson, Letters, 213–14. For American licensing provisions under Jay's Treaty: Phillips, II, 73–74, and Jackson, <name type="person" key="Pike, Zebulon Montgomery">Zebulon Pike</name>, 1, 256. In spite of Jay's Treaty, foreign traders were excluded from the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> in 1805. (Jackson, <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, 256–57.) The sentiment that led to the exclusion must have been noticeable in <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> when <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> were studying trade problems there.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0905" n="5">Although Bernard DeVoto says flatly that four of the French boatmen headed downstream in November, other students of the expedition are content to say their exact numbers cannot be determined. The issue is 
confused by two French trappers who met the Corps on its way upstream and continued to the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name> with the American boats, hoping to recover some traps and furs the Indians had taken from them. DeVoto, <hi rend="italic">Journals</hi>, 63 n. 4. Appleman, 367, 368 nn. 64, 66, 74. Jackson, <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, 237 n. 7.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0906" n="6">For the spellings and their meanings: Jackson, Letters, 316n; Appleman, 115–17. I follow Kenneth O. Owens, "<name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name>," in Lamar, 1055, for her age.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0907" n="7">Cutright, Pioneering Naturalists, 110.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0908" n="8">I, 218. For the fort in general: <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>, 113; Wood and Thiessen, 143; and the appropriate sections in Moulton, <hi rend="italic">Journals</hi>, III.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0909" n="9">Every day someone checked the expedition's thermometers at sunrise and at 4:00 P.M. The readings were relayed to the captains, who recorded the figures in their weather journals, along with data about wind, precipitation, cloudiness, etc. A line of remarks followed most weather entries. The data are reproduced by the month in Moulton's edition of the journals, and are collected in a single entry and printed as an appendix in <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>, III, 846–89.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0910" n="10">I, 222ff. Osgood, <hi rend="italic">Field Notes</hi>, 178. VII, 69. <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> in Quaife, 164–66. <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse</name> counts the spoils as 34 deer, 10 elk, 5 buffalo; <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> as 30 deer, 11 elk, 5 buffalo.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0911" n="11">Osgood, <hi rend="italic">Field Notes</hi>, 174n. Moulton, <hi rend="italic">Journals</hi>, III, 234. VI, 104.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0912" n="12">Ronda, 89–90. Osgood, Field Notes, 176–77.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0913" n="13">For <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> diplomatic adventure: 1, 227–29; Moulton, <hi rend="italic">Journals</hi>, III, 241–49, passim.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0914" n="14">I, 226.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0915" n="15">
                  <name type="person" key="Laroque, François-Antoine">Laroque</name>, reprinted in Wood and Thiessen, 137, 140. Also <name type="person" key="McKenzie, Charles">Charles McKenzie</name>, "Narrative," in ibid., 232–38; Coues, 349–50.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0916" n="16">I, 229. <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> in Quaife, 168.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0917" n="17">I, 230–32.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0918" n="18">
                  <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>, 121.</note>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.lavender.01.08" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.lavender.01.00" type="contents"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.lavender.01.10" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
