<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.sup.danisi.01">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">Western Historical Quarterly 35 (Spring 2004): 53–72. Copyright © 2004, Western History Association.)</title>
            <title type="sub">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>'s Route Map: <name type="person" key="MacKay, James">James MacKay</name>'s Map of the Missouri River</title>
            <author>
               <name type="person" key="Danisi, Thomas C.">Thomas C. Danisi</name> and <name type="person" key="Wood, W. Raymond">W. Raymond Wood</name>
            </author>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               
               
               
               
               
               <addrLine>eburke3@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
              <term>Texts</term>
            </keywords>
           <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
             <term>Articles</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-1-07</date>
            <name>Beth Burke</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="main">
            <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>'s Route Map: <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">James MacKay</name>'s Map of the Missouri River</head>
         <p>
            <name type="person" key="Danisi, Thomas C.">Thomas C. Danisi</name> and <name type="person" key="Wood, W. Raymond">
               <ref target="http://rcp.missouri.edu/raywood/index.html">W. Raymond Wood</ref>
            </name>
         </p>
         <p>(This article first appeared in the <hi rend="italic">
               <ref target="http://www.usu.edu/history/whq/">Western Historical Quarterly</ref>
            </hi> 35 (Spring 2004): 53–72. Copyright © 2004, Western History Association.)</p>
         <p>New evidence reveals that the author of the 1797 Indian Office Map was <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">James MacKay</name>, leader of the third Missouri Company expedition up the Missouri River. It probably was transmitted to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> when <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay </name>accepted a covert invitation by <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Private Joseph Field</name> to visit Camp Dubois in 1804.</p>
         <p>Nueva evidencia revela que el autor del Mapa de la Officina de los Indios (Indian Office Map) de 1797 fue <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">James McKay</name>, lider de la tercera expedicion de la Comania de Missouri (Missouri Company) por el Rio de Missouri. Este mapa fue probablemente transmitido a <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> y <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> cuando<name type="person" key="McKay, James"> McKay</name> acepto una invitació n secreta para visitar el Campamento Dubois hecha por el Soldado <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">(Private) Joseph Field</name> en 1804.</p>
         <p>Maps, no less than narratives, are among our most basic documents, and when they are examined carefully they shed great light on the time line of history and reveal the growth of knowledge as well as the progress of human endeavors. A history without maps is inconceivable.</p>
         <p>Thus, a crucial aspect in the planning of the single most important exploration in American history, that of <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Thomas Jefferson's</name> Corps of Discovery, the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition, was to obtain reliable maps to chart their route.</p>
         <p>How did <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> do this?</p>
         <p>The answer to the captains' success in finding a viable map of the Upper Missouri River is to be found in the story of cartographer <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">James MacKay</name>, a Scotsman who, based on his extensive trading with the Indians in Canada, and on his proficiency in map—making and experience in surveying, had been hired to lead the Spanish expedition up to the Missouri in Louisiana territory.</p>
         <p>A superficial look at history would indicate that <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name> was only one small player in the international intrigue of land and economic disputes in the late–eighteenth and early–nineteenth centuries. It would suggest that the handwriting on the map, in both French and English, proved that <name type="person" key="Evans, John">John Evans </name>(<name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay's</name> field assistant) and <name type="person" key="De Finiels, Nicolas">Nicolas De Finiels</name> (a Frenchman who assisted <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name> and others in various cartographic efforts) contributed to the actual drawing of the map–which is now known as the Indian Office Map.</p>
         <p>But, a cursory look at history, as always, can be misleading. It is true that it was <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">John Evans</name> who, on that 1795 expedition, traveled the Upper Missouri River to the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>, while <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name> remained in Fort Charles–795 miles above St. Louis–and it is logical to think, since it was <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name> who explored the Upper Missouri, that he would have been the one to draw the map. Also, there did exist at the time an international aspect of cooperation: <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name>, <name type="person" key="Evans, John">Evans</name>, <name type="person" key="Soulard, Antoine">Antoine Soulard</name> (surveyor general of Upper Louisiana) and <name type="person" key="De Finiels, Nicolas">De Finiels</name> all assisted one another on cartographic efforts. It is perhaps because of this, combined with <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name>'s explorations on the Upper Missouri that historians have denied <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name>'s role as the primary draftsman of the Missouri River map. The truth is to be found in detailed detective work.</p>
         <p>The story begins in the 1790s. At that time, Louisiana encompassed a huge swath of country west of the Mississippi, and distant European powers lacked the means to populate it or patrol its borders. (See Figure 1.) When Spain took control of the region in 1762, British traders in Canada had already begun establishing alliances with the various Indian nations along Louisiana's northern boundary. These alliances enabled the British to make deep forays into Spanish territory without fear of reprisal. It proved very difficult for Spain to wrest control from the British. Beginning in 1789, a few hunters, including <name type="person" key="Munier, Juan">Juan Munier</name> and <name type="person" key="Garreau, Joseph">Joseph Garreau</name>, were the first Spanish to explore the Missouri. <name type="person" key="D'Eglise, Jacques">Jacques D'Eglise</name> followed a year later. These men reported that the British had been stealing the trade from the Spanish and were underselling them in their own territory. Something had to be done and quickly: the Spanish would have to ascend the Missouri, establish relations with the Indian tribes, and somehow win them over from the British.<ref target="nlc.danisi.0101" n="1"/> In 1791, Spain appointed as governor general of Louisiana the <name type="person" key="Carondelet, Baron de">Baron de Carondelet</name>. One of <name type="person" key="Carondelet, Baron de">Carondelet</name>'s first decrees was to throw open the trade to all subjects of <name type="person" key="Carlos IV">His Catholic Majesty, Carlos IV</name>. In that year, Spain learned that the British had established a trading alliance with the river tribes on the Upper Missouri, and, if war broke out, the Spanish would lose control of that river. While <name type="person" key="Carondelet, Baron de">Carondelet</name>'s decree offered advantages, the Indians had already become allied with the British and thus discouraged Spanish traders from going upriver. This development demanded a strategic plan and, in 1793, a group of St. Louis traders formed the "Company of Explorers of the Upper Missouri," pooling their resources to finance well—equipped expeditions. While the financing appeared to come easily, finding suitable persons to lead the expedition proved challenging. The first two expeditions, led by <name type="person" key="Truteau, Jean Baptiste">Jean Baptiste Truteau </name>and a man named <name type="person" key="Lecuyer">Lecuyer</name>, made little progress on the Missouri.<ref target="nlc.danisi.0102" n="2"/>  However, in choosing <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">James MacKay</name> to lead the third expedition in 1795, the traders found a well—prepared and uniquely talented man.</p>
         <p>
            <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name> arrived in Canada some time in 1776–1777, and for the next five years his whereabouts are unknown. In 1783, the British traders <name type="person" key="Holmes">Holmes</name> and <name type="person" key="Grant, Robert">Grant</name> hired him. <name type="person" key="Grant, Robert">Robert Grant</name>, an experienced trader from Montreal associated with the North West Company took him to Grand Portage, the rendezvous for Canadian traders on the north shore of Lake Superior.<ref target="nlc.danisi.0103" n="3"/>
         </p>
         <p>Two years later <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name> was released to go to the Saskatchewan River as a clerk, but he was back on the Assiniboine River for the winter 1786–1787. On returning to <name type="person" key="Grant, Robert">Grant</name> in 1787, he was given an opportunity to travel overland to the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> villages on the Missouri River.<ref target="nlc.danisi.0104" n="4"/> That overland journey was usually made during the winter using dog trains to haul small outfits and bring back peltry and foodstuffs, especially corn. When his contract ended in 1788, <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name> went back to Montreal with the returning canoes. Relations with the Canadian traders soured, however, and he left for the United States, where he renewed association with his brother, <name type="person" key="Mackay, John">John</name>, in New York City, and began trading in the United States. In June 1789, <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name> met with <name type="person" key="Gardoqui, Don Diego">Don Diego Gardoqui</name>, the Spanish chargé  in New York City and presented him with a map, "a su modo" of the British—Canadian trade.<ref target="nlc.danisi.0105" n="5"/>
         </p>
         <p>
            <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name> started a fur—trading partnership with depots in Cahokia, Cincinnati, and New York City.<ref target="nlc.danisi.0106" n="6"/> He had arrived in Cahokia by September 1791 and established a name by 1793. On 20 May 1793, <name type="person" key="Trudeau, Zenon">Zenon Trudeau</name>, lieutenant governor of Upper Louisiana, wrote to <name type="person" key="Carondelet, Baron de">Baron de Carondelet</name>, governor general of Louisiana, that he hoped "to see within a few days a well informed Canadian mozo [young man]" who had been trading with the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> nation. He hoped to obtain from him information on the British among those Indians.<ref target="nlc.danisi.0107" n="7"/>
            <name type="person" key="Trudeau, Zenon">Trudeau</name> and <name type="person" key="Clamorgan, Jacques">Jacques Clamorgan</name>, director of the St. Louis—based fur—trading Missouri Company, were so impressed with <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name>'s abilities––to make maps, to write and speak the French language, and to trade with a variety of Indian tribes–that they hired him to head an expedition up the Missouri for the company. <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name> then left Spanish Louisiana to conclude his business in New York and Cincinnati.<ref target="nlc.danisi.0108" n="8"/>
         </p>
         <p>Two other notable men arrived in Spanish Louisiana at about the same time as <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name>: <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">John Thomas Evans</name> and <name type="person" key="Soulard, Antoine">Antoine Pierre Soulard</name>. <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name> had come to the United States looking for a tribe of<name type="native_nation" key="Welsh Indians"> Welsh</name> Indians he thought might be the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>. On 10 October 1792 he arrived in Baltimore, where he stayed and worked for various Welshmen. In March 1794, he departed by boat and landed in New Madrid [present—day Missouri] about two months later. Upon entering Spanish domains, he took the oath of allegiance that the commandant, <name type="person" key="Porten, Thomas">Thomas Porten</name>, forced on all newcomers. It appears that <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name> contracted malaria and stayed with a Welsh couple in New Madrid before he continued on toward St. Louis. On the way to St. Louis, <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name> became lost and finally turned up at a Spanish post opposite Kaskaskia, deranged from the summer heat. Fortunately, he met another Welshman, the lawyer <name type="person" key="Jones, John Rice">John Rice Jones</name>, who took care of him on the Illinois side of the river.<ref target="nlc.danisi.0109" n="9"/> A month later, <name type="person" key="Jones, John Rice">Jones</name> introduced him to a Cahokia merchant and court clerk, <name type="person" key="Arundel, William">William Arundel</name>. <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name> stayed at <name type="person" key="Arundel, William">Arundel</name>'s home until Christmas 1794, when he learned about <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">James MacKay</name>'s forthcoming expedition up the Missouri River and left for St. Louis, hoping to join.<ref target="nlc.danisi.0110" n="10"/> It was an inopportune time for <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name> to go to St. Louis. War with Britain was imminent and explaining to <name type="person" key="Trudeau, Zenon">Zenon Trudeau</name>, the lieutenant governor, that he was on a quest to find a tribe of <name type="native_nation" key="Welsh Indians">Welsh</name> Indians must have sounded preposterous to the highest ranking official in Upper Louisiana. Suspicious of British spies entering Spanish country, <name type="person" key="Trudeau, Zenon">Trudeau</name> had <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name> "[i]mprisoned, loaded with iron and put in the Stoks . . . in the dead of winter."<ref target="nlc.danisi.0111" n="11"/>
         </p>
         <p>A few months after<name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas"> Evans</name> was thrown in jail, in February 1794, <name type="person" key="Soulard, Antoine">Antoine Soulard</name> arrived at Ste. Genevieve.<ref target="nlc.danisi.0112" n="12"/> The commandant of New Bourbon, <name type="person" key="De Luzié res, Pierre Delassus">Pierre Delassus de Luzié res</name>, knew <name type="person" key="Soulard, Antoine">Soulard</name> because he had deserted the naval service at Martinique, France, with one of <name type="person" key="De Luzié res, Pierre Delassus">De Luzié res</name>'s sons. This son had told <name type="person" key="De Luzié res, Pierre Delassus">De Luzié res</name> that the two had not wished to recognize the French Republic as their home and had decided to join the family in America.<ref target="nlc.danisi.0113" n="13"/> The commandant of Ste. Genevieve had fears that Kentuckians might attack Louisiana. With no defenses in the village, <name type="person" key="Soulard, Antoine">Soulard </name>volunteered to help and began "directing the works on the fort" according to the "plans and sketches" of a Flemish engineer, <name type="person" key="Vandenbenden, Louis">Louis Vandenbenden</name>.<ref target="nlc.danisi.0114" n="14"/>The work was completed quickly, and <name type="person" key="Trudeau, Zenon">Trudeau</name> summoned <name type="person" key="Soulard, Antoine">Soulard</name> to St. Louis, who arrived there by 20 March.<ref target="nlc.danisi.0115" n="15"/>
         </p>
         <p>In August of that same year, <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name> had gone to Cincinnati to conclude his partnership in his eastern business interests with <name type="person" key="Robertson, John">John Robertson</name>. While in Cincinnati, <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name> met with <name type="person" key="Rees, John">John Rees</name>, or Rhys, a native of Wales, who told him of <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name>'s quest for <name type="native_nation" key="Welsh Indians">Welsh</name> Indians and gave him a small dictionary of <name type="native_nation" key="Welsh Indians">Welsh</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> vocabulary. <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name> had been among the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans </name>in 1787 but "had heard nothing of a <name type="native_nation" key="Welsh Indians">Welch</name> tribe. . . ." When <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name> arrived in St. Louis a few weeks later, he "sent for, &amp;  engaged for [his] assistant <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Mr. Evans</name> who spoke and wrote the Welch language with facility...."<ref target="nlc.danisi.0116" n="16"/>
            <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name>, realizing that <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name> could be an asset to the expedition, decided to employ him as his lieutenant and field operator.</p>
         <p>The story of the <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name> map of the Missouri River begins when the first expedition for the Missouri Company, headed by <name type="person" key="Truteau, Jean Baptiste">Jean Baptiste Truteau</name>, a schoolmaster, left St. Louis on 7 June 1794. <name type="person" key="Clamorgan, Jacques">Clamorgan</name> had provided <name type="person" key="Truteau, Jean Baptiste">Truteau</name> with a plan or idea so "that he may know his whereabouts."<ref target="nlc.danisi.0117" n="17"/> The north half of this plan, taken directly from <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name>'s travels in Canada in 1784 through 1788, was the first of its kind and gave a tactical view of where the British traders had encroached upon Spanish soil.<ref target="nlc.danisi.0118" n="18"/> When <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name> first met <name type="person" key="Trudeau, Zenon">Zenon Trudeau</name> and <name type="person" key="Clamorgan, Jacques">Jacques Clamorgan</name> in May 1793, he had shown them this "topographical idea of the Upper Mississippi and Missouri."<ref target="nlc.danisi.0119" n="19"/>
            <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name> had met with <name type="person" key="Soulard, Antoine">Soulard</name> to help produce a map for <name type="person" key="Carondelet, Baron de">Carondelet</name>. <name type="person" key="Trudeau, Zenon">Trudeau</name> wrote to <name type="person" key="Carondelet, Baron de">Carondelet</name> on 24 November 1794, stating that he was remitting some maps drawn by <name type="person" key="Soulard, Antoine">Soulard</name> "among which was a map of the Missouri river."<ref target="nlc.danisi.0120" n="20"/>
            <name type="person" key="Trudeau, Zenon">Trudeau</name>'s admission of a <name type="person" key="Soulard, Antoine">Soulard</name> map is interesting; <name type="person" key="Soulard, Antoine">Soulard</name> could not have completed it by himself, because during the summer and autumn months that year he suffered bouts of "most violent fever" and "would have succumbed," except that <name type="person" key="Trudeau, Zenon">Trudeau</name> and his wife took care of him.<ref target="nlc.danisi.0121" n="21"/> In other words, being so ill, <name type="person" key="Soulard, Antoine">Soulard</name>, who had not been on the Upper Missouri River, could only have completed a map of the river with <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name>'s assistance, because <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name> had visited the Upper Missouri River. Nonetheless, <name type="person" key="Trudeau, Zenon">Trudeau</name> recommended that <name type="person" key="Soulard, Antoine">Soulard</name> serve as the surveyor of Upper Louisiana, and in December, <name type="person" key="Soulard, Antoine">Soulard</name> made a voyage to New Orleans where he was appointed surveyor general on 3 February 1795.<ref target="nlc.danisi.0122" n="22"/>
         </p>
         <p>Between January and August 1795, <name type="person" key="Soulard, Antoine">Soulard</name> began to survey land grants in St. Louis and Cape Girardeau, as well as drafting a large–scale map, "Ydea Topografica," of the Missouri River Basin.<ref target="nlc.danisi.0123" n="23"/> The original Spanish map is titled "A Topographical idea of the Upper Mississippi &amp;  Missouri that shows the progress of the Spanish Discovery of the Missouri river &amp;  the encroachments [or usurpations] of the English companies over the Spanish possessions."<ref target="nlc.danisi.0124" n="24"/> The French copy attributes its drawing to <name type="person" key="Soulard, Antoine">Soulard</name> who completed it in August 1795, though <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name> revised "Ydea Topografica" when he returned from his expedition in 1797.<ref target="nlc.danisi.0125" n="25"/>
            <name type="person" key="Soulard, Antoine">Soulard</name> wrote on 15 December of that year that the map was "corrected by one of the voyagers of the company of discovery," and that he would soon present a map of the Missouri to <name type="person" key="Lemos, Gayoso de">Gayoso de Lemos</name>, the new governor general of Louisiana, "much more correct than what I gave you earlier."<ref target="nlc.danisi.0126" n="26"/>
         </p>
         <p>Charting a river requires at least two people: the surveyor and the draftsman. The surveyor takes measurements and sketches landmarks like islands, bends in the river, and large trees, recording the field notes in a book, while the draftsman draws a grid and translates the measurements from the field notes into a diagram that represents the river. In 1795, charting a river required taking detailed astronomical observations to determine longitude and latitude, the critical east and west directions. <name type="person" key="Dunbar, William">William Dunbar</name>, who lived in Spanish Louisiana in the 1790s, had been hired by the Spanish as their astronomer. <name type="person" key="Dunbar, William">Dunbar</name> had advanced the science of astronomical observation further than any of the prominent group of Philadelphian astronomers had during this period by "requiring neither assistant nor time–piece."<ref target="nlc.danisi.0127" n="27"/>
            <name type="person" key="Dunbar, William">Dunbar</name> was able to reduce the complexity yet raise the bar for accuracy; however in 1795, <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">James MacKay</name> knew only one method and, by hiring <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name>, it presupposed that an assistant was mandatory.<ref target="nlc.danisi.0128" n="28"/>
         </p>
         <p>Near the end of August 1795, the third expedition for the Missouri Company left St. Louis with a number of objectives: to make a map ascertaining the northern boundary of the province, since no chart had been drawn nor evidence collected that verified the northern extent of Louisiana; to establish forts along the Missouri River; to reach the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name> in North Dakota; and to find a water route to the Pacific Ocean.<ref target="nlc.danisi.0129" n="29"/>
            <name type="person" key="Carondelet, Baron de">Governor Carondelet</name> was so pleased with the possibility of finding a water route that he offered a cash prize of 3000 piastres to the first Spanish subject who could penetrate to the Pacific Ocean via the Missouri River. He also promised to pay the salaries of one hundred men to guard the forts that <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name> would build along the route of that river.<ref target="nlc.danisi.0130" n="30"/> How such a complex expedition with so few resources was to achieve its goal is a mystery, but<name type="person" key="Mackay, James"> MacKay</name>, having been assured that the Missouri Company was well financed, embarked upon the exploration.</p>
         <p>The expedition arrived at the <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Omaha village</name> in Nebraska in mid—October and built Fort Charles, approximately twenty miles south of present—day Sioux City, Iowa. The <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Omaha</name> chief, <name type="person" key="Blackbird">Blackbird</name>, had the reputation of being both difficult and tyrannical. He demanded daily communication with <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name>. This meant that <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name> had to remain at the fort when<name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas"> Evans</name> left for the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name> at the end of November. <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name> realized that <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name> would have to continue the survey of the river on his own, and so <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name> taught <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name> with precision and gave him a comprehensive list of instructions:</p>
         <p>You will keep a journal of each day and month of the year to avoid any error in the observations of the important journey which you are undertaking. In your journal you will place all that will be remarkable in the country that you will traverse; likewise the route, distance, latitude and longitude, when you observe it, also the winds and weather. You will also keep another journal in which you will make note of all the ... territory . . . lakes; rivers; mountains; portages, with their extent and location.<ref target="nlc.danisi.0131" n="31"/>
         </p>
         <p>
            <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name> also wrote about the accuracy of the observations:</p>
         <p>In your route from here to the home of the <name type="native_nation" key="Ponca Indians">Ponca</name>, trace out as exactly as possible a general route and distance from the Missouri as well as the rivers which fall into it; and although you cannot take the direction of each turn and current of the Missouri, since you go by land, you can mark the general course of the mountains which will be parallel to each bank. You will observe the same thing for every other river (landmark) which you may see during your journey, whether river, lake, ocean, or chain of mountains which may effect your observations.<ref target="nlc.danisi.0132" n="32"/>
         </p>
         <p>
            <name type="person" key="Mackky, James">MacKay</name>, in effect, instructed <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name> on how to take a detailed set of field notes so that when he received them, he could continue updating the map of the Missouri River. <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name> also reminded <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name> that if he ran out of ink to "use the powder, and for want of powder, in the summer you will surely find some fruit whose juice can replace both."<ref target="nlc.danisi.0133" n="33"/> Clearly, the man who needed such orders written down could not have been the author of the map.</p>
         <p>
            <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name> also gave <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name> a supplemental set of instructions to ensure that <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name>'s observations, regardless of the distance between them, remain accurate. He wrote, "As I mean to make Sunday (being a remarkable day) the day for observing the distance of the moon from the sun I wish you to do the same when convenient so that we may be the better able to compare them when you return." He treated <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name> as a novice and his student. His instructions continued: "I will always make my observations when the sun is on the meridian which will of course give the just time of day. You may draw a meridian line by the north star if you should be a couple of days in one place &amp;  if the sky be clear at night if this cannot be you may take it by the compass if you know exactly the variation." He also told <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name> not to reveal his plans to anyone, including <name type="person" key="Truteau, Jean Baptiste">Truteau</name>, the leader of the first expedition.<ref target="nlc.danisi.0134" n="34"/>
         </p>
         <p>
            <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name> had sent a message to the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name> before <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name> left to notify them that an expedition was en route. A few weeks after <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name> left Fort Charles, his party came upon a band of <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name> who chased him for an entire day and were about to overtake him when night fell.<ref target="nlc.danisi.0135" n="35"/>
            <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name> returned to Fort Charles on 6 January 1796, although he left again on the twenty-eighth.<ref target="nlc.danisi.0136" n="36"/> It took him two months to reach the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> village–traveling seven hundred miles by water and then spending an additional six weeks to talk the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> into letting him journey onward.<ref target="nlc.danisi.0137" n="37"/> On 23 September, <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name> arrived at the lower <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> village, in present—day North Dakota, and found a fort built by the merchants of Montreal, that he named Fort Makay [<name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name>'s spelling]. Carrying a formal notice written by <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name>, <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name> ordered several British traders on 8 October to leave Spanish soil. The traders were surprised to learn that it was the same <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">James MacKay</name>, a former trader and friend, who was chasing them out of the territory.<ref target="nlc.danisi.0138" n="38"/>
         </p>
         <p>
            <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name> had assumed that supplies were forthcoming, but when none arrived and what he had at Fort Makay ran out, he departed for St. Louis. <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name>'s supplies were also depleted by March 1797, when <name type="person" key="Clamorgan, Jacques">Clamorgan</name> ordered him to return to St. Louis. <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name> arrived a few days before 13 May. <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name> arrived on 15 July. <name type="person" key="Trudeau, Zenon">Trudeau</name> wrote to <name type="person" key="Carondelet, Baron de">Carondelet</name> at the end of May, informing the governor that <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name> had arrived and had already completed a substantial section of the map–the first "three hundred and fifty leagues."<ref target="nlc.danisi.0139" n="39"/> (See Figure 2.) When <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name> returned from the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>, <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name> took the Upper Missouri River data and completed drafting the expedition map. He referred to several documents that were an integral part of the expedition: <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name>'s Table of Distances and the journals written by him and <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name>.<ref target="nlc.danisi.0140" n="40"/> The map employed the French language to designate the names of rivers and locations. <name type="person" key="Clamorgan, Jacques">Jacques Clamorgan</name>, on 14 October 1797, wrote about the map to <name type="person" key="Lopez, André">André Lopez</name>, the intendant at New Orleans:</p>
         <p>I am sending to the governor, the well—chartered map at the expenses and fees of the company. I hope that the company will take back its usual vigor without delay and that it will merit in the future by its zealousness and activity in making discoveries, the bounty of the government.<ref target="nlc.danisi.0141" n="41"/>
         </p>
         <p>Two months later, on 16 January 1798,<name type="person" key="Trudeau, Zenon"> Zenon Trudeau</name> informed <name type="person" key="Gayoso, Manuel de">Manuel de Gayoso</name>, governor general of Louisiana, that he was sending the river map and "a relació n," or record, of the voyage:</p>
         <p>I am enclosing to Your Excellency a relació n of the voyage which <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">M. Mackay</name> has made in the Upper Missouri, and the map of the said river, as far as the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> nation, made by the same person, which I believe to be the most exact of those which have been formed up to the present, since <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">M. Mackay </name>was instructed in the matter and knew that he had pledged himself to procure this map with careful attention for the government. Up to the present time the government had only [information] intellectually based upon the simple relació nes of the hunters.<ref target="nlc.danisi.0142" n="42"/>
         </p>
         <p>
            <name type="person" key="Trudeau, Zenon">Trudeau</name> wrote again to <name type="person" key="Gayoso, Manuel de">Gayoso</name> on 5 March 1798, explaining that <name type="person" key="Chouteau, Mr.">Chouteau</name> would deliver another copy of the map.</p>
         <p>I have spoken to you in different letters about <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">Mr. Mackay</name> and this would be a good occasion to let you meet/know him. Even if <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">Mr. Mackay</name> would not ask for the favor of being presented to you, I will take the liberty of asking you to look upon him with interest. I can assure you that he deserves it, and in a few days you are going to appreciate him as I and all persons that already know him do. Can <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">Mackay</name> meet with you to talk about the Missouri? He is the author of the map that <name type="person" key="Chouteau, Mr.">Mr. Chouteau</name> is going to give you.<ref target="nlc.danisi.0143" n="43"/>,</p>
         <p>
            <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay </name>had suggested to <name type="person" key="Trudeau, Zenon">Trudeau</name> that he would make another map of the Missouri more detailed than the one being sent with <name type="person" key="Chouteau, Mr.">Chouteau</name>. <name type="person" key="Trudeau, Zenon">Trudeau</name> wrote to <name type="person" key="Gayoso, Manuel de">Gayoso</name> speaking about <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name> and the maps, "He also has the intention [literally: ambition] of continuing to make another complete one, but the expenses will be too considerable to propose them to you.”<ref target="nlc.danisi.0144" n="44"/> As <name type="person" key="Trudeau, Zenon">Trudeau</name> noted, the expenses would certainly have been prohibitive since the Missouri Company had expended all of its resources on the three expeditions. <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name> departed in late March 1798 to meet <name type="person" key="Gayoso, Manuel de">Gayoso</name> and talk with him about the success of the expedition. <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">John Evans</name>, after completing his work as a deputy surveyor, departed for New Orleans in the beginning of July.</p>
         <p>More evidence disputes that either <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name> or <name type="person" key="De Finiels, Nicholas">Finiels</name> drafted the Missouri River map. In 1908, <name type="person" key="Teggart, Frederick">Frederick Teggart</name> discussed an <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name> map that came into the possession of <name type="person" key="Hay, John">John Hay</name> and <name type="person" key="Harrison, William Henry">William Henry Harrison</name>.<ref target="nlc.danisi.0145" n="45"/> In late October 1797, <name type="person" key="Soulard, Antoine">Soulard</name> had appointed <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name> the deputy surveyor of Cape Girardeau and on 7 November, <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name> had departed for the district with surveying instructions.<ref target="nlc.danisi.0146" n="46"/> Sometime in May 1798, a flood devastated the district and <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name> lost most of his belongings. Intent on going to New Orleans to meet <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name> and <name type="person" key="Gayoso, Manuel de">Gayoso</name>, he tried to sell his surveying instruments and asked <name type="person" key="Cousin, Barthelemi">Bartholomew Cousin</name>, the newly appointed surveyor of Cape Girardeau to help him with his map and to buy his instruments. <name type="person" key="Cousin, Barthelemi">Cousin</name> replied that he had no use for his instruments and that his assistant would "send you your . . . chart which I have not divided because I don't remember on what scale it is drawn, nor what is the exact longitude and latitude of any plan on it...."<ref target="nlc.danisi.0147" n="47"/> In the meantime, <name type="person" key="Jones, John Rice">Jones</name> gave the incomplete chart to <name type="person" key="Hay, John">John Hay</name> who had the means to complete it.<ref target="nlc.danisi.0148" n="48"/>
            <name type="person" key="Hay, John">Hay</name> had been a British trader and had a merchant store established at Cahokia under the name Todd and <name type="person" key="Hay, John">Hay</name>. Events that were to thrust the map into the limelight began to converge: in January 1801, <name type="person" key="Jones, John Rice">Jones</name> was appointed attorney general of the Indiana Territory and moved to Vincennes, the capitol.<ref target="nlc.danisi.0149" n="49"/> When <name type="person" key="Harrison, William Henry">William Henry Harrison</name>, governor of the territory, was apprised of the expedition in 1803, <name type="person" key="Jones, John Rice">Jones</name> delivered the map to him. <name type="person" key="Harrison, William Henry">Harrison</name> wrote to <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark</name> on 13 November 1803, informing him that he had the map copied and "now send it to you by Post rider."<ref target="nlc.danisi.0150" n="50"/>
         </p>
         <p>On 26 November 1803, <name type="person" key="Harrison, William Henry">Harrison</name> wrote <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">President Jefferson</name> that he was sending a "map which is a copy of the manuscript map of <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Mr. Evans</name> who ascended the Missouri river by order of the Sp. gov't further than any other person."<ref target="nlc.danisi.0151" n="51"/> He wrote to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> on 13 January 1804 that he was sending him a map, which was a copy of the copy from <name type="person" key="Harrison, William Henry">Harrison</name>: "I now enclose a map of the Missouri as far as the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>, 12. or 1500. miles I presume above its mouth. It is said to be very accurate, having been done by a <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">mr. [sic] Evans</name> by order of the Spanish Government. But whether he corrected by astronomical observations or not we are not informed."<ref target="nlc.danisi.0152" n="52"/> The map was indeed incorrect. <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name> had given <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name> a raw copy, a template of the map, because he believed <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name> had the ability to complete it.</p>
         <p>Before<name type="person" key="Mackay, James"> MacKay</name> went to New Orleans, <name type="person" key="De Finiels, Nicholas">Finiels</name> drafted a map for him. In fact, he and <name type="person" key="De Finiels, Nicholas">Finiels</name> assisted each other, which has not been fully understood because the dates of their map–making overlap. They both produced maps during 1797 and 1798:
<name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name>, from May to December 1797; <name type="person" key="De Finiels, Nicholas">Finiels</name>, from August 1797 to June 1798. <name type="person" key="De Finiels, Nicholas">Finiels</name> arrived in St. Louis on 3 June 1797. He had been hired in Philadelphia to oversee the building of defenses at St. Louis. But <name type="person" key="Howard, Carlos">Carlos Howard</name>, the military commandant, refused to employ him. <name type="person" key="Howard, Carlos">Howard</name> had no explicit order from <name type="person" key="Carondelet, Baron de">Carondelet</name> and believed that <name type="person" key="De Finiels, Nicholas">Finiels</name>, an artillerist engineer, was not as competent as <name type="person" key="Vandenbenden, Louis">Louis Vandenbenden</name>, a fortifications engineer.<ref target="nlc.danisi.0153" n="53"/>
            <name type="person" key="De Finiels, Nicholas">Finiels</name> decided to embark upon a private mapping project during 1797–1798.</p>
         <p>
            <name type="person" key="De Finiels, Nicholas">Finiels</name> refers to a map completed in mid–1798. "La carte de cette Riviere que j'ai dressé e en 1798 sur les memoirs ds/des <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">Mess./Messieurs MacKay</name> et <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name> donnera une notion tré s exacte de la partie de son tours que Pont peut regarder comme la mieux connue jusques apresant" ("The map of this river that I drew up in 1798 [based] upon the accounts of <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">Messieurs MacKay</name> and <name type="person" key="Evans, John Thomas">Evans</name> will give a very exact notion/idea of its [the river's] course which one can regard as the best known up to the present").<ref target="nlc.danisi.0154" n="54"/> The <name type="person" key="De Finiels, Nicholas">Finiels</name> map, which measures ten feet long and a yard wide, shows the Missouri River for more than eighty miles west of its mouth.</p>
         <p>This map is <name type="person" key="De Finiels, Nicholas">Finiels</name>'s greatest achievement, a colossal, unauthorized, and personal project: mapping the central Mississippi valley. His idea for it was likely due to <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name>'s arrival from the Upper Missouri, replete with fresh data regarding the expedition and <name type="person" key="Soulard, Antoine">Soulard</name>'s "Ydea Topografica," as well as the fact that <name type="person" key="Soulard, Antoine">Soulard</name> possessed the surveying measurements for many of the villages. In terms of artistry and accuracy of detail, <name type="person" key="De Finiels, Nicholas">Finiels</name>'s map of the central Mississippi valley stands apart from any other produced in the history of North America.<ref target="nlc.danisi.0155" n="55"/> Even now, <name type="person" key="De Finiels, Nicholas">Finiels</name>'s hand translates an ancient time into a living one. The map details St. Louis, Carondelet, Prairie du Pont ("Prairie of the Bridge," now Dupo), Cahokia, River Des Peres, <name type="person" key="Chouteau, Mr.">Chouteau</name>'s Pond, the Commonfields, Cape Girardeau, Ste. Genevieve, and New Madrid. Tiny red squares represent houses, and he depicts each field under cultivation, the hills, and the green—tinted Mississippi River. The breadth and majesty of this map argue for the amount of time and concentration <name type="person" key="De Finiels, Nicholas">Finiels</name> took to complete it.</p>
         <p>The time necessary to complete this map precludes the idea that <name type="person" key="De Finiels, Nicholas">Finiels</name> could have also drafted a Missouri River map laden with all the complexities of a course of 1510 miles. But surprisingly, <name type="person" key="De Finiels, Nicholas">Finiels</name> describes another map that he drafted in 1797 near the Bon Homme Creek on the Missouri River. From the French manuscript of "Notice sur la Louisiane Supé rieure" ("An Account of Upper Louisiana"), <name type="person" key="De Finiels, Nicholas">Finiels</name> states that he made a map for <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name>–not the Missouri Company: "C'est sur ses memoires et sur ses relevé s que j'ai dressé  pour lui en 1797 la derniere carte du Missouri." ("It is upon his written statement &amp; upon his account that I drew up for him in 1797 the latest map of the Missouri.")<ref target="nlc.danisi.0156" n="56"/>
            <name type="person" key="De Finiels, Nicholas"> Finiels</name> attempts to make a distinction between <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name>'s Missouri River map (a version of the Indian Office map) and the one that he drafted for <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name> that was of an unnamed district; thus the appellation "latest map of the Missouri." The map is titled "Plan ideal de las habitaciones del riachuelo bon homme cuyos tierras no se hallan aun apeadas," or "An ideal map of the habitations of the Bon Homme creek whose lands have not been delineated [up until now]." (See Figure 3.)<ref target="nlc.danisi.0157" n="57"/> It was a proposed plan of the district subject to approval by the governor and soon to be given the name St. André . <name type="person" key="Trudeau, Zenon">Trudeau</name> forwarded the map to <name type="person" key="Gayoso, Manuel de">Gayoso</name> on 28 February 1798, adding his description of the progress of the new settlement:</p>
         <p>I am sending you a small ideal map of the American's habitations, situated on the shores of the Missouri and the Bonhomme creek. Part of these are already established and in all of them they made the corn harvest last year; currently we are working to construct a mill over that which belongs to <name type="person" key="Long, Lorenzo">Lorenzo Long</name>, who has brought in (for this) black stones and very intelligent workers, such that I have no doubt that this place will be prosperous before two years, for a distance from seven to ten leagues from St. Louis, and that each day's experience has shown me the necessity of appointing there a trustworthy person as Commander and who can correspond with me at least in the French language. I propose to you <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">Mr. James (Don Juan) MacKay</name> who has already held from your predecessor the title of Commander of the forts which are to be constructed in the Upper Missouri, he is well known as an intelligent and prudent man and the only one who speaks the French language among those who hold lands in the said place and that you can have confidence in his fidelity and it is equally well that the above—mentioned <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">Mr. MacKay</name> be named captain of the militia company that needs to be formed out of the said inhabitants. And as I have expressed to you, the commanders of the town of Ste. Genevieve, New Bourbon and Cape Girardeau have a compensation of 800 pesos yearly, the others equally deserve it and among them <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">Mr. MacKay</name>. I find that it is appropriate that you appoint him to that which I propose to you.<ref target="nlc.danisi.0158" n="58"/>
         </p>
         <p>
            <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name>'s interest in the area of this plan came naturally. Once he had completed the chart for <name type="person" key="Clamorgan, Jacques">Clamorgan</name> in October, he began looking for a place to live. The Bon Homme settlement attracted him probably because it was in need of a commandant.<ref target="nlc.danisi.0159" n="59"/> Therefore, he set himself to making a plan of the district with <name type="person" key="De Finiels, Nicholas">Finiels</name>'s assistance. Like <name type="person" key="Soulard, Antoine">Soulard</name>, in 1795, when <name type="person" key="Trudeau, Zenon">Trudeau</name> proposed him as surveyor general, <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name> also demonstrated his abilities to the lieutenant governor. Evidently the idea worked. <name type="person" key="MacKkay, James">MacKay</name> had already chosen the location for the tract he was asking <name type="person" key="Trudeau, Zenon">Trudeau</name> to grant him. <name type="person" key="Trudeau, Zenon">Trudeau</name> agreed, granting<name type="person" key="Mackay, James"> MacKay</name> about 3700 acres near the Bon Homme Creek on 23 December 1797.<ref target="nlc.danisi.0160" n="60"/>
            <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name>'s plan of the Bon Homme district is a small—scale map, illustrating houses, rivers, islands, hills, lot sizes, and the names of the owners of lots. This map is unique to <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name>'s heritage; however, when comparing it to <name type="person" key="De Finiels, Nicholas">Finiels</name>'s Mississippi Valley map, a recognizable feature stands out: the manner in which the rivers are drawn. The shape and contours of the Mississippi and Missouri Rivers, and the rendering of their sandbars, are so similar that they appear to be made by the same hand. To the untrained eye, the technical skills between <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name> and <name type="person" key="De Finiels, Nicholas">Finiels</name> would have been difficult to ascertain, but it was their artistic treatment that helped solve who drafted which map. Unaware of the Bon Homme plan, historians have mistakenly credited <name type="person" key="De Finiels, Nicholas">Finiels</name> with the drafting of <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name>'s Missouri River map.<ref target="nlc.danisi.0161" n="61"/> But an identifiable design element exists on <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name>'s Missouri River map and on the Bon Homme plan that does not appear on <name type="person" key="De Finiels, Nicholas">Finiels</name>'s map: it is the fleur—des—lis drawn by <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name> on the north arrow. (See Figure 3.) This element, an unconventional map symbol, assisted in the recognition of his maps.</p>
         <p>When <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name> began as commandant at St. André  in November 1798, he continued surveying while handling all civil and criminal matters in the district.<ref target="nlc.danisi.0162" n="62"/> Five months earlier, when <name type="person" key="Gayoso, Manuel de">Gayoso</name> appointed <name type="person" key="De Lassus, Charles">Charles De Lassus</name> as lieutenant governor, he told him that <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name> merited his special attention. <name type="person" key="De Lassus, Charles">De Lassus</name> was instructed to help <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name> fulfill his duties and to pay particular attention in "obtaining the most rapid and exact information concerning the intentions of the traders from Canada in Spanish territory."<ref target="nlc.danisi.0163" n="63"/> In 1802, <name type="person" key="Perrin du Lac, Francois">Francois Perrin du Lac</name> allegedly made a voyage up the Missouri and produced a map that he ambiguously credited to "un ancien traiteur de la rivié re des Illinois...."<ref target="nlc.danisi.0164" n="64"/> Historian <name type="person" key="Abel, Annie H.">Annie Abel</name>'s claim that <name type="person" key="Perrin du Lac, Francoise">Perrin du Lac</name> was referring to <name type="person" key="Truteau, Jean Baptiste">Jean Baptiste Trudeau</name> as the ancient trader gave rise to an arduous debate over <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name>'s expertise in the ensuing decades.<ref target="nlc.danisi.0165" n="65"/>
         </p>
         <p>One of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name>'s primary goals when planning the expedition was to find the most up—to—date maps of the Missouri River, and he had obtained several of them before arriving in St. Louis, including one by <name type="person" key="Arrowsmith, Aaron">Aaron Arrowsmith</name> and another by <name type="person" key="Thompson, David">David Thompson</name>. On 8 December 1803, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> arrived in St. Louis without <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark</name> but accompanied by two interpreters from Cahokia, <name type="person" key="Hay, John">John Hay</name> and <name type="person" key="Jarrot, Nicholas">Nicholas Jarrot</name>. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> met with <name type="person" key="De Lassus, Charles">Charles De Lassus</name>, the lieutenant governor, who had become suspicious about the expedition because <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> presented a French passport instead of a Spanish one. <name type="person" key="De Lassus, Charles">De Lassus</name> told <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> that if the papers had been in the name of the Spanish king, there would have been no difficulty granting the expedition access to the Missouri. <name type="person" key="De Lassus, Charles">De Lassus</name> needed time to write to his superiors in New Orleans and ask permission; he told <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> he would have an answer by the spring of 1804. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> "agreed to wait" and said that he would spend the winter on the east side of the Mississippi.<ref target="nlc.danisi.0166" n="66"/>
         </p>
         <p>A day later, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> and the remainder of the Corps made their formal entrance in St. Louis. "Under Sales &amp;  Cullers," <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> noted, they put ashore where "hundreds Came to the bank to view us." <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> was surprised to see some of his old friends from Vincennes and Kaskaskia. While <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> remained in St. Louis tending to business affairs, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark </name>"proceeded on" to find a site where the group could establish the temporary encampment.<ref target="nlc.danisi.0167" n="67"/>
            <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> had asked <name type="person" key="De Lassus, Charles">De Lassus</name> if he could meet with individuals in St. Louis who might be able to help him with the geographic information of the country. Although <name type="person" key="De Lassus, Charles">De Lassus</name> granted permission, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> wrote that, while the inhabitants were eager to help, "every thing must be obtained by stealth." Furthermore, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> stated that everything underwent his examination and "you may readily conceive the restraint which exists on many points." For example, when <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> met with some merchants, he reported that they were all afraid of <name type="person" key="De Lassus, Charles">De Lassus</name>, especially the inhabitants who moved more "as tho' the fear of the Commandant, than that of god, was before their eyes. . . ." Even some of the wealthiest had been jailed for slight offenses, which "has produced a general dread of <name type="person" key="De Lassus, Charles">him [De Lassus</name>] among all classes of the people." <name type="person" key="Soulard, Antoine">Antoine Soulard</name>, surveyor general of Upper Louisiana, had agreed to let<name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether"> Lewis</name> copy government information from the 1800 census, but when he realized that <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> was going to copy the whole document, he expressed extreme fear. <name type="person" key="Soulard, Antoine">Soulard</name> became so agitated that <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis </name>desisted and wrote "if it were known that he had given me permission to copy an official paper . . . it would injure him with his government."<ref target="nlc.danisi.0168" n="68"/> Although full of trepidation, <name type="person" key="Soulard, Antoine">Soulard</name> did help <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, but he failed to obtain the genuine map of the Missouri River. If <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> were to depend on <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name>'s map for the first part of their journey, it was absolutely urgent to meet with him.</p>
         <p>But <name type="person" key="De Lassus, Charles">De Lassus</name> had only granted the Americans access to St. Louis, and <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name>, commandant of St. André, wrote that his district was a "long journey" from there. <name type="person" key="De Finiels, Nicholas">Finiels</name> believed that a trip to St. Charles by water took about two days and St. André  was almost nine miles further west.<ref target="nlc.danisi.0169" n="69"/> Delays continued to hamper <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, and now, the most important person in Upper Louisiana lay out of reach. If the Scotsman was truly an expert, then they probably would meet often to strategize and make maps, yet it could be the height of summer before they departed.</p>
         <p>
            <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> believed that the transfer of the country would take place at the end of December and <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> had relied on that information. <name type="person" key="Dearborn, Henry">Henry Dearborn</name>, the secretary of war, had approved a journey up the Missouri in July 1803, and when <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> wrote to <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> on 3 October from Cincinnati, he confirmed that he would "make a tour this winter on horseback of some hundred miles ... on the South side of the Missouri." He also thought that he could prevail on <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark</name> "to undertake a similar excurtion through some other portion of the country." <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> had hoped that when he arrived in St. Louis, Louisiana would have been transferred to American soil, so that by February or 1 March, he would have procured additional information about the country that would further attest "to the utility" of the expedition. In a letter dated 16 November, <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> cautioned <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> to revise his plans because he believed by the time <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> arrived in St. Louis, the Missouri River would begin to freeze. He thought that <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> should remain at Cahokia or Kaskaskia for the winter and gain the necessary information he had requested months earlier instead of taking an ambiguous trip that may incur Spanish opposition, and be "exposed to risques," that <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> wanted to avoid at all cost.<ref target="nlc.danisi.0170" n="70"/>
         </p>
         <p>In the meantime, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> found an excellent site for the military encampment opposite the mouth of the Missouri River and named it Camp Dubois. Apparently, the site was well—known to the local population too and after <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had landed at the bank, several canoes of drunken Indians managed to camp near him. In the following days, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> noted Indians paddling up and down the Mississippi who undoubtedly alerted villagers at Portage des Sioux of the American encampment. Portage des Sioux, located on the west bank of Mississippi, was the closest Spanish settlement to Camp Dubois, about five miles up the Mississippi. <name type="person" key="Griffith, Samuel">Samuel Griffith</name>, an American farmer from Portage des Sioux, visited <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> on December 16, 23, and 24. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> ordered <name type="person" key="Shields, John">John Shields</name> to accompany <name type="person" key="Griffith, Samuel">Griffith</name> to purchase dairy items and <name type="person" key="Shields, John">Shields</name> returned on Christmas Day with "a cheese and 4 lb butter."<ref target="nlc.danisi.0171" n="71"/>
         </p>
         <p>
            <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> had sent another letter repeating his orders to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> that he should not enter the Missouri until spring, to which <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> had already indicated his compliance in his 28 December letter. Still, the most essential part of the expedition, examining an accurate map, was out of their grasp. Deciding not to wait any longer, they implemented a plan that has remained hidden for two centuries. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> dispatched <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Private Joseph Field </name>up the Missouri to locate<name type="person" key="MacKkay, James"> James MacKay</name> and invite him to Camp Dubois. <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Field</name> traveled "30 miles up" river to St. André  where <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name> was commandant.<ref target="nlc.danisi.0172" n="72"/>
         </p>
         <p>The journal entry on 10 January 1804 reveals that the historic meeting between <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> and <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name> was kept secret. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> ordered <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Field </name>up the Missouri regardless of the subtle illegality. While <name type="person" key="De Lassus, Charles">De Lassus</name> had granted access to St. Louis where he could monitor their activities, he certainly did not intend for <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name> to reveal government information. Yet, would the St. André  commandant accept the invitation? If he did, he would have to evade telling <name type="person" key="De Lassus, Charles">De Lassus</name>. And, if he brought the official map of the Missouri River, a classified government document, that too would be illegal. But <name type="person" key="MacKay, James">MacKay</name> took the risk because he needed a job. He learned in September 1803 that the United States had bought Louisiana, and he had informed a Kentucky congressman that becoming an American citizen would deprive him of his office and salary.<ref target="nlc.danisi.0173" n="73"/> By handing over the genuine map to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> updated with an additional five years of river information, <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name> would demonstrate his allegiance to the new American government.</p>
         <p>The journal entries preceding 10 January were brief, and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> does not mention when he sent <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Private Field</name> to locate <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name>. <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Field</name> probably left on 7 January, the same day that <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> began drawing a map of the Missouri River "for the purpose of correcting from the information which I may get of the countrey to the NW."<ref target="nlc.danisi.0174" n="74"/> It may have taken <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Field</name> until the morning of 9 January to find <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name>, who had witnessed the signing of a warranty deed at St. André. Later in the day, <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name> went to Marais des Lairds (Bridgeton, Missouri) to witness and authorize other documents and then went to Portage des Sioux. The portage was a thin strip of land, a peninsula between the Missouri and Mississippi Rivers north of Camp Dubois. <ref target="nlc.danisi.0175" n="75"/> After surveying some lots at Portage des Sioux on 10 January, <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name> made his way to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> headquarters at Wood River.<ref target="nlc.danisi.0176" n="76"/>
         </p>
         <p>As <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Field</name> returned to Camp Dubois, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> watched the private cross the Mississippi "between the Sheets of floating Ice with Some risque. . . ." Suspicious that <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Field</name> took too long to return, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> questioned him about the trip and was told that it had been impossible for <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Field</name> to cross, for "the Ice run so thick in the Missourie." That took time. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> also didn't like the fact that <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Field</name> had remained "so long" on the Missouri where he likely was recognized by the inhabitants. <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Field</name> allayed <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> fears by saying "that the people is greatly in favour of the Americans." <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Field</name> returned at 1:00 p.m., and <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name> arrived at camp some time thereafter.<ref target="nlc.danisi.0177" n="77"/>
         </p>
         <p>The meeting probably was long. Due to the winter weather, the afternoon hour when <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name> arrived, and the fact they needed much time to discuss the intricacies of a river map written in French, <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name> stayed overnight and possibly longer. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> journal entries for the next two days were short; he continued to complain of being ill due to the severe "Ducking" on 9 January, and indicated that Lewis may have left the camp late on 12 January. By 21 January, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> began making detailed calculations based on the distances from Camp Dubois to the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>, from the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name> to the Rocky Mountains, and from the mountains to the Pacific.<ref target="nlc.danisi.0178" n="78">78</ref>
         </p>
         <p>Finally, <name type="person" key="De Lassus, Charles">De Lassus</name> received official word that Louisiana had indeed been sold to the United States. On 21 February, he wrote to <name type="person" key="Stoddard, Amos">Captain Amos Stoddard</name>, the American military official who was to oversee the transfer of the country, and informed him that they should meet. They agreed to the dates to transfer ownership: on 9 March, Spain would transfer the country to France and on 10 March, France would transfer it to the United States. By 21 March, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had traveled up the Missouri with <name type="person" key="Chouteau, Mr.">Chouteau</name> and <name type="person" key="Gratiot">Gratiot</name>. Sometime in the spring of 1804, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> drafted a new map based on previous maps made by <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name>, <name type="person" key="Soulard, Antoine">Soulard</name>, <name type="person" key="Chouteau, Mr.">Chouteau</name>, and on information gleaned from traders. That map was sent to <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">President Jefferson</name> with <name type="person" key="Chouteau, Pierre">Pierre Chouteau</name>, who accompanied an <name type="native_nation" key="Osage Indians">Osage Indian</name> delegation to Washington. <ref target="nlc.danisi.0179" n="79"/>
         </p>
         <p>The convoluted history of the map of the Missouri River as high as the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> villages is an important but overlooked detail of the march of the Corps of Discovery. The background of <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">James MacKay</name> and the contribution of his invaluable map shows a curious international progression to what is usually regarded as a strictly national enterprise. It was a transplanted Scot with a history of British service who, at personal risk, provided the link between the preceding Spanish and fleeting French regime to the United States' assumption of authority in Louisiana. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> predecessors had already carefully laid out a third of the landmarks that the expedition's members would note in their journals–landmarks that had been named by French voyageurs nearly a century earlier, and that, indeed, persist as toponyms (though often in English translation) to this day.</p>
         <p>
            <name type="person" key="Danisi, Thomas C.">THOMAS C. DANISI</name>, an independent historian, is completing a book on <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name>. <name type="person" key="Wood, W. Raymond">W. RAYMOND WOOD</name> is professor emeritus of anthropology at the University of Missouri-Columbia.</p>
         <p>Figure 1. Major features and tribes mentioned in the text. Map ©  2003 by <name type="person" key="Wood, W. Raymond">W. R. Wood</name>.</p>
         <p>Figure 2. Detail of the lower Missouri River from the Indian Office map, created by <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">James MacKay</name>. Photo courtesy of Library of Congress.</p>
         <p>Figure 3. The Bon Homme map: The district of St. André  was located south of Bon Homme Island on the Missouri River. This map covers about 23 air miles of the Missouri Valley and locates tracts by owner, houses, springs, rivers, and the river bluffs. Photo courtesy of the Bancroft Library, University of California, Berkeley: catalog M–M 508, Box 5, #516, MSS.</p>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0101" n="1">
            <name type="person" key="Nasatir, A.P.">A.P. Nasatir</name>, <hi rend="italic">Before <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>: Documents Illustrating the History of Missouri, 1785–1804</hi>, 2 vols. (St. Louis: St. Louis Historical Documents Foundation, 1952), 1: 80–3. Many of the <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name>, <name type="person" key="De Finiels, Nicholas">De Finiels</name>, and <name type="person" key="Soulard, Antoine">Soulard </name>papers are to be found in the Papeles de Cuba Collection (hereafter PC) of the Archivo General de Indias in Seville, Spain (hereafter cited as AGI). We thank <name type="person" key="Durbin, Nancy">Nancy Durbin</name> of Lindenwood University and <name type="person" key="Price, Anna">Anna Price</name> for their French and Spanish translations of the <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name>, <name type="person" key="Soulard, Antoine">Soulard</name>, <name type="person" key="De Finiels, Nicholas">De Finiels</name>, and <name type="person" key="Trudeau, Zenon">Trudeau</name> documents.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0102" n="2">
            <name type="person" key="Beauregard, H.T.">H.T. Beauregard</name>, "Journal of <name type="person" key="Truteau, Jean Baptiste">Jean Baptiste Truteau</name> among the <name type="native_nation" key="Ankara Indians">Ankara</name> Indians in 1795," Missouri Historical Society Collections 4 (St. Louis:  Missouri Historical Society, 1912): 22.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0103" n="3">
            <name type="person" key="Wallace, W.S.">W.S. Wallace</name>, ed., <hi rend="italic">Documents relating to the North West Company</hi> (Toronto, The Champlain Society, 1934), 14.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0104" n="4">"Narrative of <name type="person" key="McKay, Donald">Donald McKay</name>," transcribed by <name type="person" key="Jackson, John C.">John C. Jackson</name>, December 1995 E.223/1, Hudson's Bay Company Archives, Winnipeg, Manitoba (hereafter HBCA); <hi rend="italic">Manchester House Journal</hi>, 17 April 1786/87, B121/a/1, HBCA; <hi rend="italic">Cumberland House Journal</hi>, 30 May 1786, B49/a/16, 34, HBCA.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0105" n="5">
            <name type="person" key="Nasatir, A.P.">Nasatir</name>, <hi rend="italic">Before <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>
            </hi>, 1: 130–1.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0106" n="6">Perrin Collection, 1737–1809, St. Clair County Circuit Court, Case File 114 (1792), Illinois Regional Archives Depository, Illinois State Archives, Archives Building, Springfield.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0107" n="7">
            <name type="person" key="Nasatir, A.P.">Nasatir</name>, <hi rend="italic">Before <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>
            </hi>, 1: 181.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0108" n="8">
            <name type="person" key="Greve, Charles Theodore">Charles Theodore Greve</name>, <hi rend="italic">Centennial History of Cincinnati and Representative Citizens</hi>, 2 vols. (Chicago: Biographical Publishing Co., 1904), 1: 360–1.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0109" n="9">
            <name type="person" key="Wood, W. Raymond">W. Raymond Wood</name>, <hi rend="italic">Prologue to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>: The <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">Mackay</name> and <name type="person" key="Evans, John">Evans</name> Expedition</hi> (Norman: University of Oklahmoa Press, 2003), 190–3.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0110" n="10">
            <name type="person" key="Nasatir, A.P.">Nasatir</name>, <hi rend="italic">Before <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>
            </hi>, 1: 97.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0111" n="11">
            <name type="person" key="Williams, Gwyn A.">Gwyn A. Williams</name>, <hi rend="italic">Madoc: The Making of a Myth</hi> (New York: Oxford University Press, 1987), 153.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0112" n="12">
            <name type="person" key="Valle, Francois">Francois Valle</name> to <name type="person" key="Trudeau, Zenon">Zenon Trudeau</name>, 6 March 1794, Letter 22, AGI–PC 209: 598; microfilm copy in the Missouri Historical Society, St. Louis.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0113" n="13">
            <name type="person" key="De Lassus, Charles">Pierre Charles Delassus De Luzieres</name> to Francisco Louis Hector <name type="person" key="Carondelet, Baron de">Carondelet</name>, 16 April 1794, AGI–PC 208a: 480.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0114" n="14">
            <name type="person" key="Peyroux, Henry">Henry Peyroux</name> to <name type="person" key="Valle, Francois">Francois Valle</name>, 26 December 1793, AGI–PC 208a: 490; <name type="person" key="Trudeau, Zenon">Trudeau</name> to <name type="person" key="Carondelet, Baron de">Carondelet</name>, 28 January 1794, AGI–PC 209: 634, AGI–PC 208a: 480.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0115" n="15">St. Louis Recorded Archives, Vol. 2, Bk. 2, Instrument 625, p. 388, Jefferson National Expansion Memorial, Courthouse, National Park Service, St. Louis, MO.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0116" n="16">Manuscript, ca. 1804, notes on Indian tribes in <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">James MacKay's</name> hand, note 4. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Family Papers, Missouri Historical Society, St. Louis. We cannot help but be curious as to where <name type="person" key="Rees, John">Rhys</name> had obtained his <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> vocabulary.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0117" n="17">
            <name type="person" key="Diller, Aubrey">Aubrey Diller</name>, "Maps of the Missouri River before <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>," in <hi rend="italic">Studies and Essays in the History of Science and Learning</hi>, ed. <name type="person" key="Montagu, Ashley">Ashley Montagu</name> (New York: Schuman, 1946), 507.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0118" n="18">
            <name type="person" key="Nasatir, A.P.">Nasatir</name>, <hi rend="italic">Before <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>
            </hi>, 1: 96, note 61; <name type="person" key="Nasatir, A.P.">A.P. Nasatir</name>, "Anglo–Spanish Rivalry on the Upper Missouri," <hi rend="italic">Mississippi Valley Historical Review</hi> 16 (March 1930): 507.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0119" n="19">
            <name type="person" key="Clamorgan, Jacques">Jacques Clamorgan</name> to <name type="person" key="Truteay, Jean Baptiste">Jean Baptiste Truteau</name>, 30 June 1794, Box 2, Folder 34, <name type="person" key="Houck, Louis">Louis Houck</name> Collection, Document 66, Missouri Historical Society, St. Louis.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0120" n="20">
            <name type="person" key="Nasatir, A.P.">Nasatir</name>, <hi rend="italic">Before <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>
            </hi>, 1: 257, note 6.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0121" n="21">
            <name type="person" key="Trudea, Zenon">Zenon Trudeau </name>to <name type="person" key="Carondelet, Baron de">Francisco Louis Hector Carondelet</name>, 8 August 1794, AGI–PC 197: 707. <name type="person" key="De Luzié res">De Luziéres</name> to <name type="person" key="Carondelet, Baron de">Carondelet</name>, 17 September 1794, AGI–PC 209: 663, 17 October, PC 209: 666.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0122" n="22">
            <name type="person" key="Soulard, Antoine">Antoine Soulard</name> to <name type="person" key="Gayoso de Lemos, Manuel">Manuel Gayoso de Lemos</name>, 15 December 1797, AGI–PC 213: 833; U.S. Congress. Senate. Substance of an Argument, 21st Cong., 2d session, 1830. S. Doc. 12, Serial 203, 27.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0123" n="23">
            <name type="person" key="Diller, Aubrey">Diller</name>, "Maps of the Missouri River," 508.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0124" n="24">This map is illustrated in <name type="person" key="Wood, W. Raymond">Wood</name>, "The Missouri River Basin," Figure 1.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0125" n="25">
            <name type="person" key="Diller, Aubrey">Diller</name>, "Maps of the Missouri River," 507–8.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0126" n="26">
            <name type="person" key="Soulard, Antoine">Antoine Soulard</name> to <name type="person" key="Gayoso de Lemos, Manuel">Manuel Gayoso de Lemos</name>, 15 December 1797, AGI–PC 213: 833–5.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0127" n="27">
            <name type="person" key="Dunbar, William">William Dunbar</name> to <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Thomas Jefferson</name>, 18 March 1806, <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Thomas Jefferson</name> Papers, Document 27579, National Archives, Washington, DC. In this letter, <name type="person" key="Dunbar, William">Dunbar</name> speaks of "<name type="person" key="Mackay, James">Mackay's</name> treatise on longitude," but this is not our <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">James MacKay</name> from St. Louis. <name type="person" key="Garnett, John">John Garnett</name>, Tables requisite to be used with the nautical ephemeris, for finding the latitude and longitude at sea. . . . (London, Commissioners of Longitude, 1806).</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0128" n="28">
            <name type="person" key="Dunbar, William">William Dunbar</name> to <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Thomas Jefferson</name>, 18 March 1806. </note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0129" n="29">
            <name type="person" key="Nasatir, A.P.">Nasatir</name>, Before <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, 1: 97.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0130" n="30">Ibid., 1: 86 and 2: 520; St. Charles Papers, 1797: Deposition of <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">James MacKay</name>, 7 March 1817, Missouri Historical Society, St. Louis; <name type="person" key="Carondelet, Baron de">Francisco Louis Hector Carondelet</name> to <name type="person" key="Clamorgan, Jacques">Jacques Clamorgan</name>, 18 September and 26 October 1796, Missouri Historical Society, St. Louis.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0131" n="31">
            <name type="person" key="Nasatir, A.P.">Nasatir</name>, <hi rend="italic">Before <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>
            </hi>, 2: 410–1.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0132" n="32">Ibid.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0133" n="33">Ibid.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0134" n="34">Ibid., 416–7. </note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0135" n="35">Ibid.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0136" n="36">Ibid., 410–4.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0137" n="37">
            <name type="person" key="De Voto, Bernard">Bernard De Voto</name>, <hi rend="italic">Course of Empire</hi> (Boston: Houghton Mifflin, 1952), 377.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0138" n="38">
            <name type="person" key="Nasatir, A.P.">Nasatir</name>, <hi rend="italic">Before <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>
            </hi>, 2: 461–2, 500.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0139" n="39">
            <name type="person" key="Nasatir, A.P.">A.P. Nasatir</name>, "Anglo–Spanish Rivalry in Iowa," <hi rend="italic">Iowa Journal of History and Politics</hi> 28 (July 1930): 359; <name type="person" key="Nasatir, A.P.">Nasatir</name>, <hi rend="italic">Before <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>
            </hi>, 2: 520 (quote).</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0140" n="40">
            <name type="person" key="Nasatir, A.P.">Nasatir</name>, <hi rend="italic">Before <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>
            </hi>, 2: 485–99. </note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0141" n="41">Ibid., 520, n. 6.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0142" n="42">Ibid., 545.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0143" n="43">
            <name type="person" key="Trudeau, Zenon">Trudeau</name> to <name type="person" key="Gayoso de Lamos, Manuel">Gayoso</name>, 5 March 1798, AGI–PC 49: 822.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0144" n="44">Ibid. A condensed version of the letter is in <name type="person" key="Nasatir, A.P.">Nasatir</name>, <hi rend="italic">Before <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>
            </hi>, 2: 545, n. 3.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0145" n="45">
            <name type="person" key="Teggart, Frederick">Frederick Teggart</name>, "Notes Supplementary to any Edition of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis </name>and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>," <hi rend="italic">American Historical Association Annual Report</hi> 1 (1908): 186. <name type="person" key="Thwaites, R. G.">Reuben Gold Thwaites</name> edited and published the letter in the <hi rend="italic">Original Journals of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition</hi> (New York: Dodd, Mead &amp; Company, 1905), 7: 291, but did not comment on it.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0146" n="46">
            <name type="person" key="Nasatir, A.P.">Nasatir</name>, "<name type="person" key="Evans, John]">John Evans</name>, Explorer and Surveyor," <hi rend="italic">Missouri Historical Review</hi> 25 (July 1931): 591, n. 29.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0147" n="47">Ibid., 608.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0148" n="48">
            <name type="person" key="Osgood, Ernest Staples">Ernest Staples Osgood</name>, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Field Notes of <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain William Clark</name>
            </hi>, 1803–1805 (New Haven: Yale University Press, 1964), 25, n. 8.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0149" n="49">"Executive Journal of Indiana Territory, 1800–1816," <hi rend="italic">Indiana Historical Society Publications</hi> 3, no. 2 (1900): 95; <name type="person" key="Carter, Clarence Edwin">Clarence Edwin Carter</name>, ed. The Territorial Papers of the United States, Orleans Territory, 7 vols. (Washington, DC, 1948), 7: 34.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0150" n="50">
            <name type="person" key="Jackson, Donald">Donald Jackson</name>, <hi rend="italic">Letters of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition</hi>, 2 vols. (Urbana: University of Illinois Press, 1978), 2: 689.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0151" n="51">
            <name type="person" key="Nasatir, A.P.">Nasatir</name>, <hi rend="italic">Before <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>
            </hi>, 2: 718–9. </note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0152" n="52">
            <name type="person" key="Jackson, Donald">Jackson</name>, <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, 1: 163.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0153" n="53">
            <name type="person" key="Nasatir, A.P.">Nasatir</name>, "Anglo–Spanish Rivalry in Iowa," 366, 369. <name type="person" key="De Finiels, Nicholas">De Finiels</name>'s wife, <name type="person" key="Riviere, Marie Anne">Marie Anne Riviere</name>, gave birth to <name type="person" key="De Finiels, Marie Susann-Adele">Marie Susann—Adele De Finiels</name> on 13 July 1797, in St. Louis (<name type="person" key="Collet, Oscar">Oscar Collet</name>, Index to St. Louis Cathedral and <name type="person" key="Carondelet, Baron de">Carondelet</name> Church Baptisms, p. 66, Missouri Historical Society, St. Louis).</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0154" n="54">
            <name type="person" key="De Finiels, Nicholas">Nicolas De Finiels</name>, "Notice sur la Louisiane Supé rieure," p. 89, Box 41, Folder 20, <name type="person" key="McDermott, John Francis">John Francis McDermott</name> Collection, Lovejoy Library, Southern Illinois University, Edwardsville (hereafter <name type="person" key="McDermott, John Francis">McDermott</name> Collection).</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0155" n="55">Reproduction de la carte du Mississippi de <name type="person" key="De Finiels, Nicholas">Nicolas De Finiels</name>, Recueil, 69 carte 34, Marine Nationale, Service historique de la Marine, Chateau de Vincennes, B.P. n–2–00300 Armé es, France; illustrated in <name type="person" key="Wood, W. Raymond">W. Raymond Wood</name>, "An Atlas of Early Maps of the American Midwest, Part 2," Illinois State Museum, Scientific Papers, Vol. 28, 2001, plate 13.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0156" n="56">"Notice sur la Louisiane Supé rieure," p. 62, <name type="person" key="McDermott, John Francis">McDermott</name> Collection.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0157" n="57">Map can be found in M–M 508, Box 5 #516, MSS, Bancroft Library, University of California, Berkeley. The Spanish word, apeadas or afseadas, is unknown.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0158" n="58">Ibid.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0159" n="59">
            <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name> was appointed commandant of St. André, the Bon Homme settlement, in 1798. See <name type="person" key="Nasatir, A.P.">Nasatir</name>, <hi rend="italic">Before <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>
            </hi>, 2: 587.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0160" n="60">American State Papers, Public Lands, ed. <name type="person" key="Lowrie, Walter">Walter Lowrie</name> (Washington, DC, 1894), 2, 495.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0161" n="61">
            <name type="person" key="De Finiels, Nicholas">Nicolas De Finiels</name>, <hi rend="italic">An Account of Upper Louisiana</hi>, ed. <name type="person" key="Ekberg, Carl J.">Carl J. Ekberg</name> and <name type="person" key="Foley, William E.">William E. Foley</name> (Columbia: University of Missouri Press, 1989), 72, n. 118. <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name> produced a rough "plan" in October 1802 of Femme Osage, <name type="person" key="Boone, Daniel">Daniel Boone</name>'s settlement. See <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">James MacKay</name> to <name type="person" key="De Lassus, Charles">Charles Dehault de Lassus</name>, 29 October 1802, AGI–PC 219: 559.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0162" n="62">
            <name type="person" key="Nasatir, A.P.">Nasatir</name>, <hi rend="italic">Before <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>
            </hi>, 2: 605 and 545, n. 3.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0163" n="63">
            <name type="person" key="Gayoso de Lemos, Manuel">Manuel Gayoso de Lemos</name> to <name type="person" key="De Lassus, Charles">Charles Dehault de Lassus</name>, 12 May 1799, AGI–PC 134a: 387.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0164" n="64">
            <name type="person" key="Abel, Annie H.">Annie H. Abel</name>, "<name type="person" key="Trudeau, Zenon">Trudeau</name>'s Description of the Upper Missouri," <hi rend="italic">Mississippi Valley Historical Review</hi> 8 (June–September 1921): 154.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0165" n="65">
            <name type="person" key="Teggart, Frederick">Frederick Teggart</name>, "Notes Supplementary to any Edition of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>," <hi rend="italic">American Historical Association Annual Report</hi> 1 (1908): 188; <name type="person" key="Abel, Annie H.">Annie H. Abel—Henderson</name>, "<name type="person" key="Mackay, James">Mackay</name>'s Table of Distances," <hi rend="italic">Mississippi Valley Historical Review</hi> 10 (March 1924): 428–46; <name type="person" key="Quaife, Milo M.">Milo M. Quaife</name>, "Extracts from <name type="person" key="MacKkay, James">McKay</name>'s Journal–and Others," <hi rend="italic">Wisconsin Historical Society, Proceedings</hi> 63 (1916): 186–210; <name type="person" key="Abel, Annie H.">Annie H. Abel</name>, "A New <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Map," <hi rend="italic">Geographical Review</hi> 1 (May 1916): 329–45; <name type="person" key="De Voto, Bernard">Bernard De Voto</name>, <hi rend="italic">Course of Empire</hi>, 372–9; <name type="person" key="Williams, David">David Williams</name>, "<name type="person" key="Evans, John">John Evans</name>' Strange Journey," <hi rend="italic">American Historical Review</hi> 54 (January 1949): 277–95, and (April 1949): 508–29; <name type="person" key="Diller, Aubrey">Aubrey Diller</name>, "<name type="person" key="MacKay, James">James Mackay</name>'s Journey in Nebraska in 1796," <hi rend="italic">Nebraska History</hi> 36 (June 1955): 123–8; <name type="person" key="Allen, John Logan">John Logan Allen</name>, <hi rend="italic">Passage Through the Garden</hi> (Urbana: University of Illionois Press, 1975), 141–2; <name type="person" key="Jackson, Donald">Jackson</name>, <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, 1: 135–6.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0166" n="66">
            <name type="person" key="Jackson, Donald">Jackson</name>, <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, 1: 104–5, 142–3.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0167" n="67">
            <name type="person" key="Holmberg, James">James Holmberg</name> , ed., <hi rend="italic">Dear Brother: Letters of <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark</name>
            </hi> to <name type="person" key="Clark, Jonathan">Jonathan Clark</name> (New Haven: Yale University Press, 2002), 61.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0168" n="68">
            <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name> to <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Thomas Jefferson</name>, 28 December 1803, in <name type="person" key="Jackson, Donald">Jackson</name>, Letters, 1: 163, 148–55.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0169" n="69">
            <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">James MacKay</name> to <name type="person" key="De Lassus, Charles">Charles Dehault de Lassus</name>, 10 July 1800, AGI–PC 217b: 180; <name type="person" key="De Finiels, Nicholas">De Finiels</name>, <hi rend="italic">An Account of Upper Louisiana</hi>, 72–3.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0170" n="70">
            <name type="person" key="Jackson, Donald">Jackson</name>, <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, 1: 131, 137.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0171" n="71">
            <name type="person" key="Moulton, Gary">Moulton</name>, <hi rend="italic">The Journals of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition</hi>, 2: 134, 140–1.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0172" n="72">Ibid., 2: 154. When <name type="person" key="Soulard, Antoine">Soulard</name> surveyed <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name>'s land on Bon Homme Creek on 5 March 1798, he stated that it was about thirty–one miles west of St. Louis. See Pintado Papers, Book IX and Book P: 141, Louisiana State University, Baton Rouge. <name type="person" key="De Finiels, Nicholas">De Finiels</name> gauged the distance at about thirty miles. See <name type="person" key="De Finiels, Nicholas">De Finiels</name>, <hi rend="italic">An Account of Upper Louisiana</hi>, 70–1.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0173" n="73">
            <name type="person" key="MacKay, James">James MacKay</name> to <name type="person" key="Fowler, John">John Fowler</name>, 24 September 1803, Breckenridge Papers, Library of Congress, Washington, DC.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0174" n="74">
            <name type="person" key="Osgood, Ernest Staples">Osgood</name>, Field Notes, 16. Various historians have agreed on this date to suggest that <name type="person" key="Mackay, James">MacKay</name>'s meeting on 10 January had been planned.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0175" n="75">
            <name type="person" key="Wood, W. Raymond">W. Raymond Wood</name>, "An Atlas of Early Maps of the American Midwest, Part 2," <hi rend="italic">Illinois State Museum, Scientific Papers</hi> 28 (2001): plate 13.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0176" n="76">See St. Louis Recorded Archives, Vol. 4, Book 1, Instrument #1128 and 1132, pp. 53–5; Jefferson National Expansion Memorial, Courthouse, St. Louis, RG 952, Series 5, U.S. Surveyor General for Missouri, Outgoing Correspondence 1816–1863, Box 32, Book Q: 315, Missouri State Archives, Jefferson City.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0177" n="77">
            <name type="person" key="Moulton, Gary">Moulton</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journals of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>
            </hi>, 2: 154.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0178" n="78">
            <name type="person" key="Osgood, Ernest Staples">Osgood</name>, <hi rend="italic">Field Notes</hi>, 14, 19–23.</note>
         <note xml:id="nlc.danisi.0179" n="79">Ibid., 27; <name type="person" key="Jackson, Donald">Donald Jackson</name>, "A New <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Map," <hi rend="italic">Missouri Historical Society Bulletin</hi> 17 (January 1961): 119–26.</note>
         <p>Copyright by the <ref target="http://www.umsl.edu/~wha/">Western History Association</ref>.  Reprinted by permission.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
