<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.white_audio05">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Salish People and the Lewis and Clark Expedition</title>
            <title type="sub">Excerpt 5</title>
            <title type="sub"/>
            <author>Salish Pend d'Oreille Culture Committee and Elders Cultural Advisory Council,
        Confederated Salish and Kootenai Tribes</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2005</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="audio">
               <ref type="x-shockwave-flash" target="white_audio05"/>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl></bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-10-10</date>
            <name>Becky Potter</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-04-12</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="main">Excerpt 5</head>
         <head type="sub"/>
         <div type="audio">
            <p>
               <hi rend="right"/>This is what I am telling. Then when I thought about it, I think it's
        about three hundred or four hundred snows ago, and even beyond that time, is what I am
        telling you about. These are true stories. These stories were interpreted to my paternal
        grandmothers, my maternal grandfathers and my paternal grandfathers by their great-great
        grandparents, their great grandparents a long time ago. These are true stories . . . Then,
        as time went by, the Indians saw the whiteman. They felt pity for the whiteman, because
        their faces were pale, whitish, and they had beards. The white men looked as if they were
        cold because their faces were pale and red. Then, when the Indians met the whiteman
        (because they had already landed), then the Indians spread out their fur blankets and
        motioned to the white men to sit on the blankets. Their chief told them, “Spread out the
        fur blankets so that the white men can sit on them because maybe they are cold.” The
        Indians thought the white men were cold because they were white-faced.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>