<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-03-01">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
March 1, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 6</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">November 2, 1805–March 22, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1990</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">365-368</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">274</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">195</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 11</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of Joseph Whitehouse, May 14, 1804–April 2, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1997</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">424</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc/>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-08-30</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1806-03-01">March 1, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-03-01.01" n="">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Saturday March 1st 1806.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
This morning Sergt. <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name> and a party set out in quest of the Elk which had been killed by the hunters the day before yesterday.    they returned with the flesh of three of them late in the evening. <name type="person" key="Thompson, John B.">Thompson</name> was left with the hunters<ref target="n28030101" n="1"/> in order to jurk and take care of the flesh of the remaining two. <name type="person" key="Cus-ka-lah">Kuskelar</name> and wife left us about noon. he had a good looking boy of about 10 years of age with him who he informed us was his slave.    this boy had been taken prisoner by the <name type="native_nation" key="Tillamook Indians">Killamucks</name> from some nation on the Coast to the S. East of them at a great distance.    like other Indian nations they adopt their slaves in their families and treat them very much as their own children.<ref target="n28030102" n="2"/>
                  <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">Reubin Fields</name> and <name type="person" key="Collins, John">Collins</name> who have been absent since yesterday morning returned without having killed any game. The birds of the Western side of the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky Mountain</name> to the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific Ocean</name>, for convenience I shall divide into two classes, which I shal designate from the habits of the birds, <hi rend="italic">Terrestrial</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Aquatic.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
The Grouse or Prarie hen<ref target="n28030103" n="3"/> is peculiarly the inhabitant of the <name type="place" key="Great Columbian Plain">Grait Plains of Columbia</name>    they do not differ from those of the upper portion of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, the tail of which is pointed or the feathers in it's center much longer than those on the sides.    this Species differs essentially in the construction of this part of their plumage from those of the <name type="place" key="Illinois">Illinois</name>
                  <ref target="n28030104" n="4"/> which have their tails composed of fathers of equal length.    in the winter season this bird is booted even to the first joint of it's toes.    the toes are also curiously bordered on their lower edges with narrow hard scales which are placed very close to each other and extend horizontally about ⅛ of an inch on each side of the toes thus adding to the width of the tread which nature seems bountifully to have furnished them at this season for passing over the snow with more ease.    in the summer season those scales fall off. They have four toes on each foot. Their colour is a mixture of dark brown redish and yellowish brown and white confusedly mixed in which the redish brown prevails most on the upper parts of the body wings and tail and the white underneath the belley and lower parts of the breast and tail.    they associate in large flocks in autumn &amp; winter and are frequently found in flocks of from five to six even in summer. They feed on grass, insects, the leaves of various shrubs in the plains and on the seeds of several species of spelts<ref target="n28030105" n="5"/> and wild rye<ref target="n28030106" n="6"/> which grow in the richer parts of the plains.    in winter their food is the buds of the willow &amp; Cottonwood also the most of the native berries furnish them with food.— The Indians of this neighbourhood eat the root of the Cattail or Cooper's flag.<ref target="n28030107" n="7"/>    it is pleasantly taisted and appears to be very nutricious.    the inner part of the root which is eaten without any previous preperation is composed of a number of capillary white flexable strong fibers among which is a mealy or starch like substance which readily desolves in the mouth and separate from the fibers which are then rejected.    it appears to me that this substance would make excellent starch; nothing can be of a purer white than it is.—
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-03-01.02" n="">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Saturday March the 1st 1806</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
This morning we despatched Sergt. <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name> with 12 men in two Canoes in quest of the Elk which had been killed by the hunters the day before yesterday.    they returned with the flesh of three of them late in the evening. <name type="person" key="Thompson, John B.">Thompson</name> was left with the hunters in order to jurk and take care of the flesh of the remaining <hi rend="italic">two.</hi>
                  <name type="person" key="Cus-ka-lah">Kuskalar</name> &amp;c. left us about noon. The boy which this Indian offered to Sell to me is about 10 years of age.    this boy had been taken prisoner by the <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Tillamook Indians">Kil a mox</name>
                  </hi> from Some Nation on the Coast to the S. East of them at a great distance.    like other Indian nations they adopt their Slaves in their famelies and treat them very much like their own Children. <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">Reuben Field</name> and <name type="person" key="Collins, John">Collins</name> who had been absent Since yesterday morning returned without killing any thing.</p>
               <p>
The birds on the western Side of the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky Mountain's</name> to <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">the Pacific Ocian</name> for Convenience I Shall devide into from the habit of the birds, <hi rend="italic">Terrestrial</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Aquatic.</hi>    i e Fowls of the air, and fowls of the water.</p>
               <p>
The <hi rend="italic">Prarie</hi> Hen sometimes called the Grouse is peculiarly the inhabitent of the <name type="place" key="Great Columbian Plain">Great Plains of Columbia</name>.    they do not differ from those of the upper portion of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, the tails of which is pointed or the feathers in its center much longer than those on the Sides.    this Species differ assentially in the construction of this part of their plumage from those of the <name type="place" key="Illinois">Illinois</name> which have their tail composed of feathers of equal length.    in the winter Season this berd is booted even to the first joint of it's toes.    the toes are also curiously bordered on their lower edges with narrow hard scales which are placed very close to each other and extend horizontally about ⅛ of an inch on each Side of the toe, thus adding to the width of the tread which nature Seams bountifully to have furnished them with at this Season for passing over the Snow with more ease.    in the Summer Season those Scales fall off.    they have four toes on each foot.    their colour is a mixture of dark brown redish and yellowish brown and white confusedly mixed in which the redish brown prevails most on the upper parts of the body wings and tail.    and the white underneath the belley and lower parts of the breast and tail.    they associate in large flocks in autumn &amp; winter and are frequently found in flocks of from five to Six even in Summer. They feed on grass, insects, the leaves of various Shrubs in the Praries, and on the Seeds of Several Species of Spelts and wild rye which grow in the richer parts of the Plains.    in the winter their food is the buds of the willow and Cottonwood also the most of the native berries furnish them with food.    they cohabit in flock &amp; the Cocks fight verry much at those Seasons.
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-03-01.03" n="">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Saturday the 1st March 1806.    a fair morning.    twelve men<ref target="n28030108" n="8"/> Set out after the Elk meat.    the day Showery and wet.    in the evening the party returned except four<ref target="n28030109" n="9"/> who Stayed out to hunt &amp; brought in the meat.    the Indian Name of the River they went up is <name type="place" key="Youngs (Kilhow-a-nah-kle) River">Kil how-a-nàk-kle</name>
                  <ref target="n28030110" n="10"/> and this River which we are on <name type="place" key="Lewis and Clark (Fort, Netul) River">Ne-tul</name>.<ref target="n28030111" n="11"/>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-03-01.04" n="">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Saturday 1st March,</hi> 1806.    We had a cloudy wet morning. I set out with 8 men and 4 hunters to bring the meat of the elk that had been killed, which was at a greater distance from the fort than any we had yet brought in. There is a large river that flows into the southeast part of <name type="place" key="Baker (Haley's) Bay">Hayley's Bay</name>;<ref target="n28030112" n="12"/> upon which, about 20 miles from its mouth, our hunters discovered falls,<ref target="n28030113" n="13"/> which had about 60 feet of a perpendicular pitch.


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-03-01.05" n="">
            <sp who="jw">
               <speaker>Whitehouse</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
March 1st Saturday    A pleasant morning, Twelve Men left the fort to go after the Elk meat.    About noon the two hunters that were out returned to the fort, &amp; had not killed any kind of game.    The afternoon proved Showery &amp; wet.    In the evening, the party that went after the Elk meat returned, &amp; brought the meat with them.    Four of our Men went out hunting.    they went up a River called by the Natives <name type="place" key="Youngs (Kilhow-a-nah-kle) River">Ir-rum-mack-hill</name>, &amp; the River that our Fort lay near, is called by the Natives <name type="place" key="Lewis and Clark (Fort, Netul) River">Ne-tul</name>.<ref target="n28030114" n="14"/>    These hunters staid out all night—



</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n28030101" n="1">
               <name type="person" key="Shields, John">Shields</name>, <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Joseph Field</name>, and <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name>; see above, <ref n="1806-02-28" type="related">February 28, 1806</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28030102" n="2">Slaves were one of the most important articles of commerce in the trade networks of the Northwest Coast and interior. The <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name> was the great artery of this trade, and the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinooks</name>, the great traders at the river's mouth, were said to have more slaves per capita than any other tribe. Treatment of slaves could be harsher than <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> indiates; they might be sacrificed at their master's death to accompany him to the next world. Unlike contemporary Anglo-American practices, Northwest slaves sometimes owned their own slaves and might fight at their master's command. Slaves could not deform the heads of their children, a practice reserved for the elite. Ruby &amp; Brown (CITC), 10, 21–22; Ruby &amp; Brown (IPN), 29, 58, 61–62.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28030103" n="3">A new species, the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbian</name> sharp-tailed grouse, <hi rend="italic">Tympanuchus phasianellus columbianus,</hi> a subspecies of those on the upper <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, <hi rend="italic">T. phasianellus</hi> [AOU, 308]. Burroughs, 213; Cutright (LCPN), 81, 244, 387, 436. Beginning with the previous sentence, a red vertical line continues through the first several lines of this paragraph, perhaps done by <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28030104" n="4">Perhaps a reference to the greater prarie-chicken, <hi rend="italic">Tympanuchus cupido</hi> [AOU, 305]. Burroughs, 211.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28030105" n="5">A term for wheat, <hi rend="italic">Triticum</hi> sp., which is not native to America. Here the term probably refers to the native species, bluebunch wheatgrass, <hi rend="italic">Agropyron spicatum</hi> (Pursh) Scribn. &amp; Smith, which is a dominant species in the <name type="place" key="Columbia Basin">Columbia basin</name>. Hitchcock et al., 1:459–61; Franklin &amp; Dyrness, 216.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28030106" n="6">Basin wildrye, <hi rend="italic">Elymus cinereus</hi> Scribn. &amp; Merrill. Hitchcock et al., 1:561.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28030107" n="7">Common cat-tail, here called cooper's flag, referring to the plant's long leaves which were placed between barrel staves by coopers to make barrels watertight.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28030108" n="8">Led by <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name>, as he himself relates.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28030109" n="9">
               <name type="person" key="Thompson, John B.">Thompson</name> joined the three from the previous day.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28030110" n="10">
               <name type="place" key="Youngs (Kilhow-a-nah-kle) River">Youngs River</name>, <name type="place" key="Clatsop County, Oreg.">Clatsop County</name>, <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>; see notes at <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> entry of <ref n="1805-11-30" type="related">November 30, 1805</ref>. The term is Chinookan, <hi rend="italic">giławanax̣ł</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28030111" n="11">The Chinookan <hi rend="italic">ní'tul</hi>; it is <name type="place" key="Lewis and Clark (Fort, Netul) River">Lewis and Clark River</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28030112" n="12">
               <name type="place" key="Youngs (Kilhow-a-nah-kle) River">Youngs River</name>, the party's <name type="place" key="Youngs (Kilhow-a-nah-kle) River">Kilhow-a-nah-kle River</name>, which actually flows into <name type="place" key="Youngs (Meriwether's) Bay">Youngs Bay</name>, 
their <name type="place" key="Youngs (Meriwether's) Bay">Meriwether's Bay</name>, <name type="place" key="Clatsop County, Oreg.">Clatsop County</name>, <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>. <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name> obviously considered <name type="place" key="Baker (Haley's) Bay">Baker (Haley's) Bay</name> to extend across the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> from the north side.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28030113" n="13">
               <name type="place" key="Youngs River Falls">Youngs River Falls</name>, about seventy-five feet high, <name type="place" key="Clatsop County, Oreg.">Clatsop County</name>, about ten miles south 
of <name type="place" key="Astoria, Oreg.">Astoria</name>. See <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> entry for <ref n="1806-03-05" type="related">March 5</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28030114" n="14">
               <name type="place" key="Youngs (Kilhow-a-nah-kle) River">Youngs River</name>, in <name type="place" key="Clatsop County, Oreg.">Clatsop County</name>, <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>, which the captains called <name type="place" key="Youngs (Kilhow-a-nah-kle) River">Kilhow-a-nah-kle</name> 
River. This party discovered <name type="place" key="Youngs River Falls">Youngs River Falls</name>. The term is Chinookan, <hi rend="italic">giławanax̣ł</hi>.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-02-28-1" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-03-02" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
