<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-04-23">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
April 23, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 7</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">March 23–June 9, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1991</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">159-162</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">296</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">214-215</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
         <geoDecl datum="WGS" xml:id="lc.geo.1806-04-23.01">
            <placeName/>
            <geo>45.9667 -121.5667</geo>
            <note>Camped at Rock Creek, Klickitat County, WA, at a Tenino Indian village.</note>
         </geoDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc/>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-10-06</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1806-04-23">April 23, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-04-23.01" n="lc.geo.1806-04-23.01">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Wednesday April 23rd 1806.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
At day light this morning we were informed that the two horses of our Interpreter <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbono</name> were absent; on enquiry it appeared that he had neglected to confine them to picquts as had been directed last evening.    we immediately dispatched <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">Reubin Feilds</name> and <name type="person" key="Labiche, François">Labuish</name> to assist <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbono</name> in recovering his horses.    one of them was found at no great distance and the other was given over as lost.    at 8 A. M. <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">Reuben Feilds</name> and <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Sergt. Gass</name> proceeded in the canoe.    at 10 <name type="person" key="Labiche, François">Labuish</name> and <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbono</name> returned unsuccessfull, they had gone back on the road nearly to the last village and suched the plains on either hand to a considerable distance.    our remaining longer would have prevented our making a timely stage which in our situation is all important; we therefore determined to proceed immediately to the next village which from the information of our guide will occupy the greater part of the day to reach    at eleven OCk. we loaded our horses and set out.    during the time we were detained this morning we had two packsaddles made.    we continued our march along a narrow rocky bottom on the N. side of the river about 12 miles to the <name type="native_nation" key="Tenino Indians">Wah-how-pum</name> Village<ref target="n32042301" n="1"/> of 12 temperary mat lodges near the Rock rapid.    these people appeared much pleased to see us, sold us 4 dogs and some wood for our small articles which we had previously prepared as our only resource to obtain fuel and food through those plains.    these articles conisted of pewter buttons, strips of tin iron and brass, twisted wire &amp;c.    we also obtained some shap-le-lell newly made from these people.    here we met with a <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Chopunnish</name> man on his return up the river with his family and about 13 head of horses most of them young and unbroken.    he offered to hire us some of them to pack as far a his nation, but we prefer bying as by hireing his horses we shal have the whole of his family most probably to mentain.    at a little distance below this village we passed five lodges of the same people who like those were waiting the arrival of the salmon.    after we had arranged our camp we caused all the old and brave men to set arround and smoke with us.    we had the violin played and some of the men danced; after which the natives entertained us with a dance after their method.<ref target="n32042302" n="2"/>    this dance differed from any I have yet seen.    they formed a circle and all sung as well the spectators as the dancers who performed within the circle. these placed their sholders together with their robes tightly drawn about them and danced in a line from side to side, several parties of from 4 to seven will be performing within the circle at the same time.    the whole concluded with a premiscuous dance in which most of them sung and danced.    these people speak a language very similar to the <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Chopunnish</name> whome they also resemble in their dress    their women wear long legings mockersons shirts and robes.    their men also dress with legings shirts robes and mockersons.    after the dance was ended the indians retired at our request and we retired to rest.    we had all our horses side hubbled and turned out to graize; at this village, a large creek<ref target="n32042303" n="3"/> falls in on the N. side which we did not observe as we decended the river.    the river is by no means as rapid as when we decended or at least not obstructed with those dangerous rapids    the water at present covers most of the rocks in the bed of the river.    the natives promised to barter their horses with us in the morning we therefore entertained a hope that we shall be enabled to proceede by land from hence with the whole of our party and baggage.    came 12 miles by land.    the sands made the march fatieguing.—
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-04-23.02" n="lc.geo.1806-04-23.01">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Wednesday 23rd 1806</hi>
                     <ref target="n32042304" n="4"/>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
at day light this morning we were informed that the two horses of our interpreter <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Shabono</name> were missing    on enquirey we were informed that he had neglected to tie up his horses as derected last evening.    we imedeately dispatch him, <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">R. Fields</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Labiche, François">Labiech</name> in Serch of the horses, one of them were 〈purch〉 found at no great distnace.    the other was not found. <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">R. Fields</name> retd. without finding the horse Set out with Sergt <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name> in the Small Canoe at about 8 A M.    at 10 <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Shabono</name> and <name type="person" key="Labiche, François">Labiech</name> returned also unsucksessfull    they had went on the back trail nearly to the last Village and took a circle around on the hills.    as our Situation was Such that we Could not detain for a horse, which would prevent our makeing a timely Stage which is a great object with us in those open plains, we Concluded to give up the horse and proceed on to the next village which we were informed was at Some distance and would take us the greater part of the day.    at 11 A. M. we packed up and Set out and proceeded up on the N. Side of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> on a high narrow bottom and rockey for 12 miles to the <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Tenino Indians">Wah-how-pum</name>
                  </hi> village near the rock rapid of 12 temporary mat Lodges, those people appeared pleased to See us.    they Sold us 4 dogs Some Shapollell and wood for our Small articles Such as awls pieces of Tin and brass.    we passed Several Lodges on the bank of the river where they were fixed waiting for the Salmon. I over took a <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Choponish</name> man whome I had Seen at the long,<ref target="n32042305" n="5"/> and who had found a bag of our powder and brought it to me at that place.    this man had his family on the [<hi rend="italic">blank</hi>] and about 3 head of horses which appeared young and unbroke.    his spous as also that of the other gave me a Cake of Chapellell and proceeded on with me to the <name type="native_nation" key="Tenino Indians">Wah howpum</name> Village and formed his Camp near us.    we Caused all the old &amp; brave men to Set around and Smoke with us.    we Caused the fiddle to be played and Some of the men danced.    after them the nativs danced.    they dance different from any Indians I have Seen.    they dance with their Sholders together and pass from Side to Side, defferent parties passing each other, from 2 to 7.    and 4 parties danceing at the Same time and Concluding the dance by passing promiscuisly throu &amp; beetween each other.    after which we Sent of the Indians and retired to bed. Those people Speak a language verry Similal to the <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Chopunish</name> and with a very inconsiderable difference.    their dress and appearance to the <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Chopunish</name> and with a very inconsiderable difference.    their dress and appearance is more like those of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Great Falls of the">Great falls of the Columbia</name>.    we had all our horses Side hobbled and let out to feed.    at this village a large Creek falls in on the N. Side which I had not observed as I decended the river.    the river is by no means as rapid as it was at the time we decended. The nativs promised to give is a horse for one of our Canoes. and offer to Sell us another for a Scarlet robe which we have not at present. <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Shabono</name> made a bargin with one of the Indian men going with us, for a horse for Which he gave his Shirt.    and two of the leather Sutes of his wife. The Sand through which we walked to day is So light that renders the march verry fatigueing.    made 12 miles by land.

</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-04-23.03" n="lc.geo.1806-04-23.01">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Wednesday 23rd of April 1806.    one of our horses broke loose and Strayed away last night    we delayed to hunt for him &amp; made two pack Saddles.    we could not find our lost horse.    about 10 A. M. Set out    proced on through high plains and banks of Sand along the river.    the day warm.    towards evening we arived at a large village at the mouth of a creek where we Camped<ref target="n32042306" n="6"/>    our canoes came up.    we purchased 4 dogs and a considerable
quantity of Chappalell &amp;C.    the day warm.    these Savages have lately mooved here &amp; have a great number of horses.    our horses are troublesome as the most of them are Studs.    but the feed is good the prarie covred with flowrs    the natives are numerous at this place.    they had a dance<ref target="n32042307" n="7"/> at our fire this evening.    nearly the Same manner &amp; way as those on the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missourie</name>.    we played the fiddle and danced &amp;C. Several of the flat heads continue on with us &amp; assist us as much as lyes in their power.—


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-04-23.04" n="lc.geo.1806-04-23.01">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Wednesday 23rd.</hi>    We had a cloudy morning. I went also by water to day, and we had very laborious work in getting along. In the evening we met the party at a large village of the <name type="native_nation" key="Tenino Indians">Wal-la-waltz nation</name>,<ref target="n32042308" n="8"/> on the north side of the river; where the other canoe had also arrived. Here we halted, unloaded the canoes and encamped. A horse had got away last night and could not be found.



</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n32042301" n="1">A Shahaptian-speaking group who lived around the mouth of <name type="place" key="Rock Creek (Klickitat County, Wash.)">Rock Creek</name> in <name type="place" key="Klickitat County, Wash.">Klickitat County</name>, <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>. See <ref n="1805-10-21" type="related">October 21, 1805</ref>; <hi rend="italic">Altas</hi> map 77. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> "<name type="native_nation" key="Tenino Indians">Wah-how-pum</name>" may come from the tribe's self-designation, <hi rend="italic">hǎhau'pǔm,</hi> "willow people." However, Spier equates the term with <hi rend="italic">Waiyǎ'mpǎm,</hi> "those of <hi rend="italic">Waiyǎ'm,</hi>" the Shahaptian name for <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Great Falls of the">Celilo Falls</name>. Spier also suggests that the name <hi rend="italic">Waiyǎ'mpǎm</hi> may not refer to a specific group but collectively to the people who congregated in this area on both sides of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>. Another possibility is Shahaptian <hi rend="italic">
                  <seg n="uxu803">x̣</seg>
                  <hi rend="superscript">w</hi>a<seg n="uluslash">l/</seg>
                  <seg n="uxu803">x̣</seg>
                  <hi rend="superscript">w</hi>aypam,</hi> representing a Shahaptian-speaking group within the <name type="place" key="Klickitat (Cataract) River">Klickitat River</name> drainage. These people under discussion are now generally subsumed under the name <name type="native_nation" key="Tenino Indians">Teninos</name>, including others in this general area. Archaeological investigations in this vicinity at the <name type="place" key="Wildcat Canyon site">Wildcat Canyon site</name> on the <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name> shore encountered evidence of occupation beginning around 8,000 years ago, with a major village documented at this locality between 2,500 and 1,000 year ago. Hodge, 2:890; Spier (TDW), 19; Ray et al.; Dumond &amp; Minor. The day's camp was at a village above <name type="place" key="Rock Creek (Klickitat County, Wash.)">Rock Creek</name>. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 77. See also <ref n="1805-10-20" type="related">figure</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32042302" n="2">While not necessarily religious in form, the circle dance here described suggests an early version of the Prophet Dance, a nativistic movement that later spread widely throughout the <name type="place" key="Columbia Plateau">Columbia Plateau</name>. Spier (PD).</note>
            <note xml:id="n32042303" n="3">
               <name type="place" key="Rock Creek (Klickitat County, Wash.)">Rock Creek</name>, in <name type="place" key="Klickitat County, Wash.">Klickitat County</name>, nameless on <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 77; it reaches the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> above the mouth of <name type="place"
                     key="John Day (Lepage's) River (Sherman-Gilliam counties, Oreg.)">John Day River (River La Page)</name> on the opposite shore.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32042304" n="4">Near this date in <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> Voorhis No. 3 is the word "<name type="native_nation" key="Tenino Indians">Wah-how-pum</name>."</note>
            <note xml:id="n32042305" n="5">The "<name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">Long Narrows" of the Columbia</name>, at <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The Dalles</name>. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 78.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32042306" n="6">At <name type="place" key="Rock Creek (Klickitat County, Wash.)">Rock Creek</name>, <name type="place" key="Klickitat County, Wash.">Klickitat County</name>, <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>, at a village of <name type="native_nation" key="Tenino Indians">Tenino Indians</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32042307" n="7">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> describe the dance more fully in their entries for this day.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32042308" n="8">A "<name type="native_nation" key="Tenino Indians">Wah-how-pum</name>" village at the mouth of <name type="place" key="Rock Creek (Klickitat County, Wash.)">Rock Creek</name>, <name type="place" key="Klickitat County, Wash.">Klickitat County</name>, <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>. 
These Shahaptian-language people are now generally classified as <name type="native_nation" key="Tenino Indians">Teninos</name>, with others in the vicinity. The party camped here, somewhat above the mouth of <name type="place"
                     key="John Day (Lepage's) River (Sherman-Gilliam counties, Oreg.)">John Day River</name>, their <name type="place"
                     key="John Day (Lepage's) River (Sherman-Gilliam counties, Oreg.)">River Lapage</name>, after party member <name type="person" key="Lepage, Jean Baptiste">Jean Baptiste Lepage</name>, opposite.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-04-22" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-04-24" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
