<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1803-09-04">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">September 4, 1803</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2003</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 2</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">August 30, 1803–August 24, 1804</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1986</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">70-72</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
         <geoDecl datum="WGS" xml:id="lc.geo.1803-09-04.01">
            <placeName/>
            <geo>40.62 -80.537</geo>
            <note>Two miles below state line, about two miles SW of Georgetown</note>
         </geoDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc/>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2003-12-09</date>
            <date/>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>
            <name/>Initial creation Transcribed</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1803-09-04">September 4, 1803</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1803-09-04.01" n="lc.geo.1803-09-04.01">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>Sept. 4th 1803.</date>
               </ab>
               <p>
Morning foggy, obliged to wait. Thermometer at 63°—    temperature of the river-water 73° being a difference of ten degrees, but yesterday there was a difference of twelve degrees, so that the water must have changed it's temperature 2d in twenty four hours, <hi rend="italic">coalder;</hi> at ¼ past 8 the murcury rose in the open air to 68°    the fogg dispeared and we set out; the difference therefore of 5° in temperature between the warter and air is not sufficient to produce the appearance of fogg—    from the watermark we fixed last evening it appeared that the river during the night had fallen an inch perpendicularly.—    the Perogue<ref target="n02090401" n="1"/> was loaded as his been my practice since I left <name type="place" key="Pittsburgh, Pa.">Pittsburgh</name>, in order as much as posseble to lighten the boat, the [man or men] who conducted her called as in distress about an hour after we had got under way, we came too and waaited her coming up    found she had sprung a leek and had nearly filled; this accedent was truly distressing, as her load consisting of articles of hard-ware, intended as presents to the Indians got wet and I fear are much damaged; proceeded about three miles further    got fast on a bar below <name type="place" key="Georgetown, Pa.">georgetown</name>, and with the assistance of some of the neighboring people got overe it with much difficulty; at <name type="place" key="Georgetown, Pa.">Georgetown</name>
                  <ref target="n02090402" n="2"/> purchased a canoe compleat with two paddles and two poles for which I gave 11$, found that my new purchase leaked so much that she was unsafe woithout some repairs; came too about a mile below the riffle on the east shore<ref target="n02090403" n="3"/> pretty early in the evening where we stayed all night having made 〈only〉 about thirteen miles this day.    opened the articles which had got wet and exposed them to the sun; set some of my hands to repareing the canoes which I effected before night    had the articles well oiled and put up in oilcloth baggs and returned to the casks in which they were previously were, hired another hand to go with me as far as <name type="place" key="Wheeling, W. Va.">Wheeling</name>—    the articles were not as much injured as I had supposed—<ref target="n02090404" n="4"/>
               </p>
               <p>
about two miles above my camp passed the line, which divides the States of <name type="place" key="Virginia">Virginia</name>
                  <ref target="n02090405" n="5"/> and <name type="place" key="Pennsylvania">Pensylvania</name> on the east side of the river and on the West that of <name type="place" key="Pennsylvania">Pensylvania</name> from the State of <name type="place" key="Ohio">Ohio</name>; this line is made vi[si]ble from the timber having been felled about sixty feet in width, the young timber has spring up but has not yet attained the hight of the other that it can with ease be traced with the eye a considirable distance—    it passes the <name type="place" key="Ohio River">Ohio River</name> at the mouth of <name type="place" key="Mill Creek (W. Va.)">mill Creek</name>
                  <ref target="n02090406" n="6"/>  The water is so low and clear that we see a great number of Fish of different kinds, the Stergeon, Bass, Cat fish, pike,<ref target="n02090407" n="7"/> &amp;c.    we fixed some spears after the indian method but have had too much to attend to of more importance than gigging fish.—

</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n02090401" n="1">The French word <hi rend="italic">pirogue</hi> was used in the fur trade for a large dugout canoe or open boat. McDermott (GMVF), 118–19; Russell (FTT), 47. It is not clear if this vessel was actually a pirogue, as <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> seems to have used the terms <hi rend="italic">pirogue</hi> and <hi rend="italic">canoe</hi> interchangeably. If it actually was a pirogue, it may have been either the red or the white pirogue so-called that figured prominently during the expedition. In this entry <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> also mentions purchasing a canoe at <name type="place" key="Georgetown, Pa.">Georgetown</name> and then speaks of two canoes (as he does the next day, September 5), but this is probably two vessels in addition to the keelboat and not two canoes in addition to the keelboat and pirogue. Again the confusion of terminology. One more vessel was purchased at <name type="place" key="Wheeling, W. Va.">Wheeling</name> on September 8, and <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> calls it a pirogue. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> correspondence during this period is of little help in sorting this out.</note>
            <note xml:id="n02090402" n="2">
               <name type="place" key="Georgetown, Pa.">Georgetown</name>, in western <name type="place" key="Beaver County, Pa.">Beaver County, Pennsylvania</name>, near the state line, was founded in 1793 by Benoni Dawson. Thwaites (EWT), 4:101 and n. 59.</note>
            <note xml:id="n02090403" n="3">In <name type="place" key="Hancock County, W. Va.">Hancock County, West Virginia</name>, about two miles below the state line.</note>
            <note xml:id="n02090404" n="4">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> may have intended a new entry on the next line; "September" is crossed out.</note>
            <note xml:id="n02090405" n="5">Present <name type="place" key="West Virginia">West Virginia</name> was part of <name type="place" key="Virginia">Virginia</name> until 1863.</note>
            <note xml:id="n02090406" n="6">
               <name type="place" key="Mill Creek (W. Va.)">Mill Creek</name> flows into the <name type="place" key="Ohio River">Ohio</name> from the south on the <name type="place" key="Pennsylvania">Pennsylvania</name>–<name type="place" key="West Virginia">West Virginia</name> border, opposite <name type="place" key="Little Beaver Creek (Ohio)">Little Beaver Creek</name>. Cramer (6th), 44.</note>
            <note xml:id="n02090407" n="7">The first fish is perhaps the shovelnose sturgeon, <hi rend="italic">Scaphirhynchus platorynchus;</hi> the bass could be the smallmouth, <hi rend="italic">Micropterus dolomieui,</hi> or the largemouth, <hi rend="italic">M. salmoides;</hi> the northern pike is <hi rend="italic">Esox lucius;</hi> the catfish could be the channel cat, <hi rend="italic">Ictalurus punctatus,</hi> or the blue, <hi rend="italic">I. furcatus.</hi> Lee et al., 44, 605, 608, 133, 446, 439.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1803-09-03" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1803-09-05" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
