<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-02-17">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
February 17, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 6</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">November 2, 1805–March 22, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1990</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">321-325</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">272</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">193</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 11</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of Joseph Whitehouse, May 14, 1804–April 2, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1997</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">420-421</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc/>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-08-26</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1806-02-17">February 17, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-02-17.01" n="">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Monday February 17th 1806.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Collins, John">Collins</name> and <name type="person" key="Windsor, Richard">Windsor</name> were permited to hunt today towards the praries in <name type="place" key="Point Adams">Point Adams</name> with a view to obtain some fresh meat for the sick.    a little before noon <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name>
                  <name type="person" key="Labiche, François">LaBuishe</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">Frazier</name> returned with the flesh and hide of an Elk which had been wouded by Sergt. <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass's</name> party and took the water where they pursued it and caught it.    they did not see Sergt. <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name> or any of his party nor learn what further succes they had had.    continue the barks with <name type="person" key="Bratton, William E.">Bratton</name>, and commenced them with <name type="person" key="Gibson, George">Gibson</name> his fever being sufficiently low this morning to permit the uce of them. I think therefore that there is no further danger of his recovery.—    at 2 P. M. <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Joseph Fields</name> arrived from the <name type="place" key="Saltmaking Camp (Oreg.)">Salt works</name> and informed us that they had about 2 Kegs of salt on hand which with what we have at this place we suppose will be sufficient to last us to our deposits of that article on the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>.    we there directed a party of six men to go with Fields in the morning in order to bring the salt and kettles to the fort.    <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name> 〈&amp; <name type="person" key="Labiche, François">Labuishe</name>〉 brought me one of the large carrion Crow or Buzzads of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> which they had wounded and taken alive.<ref target="n28021701" n="1"/> I bleive this to be the largest bird of North America.    it was not in good order and yet it weighed 25 lbs. had it have been so it might very well have weighed 10 lbs mor or 35 lbs.    between the extremities of the wings it measured 9 feet 2 inches; from the extremity of the beak to that of the toe 3 F. 9½ In. from hip to toe 2 feet, girth of head 9¾ In. girth of the neck 7½ Inches; do. of body exclusive of the wings 2 feet 3 Inches; do of leg 3 inches.    diameter of the eye 4½/10ths of an inch.    the iris of a pale scarlet red, the puple of deep sea green or black and occupyed about one third of the diameter of the eye.    the head and a part of the neck as low as the figures 1 2 is uncovered with feathers except that portion of it represented by dots (see likeness).<ref target="n28021702" n="2"/>    the tail is composed of 12 feathers of equal length, each 14 inches.    the legs are 4¾ inches in length and of a white colour un covered with feathers, they are not entirely smooth but not imbricated; the toes are four in number three of which are forward and that in the center much the longes; the fourth is short and is inserted near the inner of the three other toes and reather projecting forward.    the thye is covered with feathers as low as the knee.    the top or upper part of the toes are imbricated with broad scales lying transversly; the nails are blak and in proportion to the size of the bird comparitively with those of the halk or Eagle, short and bluntly pointed.    the under side of the wing is covered with white down and feathers.    a white stripe of about two inches in width, also marks the outer part of the wing, imbracing the lower points of the feathers, which cover the joints of the wing through their whole length or width of that part of the wing.    all the other feathers of whatever part are glossey shining black except the down which is not glossey but equally black.    the skin of the beak and head to the joining of the neck is of a pale orrange yellow the other part uncovered with feathers is of a light flesh colour.    the skin is thin and wrinkled except on the beak where it is smooth.    this bird flys very clumsily nor do I know whether it ever seizes it's prey alive, but am induced to beleive that it dose not.    we have seen it feeding on the remains of the whale &amp; other fish which have been thrown up by the waves on the sea coast.    these I beleive constitute their prinsipal food, but I have no doubt but they also feed on flesh; we did not met with this bird untill we had decended the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> below the <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Great Falls of the">great falls</name>, and have found them more abundant below tide-water than above. I beleive that this bird is reather of the Vulture genus than any other, tho' it wants some of their characteristics particularly the hair on the neck and feathers on the legs.—    this is a handsome bird at a little distance.    it's neck is proportionably longer than those of the hawks or Eagle. <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name> also brought me a grey Eagle which appeared to be of the same kind common to the U' States; it weighed 15 lb. and measured 7 Feet 7 Inches between the extremities of the wings.— At 4 P. M. Sergt. <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name> and party arrived; they had killed eight Elk. <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name> and <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse</name> also returned late in the evening, had killed one Elk.— <name type="person" key="Labiche, François">Labuishe</name> informed me that when he approached this vulture, after wounding it, that it made a loud noise very much like the barking of a dog &amp; the tongue is large firm and broad, filling the under chap and partaking of it's transverse curvature, or it's sides colapsing upwards forming a longitudinal groove; obtuse at the point, the margin armed with firm cartelaginous prickkles pointed and bending inwards.
</p>
               <p>
                  <figure rend="aps">
                     <p>Head of a Vulture (California condor, <hi rend="italic">Gymnogyps califorianus</hi>),<lb/>
February 17, 1806, Codex J, p. 80<bibl>
                           <orgName>(American Philosophical Society library, </orgName>
                           <note place="inline"> used with permission.)</note>
                        </bibl>
                     </p>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-02-17.02" n="">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Monday February 17th 1806</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Collins, John">Collins</name> and <name type="person" key="Windsor, Richard">Windser</name> were permited to hunt to day towards the praries in <name type="place" key="Point Adams">point Adams</name> with a view to obtain Some fresh meat for the Sick.    a little before noon <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name> and <name type="person" key="Labiche, François">Labiesh</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">frazier</name> Came with the flesh and hide of an Elk which had been wounded by <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Serjt. Gasses</name> party and took the water where they pursued it and cought it.    they did not See Sergt. <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name> or any of his party or learn what further Sucksess they have had. Continu the barks with <name type="person" key="Bratton, William E.">Bratten</name>, and Commenced them with <name type="person" key="Gibson, George">gibson</name> his feaver being Sufficiently low this morning to permit the use of them. I think therefore that there is no further danger of his recovery.—.    at 2 P. M. <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Joseph Field</name> arrived from the <name type="place" key="Saltmaking Camp (Oreg.)">Salt works</name> and informd us that they had about 2 Kegs of Salt on hand (say 3 bushels) which with what we have at this place we suppose will be Sufficient to last us to our deposit of that article on the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>.    we directed a party of Six men to go in the morning in order to bring the salt and Kittles to the Fort.    at 4 P. M. <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Serjt. Gass</name> and party arrive; they had killed 8 Elk. <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name> and <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse</name> also return late in the evening, they had killed one Elk, part of the meat of which they brought in with them.</p>
               <p>
The Brown, White, or Grizly <hi rend="italic">Bear</hi> are found in the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">rocky mountain</name>s in the timbered part of it or Westerly Side but rarely; they are more Common below or on the East Side of the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky Mountains</name> on the borders of the plains where there are Copses of bushes and underwood near the water cources.    they are by no means as plenty on this Side of the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky Mountains</name> as on the other, nor do I believe they are found at all in the woody country which borders this coast as far in the interior as the range of mountains which pass the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> between the enterance of <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clarks</name> and the <name type="place" key="Sandy (Quicksand) River">Quick sand Rivers</name>
                  <ref target="n28021703" n="3"/> or below the <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Great Falls of the">Great falls of Columbia</name>.</p>
               <p>
The Black <hi rend="italic">Bear</hi> differs not any from those Common to the U. States, and are found under the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky Mountains</name> in the woody country on the borders of the <name type="place" key="Great Columbian Plain">Great Plain's of Columbia</name> and also in this tract of woody country which lie between these plains and the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific Ocian</name>.    their econimy and habits are also the Same with those of the United States.—.

</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-02-17.03" n="">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Monday 17th Feby. 1806.    a little Snow fell this fournoon.    three hunters<ref target="n28021704" n="4"/> came in with the meat of an Elk which they took out of a creek where
some of the hunters had killed    in the after part of the day Sgt. <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name> and 2 men<ref target="n28021705" n="5"/> returned to the Fort.    they had killed Eight Elk, and jurked 2 of them. Some of the men killed a gray Eagle and a new kind of a Turkey buzzad.<ref target="n28021706" n="6"/>    one man<ref target="n28021707" n="7"/> came from the <name type="place" key="Saltmaking Camp (Oreg.)">Salt works</name> for help to move in the Salt &amp; kittles. <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse</name> came in    had killed one Elk.—


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-02-17.04" n="">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Monday 17th.</hi>    The day was stormy; we set out for the fort, and arrived there in the afternoon. We found the sick men<ref target="n28021708" n="8"/> at the fort, and still very bad. One of the men<ref target="n28021709" n="9"/> brought word from the <name type="place" key="Saltmaking Camp (Oreg.)">salt works</name>, that they had made about four bushels of salt; and the Commanding Officers thought that would be sufficient to serve the party, until we should arrive at the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> where there is some deposited.


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-02-17.05" n="">
            <sp who="jw">
               <speaker>Whitehouse</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Monday Febry 17th    during last night some Snow fell.    this Morning the weather Clear.    the three hunters that went out Yesterday returned this forenoon, and brought with them, an Elk which they found dead in the River &amp; which they supposed some of our hunters had killed.    In the afternoon Serjeant <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name> &amp; 2 of our hunters returned to the fort; they had killed 8 Elk &amp; had Jerked the meat of 2 of them.    One of our Men came from the <name type="place" key="Saltmaking Camp (Oreg.)">Salt works</name>.    He came to get some help from us, to help move in the kettles &amp; Salt from the <name type="place" key="Saltmaking Camp (Oreg.)">Salt works</name>.    One of our hunters killed a very large Grey Eagle.<ref target="n28021710" n="10"/>    Two of our hunters<ref target="n28021711" n="11"/> also came to the fort    they had killed One Elk.—



</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n28021701" n="1">The first several lines of this material about the condor have a vertical line through them, perhaps placed by <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28021702" n="2">A sketch of the California condor's head in <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> Codex J, p. 80 (fig. 39).</note>
            <note xml:id="n28021703" n="3">Respectively the <name type="place" key="Deschutes (Clark's, Towanahiook's) River">Deschutes River</name>, <name type="place" key="Sherman County, Oreg.">Sherman County</name>, and the <name type="place" key="Sandy (Quicksand) River">Sandy River</name>, <name type="place" key="Multnomah County, Oreg.">Multnomah County</name>, both in <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>. The mountains are the <name type="place" key="Cascade Range">Cascade Range</name>. Eventually they named the <name type="place" key="Deschutes (Clark's, Towanahiook's) River">Deschutes</name> the "<name type="place" key="Deschutes (Clark's, Towanahiook's) River">Towarnahiooks</name>" (variously spelled), giving <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> name to the present <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">Bitterroot</name>-<name type="place"
                     key="Clark Fork (Clark's, East Fork Clark's, Flathead) River">Clark Fork</name>-<name type="place"
                     key="Pend Oreille (Clark's, Flathead, Lastaro, Lastaw) River">Pend Oreille</name> combination of rivers. See Introduction to the <hi rend="italic">Atlas,</hi> and <ref n="1805-10-22" type="related">October 22, 1805</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28021704" n="4">The three from yesterday.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28021705" n="5">
               <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">Reubin Field</name> and <name type="person" key="Thompson, John B.">Thompson</name>; see the entry of <ref n="1806-02-11" type="related">February 11</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28021706" n="6">The California condor noted on <ref n="1805-10-30" type="related">October 30</ref> and <ref n="1805-11-18" type="related">November 18, 1805</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28021707" n="7">
               <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Joseph Field</name>, report the captains.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28021708" n="8">Gibson and <name type="person" key="Bratton, William E.">Bratton</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28021709" n="9">
               <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Joseph Field</name>, relate the captains.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28021710" n="10">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> says <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name> brought a golden eagle to him.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28021711" n="11">
               <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name> and <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse</name>, report <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, and <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-02-16" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-02-18" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
