<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-08-12">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
August 12, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 8</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">June 10–September 26, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1987</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">157-159, 289-296</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">348-349</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">266-267</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
         <geoDecl datum="WGS" xml:id="lc.geo.1806-08-12.01">
            <placeName/>
            <geo>47.8111 -102.701</geo>
            <note>Clark and the rest of the party reunited today. Their camp was located at Bear Den Creek, McKenzie County, ND.</note>
         </geoDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc/>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-12-10</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1806-08-12">August 12, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-08-12.01" n="lc.geo.1806-08-12.01">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Thursday August 12th 1806.</hi>
                     <ref target="n37081201" n="1"/>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
Being anxious to overtake <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name> who from the appearance of his camps could be at no great distance before me, we set out early and proceeded with all possible expedition    at 8 A. M. the bowsman informed me that there was a canoe and a camp he beleived of whitemen on the N. E. shore. I directed the perogue and canoes to come too at this place and found it to be the camp of two hunters from the <name type="place" key="Illinois">Illinois</name> by name <name type="person" key="Dickson, Joseph">Joseph Dickson</name> and <name type="person" key="Hancock, Forrest">Forest Hancock</name>.<ref target="n37081202" n="2"/>    these men informed me that <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. C.</name> had passed them about noon the day before.    they also informed me that they had left the <name type="place" key="Illinois">Illinois</name> in the summer 1804 since which time they had been ascended the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, hunting and traping beaver; that they had been robed by the indians and the former wounded last winter by the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">Tetons of the birnt woods</name>;<ref target="n37081203" n="3"/> that they had hitherto been unsuccessfull in their voyage having as yet caught but little beaver, but were still determined to proceed. I gave them a short discription of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, a list of distances to the most conspicuous streams and remarkable places on the river above and pointed out to them the places where the beaver most abounded. I also gave them a file and a couple of pounds of powder with some lead.    these were articles which they assured me they were in great want of. I remained with these men an hour and a half when I took leave of them and proceeded.    〈at one OCK in the〉 while I halted with these men <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name> and <name type="person" key="Collins, John">Collins</name> who seperated from us on the 3rd ist. rejoined us.    they were well no accedent having happened.    they informed me that after proceeding the first day and not overtaking us that they had concluded that we were behind and had delayed several days in waiting for us and had thus been unable to join us untill the present momet.    my wounds felt very stiff and soar this morning but gave me no considerable pain.    there was much less inflamation than I had reason to apprehend there would be. I had last evening applyed a poltice of peruvian barks.<ref target="n37081204" n="4"/>    at 1 P. M. I overtook <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name> and party and had the pleasure of finding them all well.<ref target="n37081205" n="5"/>    as wrighting in my present situation is extreemly painfull to me I shall desist untill I recover and leave to my frind <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. C.</name> the continuation of our journal.<ref target="n37081206" n="6"/>    however I must notice a singular Cherry<ref target="n37081207" n="7"/> which is found on the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> in the bottom lands about the beaverbends and some little distance below the <name type="place" key="Little Muddy (White Earth) River">white earth river</name>.    this production is not very abundant even in the small tract of country to which it seems to be confined.    the stem is compound erect and subdivided or branching without any regular order it rises to the hight of eight or ten feet seldom puting up more than one stem from the same root not growing in cops as the Choke Cherry dose. the bark is smooth and of a dark brown colour.    the leaf is peteolate, oval accutely pointed at it's apex, from one and a ¼ to 1½ inches in length and from ½ to ¾ of an inch in width, finely or minutely serrate, pale green and free from bubessence.    the fruit is a globular berry about the size of a buck-shot of a fine scarlet red; like the cherries cultivated in the U' States each is supported by a seperate celindric flexable branch peduncle which issue from the extremities of the boughs    the peduncle of this cherry swells as it approahes the fruit being largest at the point of insertion.    the pulp of this fruit is of an agreeable ascid flavour and is now ripe.    the style and stigma<ref target="n37081208" n="8"/> are permanent. I have never seen it in blume.

</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-08-12.02" n="lc.geo.1806-08-12.01">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Thursday 12th August 1806</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
I set out early this morning and had not proceeded on far before <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name> discovered he had lost his Tomahk. I derected him to land his Skin Canoe and go back to our Camp of last night in Serch of it, and proceeded on my self with the two wood and one Skin Canoe to a large bottom on the N. E. Side above the head of Jins [<hi rend="italic">NB: Qu: an</hi>] island<ref target="n37081209" n="9"/> and landed to take brackfast as well as to delay untill <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Gibson, George">Gibson</name> Should arive. Sent out <name type="person" key="Shields, John">Shields</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Labiche, François">Labiech</name> to hunt deer in the bottom, at 2 〈a〉 P m. <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name> and <name type="person" key="Gibson, George">gibson</name> arived having found the tomahawk at our camp they killed 3 Elk &amp;c.    one of the Canoes of Buffalow Skin by accident got a hole peirced in her of about 6 inches diamuter. I derected two of the men to patch the Canoe with a piece of Elk skin over the hole, which they did and it proved all Sufficient, after which the Canoe did not leak one drop. The two hunters returned without haveing killed any thing.    at meridian <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt Lewis</name> hove in Sight with the party which went by way of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> as well as that which accompanied him from <name type="place" key="Lolo (Travelers' Rest) Creek (Mont.)">Travellers rest</name> on <name type="place"
                        key="Clark Fork (Clark's, East Fork Clark's, Flathead) River">Clarks river</name>; I was alarmed on the landing of the Canoes to be informed that <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name> was wounded by an accident—. I found him lying in the Perogue, he informed me that his wound was slight and would be well in 20 or 30 days this information relieved me very much. I examined the wound and found it a very bad flesh wound the ball had passed through the fleshey part of his left thy below the hip bone and cut the cheek of the right buttock for 3 inches in length and the debth of the ball. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt L.</name> informed me the accident happened the day before by one of the men <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Peter Crusat</name> misstakeig him in the thick bushes to be an Elk. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt Lewis</name> with this <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Crusat</name> and Several other men were out in the bottom Shooting of Elk, and had Scattered in a thick part of the woods in pursute of the Elk. <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Crusat</name> Seeing <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt L.</name> passing through the bushes and takeing him to be an Elk from the Colour of his Cloathes which were of leather and very nearly that of the Elk fired and unfortunately the ball passed through the thy as aforesaid. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt Lewis</name> thinking it indians who had Shot him hobbled to the canoes as fast as possible and was followered by <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Crusat</name>, the mistake was then discovered. This <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Crusat</name> is near Sighted and has the use of but one eye, he is an attentive industerous man and one whome we both have placed the greatest Confidence in dureing the whole route.— After <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name> and my Self parted at <name type="place" key="Lolo (Travelers' Rest) Creek (Mont.)">Travellers rest</name>,<ref target="n37081210" n="10"/> he with the Indians proceeded down the West Side of <name type="place"
                        key="Clark Fork (Clark's, East Fork Clark's, Flathead) River">Clarks river</name> Seven miles and crossed on rafts 2 miles below the East fork 120 yards wide, after Crossing the river he proceeded up the North Side of the east fork and encampd.    here the Indians left him and proceeded down <name type="place"
                        key="Clark Fork (Clark's, East Fork Clark's, Flathead) River">Clarks river</name> in Serch of the <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Tushepaws</name>.</hi>    an Indian man Came up with <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Cap L.</name> from the W. of the mountains and proceeded on with those who had accompanied us. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. L.</name> proceeded up the <name type="place"
                        key="Clark Fork (Clark's, East Fork Clark's, Flathead) River">E. fork of Clarks river</name> 17 ms. to the enterance of <name type="place" key="North Fork Blackfoot (Cohahlarishkit) River">Cokahlarishkit river or the river to buffalow</name>, he proceeded up on the North Side of this river which is 60 yards wide crossing Several Small Streams and the N. fork, and passing over part of the dividing mountain onto the waters of <name type="place" key="Dearborn River">Deabourns river</name> in the plains and in a Derection to the N. extremity of Easte range of <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">rocky mountains</name> which pass the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> at the <name type="place" key="Half-Breed (Pine Island) Rapids">pine Island Rapid</name>.    from thence he bore his Course to the N E untill he Struck <name type="place" key="Sun (Mah-pah-pah,-ah-zhah, Medicine) River">Meadcin river</name> near where that river Enters the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">rocky Mts.</name> and proceeded down <name type="place" key="Sun (Mah-pah-pah,-ah-zhah, Medicine) River">Medicine river</name> to the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> at the <name type="place" key="White Bear Islands">white bear Islands</name> at the upper part of the portage.    this rout is a very good one tho not the most derect rout, the most derect rout would be to proceed up the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> above <name type="place" key="Dearborn River">Dearborns river</name> and take a right hand road &amp; fall on a South branch of the <name type="place" key="North Fork Blackfoot (Cohahlarishkit) River">Cokatlarishkit R.</name> and proceed down that river to the main road    but the best rout would be from the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">falls of the Missouri</name> by <name type="place" key="Square Butte (Fort Mountain)">fort mountain</name> and passing the N. extremity of that range of the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky Mountains</name> which pass the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> at the <name type="place" key="Half-Breed (Pine Island) Rapids">pine Island rapid</name> Course nearly S. W. and to the gap through which the great road passeds the dividing mountain the distance from the falls to this gap about 45 miles through a tolerable leavel plain on an old indian road.    and the distance from thence to <name type="place"
                        key="Clark Fork (Clark's, East Fork Clark's, Flathead) River">Clarks river</name> is 105 miles. The total distance from the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">falls of the Missouri</name> to <name type="place"
                        key="Clark Fork (Clark's, East Fork Clark's, Flathead) River">Clarks river</name> is only <hi rend="italic">150</hi> miles of a tolerable road—    <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt L.</name> arived at the <name type="place" key="White Bear Islands">white Bear Islands</name> and encampd. on the West Side of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> and in the morning he discovered that the Indians had taken of Seven of his best horses, <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">drewyer</name> prosued the indians two day's on the rout towards <name type="place"
                        key="Clark Fork (Clark's, East Fork Clark's, Flathead) River">Clarks river</name>.    he Saw their camp on <name type="place" key="Dearborn River">Dearborns river</name> near the road on which <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name> &amp; party Come on a by place where they had left only one or two day at this encampment he Saw great appearanc of horses—    on the return of <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt L.</name> took <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name> &amp; the <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph and Reubin">2 fieldses</name> &amp; proceeded on his intended rout up <name type="place" key="Marias River">Marias river</name> leaving <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Sergt. Gass</name>, <name type="person" key="Thompson, John B.">Thompson</name>, <name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">Frazier</name>, <name type="person" key="Werner, William">Werner</name>, <name type="person" key="McNeal, Hugh">McNeal</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Goodrich, Silas">Goodrich</name> at the portage to prepare Geer and repar the wheels &amp; Carrage against the arival of the Canoes and he also left 4 horses for the purpose of hauling the Canoes across. The Canoes arrived on the 16th, and on the 26th they had all except one across, the Plains becom So muddy from the emence rains which had fallen, that they Could not get her over the portage.    on the 28th they joined <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt Lewis</name> at the <name type="place" key="Grog Spring">Grog Spring</name> a fiew miles above the enterance of <name type="place" key="Marias River">Marias river</name>—. From the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">Falls of Missouri</name>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. L.</name> proceeded on with <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name> &amp; the <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph and Reubin">2 fieldses</name>    Courss<ref target="n37081211" n="11"/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <table rows="16" cols="3">
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                           <hi rend="right">17th July</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 10° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">20</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">miles from the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">Great falls of the Missouri</name> to <name type="place" key="Teton (Rose, Tansy) River">rose river</name> through<lb/>
an open fertile plain.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                           <hi rend="right">18th July</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 25° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">7</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">miles to the Sourse of <name type="place" key="Dugout Coulee (Buffalo Creek)">Buffalow Creek</name>, passing a dividing ridge<lb/>
dividing the waters of <name type="place" key="Marias River">Mairias river</name> from <name type="place" key="Teton (Rose, Tansy) River">rose river</name> at 6<lb/>
miles    Country hilly &amp;c.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 15° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">12</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Miles down <name type="place" key="Dugout Coulee (Buffalo Creek)">Buffalow Creek</name>    here the timber Commences<lb/>
Creek 25 Yds wide    no running water.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">North</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">5</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">miles to <name type="place" key="Marias River">Marias river</name> 130 yards wide 3 feet deep.    here <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt<lb/>
Lewis</name> encamped the 18th July 1806</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 80° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">20</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">miles up <name type="place" key="Marias River">Marias river</name> on its North Side    passed a large Creek<lb/>
on the South Side with Some timber in it's vally at 8 miles    also<lb/>
another large Creek on the N. Side at 15 miles 30 yards wide<lb/>
with but little water—.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                           <hi rend="right">July 20th</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 80° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">28</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Miles with the river in it's course upwds.    on it's N. Side river<lb/>
120 yds wide, passed a Creek on South Side at 6 miles, one<lb/>
at 22 miles on the N. Side the last has no water, Some little<lb/>
timber, the genl. course of this river is very Streight its vally<lb/>
½ m. wide.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                           <hi rend="right">July 21st</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 80° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">15</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Miles to the forks of the river the Main Southern branch bears<lb/>
S. 75° W. about 30 miles to the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">rocky Mountains</name>.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 40° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">6</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">miles up the North branch 30 yds wd. confined close between<lb/>
clifts of rocks, Shallow, rapid and not navagable.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 25° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">7</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Miles up the North fork, hills broken &amp; pore.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 30° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">7</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">M. up the river, water transparent.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 80° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">10</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">M. through the plains    the river maeking a considerable bend<lb/>
to the right or N W.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 75° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">11</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">M. through the plains on the N. Side of the river which here<lb/>
made a considerable bend to the left or S. haveing passed the<lb/>
river twice.</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>
here <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt Lewis</name> Continued the 23rd 24th &amp; 25th of July to make Some celestial observations but the weather proved So Cloudy that he only made the following observations on the 23rd of July 〈which gave〉</p>
               <p>
                  <table rows="4" cols="3">
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">     Observed Meridian Altd. of ☉'s L. L. with Octant by
the</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="2" cols="1">}</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="2" cols="1">62° 00' 00"</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">back observation—</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">     <hi rend="italic">Latitude</hi> deduced from this observation [<hi rend="italic">blank</hi>]</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">     observed equal altitudes of the Sun with the Sextant.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <table rows="4" cols="11">
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">h</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">m</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> s</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">h</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">m</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> s</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">A M</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">7</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">40</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">57</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">P M</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">4</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">32</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">40</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="3" cols="1">}</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="3" cols="1">Altitude of ☉<lb/>
56° 8' 45"</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">"</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">42</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">30</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">"</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">33</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">13</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">"</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">43</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  5</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">"</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">34</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">43</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>
On the 26th of July <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt Lewis</name> Set out on his return to the enterance of <name type="place" key="Marias River">Marias river</name> to meet with the party with, the Canoes from the falls. his course was through the plains.</p>
               <p>
S. E.    5    Miles—    passing a Small Creek from the mts—</p>
               <p>
S. 70° E.    9    Miles to a principal branch of <name type="place" key="Marias River">Marias River</name> 65 yards wide not very deep at 7 mile.    this last branch is Shallow and rapid about the Size of the former from the 〈N W〉 S W. both of those Streams Contain a great preportion of timber—    here we find the 3 Specis of Cotton before mentioned</p>
               <p>
N 80° E.    4    miles down <name type="place" key="Marias River">Marias river</name> and met with 8 Indians of the <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfoot</name> nation with about 30 horses, those Indians professed friendship and Set out with him and encamped together the night of the 26th of July, thy informed him that there was two large bands of their nation in that quarter one of which would be at the enterance of <name type="place" key="Marias River">Marias river</name> in a fiew days.    they also informed that a french Trader was with one of those bands, that they traded with the white people on the <name type="place" key="Saskatchewan River">Suskashwen River</name> at 6 easy days march or about 150 miles distant from whome they precured Guns Powder Lead blankets &amp;c. in exchange for wolf and beaver Skins. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt Lewis</name> gave them a Flag Meadel &amp; Handkerchief <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. L.</name> informed those Indians where he was from &amp; where he had been and his objects &amp; friendly views &amp;c. of which they appeared to be well Satisfied.</p>
               <p>
"on the morning of the 27th at day light the indians got up and crouded around the fire, <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Jo. Field</name> who was on post had carelessly laid his gun down behind him near where his brother was Sleeping.    one of the Indians Slipd. behind him and took his gun and that of his brother unperceived by him, at the Same instant two others advanced and Seized the guns of <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name> and <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt Lewis</name> who were yet asleep. <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Jo. Fields</name> Seeing this turned about to take his gun and Saw the fellow running off with his and his brothers, he called to his brother who    instantly jumped up and prosued the indian with him whome they overtook at the distance of 50 or 60 paces Siezed their guns and rested them from him and <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">R. Field</name> as he Seized his gun Stabed the indian to the heart with his knif who fell dead; (this <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Cap L.</name> did not know untill Some time after.[)]    <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">drewyer</name> who awoke at the first alarm jumped up and seized &amp; rested his gun from the indian &amp;c. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt L.</name> awoke and asked what was the matter Seeing <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name> in a Scuffle for his gun he turned to get his gun and found her gorn, he drew a pistol from his holsters and prosued the Indian whom he Saw in possession of his gun making off    he presented the pistol and the indian lay down the gun.    the <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph and Reubin">two Fields</name> Came up and drew up to Shoot the Indian which <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt L.</name> forbid the indians then attempted to drive off all the horses. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt L.</name> derected the men to fire on them if they attempted to drive off the horses, and prosued two fellows who Continued to drive of his horses he Shot the indian who had taken his gun and then in possession of his horse through the belly, he fell and raised on his elbow and fired at <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt L.</name>    the other made his escape into a nitch out of Sight with his bow and arrows and as <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt L.</name> guns was empty and he without his Shot pouch he returnd. to the Camp where the <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph and Reubin">2 fields</name> and <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name> joind him having prosued the indians across the river    the were now in possession of the most of their own as well as the indian horses and a gun Several bows &amp; arrows and all the indians baggage the gun &amp; Some feathers and flag they took and burnt all the 〈rest〉 other articles.    and Saddled up a many of the best horses as they wished with Some Spear horses, and Set out for to intersept the party at <name type="place" key="Marias River">Marias river</name> and proceded on a little to the S. of East <hi rend="italic">112</hi> Miles to the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> at the <name type="place" key="Grog Spring">Grog Spring</name>.    here they met with Canoes and party decending joined them leaving their horses on the river bank, and proceeded on to the enterance of <name type="place" key="Marias River">Marias river</name> opened the deposits, found Several articles damaged.    3 Beaver traps could not be found, the red perogue unfit for Service, from thenc they proceeded without delay to the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">River Rochejhone</name>    See cources of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt Lewis</name> rout in next book.["]<ref target="n37081212" n="12"/>
               </p>
               <p>
at 2 P. M. <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Gibson, George">Gibson</name> arived in the Skin Canoe with the Skins and the greater part of the flesh of 3 Elk which they had killed a fiew miles above.    the two men <name type="person" key="Dixon, Joseph">Dixon</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Hancock, Forrest">Handcock</name> the two men we had met above came down intending to proceed on down with us to the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>.    at 3 P M we proceded on all together 〈after〉 having left the 2 leather Canoes on the bank.    a little below the enterance of <name type="place" key="Bear Den (Charbonneau's, Indian) Creek">〈Jos〉 Shabonos Creek</name> we Came too on a large Sand point from the S. E. Side and Encamped.<ref target="n37081213" n="13"/>    the wind blew very hard from the S W. and Some rain. I washed <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt L.</name> wound which has become Sore and Somewhat painfull to him.



</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-08-12.03" n="lc.geo.1806-08-12.01">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Tuesday 12th August 1806.    a fair morning.    we Set out eairly and procd. on    about 8 A. M. we met two trappers Americans by the names of <name type="person" key="Dickson, Joseph">Jos Dixon</name> &amp; forrest <name type="person" key="Hancock, Forrest">Handcock</name>    they were from the <name type="place" key="Illinois">Ellynoise</name> country, and have gathered a great deal of peltry Since they have been out about 2 years and have carshed the most of it in the ground    they tells us that they are determined to Stay up this river and go to the head where the beaver is pleanty and trap and hunt untill they make a fortune before they return.    they had 20 odd good traps and tools for building canoes &amp;C.    they informed us that <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name> passed here about 12 oClock yesterday and Said that they would go on Slowly untill we come up. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name> gave them Some powder and Several articles    while we were here <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name> and <name type="person" key="Collins, John">Collins</name> Come up and joined us.    they informed us that they had waited    expected we were behind    they had killed 6 buffaloe 13 deer 5 Elk &amp; 31 beaver. <name type="person" key="Dickson, Joseph">Mr. Dixon</name> concludes to go back to the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name> in hopes to git a frenchman or Some body to go with him to the head of the river. So we procd. on    about 10 A. M. we overtook <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name> and party all alive and well    they informed us that they after they left us at the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Three Forks of the">three forks</name> followed on up the <name type="place" key="Gallatin (South, Southeast Fork) River">South fork or Gallentines River</name> nearly to its head which was about 30 miles, and that the beavers abound on that river    that their dams overflowed the bottoms So that they had difficulty to cross the river    they then Struck for the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">River Roshjone</name> leaving the Mountn. a Short distance to the right    crossd over a low ridge 10 miles then come on the head waters of the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">roshjone</name>    followed down Some distance before they found any timber that they could make canoes of.    they Saw no Indians but Saw Indn. tracks and the Indn. Stole 25 of the horses    they having the two Small canoes done lashed them and <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Sergt. pryor</name> Set out with 3 men and the rest of the horses by land in order to take them to the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name> 25 in number which now remained, but the 2nd night the Indn. Stole all the horses and they had to return to the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Roshjone</name> and killd. buffaloe and made leather canoes of them and followed on down    they informed us that the distance from where they Struck the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">River Roshjone</name> to its mouth is 836 miles and a pleasant river bottoms and timber on this river    the buffaloe So pleanty and Swimming the river So that they could Scarsely pass down this river    mountn. Sheep also in many places.    we fired the blunderbusses and Small arms being rejoiced to meet all together again.    2 of <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clarks</name> party were a hunting and killed a Spotted Elk    had white spots about it and different from any we have ever Seen before.    we left their buffaloe canoes and after a delay of three hours we procd. on. <name type="person" key="Dickson, Joseph">Mr. Dixon</name> and <name type="person" key="Hancock, Forrest">Handcock</name> accompy. us to the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>.    we Camped on a Sand beach on acct. of the Musquetoes    a little rain this evening &amp;C—


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-08-12.04" n="lc.geo.1806-08-12.01">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Tuesday 12th.</hi>    The morning was pleasant and we proceeded on. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Lewis</name> is in good spirits; but his wound stiff and sore. Having gone about nine miles we met with two men on the river trapping and hunting. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Lewis</name> gave them some ammunition and directions with respect to the river above. They informed us that Captain <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clarke</name> and party has passed them yesterday at noon. We proceeded on and at 10 o'clock overtook <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain Clarke</name> and his party, all in good health. The two men<ref target="n37081214" n="14"/> with the small canoe, who had been some time absent, came down and joined at the place where we met with the two strangers: and now, (thanks to God) we are all together again in good health, except <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Lewis</name>, and his wound is not serious.</p>
               <p>
After the Corps were separated among the mountains,<ref target="n37081215" n="15"/> as before mentioned, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain Clarke's</name> party proceeded on to the Canoe deposit, near the head of the main branch of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> (called <name type="place" key="Jefferson River (North, Southwest Fork)">Jefferson's river</name>) and having descended with the canoes to the mouth of the branch, which they called <name type="place" key="Gallatin (South, Southeast Fork) River">Gallatin</name>, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain Clarke</name> with ten men left those, who were to take down the canoes to the falls; travelled three days up <name type="place" key="Gallatin (South, Southeast Fork) River">Gallatin's river</name> towards the south, when they crossed a ridge and came upon the waters of the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Jaune or
Yellow-stone river</name>. Having gone about 100 miles down this river by land they made two canoes, and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain Clarke</name> having sent off a sergeant and three men with the horses to the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> villages, went down himself with six other men by water. On the second day after the sergeant and his party had started for the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> villages, the Indians stole the whole of the horses, and the party were obliged to descend the river in skin canoes. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain Clarke's</name> party in their route had found game plenty of different kinds, buffaloe, elk, deer, beaver, otter and some other animals. They also found the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellow-Stone river</name> a pleasant and navigable stream, with a rich soil along it; 
but timber scarce.</p>
               <p>
We here took the men on board, and left the buffaloe canoes. At night we encamped on a sand beach, as the musquitoes are not so bad there as in the woods.



</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n37081201" n="1">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> journalizing in Codex Lb, and for the expedition, ends at this entry. There follows a note by <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>: "To be anexed to Book No. 12 at the last." Book No. 12 is <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle's</name> designation for Codex L. Coues has added the dates of Codex Lb, "Aug. 9–12 1806."</note>
            <note xml:id="n37081202" n="2">
               <name type="person" key="Dickson, Joseph">Joseph Dickson</name>, or <name type="person" key="Dixon, Joseph">Dixon</name>, having lived in <name type="place" key="Pennsylvania">Pennsylvania</name> and <name type="place" key="Tennessee">Tennessee</name>, settled in <name type="place" key="Cahokia, Ill.">Cahokia</name>, <name type="place" key="Illinois">Illinois</name>, with his wife and children in 1802; he spent much of his time hunting and trapping in <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, where he met <name type="person" key="Hancock, Forrest">Forrest Hancock</name>, who had come to <name type="place" key="Boone's Settlement">Boone's Settlement</name> in 1799. The two started up the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> in August 1804; they may have spent the following winter in the vicinity of <name type="place" key="Sioux City, Iowa">Sioux City</name>, <name type="place" key="Iowa">Iowa</name>. The next year they worked with the trader <name type="person" key="Courtin, Charles">Charles Courtin</name>, wintering in <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name>
               <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name> country. Their meeting with <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> on this day (see <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> entry), was the expedition party's first direct contact with the European world since April 1805. <name type="person" key="Colter, John">John Colter</name>, who may have known <name type="person" key="Dickson, Joseph">Dickson</name> before, persuaded the captains to let him join the two in a trapping venture to the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone</name>, in what has become known as the "Fourth Expedition" to the region, those of <name type="person" key="LeRaye, Charles">Charles LeRaye</name> (which is highly questionable), <name type="person" key="Larocque, François-Antoine">François Antoine Larocque</name>, and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> being the first three. How far up the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone</name> they traveled is not known, but the party broke up over some dispute and <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name> and <name type="person" key="Hancock, Forrest">Hancock</name> returned to the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> villages. <name type="person" key="Dickson, Joseph">Dickson</name> spent the winter of 1806–7 alone on the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone</name>, enduring great hardship. On his journey downriver in the spring, he barely escaped the hostility of the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name>. Thereafter he remained in <name type="place" key="Illinois">Illinois</name> and became a highly respectable citizen, having "got religion" as a result of his suffering in the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rockies</name>. <name type="person" key="Dickson, Joseph">Dickson</name> (HH); <name type="person" key="Dickson, Joseph">Dickson</name> (JD); Harris, 33–58 (which varies considerably from other accounts).</note>
            <note xml:id="n37081203" n="3">The <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">Brulé</name>, or <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Brulé or Bois Brule">Bois Brulé</name>, <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>; see <ref n="1804-09-24" type="related">September 24, 1804</ref>, and <ref n="1804-1805.winter.part2" type="related">
                  <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name> Miscellany</ref>, in vol. 3.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37081204" n="4">Peruvian bark, or <hi rend="italic">cinchona,</hi> was a general remedy for fevers. Chuinard (OOMD), 65, 156–57 n. 8.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37081205" n="5">The two parties reunited at the place <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had halted for lunch, in <name type="place" key="Mountrail County, N. Dak.">Mountrail County</name>, <name type="place" key="North Dakota">North Dakota</name>, some six miles south of present <name type="place" key="Sanish, N. Dak.">Sanish</name>. The site does not appear on any <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map, but it was below <name type="place" key="Little Knife River (Goat Pen Creek)">Little Knife River</name> (the captains'<name type="place" key="Little Knife River (Goat Pen Creek)"> Goat Pen Creek</name>). The site is now inundated by <name type="place" key="Garrison Reservoir">Garrison Reservoir</name>. Mattison (GR), 49–50; <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 34; MRC map 56.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37081206" n="6">In fact, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> never resumed writing his journals after this date.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37081207" n="7">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> last botanical description in the journals is of the pin, or bird, cherry, <hi rend="italic">Prunus pensylvanica</hi> L. f. It is a biogeographically interesting species of the northern Midwest that is more common in the East, with relic populations in the <name type="place" key="Black Hills">Black Hills</name> of <name type="place" key="South Dakota">South Dakota</name> and in the <name type="place" key="Colorado">Colorado</name> front range of the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rockies</name>. The specimen he described here may be the one in the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> herbarium. Academy of Natural Sciences, <name type="place" key="Philadelphia, Pa.">Philadelphia</name>. The cherry "cultivated in the U' States" he used for comparison is probably black cherry, <hi rend="italic">P. serotina</hi> Ehrh. Barkley, 148; Cutright (LCPN), 325–26.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37081208" n="8">Coues patched the damaged page at this point with a two-cent postage stamp (Scott #220) bearing the words "Dec. 20 1892 Coues." He also used a portion of the stamp to patch another tear a few pages earlier.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37081209" n="9">The party first passed this island on <ref n="1805-04-15" type="related">April 15, 1805</ref>, on the outbound journey, but did not refer to it by any name. It is nameless on <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> maps 34 and 47 and would be the "Knife R. Towhead" of MRC map 56, between <name type="place" key="Mountrail County, N. Dak.">Mountrail</name> and <name type="place" key="McKenzie County, N. Dak.">McKenzie</name> counties, <name type="place" key="North Dakota">North Dakota</name>, or near it. The meeting place of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> northeast of the head of the island would be in <name type="place" key="Mountrail County, N. Dak.">Mountrail County</name>, some six miles south of present <name type="place" key="Sanish, N. Dak.">Sanish</name>, now under <name type="place" key="Garrison Reservoir">Garrison Reservoir</name>. Mattison (GR), 48–50. The letters after <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle's</name> "Qu:" are not distinct.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37081210" n="10">For <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> narrative of his exploration after the captains' separation on July 3, 1806, see his journal entries for <ref n="1806-07-03" type="related">July 3</ref> to August 12, 1806</note>
            <note xml:id="n37081211" n="11">The courses and distances match <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>, but the dates and separations are somewhat incorrect.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37081212" n="12">A reference to <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> copy of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> courses from <name type="place" key="Lolo (Travelers' Rest) Creek (Mont.)">Travelers' Rest</name> to the <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Great Falls of the">Great Falls</name> in Codex N. It is placed after <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> entry of <ref n="1806-07-10" type="related">July 10, 1806</ref>. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> is summarizing <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> remarks for <ref n="1806-07-27" type="related">July 27</ref> and <ref n="1806-07-28" type="related">28</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37081213" n="13">"<name type="place" key="Bear Den (Charbonneau's, Indian) Creek">Shabonos Creek</name>," which they passed going west on <ref n="1805-04-14" type="related">April 14, 1805</ref>, is now <name type="place" key="Bear Den (Charbonneau's, Indian) Creek">Bear Den Creek</name> in <name type="place" key="McKenzie County, N. Dak.">McKenzie County</name>. The camp would be near the <name type="place" key="McKenzie County, N. Dak.">McKenzie</name>-<name type="place" key="Mountrail County, N. Dak.">Mountrail</name> county line, on a site now inundated by <name type="place" key="Garrison Reservoir">Garrison Reservoir</name>. Mattison (GR), 48–49; <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> maps 34, 47, 56; MRC map 56.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37081214" n="14">
               <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name> and <name type="person" key="Collins, John">Collins</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37081215" n="15">As noted, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> account of the exploration of the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone</name> appears in his journals for <ref n="1806-07-03" type="related">July 3</ref> to August 12, 1806.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-08-11" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-08-13" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
