<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-07-08">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
July 8, 1805</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 4</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">April7–July 27, 1805</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1987</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">366-368</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">181</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">109-110</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 11</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of Joseph Whitehouse, May 14, 1804–April 2, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1997</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">220-221</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc/>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-02-09</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1805-07-08">July 8, 1805</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-07-08.01" n="">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Monday July 8th 1805.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name> Determined to make a second effort to replace the notes which he had made with rispect to the river and falls    accordingly he set out after an early breakfast and took with him the greater part of the men<ref target="n16070801" n="1"/> with a view also to kill buffaloe should there be any in that quarter.    after geting some distance in the plains he divided the party and sent them in different directions and himself and two others struck the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> at the entrance of <name type="place" key="Sun (Mah-pah-pah,-ah-zhah, Medicine) River">medicine river</name> and continued down it to the great Cataract,
from whence he returned through the plains to camp where he arrived late in the evening.    the hunters also returned having killed 3 buffaloe 2 Antelopes and a deer.    he informed me that the immence herds of buffaloe which we had seen for some time past in this neighbourhood have almost entirely disappeared and he beleives are gone down the river.—</p>
               <p>
The day being warm and fair about 12 OCk. the boat was sufficiently dry to receive a coat of the composition which I accordingly applyed.    this adds very much to her appearance whether it will be effectual or not.    it gives her hull the appearance of being formed of one solid piece.    after the first coat had cooled I gave her a second which I think has made it sufficiently thick. The mountains which ly before us from the South, to the N. W. still continue covered with snow.    one hunter also passed the river to hunt this morning    in the evening he returned having killed a Buck and a male Antelope. The party who were down with <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name> also killed a small fox which they brought with them.    it was a female appeared to give suck, otherwise it is so much like the comm small fox of this country commonly called the kit fox that I should have taken it for a young one of that species; however on closer examination it did apear to differ somewhat; it's colour was of a lighter brown, it's years proportionably larger, and the tale not so large or the hair not so long which formed it.    they are very delicately formed, exceedingly fleet, and not as large as the common domestic cat.    their tallons appear longer than any species of fox I ever saw and seem therefore prepared more amply by nature for the purpose of burrowing.    there is sufficient difference for discrimination between it and the kit fox, and to satisfy me perfectly that it is a distinct species.<ref target="n16070802" n="2"/>    the men also brought me a living ground squirrel<ref target="n16070803" n="3"/> which is something larger than those of the U' States or those of that kind which are also common here.    this is a much hadsomer anamal.    like the other it's principal colour is a redish brown but is marked longitudinally with a much greater number of black or dark bron stripes; the spaces between which is marked by ranges of pure white circular spots, about the size of a brister blue shot.<ref target="n16070804" n="4"/>    these colours imbrace the head neck back and sides; the tail is flat, or the long hair projecting horizontally from two sides of it only gives it that appearance.    the belly and breast are of much lighter brown or nearly white.    this is an inhabitant of the open plain altogether, wher it burrows and resides; nor is it like the other found among clifts of rocks or in the woodlands.    their burrows sometimes like those of the mole run horizontally near the surface of the ground for a considerable distance, but those in which they reside or take refuge strike much deeper in the earth.—    Slight rain this afternoon.    musquetoes troublesome as usual.—</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-07-08.02" n="">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>July 8th Monday 1805</date>
               </ab>
               <p>
A worm morning flying Clouds    I deturmin take the width of the river at <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">the falls</name> &amp; the <name type="place" key="Sun (Mah-pah-pah,-ah-zhah, Medicine) River">Medison river</name> and to take the greater part of the men which Can be Speared to Kill Buffalow for their Skins as well as meat, devided the party &amp; Sent them in different directions to hunt &amp; proceeded my Self to the mouth of <name type="place" key="Sun (Mah-pah-pah,-ah-zhah, Medicine) River">Medison river</name>    measured it and found it to be 137 yards wide, in the narrowest part of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> imediately above <name type="place" key="Sun (Mah-pah-pah,-ah-zhah, Medicine) River">Medison river</name> the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> is 300 yards wide, below and a little above the falls 1440 yards wide with the direction of the upper great fall 580 yards wide, at the great Spring 270 yards wide, at the <name type="place" key="Rainbow (Handsome, Beautiful) Falls">handsom fall</name>s of 47 ft. 8 I. the river is 473 yards wide, at the lower <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">great falls the river</name> is confined within 280 yards, below <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">the falls</name> the water occupies 93 yards only—    after takeing the wedth of the river at those Sundery placies I
returned thro' the plains in a direct line to Camp. Some rain this evening after a verry hot day.—    the mountains which are in view to the South &amp; N W. are Covered with Snow.    those nearer us and form a ¾ Circle around us is not Covered with Snow at this time. The hunters killed 3 buffalow, two antelopes, &amp; a Deer to day—    the emence herds of buffalow which was near us a fiew days ago, has proceeded on down the river, we Can See but a fiew Bulls in the plains </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-07-08.03" n="">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
July 8th Monday 1805.    a clear pleasant morning one man went across the river a hunting eairly this morning    about 9 oClock A. M. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name> and all the men that could be Spared from Camp Set out to go down the river a hunting down past <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">the falls</name> and <name type="place" key="Giant Springs">big Spring</name> &amp;.C.    the men that remained in Camp employed in paying<ref target="n16070805" n="5"/> over the outside of the Iron boat with coal Tallow and base wax<ref target="n16070806" n="6"/> in Stead of pitch.    we went about 6 miles through the plains then went to the big Spring. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name> measured the width of t[he] River at the Spring and middle falls and found it to be [<hi rend="italic">blank</hi>] yards wide at the Spring and [<hi rend="italic">blank</hi>] yards wide at the middle falls.    in the afternoon we all returned to Camp    had killed Several buffalow one of which was fat.    killed 1 or 2 antelopes and a curious yallow fox<ref target="n16070807" n="7"/> and Several rattle Snakes.    towards evening the hunter returned from across the river    had killed one buck Deer and a buck antelope &amp;C. Some Thunder and light Showers this afternoon    The River falling. The Musquetoes troublesome.



</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-07-08.04" n="">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Monday 8th.</hi>    Again we had a fine morning, and a number of the party went out to hunt. In the evening they all came in, and had killed but three buffaloe, a deer and a cabre; and caught a small animal almost like a cat, of a light colour.<ref target="n16070808" n="8"/> Yesterday one of the men caught a small squirrel,<ref target="n16070809" n="9"/> like a ground squirrel, but of a more dun colour, and more spotted. We finished the boat this evening, having covered her with tallow and coal-dust. We called her the Experiment, and expect she will answer our purpose.


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-07-08.05" n="">
            <sp who="jw">
               <speaker>Whitehouse</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">July 8th Monday 1805</hi>.    a clear pleasant morning.    one man went across the River a hunting.    about 9 oClock A. M. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name> and all the men that could be Spared from Camp Set out for to go down to <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">the falls</name> a hunting.    I remained in Camp makeing leather cloathes &amp;c.    the rest of the men at Camp was employed in makeing coal &amp; tallow and Beese wax mixed and payed<ref target="n16070810" n="10"/> over the leather on the Iron boat &amp;c.    in the afternoon the hunters returned from <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">the falls</name> and plains.    had killed Several buffalow, 1 antelope and a yallow fox, also 2 rattle Snakes, &amp;c.    <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name> measured the width of the River at the <name type="place" key="Giant Springs">great Spring</name> &amp; middle falls, &amp;c.    the hunter returned from over the river and had killed one buck Deer and a buck antelope or goat kind &amp;c.    Some Thunder and light Sprinkling of rain, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
Monday July 8th    A Clear pleasant morning, one of our party went across the River a hunting, About 9 o'Clock A. M. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain Clarke</name> and all the Men that could be spared from Camp, set out for to go down to <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">the falls</name> a 
hunting.—</p>
               <p>
The party of men, left at the Camp, were employed in making leather Cloathing, for the party, burning of coal, &amp; mixing it with tallow to pay the bottom of our Iron boat &amp;ca.    In the afternoon the party that went with <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain Clark</name> to the falls of the River, and those that had went out to hunt in the plains, returned; they had killed several Buffalo, 1 Antelope, &amp; a Red fox, also two very large rattle Snakes.—    <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain Clark</name> measured the width of the River at the <name type="place" key="Giant Springs">great Spring</name> &amp; middle falls; which were as follows; at the <name type="place" key="Giant Springs">great Spring</name> 70 Yds wide &amp; at <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">the falls</name> 95 〈feet〉 Yards wide.    In the Evening, the hunter that had went over the River returned, and brought with him, to Camp a large buck deer and a Male Antelope which he had killed, we had this Evening some thunder and light rain—



</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n16070801" n="1">
               <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> notes that he was included; he may have been one of the two who accompanied <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> the whole day, although his entry is not clear on this point.</note>
            <note xml:id="n16070802" n="2">Apparently the swift fox, in spite of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> doubts. His use of the common name kit fox, an alternate name for the swift fox, indicates that the animal was popularly known,
perhaps in the fur trade, although unknown to science. See note for <ref n="1805-07-06" type="related">July 6, 1805</ref>. It was
probably <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name> who drew a red vertical line through the material beginning with "The party who" to the end of the entry.</note>
            <note xml:id="n16070803" n="3">The first scientific description of the thirteen-lined ground squirrel, <hi rend="italic">Spermophilus tridecemlineatus</hi>. Cutright (LCPN), 166; Jones et al., 143–45. See also Coues (HLC), 2: 405–6
n. 23.</note>
            <note xml:id="n16070804" n="4">Apparently Bristol Blue shot, the size still referred to as BB. Pendergast, 40.</note>
            <note xml:id="n16070805" n="5">In the nautical sense meaning to coat with tar, pitch, and the like.</note>
            <note xml:id="n16070806" n="6">Beeswax.</note>
            <note xml:id="n16070807" n="7">Apparently the swift fox, <hi rend="italic">Vulpes velox</hi> (see <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> entry for this day).</note>
            <note xml:id="n16070808" n="8">The swift fox, <hi rend="italic">Vulpes velox</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n16070809" n="9">The thirteen-lined ground squirrel, <hi rend="italic">Spermophilus tridecemlineatus</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n16070810" n="10">To coat with tar and pitch, but in this case the men used available materials.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-07-07" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-07-09" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
