<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-06-02">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
June 2, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 7</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">March 23–June 9, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1991</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">325-330</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">318-319</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">235</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc/>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-10-26</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1806-06-02">June 2, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-06-02.01" n="">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Monday June 2cd 1806.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="McNeal, Hugh">McNeal</name> and <name type="person" key="York">york</name> were sent on a trading voyage over the river this morning.    having exhausted all our merchandize we are obliged to have recourse to every subterfuge in order to prepare in the most ample manner in our power to meet that wretched portion of our journy, the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky Mountain</name>, where hungar and cold in their most rigorous forms assail the waried traveller; not any of us have yet forgotten our sufferings in those mountains in September last, and I think it probable we never shall. Our traders <name type="person" key="McNeal, Hugh">McNeal</name> and <name type="person" key="York">York</name> were furnished with the buttons which <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. C.</name> and myself cut off our coats, some eye water and Basilicon which we made for that purpose and some Phials and small tin boxes which I had brought out with Phosphorus.    in the evening they returned with about 3 bushels of roots and some bread having made a successfull voyage, not much less pleasing to us than the return of a good cargo to an East India Merchant.—    <name type="person" key="Collins, John">Collins</name>, <name type="person" key="Shields, John">Sheilds</name>, <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">R</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">J. Feilds</name> and <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name> set out on a hunting excurtion to the <name type="place" key="Weippe Prairie (Camas Flats, Quawmash Flats)">Quawmash grounds</name> on the lower side of <name type="place" key="Lolo (Collins's) Creek (Idaho)">Collins's Creek</name>.    our horses many of them have become so wild that we cannot take them without the assistance of the Indians who are extreemly dextrous in throwing a rope and taking them with a noose about the neck; as we frequently want the use of our horses when we cannot get the assistance of the indians to take them, we had a strong pound formed today in order to take them at pleasure. <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name> arrived this evening with <name type="person" key="Cut Nose">Neeshneparkkeeook</name> and <name type="person" key="Hohots Ilppilp">Hohâstillpilp</name> who had accompanyed him to the lodges of the persons who had our tomahawks.    he obtained both the tomahawks principally by the influence of the former of these Cheifs.    the one which had been stolen we prized most as it was the private property of the late <name type="person" key="Floyd, Charles">Sergt. Floyd</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. C.</name> was desireous of returning it to his friends.    the man who had this tomahawk had purchased it from the Indian that had stolen it, and was himself at the moment of their arrival just expiring.    his relations were unwilling to give up the tomehawk as they intended to bury it with the disceased owner, but were at length induced to do so for the consideration of a hadkerchief, two strands of beads, which [<hi rend="italic">X: <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Cap C.</name> Sent by</hi>]<ref target="n35060201" n="1"/>
                  <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name> gave them and two horses given by the cheifs to be killed agreeably to their custom at the grave of the disceased. The bands of the <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Chopunnish</name> who reside above the junction of <name type="place"
                        key="Salmon (Lewis's, Main Fork Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">Lewis's river</name> and the <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Kooskooske</name> bury their dead in the earth and place stones on the grave.    they also stick little splinters of wood in betwen the interstices of the irregular mass of stone piled on the grave and afterwards cover the whole with a roof of board or split timber.    the custom of sacreficing horses to the disceased appears to be common to all the nations of the <name type="place" key="Great Columbian Plain">plains of Columbia</name>.    a wife of <name type="person" key="Cut Nose">Neeshneeparkkeeook</name> died some short time since, himself and hir relations saceficed 28 horses to her. The Indians inform us that there are a plenty of Moos<ref target="n35060202" n="2"/> to the S. E. of them on the <name type="place"
                        key="Salmon (Lewis's, Main Fork Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">East branch of Lewis's river</name> which they call <name type="place"
                        key="Salmon (Lewis's, Main Fork Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">Tommanamah R.</name>
                  <ref target="n35060203" n="3"/>    about Noon <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Sergt. Ordway</name>
                  <name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">Frazier</name> and <name type="person" key="Weiser, Peter">Wizer</name> returned with 17 salmon and some roots of cows; the distance was so great from which they had brought the fish that most of them were nearly spoiled.    these fish were as fat as any I ever saw; sufficiently so to cook themselves without the addition of grease; those which were sound were extreemly delicious; their flesh is of a fine rose colour with a small admixture of yellow.<ref target="n35060204" n="4"/>    these men set out on the 27th ult. and in stead of finding the fishing shore at the distance of half a days ride as we had been informed, they did not reach the place at which they obtained their fish untill the evening of the 29th having travelled by their estimate near 70 miles.    the rout they had taken however was not a direct one; the Indians conducted them in the first instance to the <name type="place"
                        key="Salmon (Lewis's, Main Fork Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">East branch of Lewis's river</name> about 20 miles above it's junction with the <name type="place"
                        key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">South branch</name>,<ref target="n35060205" n="5"/> a distance of about 50 Ms. where they informed them they might obtain fish; but on their arrival at that place finding that the salmon had not yet arrived or were not taken, they were conducted down that river to a fishery a few miles below the junction of the forks of <name type="place"
                        key="Salmon (Lewis's, Main Fork Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">Lewis's river</name> about 20 ms. further, here with some difficulty and remaining one day they purchased the salmon which they brought with them.<ref target="n35060206" n="6"/>    the first 20 Ms. of their rout was up <name type="place" key="Lawyer (Commearp) Creek">Commeâp Creek</name> and through a plain open country, the hills of the creek continued high and broken with some timber near it's borders. the ballance of their rout was though a high broken mountanous country generally well timbered with pine the soil fertile    in this quarter they met with an abundance of deer and some bighorned animals.    the <name type="place"
                        key="Salmon (Lewis's, Main Fork Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">East fork of Lewis's river</name> they discribe as one continued rapid about 150 Yds. wide it's banks are in most places solid and perpendicular rocks, which rise to a great hight; it's hills are mountains high.    on the tops of some of those hills over which they passed, the snow had not entirely disappeared, and the grass was just springing up.    at the fishery on <name type="place"
                        key="Salmon (Lewis's, Main Fork Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">Lewis's river</name> below the forks there is a very considerable rapid nearly as great from the information of <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Segt. Ordway</name> as the <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Great Falls of the">great falls [<hi rend="italic">NB: rapids</hi>]<ref target="n35060207" n="7"/> of the Columbia</name> the river 200 Yds. wide.    their common house at this fishery is built of split timber 150 feet long and 35 feet wide flat at top. The general course from hence to the forks of <name type="place"
                        key="Salmon (Lewis's, Main Fork Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">Lewis's river</name> is a little to the West of south about 45 Ms.—    The men at this season resort their fisheries while the women are employed in collecting roots.    both forks of <name type="place"
                        key="Salmon (Lewis's, Main Fork Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">Lewis's river</name> above their junction appear to enter a high Mountainous country.—    my sick horse being much reduced and apearing to be in such an agoni of pain that there was no hope of his recovery I ordered him shot this evening.    the other horses which we casterated are all nearly recovered, and I have no hesitation in declaring my beleif that the indian method of gelding is preferable to that practiced by ourselves.—
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-06-02.02" n="">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Monday June 2nd 1806</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="McNeal, Hugh">McNeal</name> and <name type="person" key="York">York</name> were Sent on a tradeing voyage over the river this morning.    having exhosted all our Merchendize we were obliged to have recourse to every Subterfuge in order to prepare in the most ample manner in our power to meet that wretched portion of our journy, the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky Mountains</name>, where hungar and Cold in their most regorous form assail the waried traveller; not any of us have yet forgotten our those mountains in September last, I think it probable we never Shall. Our traders <name type="person" key="McNeal, Hugh">McNeal</name> and <name type="person" key="York">York</name> are furnished with the buttons which <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt L—</name>. and my Self Cut off of our Coats, Some eye water and Basilicon which we made for that purpose and Some phials of eye water and Some tin boxes which <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt L.</name> had brought from <name type="place" key="Philadelphia, Pa.">Philadelphia</name>.    in the evening they returned with about 3 bushels of roots and Some bread haveing made a Suckcessfull voyage, not much less pleasing to us than the return of a good Cargo to an East India merchant.—</p>
               <p>
Shields, <name type="person" key="Collins, John">Collins</name>, Reuben &amp; <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Joseph Field</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name> Set out on a hunting excurtion to the quaw mash the lower side of <name type="place" key="Lolo (Collins's) Creek (Idaho)">Collins Creek</name> &amp; towards the Mountains.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name> arived this evening with <name type="person" key="Cut Nose">Neeshneparkkeeook</name> and <name type="person" key="Hohots Ilppilp">Hohashillpilp</name> who had accompanied him to the lodge of the person who had our tomahawks.    he obtained both the tomahawks principally by the influence of the former of those Chiefs.    the one which had been Stolen we prized most as it was the private property of the late <name type="person" key="Floyd, Charles">Serjt. Floyd</name> and I was desireous of returning it to his friends. The man who had this tomahawk had purchased it from the man who had Stolen it, and was himself at the moment of their arival just expireing.    his relations were unwilling to give up the tomahawk as they intended to bury it with the deceased owner, but were at length to do so for the Consideration of a handkerchief, two Strands of beeds, which drewyer gave them and two horses given by the Chiefs to be Killed agreeable to their custom at the grave of the deceased. The custom of Sacrificeing horses to the disceased appears to be Common to all the nations of the <name type="place" key="Great Columbian Plain">plains of the Columbia</name>.    a Wife of <name type="person" key="Cut Nose">Neeshneeparkkeeook</name> died Some Short time Sence, himself and her relations sacrificed horses to her. The indians inform us that there is a plenty of Moos to the S. E. of them on the <name type="place"
                        key="Salmon (Lewis's, Main Fork Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">East branch of Lewis's river</name> which they Call <name type="place"
                        key="Salmon (Lewis's, Main Fork Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">
                     <hi rend="italic">Tommawamah</hi> River</name>. About noon <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Sergt. Ordway</name>
                  <name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">Frazier</name> and <name type="person" key="Weiser, Peter">Wiser</name> returnd. with 17 Salmon and Some roots of the Cows; the distance was So great from whence they brought the fish, that most of them were nearly Spoiled.    those fish were at fat as any I ever saw; Sufficiently So to cook themselves without the addition of Grease or butter; those which were Sound were extreemly delicious; their flesh is of a fine rose colour with a Small admixture of yellow.    these men Set out on the 27th ulto: and in Sted of finding the fishing Shore at the distance of half a days ride as we had been informed, they did not reach the place at which they obtained their fish untill the evening of the 29th haveing traveled near 70 miles.    the rout they had taken however was not a direct one; the Indians Conducted them in the first instance to the <name type="place"
                        key="Salmon (Lewis's, Main Fork Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">East fork of Lewis's river</name> about 10 miles above it's junction with the <name type="place"
                        key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">South branch</name>, a distance of about 50 miles where they informed them they might obtain fish; but on their arival at that place finding that the Salmon had not arived or were not taken, they were Conducted down that river to a fishery a fiew miles below the junction of the forks of <name type="place"
                        key="Salmon (Lewis's, Main Fork Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">Lewis's River</name> about 20 miles further, here they remained one day and with some dificuelty, they purchased the Salmon which they brought with them.    the first 20 ms. of their rout was up <name type="place" key="Lawyer (Commearp) Creek">Commeâp Creek</name> and through a plain open Country, the hills of the Creek Continued high and broken with Some timber near it's borders, the ballance of heir rout was through a high broken Mountanious Country.    generally well timbered with pine the soil fertile.    in this quarter the meet with abundance of deer and Some big-horned Animals. The <name type="place"
                        key="Salmon (Lewis's, Main Fork Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">East fork of Lewis's river</name> they discribe as one Continued rapid of about 150 yards wide, it's banks are in most places Solid and perpindicular rocks, which rise to a great hight; it's hills are mountanious high.    on the top of Some of those hills over which they passed, the Snow had not entirely disappeared, and the grass was just springing up.    at the fishery on <name type="place"
                        key="Salmon (Lewis's, Main Fork Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">Lewis's river</name> below the forks there is a very Considerable rapid, nearly as Great from the information of <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Sergt. Ordway</name> as the <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Great Falls of the">Great falls of the Columbia</name>    the river 200 yards wide.    their common house at this fishery is built of Split timber 150 feet long and 35 feet in width, flat at top.    the general Course from here to the forks of <name type="place"
                        key="Salmon (Lewis's, Main Fork Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">Lewis's river</name> is a little to the west of South about 45 ms. The men at this Season resort their fisheries while the womin are employed in collecting roots—.    both forks above the junction of <name type="place"
                        key="Salmon (Lewis's, Main Fork Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">Lewis's river</name> appear to enter a high Mountainious Country.    our horses are all recovering &amp; I have no hesitation in declareing that I believe that the Indian Method of guilding preferable to that practised by ourselves.—

</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-06-02.03" n="">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Monday 2nd June 1806.    a fair morning.    we Set out eairly and turned down the river    passd 2 more villages    about 12 oClock we arived at our Camp.<ref target="n35060208" n="8"/>    found the river verry high indeed. Swam the horses across and got across in an Indian canoe as our men informed us that as Some of our men were crossing several days past our large canoe ran against Some trees as they
were going to Shore and the canoe upset and Sank emediately.    the men got Safe to Shore but lost three blankets one blanket cappo and Several articles, they had for trade &amp;C.    they had killed a horse soon after we went away to eat which the natives gave us for that purpose    Soon after our hunters killed and brought to Camp 12 Deer. Some of our castrated horses are nearly well and one is Sick and like to dye. So Some of our men went and Shot him &amp;C.    towards evening the head chief<ref target="n35060209" n="9"/> of the <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">cho-pennish</name> nation came to our Camp with <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">George Drewyer</name> and brought and gave up a tommahawk<ref target="n35060210" n="10"/> which <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt Clark</name> lost last fall which the chief kept for us.


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-06-02.04" n="">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Monday 2nd.</hi>    The morning was cloudy, and six of the men<ref target="n35060211" n="11"/> went out to hunt. About noon three men,<ref target="n35060212" n="12"/> who had gone over to <name type="place"
                        key="Salmon (Lewis's, Main Fork Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">Lewis's river</name>, about two and half days' journey distant, to get some fish, returned with a few very good salmon, and some roots which they bought at the different villages of the natives, which they passed. One of these men got two Spanish dollars from an Indian for an old razor.<ref target="n35060213" n="13"/> They said they got the dollars from about a <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Snake Indian's</name> neck, they had killed some time ago. There are several dollars among these people which they get in some way. We suppose the <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Snake Indians</name>, some of whom do not live very far from <name type="place" key="New Mexico">New Mexico</name>, got them from 
the Spaniards in that quarter.<ref target="n35060214" n="14"/> The <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Snake Indians</name> also get horses from the 
Spaniards.— The men had a very disagreeable trip as the roads were mountainous and slippery. They saw a number of deer, and of the ibex or big-horn.




</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n35060201" n="1">The interlineation is in red ink but does not appear to be <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle's</name> handwriting. Square brackets begin at "<name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name> arrived" and end after "of the disceased." Written in pencil, the marks may be Coues's work.</note>
            <note xml:id="n35060202" n="2">Moose, <hi rend="italic">Alces alces.</hi> Apparently neither of the captains ever saw a moose on the expedition; see <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> entry of <ref n="1806-07-07" type="related">July 7, 1806</ref>. Burroughs, 139–40.</note>
            <note xml:id="n35060203" n="3">
               <name type="place"
                     key="Salmon (Lewis's, Main Fork Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">Tommanamah</name> is <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
               <hi rend="italic">tamá·nma,</hi> for the <name type="place"
                     key="Salmon (Lewis's, Main Fork Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">Salmon River</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n35060204" n="4">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> does not provide enough information for positive identification of this species of salmon.</note>
            <note xml:id="n35060205" n="5">The "<name type="place"
                     key="Salmon (Lewis's, Main Fork Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">East branch of Lewis's river</name>" is the <name type="place"
                     key="Salmon (Lewis's, Main Fork Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">Salmon</name>, while the "<name type="place"
                     key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">South branch</name>" is the <name type="place"
                     key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Snake River</name> below the mouth of the <name type="place"
                     key="Salmon (Lewis's, Main Fork Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">Salmon</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n35060206" n="6">The <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> party followed a westerly route along <name type="place" key="Lawyer (Commearp) Creek">Lawyer ("Commeap") Creek</name> to <name type="place" key="Deer Creek (Idaho)">Deer Creek</name> near the <name type="place" key="Lewis County, Idaho">Lewis</name>–<name type="place" key="Nez Perce County, Idaho">Nez Perce</name> County line, then south to the <name type="place"
                     key="Salmon (Lewis's, Main Fork Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">Salmon</name> and westerly again to the <name type="place"
                     key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Snake River</name> near the <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>-<name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name> border separating <name type="place" key="Wallowa County, Oreg.">Wallowa</name> and <name type="place" key="Asotin County, Wash.">Asotin</name> counties. On their return the party retraced their route to <name type="place" key="Deer Creek (Idaho)">Deer Creek</name>, then followed a trail south of their outbound passage, reaching the <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Clearwater River</name> near <name type="place" key="Kooskia, Idaho">Kooskia</name>, <name type="place" key="Idaho County, Idaho">Idaho County</name>, and finally following the <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Clearwater</name> back to <name type="place" key="Camp Chopunnish (Idaho)">Camp Chopunnish</name>. Peebles (RLC), 21, and 19 fig. 5. Merle Wells of the Idaho Historical Society has been working on a more precise tracing of <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway's</name> route that differs with Peebles's. A more detailed account of <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway's</name> route using Well's studies is taken up <ref n="1806-05-28" type="related">
                  <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway's</name> journal</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n35060207" n="7">
               <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name> inserted this word and also probably underlined "falls," both in red.</note>
            <note xml:id="n35060208" n="8">
               <name type="place" key="Camp Chopunnish (Idaho)">Camp Chopunnish</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n35060209" n="9">Actually two chiefs, <name type="person" key="Cut Nose">Cut Nose</name> and <name type="person" key="Hohots Ilppilp">Hohots Ilppilp</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n35060210" n="10">Actually two, report <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, one of which had been stolen and was <name type="person" key="Floyd, Charles">Sergeant
Floyd's</name>, which <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> hoped to return to the dead soldier's friends.</note>
            <note xml:id="n35060211" n="11">
               <name type="person" key="Shields, John">Shields</name>, <name type="person" key="Collins, John">Collins</name>, the <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph and Reubin">Field brothers</name>, and <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name> went out, according to the captains; 
no sixth man is mentioned.</note>
            <note xml:id="n35060212" n="12">
               <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> with <name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">Frazer</name> and <name type="person" key="Weiser, Peter">Weiser</name> had gone to the <name type="place"
                     key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Snake River</name> for salmon. For a detailed 
account of their journey, see <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway's</name> entries of May 28–June 2, 1806, where the question of their route is examined in the notes.</note>
            <note xml:id="n35060213" n="13">
               <name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">Frazer</name>; see <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway's</name> entry of <ref n="1806-05-29" type="related">May 29</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n35060214" n="14">An example of how European goods penetrated to people who had never seen whites. 
The Spanish coins may have passed through several hands. See James P. Ronda, "<name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">Frazer's</name> Razor: The Ethnohistory of a Common Object," <hi rend="italic">We Proceeded On</hi> 7 (August 1981): 12–13.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-06-01" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-06-03" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
