<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-02-13">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
February 13, 1805</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 3</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">August 25, 1804–April 6, 1805</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1987</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">293-295</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">114</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 11</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of Joseph Whitehouse, May 14, 1804–April 2, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1997</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">125</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc/>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-04-02</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1805-02-13">February 13, 1805</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-02-13.01" n="">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">13th February Wednesday 1805.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
The morning cloudy    thermometer 2° below naught    wind from S. E.    visited by the <name type="person" key="Black Cat (Posecopsahe)">Black-Cat</name>    gave him a <hi rend="italic">battle ax</hi> with which he appeared much gratifyed.—
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-02-13.02" n="">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>
                  <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>
                  <ref target="n09021301" n="1"/>
               </speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
I returned last night from a hunting party much fatigued, haveing walked 30 miles on the ice and through of wood land Points in which the Snow was nearly Knee Deep</p>
               <p>
The 1st day [<hi rend="italic">EC?: Feb. 4</hi>] I left the fort    proceeded on the ice to <name type="place" key="Mandan Island">
                     <hi rend="italic">new Mandan</hi> Island</name>,<ref target="n09021302" n="2"/> 22 miles &amp; Camped    Killed nothing, &amp; nothing to eat,</p>
               <p>
The 2d day    the morning verry Cold &amp; Windey, I broke thro the ice and got my feet and legs wet, Sent out 4 hunters thro' a point to Kill a Deer &amp; Cook it by the time the party Should get up, those hunters killed a Deer &amp; 2 Buffalow Bulls    the Buffalow too Meagur to eate, we eate the Deer &amp; proceeded on to an old Indian Lodge,<ref target="n09021303" n="3"/> Sent out the hunters &amp; they brought in three lean Deer, which we made use of for food,—    walking on uneaven ice has blistered the bottom of my feat, and walking is painfull to me—</p>
               <p>
3rd day    Cold morning the after party of the Day worm, Camped on a Sand point near the mouth of a Creek on the S W. Side we Call <name type="place" key="Square Butte (Hunting) Creek">hunting Creek</name>,<ref target="n09021304" n="4"/> I turned out with the hunters, I Killed 2 Deer the hunters killed an Elk, Buffalow Bull &amp; 5 Deer.    all Meager</p>
               <p>
4th Day    hunted the two bottoms near the Camp    Killed 9 Elk, 18 Deer, brought to camp all the meat fit to eate &amp; had the bones taken out.    every man ingaged either in hunting or Collecting &amp; packing the meat to Camp</p>
               <p>
5th Day    Dispatched one of the party our Interpeter &amp; 2 french men with the 3 horses loaded with the best of the meat to the fort 44 miles Distant, the remaining meat I had packed on the 2 Slays &amp; drawn down to the next point about 3 miles below, at this place I had all the meat Collected which was killed yesterday &amp; had escaped the wolves, Raven<ref target="n09021305" n="5"/> &amp; Magpie, (which are verry noumerous about this Place) and put into a close pen made of logs to secure it from the wolves &amp; birds &amp; proceeded on to a large bottom nearly opposit the <name type="place" key="Heart (Ches-che-tar and similar spellings) River">Chisscheter (heart) River</name>,<ref target="n09021306" n="6"/> in this bottom we found but little game, Great No. of wolves, on the hills Saw Several parsels of Buffalow.—    Camped. I killed a Buck</p>
               <p>
6th Day    The Buffalow Seen last night provd to be Bulls.    lean &amp; unfit for to make uce of as food, the Distance from Camp being nearly 60 miles, and the packing of meat that distance attended with much difficuity deturmined me to return and hunt the points above, we Set out on our return and halted at an old Indian lodge 40 miles below <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name>
                  <ref target="n09021307" n="7"/>    Killed 3 Elk &amp; 2 Deer—.</p>
               <p>
7th Day    a cold Day    wind blew hard from the N. W.    <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">J Fields</name> got one of his ears frosed    deturmined to lay by and hunt to day    Killed an Elk &amp; 6 deer,* this meat I had Boned &amp; put onto a Close pen made of logs—*    all that was fit for use—</p>
               <p>
8th day    air keen    halted at the old Camp we Stayed in on the 2d night after we left the Fort,<ref target="n09021308" n="8"/> expecting to meat the horses at this Place, killed 3 Deer, Several men being nearly out of Mockersons &amp; the horses not returning deturmind me to return to 〈Camp〉 the Fort on tomorrow</p>
               <p>
9th day.    Set out early, Saw great numbers of <hi rend="italic">Grouse</hi> feeding on the young willows, on the Sand bars    one man<ref target="n09021309" n="9"/> I sent in persute of a gangue of Elk killed three near the old <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Ricara</name> Village and joined at the fort, Sent him back to Secure the meat one man with him—    The ice on the parts of the River which was verry rough, as I went down, was Smothe on my return, this is owing to the rise and fall of the water, which takes place every day or two, and Caused by partial thaws, and obstructions in the passage of the water thro the Ice, which frequently attaches itself to the bottom.—    the water when riseing forses its way thro the cracks &amp; air holes above the old ice, &amp; in one night becoms a Smothe Surface of ice 4 to 6 Inchs thick,—    the river falls &amp; the ice Sink in places with the water and attaches itself to the bottom, and when it again rises to its former hite, frequently leavs a valley of Several feet to Supply with water to bring it on a leavel Surfice.</p>
               <p>
The water of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> at this time is Clear with little Tinges.</p>
               <p>
I saw Several old Villages near the <name type="place" key="Heart (Ches-che-tar and similar spellings) River">Chisscheta River</name>    on enquirey found they were <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> Villages destroyed by the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sous</name> &amp; Small Pox, they noumerous and lived in [<hi rend="italic">NB: 9</hi>] 6<ref target="n09021310" n="10"/>    Villages near that place. 
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-02-13.03" n="">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Wednesday 13th Feby. 1805</hi>.    2 men sent 18 mls. down the River to butcher an Elk which the hunters killed yesterday and to hunt, Snow the later part of the day.    the 2 men returned    had dressed the elk but killed nothing.—
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-02-13.04" n="">
            <sp who="jw">
               <speaker>Whitehouse</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Wednesday February 13th    This day clear &amp; pleasant weather.—    The blacksmith<ref target="n09021311" n="11"/> was employed shoeing the horses, in Order to go and fetch to the Fort, the meat that was killed by <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain Clark</name> and his party.—


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n09021301" n="1">Having returned from his hunting trip, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> resumed keeping Codex C. He gives a brief summary of the trip, detailed enough to suggest his keeping some brief notes while traveling, notes that are unknown today.</note>
            <note xml:id="n09021302" n="2">Shown on <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 29 as <name type="place" key="Mandan Island">Mandan Island</name>, in <name type="place" key="McLean County, N. Dak.">McLean County</name>, <name type="place" key="North Dakota">North Dakota</name>, four to five miles below <name type="place" key="Washburn, N. Dak.">Washburn</name> and a little above <name type="place" key="Sanger, N. Dak.">Sanger</name>. The camp might have been on the island, on the starboard side, or on the larboard side, in <name type="place" key="Oliver County, N. Dak.">Oliver County</name>, since the <name type="place" key="Missouri">Missouri</name> could be crossed on the ice, as the hunting party clearly did on subsequent days. MRC map 51.</note>
            <note xml:id="n09021303" n="3">Probably an earth lodge in one of the abandoned villages shown on <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> maps 28 and 29, downriver from <name type="place" key="Mandan Island">Mandan Island</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n09021304" n="4">Shown on <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 28, evidently <name type="place" key="Square Butte (Hunting) Creek">Square Butte Creek</name> in <name type="place" key="Oliver County, N. Dak.">Oliver County</name>, <name type="place" key="North Dakota">North Dakota</name>, its mouth a little below the <name type="place" key="Morton County, N. Dak.">Morton County</name> line. The party had passed it the previous <ref n="1804-10-22" type="related">October 22</ref>, but <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> probably bestowed the name during this hunting trip. MRC map 50.</note>
            <note xml:id="n09021305" n="5">The common raven, <hi rend="italic">Corvus corax</hi> [AOU, 486], evidently, with which the captains were familiar. Burroughs, 248. The meat cache was apparently near <name type="place" key="Mandan, N. Dak.">Mandan</name>, <name type="place" key="Morton County, N. Dak.">Morton County</name>. MRC map 50.</note>
            <note xml:id="n09021306" n="6">Opposite the mouth of <name type="place" key="Heart (Ches-che-tar and similar spellings) River">Heart River</name> they would be in or near present <name type="place" key="Bismark, N. Dak.">Bismarck</name>, <name type="place" key="Burleigh County, N. Dak.">Burleigh County</name>, <name type="place" key="North Dakota">North Dakota</name>. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> Map 28; MRC map 50.</note>
            <note xml:id="n09021307" n="7">Again he may mean an earth lodge in one of the abandoned villages in the area between <name type="place" key="Heart (Ches-che-tar and similar spellings) River">Heart River</name> and <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name>. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> maps 28, 29.</note>
            <note xml:id="n09021308" n="8">Presumably below <name type="place" key="Mandan Island">Mandan Island</name>, where they stayed the first night out (see n. 2, above), but <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> maps 28 and 29 show no hunting camps in the area. Probably <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> refers to another abandoned village, since he indicates that they stayed at "an old Indian lodge" on the second night out (see above). MRC maps 50, 51.</note>
            <note xml:id="n09021309" n="9">Probably <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name>; see <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> entry for <ref n="1805-02-12" type="related">February 12</ref>, above.</note>
            <note xml:id="n09021310" n="10">Eight old <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> villages and an old hunting camp can be counted in the <name type="place" key="Heart (Ches-che-tar and similar spellings) River">Heart River</name> area on <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 28.</note>
            <note xml:id="n09021311" n="11">
               <name type="person" key="Shields, John">Shields</name>.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-02-12" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-02-14" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
