<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-08-18">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
August 18, 1805</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 5</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">July 28–November 1, 1805</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1989</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">117-119</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">206</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">127</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 11</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of Joseph Whitehouse, May 14, 1804–April 2, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1997</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">276-277</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
         <geoDecl datum="WGS" xml:id="lc.geo.1805-08-18.01">
            <placeName/>
            <geo>44.7167 -112.6667</geo>
            <note>Camped along Horse Prairie Creek, near Red Butte, eight miles west of Grant, Beaverhead County, MT.</note>
         </geoDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc/>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-06-07</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1805-08-18">August 18, 1805</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-08-18.01" n="lc.geo.1805-08-18.01">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Sunday August 18th 1805.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
This morning while <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt Clark</name> was busily engaged in preparing for his rout, I exposed some articles to barter with the Indians for horses as I wished a few at this moment to releive the men who were going with <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt Clark</name> from the labour of carrying their baggage and also one to keep here in order to pack the meat to camp which the hunters might kill. I soon obtained three very good horses for which I gave an uniform coat, a pair of legings, a few handkerchiefs, three knives and some other small articles the whole of which did not cost more than about 20$ in the U' States.    the Indians seemed quite as well pleased with their bargin as I was.    the men also purchased one for an old checked shirt a pair of old legings and a knife.    two of those I purchased <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. C.</name> took on with him. at 10 A. M. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name> departed with his detatchment and all the Indians except 2 men and 2 women who remained with us. Two of the inferior chiefs were a little displeased at not having received a present equivolent to that given the first Chief.    to releive this difficulty <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name> bestoed a couple of his old coats on them and I promised that if they wer active in assisting me over the mountains with horses that I would give them an additional present; this seemed perfectly to satisfy them and they all set out in a good humour. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name> encamped this evening near the narrow pass between the hills on <name type="place" key="Beaverhead (Jefferson) River">Jefferson's river</name> in the <name type="place" key="Shoshone Cove">Shoshone Cove</name>.<ref target="n20081801" n="1"/> his hunters killed one deer which the party with the aid of the Indians readily consumed in the course of the evening.—    after there departure this morning I had all the stores and baggage of every discription opened and aired.    and began the operation of forming the packages in proper parsels for the purpose of transporting them on horseback.    the rain in the evening compelled me to desist from my operations. I had the raw hides put in the water in order to cut them in throngs proper for lashing the packages and forming the necessary geer for pack horses, a business which I fortunately had not to learn on this occasion. <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name> Killed one deer this evening.    a beaver was also caught by one of the party. I had the net arranged and set this evening to catch some trout which we could see in great abundance at the bottom of the river. This day I completed my thirty first year, and conceived that I had in all human probability now existed about half the period which I am to remain in this Sublunary world. I reflected that I had as yet done but little, very little indeed, to further the hapiness of the human race, or to advance the information of the succeeding generation. I viewed with regret the many hours I have spent in indolence, and now soarly feel the want of that information which those hours would have given me had they been judiciously expended.    but since they are past and cannot be recalled, I dash from me the gloomy thought and resolved in future, to redouble my exertions and at least indeavour to promote those two primary objects of human existence, by giving them the aid of that portion of talents which nature and fortune have bestoed on me; or in future, to live for <hi rend="italic">mankind,</hi> as I have heretofore lived <hi rend="italic">for myself.—</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-08-18.02" n="lc.geo.1805-08-18.01">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>August 18th Sunday 1805
</date>
               </ab>
               <p>
Purchased of the Indians three horses for which we gave a Chiefs Coat Some Handkerchiefs a Shirt Legins &amp; a fiew arrow points &amp;c. I gave two of my coats to two of the under Chiefs who appeared not well Satisfied that the first Chief was dressed so much finer than themselves.    at 10 oClock I Set out accompanied by the Indians except 3 <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">the interpreter</name> and <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">wife</name>, the fore part of the day worm, at 12 oClock it became hasey with a mist of rain wind hard from the S. W. and Cold which increased untill night the rain Seased in about two hours. We proceeded on thro' a wide leavel vallie without wood except willows &amp; Srubs for 15 miles and Encamped at a place the high lands approach within 200 yards in 2 points    the River here only 10 yards wide Several Small Streams branching out on each Side below.    all the Indians proceeded on except the 3 Chiefs &amp; two young men.    my hunters killed two Deer which we eate. The Course from the forks is West 9 miles N. 60° W. 6 miles. The Latd. of the forks agreeable to observations is 43° 30' 43" North—    [<hi rend="italic">EC: actually about 45°</hi>]
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-08-18.03" n="lc.geo.1805-08-18.01">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Sunday 18th August 1805</hi>.    a clear morning.    one beaver Caught last
night in a trap. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name> and 11 men got in readiness this morning to go with the natives over the Mountain to See if possable to make canoes for us to descend the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbian river</name> to the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">western ocian</name>. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name> bought three horses of the natives.    gave a uniform coat and a knife for one and red leggins &amp; a hankerchief &amp; knife for an other.    a fiew arrow points hove in about the Same given for the other    Some of the men bought one to carry their baggage on and gave an ordinary check Shirt a pair of old red leggins and a knife only for a tollarable good pack horse.    about 10 oClock A. m <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name> &amp; 11 men Set out with the natives all except 2 men &amp; 2 of the women Stayed at our Camp.    we put out our baggage &amp; Indian goods to dry and air.    we had Showers of rain this afternoon.    one hunter out who killed one deer.    we got one of the Indians horses to pack it into Camp.—

</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-08-18.04" n="lc.geo.1805-08-18.01">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Sunday 18th.</hi>    A fine morning. We bought three horses of the Indians. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain Clarke</name> and 11 more, with <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">our interpreter</name> and <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">his wife</name>, and all the Indians set out at 11 o'clock to go over to the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>.— The Indians went for horses to carry our baggage, and we to search for timber to make canoes for descending the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>. We proceeded up the north branch which is the largest and longest branch of <name type="place" key="Beaverhead (Jefferson) River">Jefferson river</name>,<ref target="n20081802" n="2"/> through a handsome valley about 5<ref target="n20081803" n="3"/> miles wide. In this we found a number of springs and small branches, but no timber. There is plenty of grass and clover, and also some flax all along it. The Indians all except 5 went on ahead. We travelled 15 miles and encamped<ref target="n20081804" n="4"/> close on the branch which is about 5 yards wide. Here we killed two small deer. The country all around is very mountainous, with some few pine trees on the mountains. At three o'clock this afternoon there was a violent gust of wind, and some rain fell. In about an hour the weather became clear, and very cold, and continued cold all night.


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-08-18.05" n="lc.geo.1805-08-18.01">
            <sp who="jw">
               <speaker>Whitehouse</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Sunday 18th August 1805</hi>.    One beaver caught in a trap l. n.<ref target="n20081805" n="5"/>    a clear morning.    <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name> and 11 men got in readiness to Set out with the natives to go over the mountain to the other River, to make canoes &amp;c.    
<name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name> bought 4 horses of the natives Gave them, Some he gave a uniform coat a knife &amp; a hankerchief.    others he gave red leggins a knife a hankch. and a fiew arrow points &amp;c.    2 of the men joined and bought a horse to take their baggage on &amp; gave only one brich cloath one old or poo[r] Shirt &amp; one knife, for a good pack horse.    these Indian are verry poor and vallue a little worth a great deal, as they never had Scarsely any kind of a kinife or Tommahawk or any weapons of war or to use.    2 or 3 guns only to be seen among them which we expect they got from Some other nation, who traded with the french or Spanish tradors.    gave their horses &amp;c. for them.    they are tollarably well dressed with Skins Such as antelope and Mountain rams Skins &amp;c.    they have a fiew beeds and ear bobs among them.    they gave <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name> a kind of an ornament which Spread around the Shoulders    it was made of wezels<ref target="n20081806" n="6"/> tales &amp; Some other ornemental afares.    they have little things made of mussell shell which they hang in their ears with their beeds &amp;    about 10 oClock A. m. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name> 11 men and all the natives but 4[,] 2 women &amp; 2 men which Stayed at our Camp, Set out with their horses &amp; considerable baggage to cross the mountain and Send back the horses for us to pack over all the baggage, which we wish to take over    we put out the Indian goods &amp;c to air &amp; Sort    we had Some Showers of rain this afternoon    the one hunter killed one Deer to day—</p>
               <p>
Sunday August 18th    We had a clear morning, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain Clark</name> and 11 of our men got themselves in readiness to set out with some Indians; to go over the mountains to the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>; in order to make Canoes &amp;ca.    <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Lewis</name> purchased from the Indians that were encamped with us 4 more horses, he gave them for those horses, a Uniform Coat, knives, a handerchief red leggins &amp;ca.    two of the Men also purchased one horse from them to carry their baggage, for which they gave them a breech Cloth, an old Shirt &amp; knife.    These Indians 〈are〉 had the appearance of being very poor, &amp; set a great value, on the most trifling article.    they had no knives, or tomahawks among them; or any War like Instruments (excepting 3 Guns which we expect they had got from some other Indians, that had purchased them from French or Spanish traders, for horses,)    These Indians were tolerable well made Men, have very good countenances, but are darker colour'd, than the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> Indians, Their dress was made out of the Skins of Antelopes &amp; mountain Rams or Ibex, they had some Beads &amp; ear bobs among them.    They gave <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Lewis</name> an ornament, which, they used to wear round their Shoulders, This consisted of Weasels tails sewed together, and ornamented with Muscle Shells &amp;ca—.    About 10 o'Clock A. M. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain Clark</name>, 11 of our party &amp; all the Indians excepting 4, (two of which were Men) left our camp, &amp; set out with their horses, &amp; a considerable quantity of our baggage, to go across the Mountain; &amp; intend to send back the Horses for us, to pack &amp; bring over the remainder of them.    We put out the Indian goods to air, &amp; to assort them.—    We had some Rain in the afternoon.—    One of our hunters that was out killed a deer, which he brought to our Camp.—


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n20081801" n="1">
               <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> route appears as a dotted line on <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 67. The campsite, labeled "W. C. Camp" on the map, was near <name type="place" key="Red Butte">Red Butte</name>, about eight miles west of <name type="place" key="Grant, Mont.">Grant</name>, <name type="place" key="Beaverhead County, Mont.">Beaverhead County</name>, <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>. Peebles (RW), 6.</note>
            <note xml:id="n20081802" n="2">They went up <name type="place" key="Horse Prairie Creek (West Fork Jefferson River)">Horse Prairie Creek</name>, not the main branch of <name type="place" key="Beaverhead (Jefferson) River">Beaverhead</name> (<name type="place" key="Beaverhead (Jefferson) River">Jefferson</name> to the party) River, but the best for their purposes, into <name type="place" key="Shoshone Cove">Shoshone Cove</name>, <name type="place" key="Beaverhead County, Mont.">Beaverhead County</name>, <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n20081803" n="3">The numeral in <name type="person" key="McKeehan, David">McKeehan's</name> edition is nearly illegible, and the interpretation could be debatable.</note>
            <note xml:id="n20081804" n="4">Near <name type="place" key="Red Butte">Red Butte</name>, some eight miles west of <name type="place" key="Grant, Mont.">Grant</name>, <name type="place" key="Beaverhead County, Mont.">Beaverhead County</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n20081805" n="5">Meaning last night, as in <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway's</name> journal.</note>
            <note xml:id="n20081806" n="6">Long-tailed weasel, <hi rend="italic">Mustela frenata</hi>. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> received such a tippet from <name type="person" key="Cameahwait">Cameahwait</name>, chief of the <name type="place" key="Shoshone Indians, Lemhi">Lemhi Shoshones</name>; it is <ref n="1805-08-20" type="related">shown</ref> in vol. 5, p. xii.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-08-17" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-08-19" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
