<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1804-12-25">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
December 25, 1804</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 3</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">August 25, 1804–April 6, 1805</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1987</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">261</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">106</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">68</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 11</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of Joseph Whitehouse, May 14, 1804–April 2, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1997</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">113-114</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc/>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-03-30</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1804-12-25">December 25, 1804</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1804-12-25.01" n="">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>25th <hi rend="italic">December Christmass</hi> Tuesday</date>
               </ab>
               <p>
I was awakened before Day by a discharge of 3 platoons<ref target="n08122501" n="1"/> from the Party and the french, the men merrily Disposed, I give them all a little Taffia and permited 3 Cannon fired, at raising Our flag, Some men went out to hunt &amp; the Others to Danceing and Continued untill 9 oClock P, M, when the frolick ended &amp;c.

</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1804-12-25.02" n="">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Tuesday 25th Decr</hi>. 1804.    cloudy.    we fired the Swivels at day break &amp; each man fired one round.    our officers Gave the party a drink of Taffee.    we had the Best to eat that could be had, &amp; continued firing dancing &amp; frolicking dureing the whole day.    the Savages did not Trouble us as we had requested them not to come as it was a Great medician day with us.    we enjoyed a merry cristmas dureing the day &amp; evening untill nine oClock—all in peace &amp; quietness.

</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1804-12-25.03" n="">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Tuesday 25th.</hi>    The morning was ushered in by two discharges of a swivel, and a round of small arms by the whole corps. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain Clarke</name> then presented to each man a glass of brandy, and we hoisted the American flag in the garrison, and its first waving in fort Mandan was celebrated with another glass.— The men then cleared out one of the rooms and commenced dancing. At 10 o'clock we had another glass of brandy, and at 1 a gun was fired as a signal for dinner. At half past 2, another gun was fired, as a notice to assemble at the dance, which was continued in a jovial manner till 8 at night; and without the presence of any females, except three squaws, wives to our interpreter,<ref target="n08122502" n="2"/> who took no other part than the amusement of looking on. None of the natives came to the garrison this day; the commanding officers having requested they should not, which was strictly attended to. During the remainder of the month we lived in peace and tranquility in the garrison, and were daily visited by the natives.


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1804-12-25.04" n="">
            <sp who="jw">
               <speaker>Whitehouse</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Tuesday 25th Decr. 1804.<ref target="n08122503" n="3"/>    we ushred in the morning with a discharge 
of the Swivvel, and one round of Small arms of all the party.    then another from the Swivel.    then <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name> presented a glass of brandy to each man of the party.    we hoisted the american flag and each man had another Glass of brandy.    the men prepared one of the rooms and commenced dancing.    at 10 oC. we had another glass of brandy, at one a gun was fired as a Signal for diner.    half past two another gun was fired to assemble at the dance, and So we kept it up in a jovel manner untill Eight oC. at night, all without the compy. of the female Seck, except three Squaws the Intreptirs wives and they took no part with us only to look on.    agreeable to the officers request the natives all Stayed at their villages all day.—</p>
               <p>
Tuesday Decemr 25th    This morning being Christmass, the day was announced by the discharge of our swivels, and one Round from our small arms of the whole company; about 7 o'Clock A. M. we fired our Swivels again, when <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain Clark</name> came out of his quarters, and presented a Glass of Brandy to each Man of our party.—    He then ordered the American Flag to be hoisted, which being done; he presented them again with another Glass of brandy.—    The Men then prepared one of the Rooms, and commenced dancing, we having with us Two Violins &amp; plenty of Musicans in our party.—</p>
               <p>
At 10 o'Clock A. M. the whole of the party were again served with another Glass brandy    they continued dancing 'till 1 o'Clock P. M. when our Cannon was fir'd off, as a signal for dinner, at half an hour past 2 oClock P. M. we fired off our Cannon, and repaired to the Room to dance, which they continued at till 8 o'Clock P. M.    There was none of the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>, Excepting 3 Squaws our Interpreters Wives at the Fort, the Officer having requested the Natives, to stay in their Towns, which they complied with, the Officers this day named our Fort, <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name>,—


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n08122501" n="1">Here "platoon" is used in its old sense of volleys, or a group of men firing in unison.</note>
            <note xml:id="n08122502" n="2">The wife of <name type="person" key="Jusseaume, René">Rene Jusseaume</name> and <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Toussaint Charbonneau's</name> two wives, including <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name>; see <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> entries of <ref n="1804-10-27" type="related">October 27</ref> and <ref n="1804-11-04" type="related">November 4, 1804</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n08122503" n="3">From this date until December 31 there is a gap in <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse's</name> writing in both the 
original journal and the fair copy.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1804-12-24" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1804-12-26" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
