<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-09-13">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
September 13, 1805</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 5</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">July 28–November 1, 1805</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1989</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">202-204</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">223</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">141</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 11</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of Joseph Whitehouse, May 14, 1804–April 2, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1997</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">312-314</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
         <geoDecl datum="WGS" xml:id="lc.geo.1805-09-13.01">
            <placeName/>
            <geo>46.6376 -114.553</geo>
            <note>Camped at the lower end of Packer Meadows, Idaho County, ID.</note>
         </geoDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc/>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-06-15</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1805-09-13">September 13, 1805</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-09-13.01" n="lc.geo.1805-09-13.01">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>
                  <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>
                  <ref target="n22091301" n="1"/>
               </speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <table rows="4" cols="3">
                     <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Course &amp; Distance &amp;c. Sept. 13th 1805</hi>
                     </head>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  2</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">miles up the Said Creek through an emencely bad road,<lb/>
rocks, Steep hill sides &amp; fallen timber inumerable    The<lb/>
Snow toped mountains at a long distance from S W to S E<lb/>
none else to be Seen in any other Directions to hot Springs<lb/>
on the right. Those springs come out in maney places in the<lb/>
rocks and nearly boiling hot</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 30° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  3</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">miles to the creek    passed a round about of 3 miles to our<lb/>
left of intolerable road timber &amp;c as usial    halted to noon it<lb/>
&amp; wate for <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name> who lost his horse</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 30° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                           <hi rend="underline">  7</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">miles over a mountain &amp; a Dividing ridge of flat gradey land<lb/>
to a Creek from the left passing thro a glade of ½ a mile in<lb/>
width, keeping down the Creek 2 mile &amp; Encamped. The<lb/>
Country as usial except the Glades which is open &amp; boggey,<lb/>
water Clare and Sandey. Snow toped Mountains to the S E. at<lb/>
the head of this Creek which we call [<hi rend="italic">blank</hi>] Creek. The after<lb/>
part of the day Cloudy. I killed 4 Pheasents &amp; <name type="person" key="Shields, John">Shields</name> killed<lb/>
a Black tail Deer.    a horse found in the glades left lame by<lb/>
Some Indians &amp;c.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                           <hi rend="right">m</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                           <hi rend="double underline">12</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-09-13.02" n="lc.geo.1805-09-13.01">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">September 13th Wednesday</hi> [<hi rend="italic">NB: Friday</hi>] <hi rend="italic">1805</hi>.</date>
               </ab>
               <p>	  	
a cloud morning    <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt Lewis</name> and one of our guides lost their horses, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt Lewis</name> &amp; 4 men detained to hunt the horses, I proceeded on with the partey up the Creek at 2 miles passed Several Springs which I observed the Deer Elk &amp;c. had made roads to, and below one of the Indians had made a whole to bathe, I tasted this water and found it hot &amp; not bad tasted    The last [<hi rend="italic">blank</hi>]    in further examonation I found this water nearly boiling hot at the places it Spouted from the rocks (which a hard Corse Grit, and of great size the rocks on the Side of the Mountain of the Same texture[)]    I put my finger in the water, at first could not bare it in a Second—<ref target="n22091302" n="2"/>    as Several roads led from these Springs in different derections, my Guide took a wrong road and took us out of our rout 3 miles through intolerable rout, after falling into the right road I proceeded on thro tolerabl rout for abt. 4 or 5 miles and halted to let our horses graze as well as waite for <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt Lewis</name> who has not yet Come up, The pine Countrey falling timber &amp;c. &amp;c. Continue. This Creek is verry much damed up with the beaver, but we can See none, dispatched two men back to hunt <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt Lewis</name> horse, after he came up, and we proceeded over a mountain to the head of the Creek which we left to our left and at 6 miles from the place I nooned it, we fell on a Small Creek from the left which Passed through open glades Some of which ½ a mile wide,<ref target="n22091303" n="3"/> we proceeded down this Creek about 2 miles to where the mountains Closed on either Side crossing the Creek Several tmes &amp; Encamped.</p>
               <p>
One Deer &amp; Some Pheasants killed this morning, I shot 4 Pheasents of the Common Kind except the taile was black.<ref target="n22091304" n="4"/> The road over the last mountain was thick Steep &amp; Stoney as usial, after passing the head of <name type="place" key="Lolo (Travelers' Rest) Creek (Mont.)">Travelers rest Creek</name>, the road was verry fine leavel open &amp; firm    Some mountains in view to the S E &amp; S W. Covered with Snow.<ref target="n22091305" n="5"/>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-09-13.03" n="lc.geo.1805-09-13.01">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>	
Friday 13th Sept. 1805.    cloudy.    we got all our horses up except one which <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name> rode we could not find, and a colt also.    we then loaded our horses and proceeded on a Short distance and came to a warm Spring<ref target="n22091306" n="6"/> which run from a ledge of rocks and nearly boiled and issued out in several places    it had been frequented by the Savages.    a little dam was fixed and had been used for a bathing place.    we drank a little of the water and washed our faces in it.    a handsome green on the creek near this Spring.    we had Some difficulty here in finding the direct trail.    we went round a bad way came on the trail again and halted to dine at or near the head of Sd. Creek at a beaver dam.    then proceeded on ascended a high rough mountain    over took the hunters who had killed a deer. 2 of them sent back to look for <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewises</name> horse.    we crossed the dividing ridge<ref target="n22091307" n="7"/> and a number of Spring runs and found it to be only about half a mile from the head Spring of the waters running East to the head Spring of the waters runing west.    each heading in an open marshy Swamp which is level and full of Springs.    we came on a creek running west on which we Camped.—<ref target="n22091308" n="8"/>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-09-13.04" n="lc.geo.1805-09-13.01">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Friday 13th.</hi>    A cloudy morning. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis's</name> horse could not be found; but some of the men were left to hunt for him and we proceeded on. When we had gone 2 miles, we came to a most beautiful warm spring, the water of which is considerably above blood-heat; and I could not bear my hand in it without uneasiness. There are so many paths leading to and from this spring, that our guide took a wrong one for a mile or two, and we had bad travelling across till we got into the road again. At noon we halted. Game is scarce; and 
our hunters killed nothing since yesterday morning; though 4 of the best were constantly out, and every one of them furnished with a good horse. While we remained here, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Lewis</name> and the men, who had been left with him, came up; but had not found the horse. At 2 o'clock we proceeded on again over a mountain, and in our way found a deer, which our hunters had killed and hung up. In a short time we met with them, and <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name> sent two back to look for the horse. We passed over a dividing ridge to the waters 
of another creek, and after travelling 12 miles we encamped on the creek, up which there are some prairies or plains.


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-09-13.05" n="lc.geo.1805-09-13.01">
            <sp who="jw">
               <speaker>Whitehouse</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Friday 13th Sept. 1805</hi>.    cloudy.    we got our horses up all but the one <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name> rode and a colt which our young Indian rode.    we hunted Some time for them but could not find them.    then all but 2 or three loaded the horses and proceeded on    a Short distance passed a warm Spring, which nearly boiled where it Issued out of the rocks    a Short distance below the natives has dammed it up to bathe themselves in, and the water in that place is considerable above blood heat.    it runs out in Sundry places and Some places cooler than others.    Several of us drank of the water, it has a little sulpur taste and verry clear.    these Springs are very beautiful to See, and we think them to be as good to bathe in &amp;c. as any other ever yet found in the United States.    a handsom green or Small meadow on the creek near Sd. Springs.    a little above we could not git along the Indian trail for the timber which had been blown down in a thicket of pine &amp;c.    So we went around a hill came on the trail again and proceeded on untill about 11 oClock and halted to dine and let our horses feed on the main fork of the creek where was Several beaver dams.    <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name> and the men who Stayed back to hunt their horses joined us, but had not found them    our hunters gone on a head    the mountains rough and rocks which appear above the timber like towers in Some places.    the day proved pleasant.    we proceeded on assended a high mountain, over took the hunters.    they had killed a Deer.    2 of them Sent back after <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewiss</name> horse.    we crossed the dividing ridge found it only about half a mile from the head Spring of the water running East to a branch running west.    each heading on an open Swamp, which is level and full of Springs.    Came [<hi rend="italic">blank</hi>] miles this day and Camped on the branch running west where we had good feed for our horses.</p>
               <p>
Friday Septemr. 13th    We had Cloudy weather; We got up all our Horses, but the one that <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Lewis</name> had rode &amp; a Colt which was rode by the Young Indian, who attended our Interpreter; which we had got from the <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Snake</name> Nation of Indians</p>
               <p>
The men all turned out to hunt for this horse &amp; Colt, but returned to us without success.    We on the return of our Men loaded our horses with our Goods &amp; baggage excepting 3 which we left for Men, to ride &amp; seek the lost horses, we proceeded on our way a short distance when we came to a Warm spring, where the water was nearly boiling hot, where it issued out of the Rocks.    We found a short distance below that place a dam, which the Natives had made in Order to stop the Water, that they might have a bathing place.    the water at this Bath was considerable above blood heat, this bath run out at different places, some of which was considerable cooler than others.—    Several of our party drank of the Water that was in this Bath, it had strongly the taste of Sulphur, &amp; was very clear.    The same kind of Sulphurous springs are to be found near this place, &amp; has a handsome appearance, Our officers were of opinion that those Springs were very healthy to bathe in; Near this spring run lies a very handsome Creek, with a very handsome Meadow lying 
along it, &amp; this Meadow lay near to the Spring, &amp; a small distance above it—    We could not get along the Indian trail, for the timber that had been blown down in a thicket of Pine &amp; other Trees.—    We went round this falling timber, and round a hill, and got into the road again.    We proceeded on our Journey 'till about 11 o'Clock A. M. when we halted to dine &amp; let our horses feed which was on the Main fork of the Creek,—    where we saw several beaver dams, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Lewis</name> &amp; the Men that staid behind to hunt the horses joined us, but they had not found them.    Our hunters went on ahead to hunt, 'till the evening.    The Mountains we found this day were very rough, and Rocks, which appear above the timber like Towers.—    The day proved very pleasant, and we proceeded on, &amp; ascended a high mountain; &amp; overtook our hunters who had killed a deer, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Lewis</name> sent back 2 of these hunters, to hunt for his Horse &amp; the Colt which was lost—    We proceeded on, and crossed the dividing ridge, &amp; found it only about half a mile from the head of a spring where the Water run an east Course, to a branch of Water which run a West course, each heading in an Open Swamp which lies level &amp; abounds with Springs.    We came only 18 Miles this day &amp; encamped on the branch which run a West course; where we found good Grass for our Horses.—


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n22091301" n="1">Opposite this entry in the Elkskin-bound Journal is a sketch map (<ref n="1805-09-11" type="related">fig. 5</ref>) showing the party's route for about September 11–12, with campsites for those days noted.</note>
            <note xml:id="n22091302" n="2">
               <name type="place" key="Lolo Hot Springs">Lolo Hot Springs</name>, <name type="place" key="Missoula County, Mont.">Missoula County</name>, <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>. Space, 6; <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 69. The springs emerge from granitic rocks of the Cretaceous-age Idaho baholith very near the batholith's contact with rocks of the Precambrian Belt Group. The large size or texture of the crystals in the granite is indicative of the rock having cooled slowly at a great depth in the earth. The temperature of the hot springs has been measured at 111° F.</note>
            <note xml:id="n22091303" n="3">They crossed the present <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>-<name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name> state line into <name type="place" key="Idaho County, Idaho">Idaho County</name>, <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>, east of <name type="place" key="Lolo Pass">Lolo Pass</name>, and went down <name type="place" key="Pack (Glade) Creek">Pack Creek</name> (<name type="place" key="Pack (Glade) Creek">Glade Creek</name> on <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 70) to <name type="place" key="Packer Meadows (Quawmash Glades)">Packer Meadows</name>. The camp was at the lower end of the meadows. Space, 6; Peebles (LT), 4; <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 69.</note>
            <note xml:id="n22091304" n="4">Spruce grouse, <hi rend="italic">Dendragapus canadensis</hi> [AOU, 298], then unknown to science. See below, <ref n="1805-09-20" type="related">September 20, 1805</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n22091305" n="5">The <name type="place" key="Bitterroot Range">Bitterroot Range</name>, which they were now crossing. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 69, 70.</note>
            <note xml:id="n22091306" n="6">
               <name type="place" key="Lolo Hot Springs">Lolo Hot Springs</name>, <name type="place" key="Missoula County, Mont.">Missoula County</name>, <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n22091307" n="7">The explorers crossed the <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>-<name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name> state line into <name type="place" key="Idaho County, Idaho">Idaho County</name>, <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>, east of <name type="place" key="Lolo Pass">Lolo Pass</name>, and followed <name type="place" key="Pack (Glade) Creek">Pack Creek</name> (their <name type="place" key="Pack (Glade) Creek">Glade Creek</name>) to <name type="place" key="Packer Meadows (Quawmash Glades)">Packer Meadows</name>, <name type="place" key="Idaho County, Idaho">Idaho County</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n22091308" n="8">At the lower end of <name type="place" key="Packer Meadows (Quawmash Glades)">Packer Meadows</name>.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-09-12" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-09-14" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
