<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.lc.images_mandan">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">Texts</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2005</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh">
               <term/>
               <term/>
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-11-18</date>
            <name>Becky Potter</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="main">Mandan</head>
         <div type="additional">
            <p>
Unlike many other Plains Native peoples, the Mandans preferred to stay in one place and farm, living in fortified villages of earth lodges along the middle Missouri River where they grew squash, corn, and beans. Their way of life closely resembled their neighbors, the Arikaras and Hidatsas. When the Mandans were not raising crops, they hunted buffalo and traded. The Mandans' villages in the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries were important trade centers for Native and European peoples on the Plains and beyond. Disease, however, stalked the Mandans. A terrible smallpox epidemic in 1781 decimated them, and another epidemic in 1837 wiped out ninety percent of those who had survived. Of the estimated nine thousand Mandans in 1750, only around 150 were alive after 1837. For strength and protection, they joined with the Hidatas and Arikaras; all three communities in succeeding years were relocated to the Fort Berthold Reservation in North Dakota. The Mandans, Hidatsas, and Arikaras came together as the Three Affiliated Tribes, who governed jointly and represented their collective interest to the federal government, as represented by this photograph of one of their delegations to Washington D.C. the Three Affiliated Tribes do maintain distinct languages, cultures, and places of residence. Today, despite over a century of struggle, challenges, and intrusion by outsiders, the Mandans have grown in size and are working to preserve and promote their traditional culture and language.<lb/>
               <lb/>
               <figure>
                  <p>Mandan and Arikara delegation</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>