<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.lc.images_cheyenne">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">Texts</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2005</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh">
               <term/>
               <term/>
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-11-18</date>
            <name>Becky Potter</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="main">Cheyenne</head>
         <div type="additional">
            <p>

Like some other Native peoples of the Plains, the Cheyennes abandoned farming as a way of life when they moved from the Great Lakes region to the Plains. By the time of the Corps of Discovery, the Cheyennes were mobile horse riders and noted fighters, allied with the Arapahos and living in the region around the headwaters of the Platte River in Wyoming and western Nebraska. Their lives, like the Arapahos, centered on the buffalo. Even decades later, as seen in this picture, the Cheyennes preferred to hunt buffalo and live in portable tepee lodges. As with the Arapahos, the Cheyennes split into northern and southern divisions in the decades immediately following the Corps of Discovery. The Northern Cheyenne, after fighting victoriously with the Lakotas against Custer at the Little Bighorn in 1876, were placed on the Northern Cheyenne Reservation in Montana, while the Southern Cheyenne were eventually resettled on the Cheyenne-Arapaho Reservation in western Oklahoma. Today both divisions of the Cheyennes are creatively developing economic solutions to decades-old impoverishment on their reservations and taking steps to ensure the vitality of their language and culture.
<lb/>
               <lb/>
               <table rows="1" cols="5">
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell role="desc" rows="1" cols="1">
                        <figure>
                           <p>Cheyenne lodges with buffalo <lb/>meat drying, 1870</p>
                        </figure>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/>
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/>
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/>
                     <cell role="desc" rows="1" cols="1">
                        <figure>
                           <p>Cheyennes and Arapahos<lb/> at
Seger Colony, 1886</p>
                        </figure>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>