<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.lc.images_shoshone">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">Texts</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2005</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh">
               <term/>
               <term/>
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-11-18</date>
            <name>Becky Potter</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="main">Shoshone</head>
         <div type="additional">
            <p>
The Shoshones at the time of the Corps of Discovery inhabited a huge territory, which anthropologists—and not the Shoshones themselves—have separated into three divisions to reflect some differences among them. The homeland of the Eastern Shoshones was present-day western Wyoming; one of the most famous leaders of the Eastern Shoshones in the decades after the Corps of Discovery was Washakie, pictured here. The Northern Shoshones lived in the region that became central and southern Idaho, and were enemies of the Blackfeet and Atsinas, with whom they fiercely competed for buffalo. Nevada and northwestern Utah was home to the Western Shoshones. Horses, tepees, and the hunting of buffalo were central to both Eastern and Northern Shoshones, and so their way of life in general resembled other mobile Native peoples of the Plains, including the Arapahos and Crows. Salmon fishing was important to Northern Shoshones, since they lived near rivers rich with them. Because the Western Shoshones lived in a very different environment, the Great Basin, and did not have easy access to either horses or buffalo herds, some of their material culture (they often lived in domed wikiups or circular brush huts and were accomplished basketmakers) and hunting and foraging practices differed from the other Shoshones. The Shoshones proved to be very important to the Corps of Discovery, because the woman Sacagawea was born a Lemhi Shoshone, one of the subgroups of the Northern Shoshone. After encountering the Corps of Discovery, the Shoshones, like other Native nations in the American West, were besieged by the culture and military might of the expanding United States during the rest of the nineteenth century. Eventually, despite varying efforts at resistance, the Shoshone communities were confined to different reservations, scattered across Wyoming, Nevada, Utah, and California. The severe impoverishment and assault on cultural sovereignty of the reservation years has been alleviated in varying degrees in recent decades through efforts by Shoshone reservation communities to pursue new strategies of economic development and to revitalize their language, beliefs, and practices through research, documentation, and teaching.


<lb/>
               <lb/>
               <figure>
                  <p>Chief Washakie of<lb/> the Shoshones, 1880</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>