<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.lc.images_pawnee">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">Texts</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2005</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh">
               <term/>
               <term/>
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-11-18</date>
            <name>Becky Potter</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="main">Pawnee</head>
         <div type="additional">
            <p>
Four different groups, or bands, make up the Pawnees, and it was not until the mid-nineteenth century that they were known as a single tribe. At the time that the Corps of Discovery traveled east of their homeland, the four bands of the Pawnees lived in eastern and central Nebraska, along the Platte and Loup rivers. As illustrated by this picture, taken several decades later, the Pawnees usually lived in earthlodges, built and owned by women from two to ten families, with the villages set up on terraces above rivers. The Pawnees were accomplished horse riders and hunters (especially of buffalo) yet also cultivated garden crops such as beans, corn, pumpkin, and squash. Just prior to the Corps of Discovery, the Pawnee bands reportedly had suffered greatly from a devastating smallpox epidemic. In the following decades, the Pawnees were forced to surrender their ancestral lands and relocate southward to a reservation in Indian Territory (the present state of Oklahoma), where they live today. Following their adoption of the Ghost Dance in 1892, the Pawnees revived many of their old ceremonies, dances, games, and songs despite the many difficulties of early reservation life. Some of these hallmarks of their traditional culture endure today as the Pawnees vigorously reclaim and renegotiate their identity and distinctive way of life in the twenty-first century.
<lb/>
               <lb/>
               <figure>
                  <p>Pawnee home, ca. 1871</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>