<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.lc.images_sioux">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">Texts</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2005</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh">
               <term/>
               <term/>
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-11-18</date>
            <name>Becky Potter</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="main">Sioux</head>
         <div type="additional">
            <p>
Perhaps the Native nation most well-known to outsiders, the Sioux are separated into three main divisions, which reflect some differences in dialect, traditions, and land. At the time of the Corps of Discovery, the Santee (or Eastern) Sioux lived in the western Great Lakes region (present day Minnesota and northern Iowa); the Yankton-Yanktonai Sioux were found from the middle course of the Missouri River northward through the eastern part of present-day North and South Dakota; the homeland of the westernmost division of the Sioux, the Teton Sioux or Lakotas, encompassed present-day western South Dakota, eastern Wyoming and Montana, northwestern Nebraska and southwestern North Dakota. The Corps of Discovery met with representatives of the Yankton-Yanktonai and Lakota divisions of the Sioux. Famed horse riders, traders, and aggressive fighters, with enemies that included the Crows and Pawnees and allies consisting of the Cheyennes and Arapahos, most of the Sioux mobile way of life centered on following and hunting the vast buffalo herds of the Plains (some of the Santee Sioux raised crops). They lived in camps of portable tepees like those pictured here, although these photographs are from generations later. The decades following the Corps of Discovery proved very difficult for the Sioux, owing to rapidly diminishing buffalo herds, an explosion of white settlement,  a growing American military presence in the West, and increasing pressure from non-Native missionaries. The Sioux mightily resisted these changes, fighting back against the invasion of their homeland and threats to their way of life. Despite some spectacular victories, they ultimately lost and were confined to reservations scattered across their former homeland. These reservations include Pine Ridge, seen here. In recent decades, some Sioux have worked for change on a national level as activists in the courtroom (seeking the return of the Black Hills) and in the halls of Congress, and by taking part in some well-known protests. At home, the Sioux are working hard in the twenty-first century to combat poverty on the reservations, preserve their language for future generations, and to keep vital a number of their older rituals, healing practices, and spiritual beliefs.
<lb/>
               <lb/>
               <table rows="1" cols="5">
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell role="desc" rows="1" cols="1">
                        <hi rend="center">
                           <figure>
                              <p>Sioux camp at Pine Ridge,<lb/> South Dakota, 1897</p>
                           </figure>
                        </hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/>
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/>
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/>
                     <cell role="desc" rows="1" cols="1">
                        <hi rend="center">
                           <figure>
                              <p>Sioux village</p>
                           </figure>
                        </hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table rows="1" cols="1">
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell role="desc" rows="1" cols="1">
                        <hi rend="center">
                           <figure>
                              <p>Sioux village on Laramie River,<lb/> Nebraska, 1874</p>
                           </figure>
                        </hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>