<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.lc.images_nezperce">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">Texts</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2005</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh">
               <term/>
               <term/>
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-11-18</date>
            <name>Becky Potter</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="main">Nez Perce</head>
         <div type="additional">
            <p>The Nez Perce people assisted the Corps of Discovery and proved instrumental to its survival during the crossing of the Rocky Mountains. This nation, whose culture and language are more closely related to Native peoples of the Pacific Northwest than the Plains, has long hunted, fished, and gathered in the Columbia River Basin in the northern Rocky Mountains. As evidenced by this picture taken some seven decades after the Corps of Discovery, the Nez Perce people were quick to see the advantages of horses when they arrived in the eighteenth century, and soon they adapted to portable tepees, venturing eastward onto the Plains in search of buffalo, and becoming allied with the Crows. In the nineteenth century, the Nez Perce people learned to be skilled traders with outsiders but also actively resisted the waves of white settlers who arrived at the middle of the century. They were restricted by treaty to a reservation in 1855, yet some, such as Chief Joseph and Looking Glass, seen here, refused to sign and eventually were engaged in a bloody and ultimately futile war with the United States Army in 1877. Today the Nez Perce are ardently working on several fronts to preserve and revitalize their cultural sovereignty, including writing their own histories and controlling other forms of representation of them, and also reviving their traditional language, crafts, beliefs, and other practices.<lb/>
               <lb/>
               <figure>
                  <p>Looking Glass<lb/>Nez Perce chief, 1877</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>