<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.lc.images_flathead">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">Texts</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2005</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh">
               <term/>
               <term/>
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-11-18</date>
            <name>Becky Potter</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="main">Flathead</head>
         <div type="additional">
            <p>
The Flatheads, more properly known as the Selish (often rendered as "Salish" by English-language speakers), hunted buffalo and other game and harvested wild plants on both sides of the Continental Divide in the present state of Montana in the early nineteenth century, focused on the Bitterroot Valley. The breathtaking ruggedness and beauty of their mountainous homeland can be glimpsed in the background of this posed photograph, taken generations after the Corps of Discovery encountered a Selish band on a buffalo hunt. Even during the early reservation years, as this photograph shows, many Selish still preferred traditional attire and portable tepee lodges. The Selish have lived in their homeland for a very long time, dating back thousands of years. Just after the mid-nineteenth century, the Selish, along with the Kootenai and Pend d'Oreilles Indians, were forced to cede much of their ancestral lands. Today, they share the Flathead Reservation in western Montana with these other Native communities. Despite over a century of harsh reservation conditions and encroachment by outsiders, the Selish in the twenty-first century continue to celebrate their culture and identity, and are taking great strides to ensure that their language and way of life are not forgotten.<lb/>
               <lb/>
               <figure>
                  <p>Flathead family</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>