<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.lc.images_kiowa">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">Texts</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2005</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh">
               <term/>
               <term/>
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-06-17</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="main">Kiowa-Apache</head>
         <div type="additional">
            <p>
When the Corps of Discovery traveled west, to the south and west of them in the present state of Kansas lived a Native group who spoke a different language than their Plains neighbors. The Kiowa-Apaches, informally known as the Plains Apache, were Athapaskan speakers, connected through language to the Apaches of the southwest, yet living much as other Plains Native peoples did: as mobile bison hunters who were seasoned horse riders and lived in tepees. In the generations after the Corps of Discovery, the Kiowa-Apaches traded and were allied with such peoples as the Arapahos, Cheyennes, and Kiowas. On generally friendly terms with the United States, they eventually agreed to settle with some other Native peoples (Kiowas, Comanches) on a reservation in Indian Territory (Oklahoma). Such leaders as Pacer, pictured here, played key roles in helping the Kiowa-Apaches to achieve a peaceful transition to reservation life. After over a century of dwindling numbers and coping with continual assaults on their health, culture, and remaining land, the Kiowa-Apaches, officially known in the twenty-first century as the Apache Tribe of Oklahoma, are now devoting much energy to preserving their distinctive legacy and revitalizing their way of life for generations to come.<lb/>
               <lb/>
               <figure>
                  <p>Pacer (Peso, Essa-queta),<lb/>
Kiowa-Apache chief, ca. 1870</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>