<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-07-01">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
July 1, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 8</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">June 10–September 26, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1987</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">74-78</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">329</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">247</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="category">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-11-05</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1806-07-01">July 1, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-07-01.01" n="">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Tuesday July 1st 1806.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
This morning early we sent out all our hunters.    set <name type="person" key="Shields, John">Sheilds</name> at work to repair some of our guns which were out of order    <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name> &amp; my self consurted the following plan viz.    from this place I determined to go with a small party by the most direct rout to the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">falls of the Missouri</name>, there to leave <name type="person" key="Thompson, John B.">Thompson</name>
                  <name type="person" key="McNeal, Hugh">McNeal</name> and <name type="person" key="Goodrich, Silas">goodrich</name> to prepare carriages and geer for the purpose of transporting the canoes and baggage over the portage, and myself and six volunteers to ascend <name type="place" key="Marias River">Maria's river</name> with a view to explore the country and ascertain whether any branch of that river lies as far north as Latd. 50 and again return and join the party who are to decend the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, at the entrance of <name type="place" key="Marias River">Maria's river</name>. I now called for the volunteers to accompany me on this rout, many turned out, from whom I scelected<ref target="n36070101" n="1"/>
                  <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name> the <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph and Reubin">two Feildses</name>, <name type="person" key="Werner, William">Werner</name>, <name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">Frazier</name> and <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Sergt Gass</name> accompanied me    the other part of the men are to proceed with <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt Clark</name> to the head of <name type="place" key="Jefferson River (North, Southwest Fork)">Jefferson's river</name> where we deposited sundry articles and left our canoes.<ref target="n36070102" n="2"/>    from hence <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Sergt Ordway</name> with a party of 9 men are to decend the river with the canoes; <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt C.</name> with the remaining ten including <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbono</name> and <name type="person" key="York">York</name> will proceed to the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone river</name> at it's nearest approach to the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Three Forks of the">three forks of the missouri</name>, here he will build a canoe and decend the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone river</name> with <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbono</name> the <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">indian woman</name>, his servant <name type="person" key="York">York</name> and five others to the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">missouri</name> where should he arrive first he will wait my arrival. <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Sergt Pryor</name> with two other men are to proceed with the horses by land to the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name> and thence to the British posts on the <name type="place" key="Assiniboine River">Assinniboin</name> with a letter to <name type="person" key="Heney, Hugh">Mr. Heney [<hi rend="italic">NB: Haney</hi>]</name>
                  <ref target="n36070103" n="3"/> whom we wish to engage to 〈procure〉 prevail on the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name> Chefs to join us on the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, and accompany them with us to the seat of the general government.    these arrangements being made the party were informed of our design and prepared themselves acecordingly.    our hunters killed 13 deer in the course of this day of which 7 were fine bucks, deer are large and in fine order.    the indians inform us that there are a great number of white buffaloe or mountain sheep of the snowey hights of the mountains West of this [<hi rend="italic">NB:</hi>
                  <name type="place"
                        key="Clark Fork (Clark's, East Fork Clark's, Flathead) River">
                     <hi rend="italic">Clarks</hi>] river</name>; they state that they inhabit the most rocky and inaccessible parts, and run but badly, that they kill them with great ease with their arrows when they can find them.<ref target="n36070104" n="4"/>    the indian warrior who overtook us on the 26th Ult. made me a present of an excellent horse which he said he gave for the good council we had given himself and nation and also to assure us of his attatchment to the white men and his desire to be at peace with the <name type="native_nation" key="Atsina Indians">Minnetares of Fort de Prarie</name>.    we had our venison fleeced and exposed in the sun on pole to dry.    the dove<ref target="n36070105" n="5"/> the black woodpecker,<ref target="n36070106" n="6"/> the lark woodpecker,<ref target="n36070107" n="7"/> the logcock, the prarie lark,<ref target="n36070108" n="8"/> sandhill crain, prarie hen with the short and pointed tail,<ref target="n36070109" n="9"/> the robin,<ref target="n36070110" n="10"/> a speceis of brown plover,<ref target="n36070111" n="11"/> a few curloos, small black birds,<ref target="n36070112" n="12"/> ravens<ref target="n36070113" n="13"/> hawks and a variety of sparrows as well as the bee martin<ref target="n36070114" n="14"/> and the several species of Corvus genus are found in this vally.—</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Windsor, Richard">Windsor</name> birst his gun near the muzzle a few days since; this <name type="person" key="Shields, John">Sheilds</name> cut off and I then exchanged it with the Cheif for the one we had given him for conducting us over the mountains.    he was much pleased with the exchange and shot his gun several times; he shoots very well for an inexperienced person.<ref target="n36070115" n="15"/>
               </p>
               <p>
The little animal found in the plains of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> which I have called the <hi rend="italic">barking squirrel</hi>
                  <ref target="n36070116" n="16"/> weighs from 3 to 3½ pounds.    it's form is that of the squirrel.    it's colour is an uniform light brick red grey, the red reather predominating.    the under side of the neck and bely are lighter coloured than the other parts of the body.    the legs are short, and it is wide across the breast and sholders in proportion to it's size, appears strongly formed in that part; the head is also bony muscular and stout, reather more blontly terminated wider and flatter than the common squirrel.    the upper lip is split or divided to the nose.    the ears are short and lie close to the head, having the appearance of being cut off, in this particular they resemble the guinea pig.    the teeth are like those of the squrrel rat &amp;c.    they have a false jaw or pocket between the skin and the mustle of the jaw like that of the common ground squrrel but not so large in proportion to their size.    they have large and full whiskers on each side of the nose, a few long hairs of the same kind on each jaw and over the eyes.    the eye is small and black.    they have five toes on each foot of which the two outer toes on each foot are much shoter than those in the center particularly the two inner toes of the fore feet, the toes of the fore feet are remarkably long and sharp and seem well adapted to cratching or burrowing those of the hind feet are neither as long or sharp as the former; the nails are black.    the hair of this animal is about as long and equally as course as that of the common grey squrrel of our country, and the hair of the tail is not longer than that of the body except immediately at the extremity where it is somewhat longer and frequently of a dark brown colour.    the part of generation in the female is placed on the lower region of the belly between the hinder legs so far forward that she must lie on her back to copolate.    the whole length of this animal is one foot five inches from the extremity of the nose to that of the tail of which the tail occupyes 4 inches.    it is nearly double the size of the whistleing squirrel of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>.    it is much more quick active and fleet than it's form would indicate.    these squirrels burrow in the ground in the open plains usually at a considerable distance from the water yet are never seen at any distance from their burrows.    six or eight usually reside in one burrow to which there is never more than one entrance.    these burrows are of great debth. I once dug and pursued a burrow to the debth of ten feet and did not reach it's greatest debth.    they generally associate in large societies placing their burrows near each other and frequently occupy in this manner several hundred acres of land.    when at rest above ground their position is generally erect on their hinder feet and rump; thus they will generally set and bark at you as you approach them, their note being much that of the little toy dogs, their yelps are in quick succession and at each they a motion to their tails upwards.    they feed on the grass and weeds within the limits of their village which they never appear to exceed on any occasion.    as they are usually numerous they keep the grass and weeds within their district very closely graized and as clean as if it had been swept.    the earth which they throw out of their burrows is usually formed into a conic mound around the entrance.    this little animal is frequently very fat and it's flesh is not unpleasant.    as soon as the hard frosts commence it shuts up it's burrow and continues within untill spring.    it will eat grain or meat.<ref target="n36070117" n="17"/>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-07-01.02" n="">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Tuesday July 1st 1806</hi> on <name type="place"
                           key="Clark Fork (Clark's, East Fork Clark's, Flathead) River">Clark's river</name>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
We Sent out all the hunters very early this morning    by 12 OClock they all returned haveing killd. 12 Deer Six of them large fat Bucks, this is like once more returning to the land of liveing a plenty of meat and that very good.    as <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name> and Myself part at this place we made a division of our party and such baggage and provisions as is Souteable.    the party who will accompany <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt L.</name> is <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">G. Drewyer</name>, <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Sergt. Gass</name>, <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Jo.</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">R. Fields</name>, <name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">Frazier</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Werner, William">Werner</name>, and <name type="person" key="Thompson, John B.">Thompson</name>
                  <name type="person" key="Goodrich, Silas">Goodrich</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="McNeal, Hugh">McNear</name> as far as the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">Falls of Missouri</name> at which place the 3 latter will remain untill I Send down the Canoes from the head of <name type="place" key="Jefferson River (North, Southwest Fork)">Jeffersons river</name>.    they will then join that party and after passing the portage around the falls, proceed on down to the enterance of <name type="place" key="Marias River">Maria</name> where <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name> will join them after haveing assended that river as high up as Latd. 50° North.    from the head of <name type="place" key="Jefferson River (North, Southwest Fork)">Jeffersons river</name> I shall proceed on to the head of the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Rockejhone</name>
                  <ref target="n36070118" n="18"/> with a party of 9 or 10 men and desend that river.    from the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">R Rockejhone</name> I Shall dispatch <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Sergt. Pryor</name> with the horses to the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name> and from thence to the Tradeing Establishments of the N. W. Co on the <name type="place" key="Assiniboine River">Assinniboin River</name> with a letter which we have written for the purpose to engage <name type="person" key="Heney, Hugh">Mr. H. Haney</name> to endeaver to get Some of the principal Chiefs of the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Scioux</name> to accompany us to the Seat of our government &amp;.    we divide the Loading and apportion the horses. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt L.</name> only takes 17 horses with him, 8 only of which he intends to take up <name type="place" key="Marias River">the Maria</name> &amp;c. One of the Indians who accompaned us Swam <name type="place"
                        key="Clark Fork (Clark's, East Fork Clark's, Flathead) River">Clarks river</name> and examined the Country around, on his return he informed us that he had discovered where a Band of the <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Tushepaws</name>
                  </hi> had encamped this Spring    passed of 64 Lodges, &amp; that they had passed Down <name type="place"
                        key="Clark Fork (Clark's, East Fork Clark's, Flathead) River">Clarks river</name> and that it was probable that they were near the <name type="place" key="Weippe Prairie (Camas Flats, Quawmash Flats)">quawmash flatts</name> on a Easterly branch of that river.    those guides expressed a desire to return to their nation and not accompany us further, we informed them that if they was deturmined to return we would kill some meat for them, but wished that they would accompy <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name> on the rout to the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">falls of Missouri</name> only 2 nights and show him the right road to cross the Mountains.    this they agreed to do.    we gave a medal<ref target="n36070119" n="19"/> of the Small Size to the young man Son to the late Great Chief of the <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Chopunnish</name> Nation who had been remarkably kind to us in every instance, to all the others we tied a bunch of blue ribon about the hair, which pleased them very much.    the Indian man who overtook us in the Mountain, presented <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name> with a horse and said that he opened his ears to what we had said, and hoped that <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Cap Lewis</name> would see the <name type="native_nation" key="Atsina Indians">Crovanters of Fort De Prarie</name>
                  <ref target="n36070120" n="20"/> and make a good peace that it was their desire to be at peace. Shew them the horse as a token of their wishes &amp;c.
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-07-01.03" n="">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Tuesday 1st July 1806.    cloudy.    all the hunters turned out eairly a hunting    they all returned by noon    had killed in all twelve deer &amp; Some of them large fat bucks.    in the afternoon our officers had a talk with the guides that came over the mountains with us.    they told our officers that they wished to live in peace and bury their war Stripes<ref target="n36070121" n="21"/> in the ground.    one of them gave <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name> a good horse.


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-07-01.04" n="">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Tuesday 1st July,</hi> 1806.    We had a fine morning, and remained here to rest ourselves and horses after the severe fatigue of coming over the mountains, and some hunters went out. The Indians still continue with us. Here the party is to be separated; some of us are to go straight across to the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">falls of the Missouri</name> and some to the head waters of <name type="place" key="Jefferson River (North, Southwest Fork)">Jefferson river</name>, where we left the canoes.<ref target="n36070122" n="22"/> At the falls, we expect to be subdivided, as <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name>, myself and four or five men, intend to go up <name type="place" key="Marias River">Maria's river</name>, as far as the 50th degree of latitude; and a party to remain at the falls to prepare harness and other things necessary for hauling our canoes and baggage over the portage.— Perhaps <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clarke</name>, who goes up the river here, may also take a party and go down the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Riviere Jaune</name>, or <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellow-stone river</name>. In the afternoon our hunters came in, and had killed twelve deer, most of them in good order.


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n36070101" n="1">It appears that <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> has crossed out this sentence to here then added the words "accompanied me" to make a new sentence.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36070102" n="2">
               <name type="place" key="Camp Fortunate (Mont.)">Camp Fortunate</name> at the forks of the <name type="place" key="Beaverhead (Jefferson) River">Beaverhead River</name>, in <name type="place" key="Beaverhead County, Mont.">Beaverhead County</name>, <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>; see <ref n="1805-08-17" type="related">August 17, 1805</ref>. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 66.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36070103" n="3">
               <name type="person" key="Heney, Hugh">Hugh Heney</name>, whom they met at the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>-<name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> villages; see <ref n="1804-12-16" type="related">December 16, 1804</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36070104" n="4">A red vertical line crosses through this sentence, apparently done by <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36070105" n="5">Mourning dove, <hi rend="italic">Zenaida macroura</hi> [AOU, 316]. Holmgren, 34. The remainder of this paragraph has <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle's</name> red line through it.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36070106" n="6">Lewis's woodpecker, <hi rend="italic">Melanerpes lewis</hi> [AOU, 408]; see <ref n="1806-05-27" type="related">May 27, 1806</ref>. Holmgren, 34; Burroughs, 239–40.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36070107" n="7">Common, or northern, flicker, <hi rend="italic">Colaptes auratus</hi> [AOU, 412]. Burroughs, 241–42; Holmgren, 34.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36070108" n="8">Probably the horned lark, <hi rend="italic">Eremophila alpestris</hi> [AOU, 474]. Holmgren, 31.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36070109" n="9">Sharp-tailed grouse, <hi rend="italic">Tympanuchus phasianellus</hi> [AOU, 308]; see <ref n="1806-03-01" type="related">March 1, 1806</ref>. Holmgren, 29; Burroughs, 213.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36070110" n="10">American robin, <hi rend="italic">Turdus migratorius</hi> [AOU, 761].</note>
            <note xml:id="n36070111" n="11">Probably the upland sandpiper, <hi rend="italic">Bartramia longicauda</hi> [AOU, 261]; see <ref n="1805-07-22" type="related">July 22, 1805</ref>. Holmgren, 33; Burroughs, 227.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36070112" n="12">Either the rusty blackbird, <hi rend="italic">Euphagus carolinus</hi> [AOU, 509], or Brewer's blackbird, <hi rend="italic">E. cyanocephalus</hi> [AOU, 510]. Holmgren, 28.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36070113" n="13">Common raven, <hi rend="italic">Corvus corax</hi> [AOU, 486].</note>
            <note xml:id="n36070114" n="14">Either the eastern kingbird, <hi rend="italic">Tyrannus tyrannus</hi> [AOU, 444], or the western kingbird, more likely the latter.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36070115" n="15">Here on pp. 70–71 of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> Codex L appears his table of courses and distances for June 24–30, 1806. It has been placed under the last of those dates.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36070116" n="16">Prairie dog; see <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> description at <ref n="1804-09-07" type="related">September 7, 1804</ref>. The first few lines of this passage are crossed out with a red vertical line, probably <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle's</name> doing.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36070117" n="17">These last two sentences are crowded in at the bottom of p. 73, Codex L. Thwaites (LC), 5:178, transcribed the passages as, "and continues untill spring.    it will eat neither grain or meat." Accepting the present reading, it is assumed that Lewis left out the negative but did mean that the prarie dog ate neither grain nor meat.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36070118" n="18">More correctly, the French term <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Roche Jaune</name>,</hi> for the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone River</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36070119" n="19">Probably the 55 mm <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> medal; see <ref n="1804-08-03" type="related">August 3, 1804</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36070120" n="20">
               <name type="native_nation" key="Atsina Indians">Gros ventres or big bellies</name>, again the <name type="native_nation" key="Atsina Indians">Atsinas</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36070121" n="21">Perhaps the men spoke figuratively of cleaning the war paint off their faces.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36070122" n="22">For a more detailed account of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> plans, see their entries for this date.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-06-30-1" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-07-02" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
