<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.preface.v10">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">Volume 10 Preface</title>
            <title type="sub"/>
            <author>Gary E. Moulton</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition, Volume 10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Patrick Gass</name>, May 14, 1804–September 23, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">vii</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="category">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-04-28</date>
            <date/>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>
            <name/>Initial creation Transcribed</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="main">Volume 10 Preface</head>
         <head type="sub"/>
         <div type="preface">
            <p>
This volume, the previous one, and the one to follow rely largely on the editorial 
work of previous books in this edition. Therefore, the editorial notes and supporting material in these three books owe a debt to former consultants and friends of 
the project. Once again we extend our great appreciation to the unselfish work of 
these generous people.</p>
            <p>
Nevertheless, we have several persons to thank specifically for help with this volume. The journal of <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Sergeant Patrick Gass</name> is to be found only in printed form; the 
original has been lost since its first publication in 1807. We used a copy from the 
University Archives and Special Collections, University of Nebraska Libraries, which 
was generously microfilmed for us by Joseph G. Svoboda. We were also aided there 
by Michele L. Fagan and Lynn R. Beideck-Porn. At our host institution, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln, help came from John R. Wunder, Linda J. Ratcliffe, and 
Gretchen Walker of the Center for Great Plains Studies, and Thomas W. Dunlay and 
Doris VanSchooten of the project.</p>
            <p>
Scholars again provided advice in their respective disciplines. BOTANY: Steven J. 
Brunsfeld, University of Idaho; A. T. Harrison, Westminster College, Salt Lake City; 
ENTOMOLOGY: Kenneth P. Pruess, University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
            <p>
The project received financial support from Samuel H. Douglas III (Whittier, 
California), Nelson S. Weller (Piedmont, California), the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Trail 
Heritage Foundation, and the National Endowment for the Humanities, an independent federal agency.</p>
            <p>
We extend our sincerest appreciation to all these individuals. Any deficiencies in 
the present work, however, are entirely the fault of the editor.
</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
