<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.v02.appendix.a">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">Volume 2 Appendix A</title>
            <title type="sub">Members of the Expedition</title>
            <author>Gary E. Moulton</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition, Volume 2</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">August 30, 1803–August 24, 1804</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1986</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">509-529</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="category">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-02-24</date>
            <date/>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>
            <name/>Initial creation Transcribed</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="main">Volume 2 Appendix A</head>
         <head type="sub">Members of the Expedition</head>
         <div type="appendix">
            <p>
Illustrators charged with making a picture to represent "The <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition" have usually produced variations on a familiar theme: the two captains, slightly differentiated by dress, gaze off into the western distance; <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name> stands nearby with her infant, sometimes pointing the way. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> black servant, <name type="person" key="York">York</name>, is usually prominent, especially in recent years, and <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Toussaint Charbonneau</name> and <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>
               <name type="person" key="Seaman">dog</name>, <name type="person" key="Seaman">Scannon</name> (or <name type="person" key="Seaman">Seaman</name>), are frequently present. In the background an anonymous collection of buckskin-clad figures representing the rest of the party follow their leaders' gaze toward the horizon or go about their labors. This familiar picture represents the popular conception of the expedition; unfortunately, it also represents fairly accurately the actual state of knowledge about the men who went with the captains on their great trek.<ref target="n01" n="1"/>
            </p>
            <p>
	About the captains there is abundant information; most of the Corps of Discovery, however, lived obscure lives before and after their season of glory. For many there exists the scantiest record, or none at all, about their lives before 1803 and after 1806. The records of the expedition themselves provide, in most cases, only the barest hints about their personalities, virtues, and weaknesses. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark</name> seems to have thought of the permanent party as his "Band of Brothers," in some sense; he had some interest in their later careers, but even he apparently lost track of several of them. Some twenty years after the return to <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>, he drew up a list of thirty-four; eighteen, including <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, he knew or believed to be dead—six of them, in testimony to the hazards of frontier life, listed as "killed"—and for five he apparently had no information. One of those he thought dead, <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Patrick Gass</name>, not only was alive but would outlive <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> and every other expedition member.<ref target="n02" n="2"/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name> has attracted much attention in this century from historians and writers of fiction, but the amount written about her far exceeds the actual information about her life and personality. <name type="person" key="York">York</name> is a natural symbol of black participation in the westward movement, but even less is known of him as a man. <name type="person" key="Colter, John">John Colter</name> acquired fame in his own right as an explorer through his travels and adventures in the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rockies</name> after the expedition. <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Toussaint</name> and <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Jean Baptiste">Jean Baptiste Charbonneau</name> have shared some of <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea's</name> glory. For most of the rest, even such journal keepers as <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">John Ordway</name> and <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Joseph Whitehouse</name>, we can give at best a brief sketch of their lives. For some, we cannot even be sure of the correct spelling of their names.</p>
            <p>
	The captains drew their men from three principal sources: Anglo-American frontiersmen from the <name type="place" key="Ohio River">Ohio</name> Valley, U.S. Army enlisted men, and the French settlers of <name type="place" key="Illinois">Illinois</name> and <name type="place" key="Missouri">Missouri</name>. In the letter offering <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> the chance to second him on the expedition, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> wrote that his friend should recruit some young men in <name type="place" key="Kentucky">Kentucky</name> and <name type="place" key="Indiana">Indiana</name>. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> was instructed to pick backwoodsmen, skilled in hunting and outdoor life and used to hardship, rather than "young gentlemen." <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had several recruits gathered at <name type="place" key="Clarksville, Ind.">Clarksville</name>, <name type="place" key="Indiana Territory">Indiana Territory</name>, when <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> picked him up in October 1803; those have become known as the "Nine Young Men from <name type="place" key="Kentucky">Kentucky</name>," although two of the men listed under that head, <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">George Shannon</name> and <name type="person" key="Colter, John">John Colter</name>, may have joined Lewis on his journey down the <name type="place" key="Ohio River">Ohio</name> by the time he reached <name type="place" key="Cincinnati, Ohio">Cincinnati</name>.<ref target="n03" n="3"/>
            </p>
            <p>
	Most of the remaining men evidently joined the expedition during the winter at <name type="place" key="Dubois River">River Dubois</name>. Many were enlisted men from four companies of the U.S. Army stationed at small posts in the West: <name type="person" key="Bissell, Daniel">Captain Daniel Bissell's</name> company of the First Infantry Regiment, stationed at <name type="place" key="Fort Massac (Ill.)">Fort Massac</name>, <name type="place" key="Illinois">Illinois</name>; <name type="person" key="Bissell, Russell">Captain Russell Bissell's</name> company of the same regiment, stationed at <name type="place" key="Fort Kaskaskia (Ill.)">Fort Kaskaskia</name>, <name type="place" key="Illinois">Illinois</name>; <name type="person" key="Campbell, John">Captain John Campbell's</name> company of the Second Infantry Regiment, stationed in <name type="place" key="Tennessee">Tennessee</name>; and <name type="person" key="Stoddard, Amos">Captain Amos Stoddard's</name> company of artillerists, stationed at <name type="place" key="Fort Kaskaskia (Ill.)">Fort Kaskaskia</name>. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> seems to have suspected that the men sent from <name type="place" key="Tennessee">Tennessee</name>, at least, were picked on the time-honored principle of getting rid of those who could best be spared by their original unit (see <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> entry, <ref n="1803-12-22" type="related">December 22, 1803</ref>). Some backwoodsmen from the <name type="place" key="Illinois">Illinois</name> and <name type="place" key="Missouri">Missouri</name> settlements may have joined during the winter, but for a number of men there is no indication of when and where they first joined or whether they were already in the army. All those not already in the military service who were chosen for the permanent party enlisted as soldiers, except <name type="person" key="York">York</name>, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> slave, and <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">George Drouillard</name>, the civilian interpreter and hunter. Two French boatmen with experience in the Indian trade on the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, <name type="person" key="Labiche, François">Fran<seg n="u231">ç</seg>ois Labiche</name> and <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Pierre Cruzatte</name>, enlisted for the permanent party.<ref target="n04" n="4"/>
            </p>
            <p>
	It would appear that the captains decided during the winter of 1803–4 that they would send back a party of men from somewhere up the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> during the first year of the expedition. Such a party could carry back dispatches, maps, completed journals, and plant, animal, mineral, and anthropological specimens to <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">President Jefferson</name>, giving him a progress report and sparing the expedition the labor of carrying such objects for the entire journey. The thought that something would be saved if they themselves failed to return must have been in their minds. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>
               <name type="place" key="Camp Dubois (Camp Wood, River Dubois) (Ill.)">Dubois</name> Journal contains several lists of names, marked and annotated, showing that he was evaluating the men and trying to determine, on the basis of character and ability, who should be in the permanent and return parties. By <ref n="1804-04-01" type="related">April 1, 1804</ref>, as indicated by a detachment order, the captains had determined the constitution of the two parties, so far as the enlisted soldiers were concerned, and for the most part they adhered to that plan. Certain changes became necessary because of subsequent events, a possibility they had no doubt anticipated from the start. For instance, the two enlisted French boatmen, <name type="person" key="Labiche, François">Fran<seg n="u231">ç</seg>ois Labiche</name> and <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Pierre Cruzatte</name>, joined the ranks of the permanent party. <name type="person" key="Reed, Moses B.">Moses B. Reed</name> and <name type="person" key="Newman, John">John Newman</name> were expelled from the permanent party, the first for desertion, the other for insubordination. <name type="person" key="Floyd, Charles">Sergeant Charles Floyd</name> died, and <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Patrick Gass</name>, another member of the permanent party, assumed his rank. To make up the losses in the permanent party, the captains transferred <name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">Robert Frazer</name> from the original return party and enlisted <name type="person" key="Lepage, Jean Baptiste">Jean Baptiste Lepage</name>, a French trapper encountered at the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> villages.</p>
            <p>
	As matters developed, the return party did not set out during the summer or fall of 1804, as originally planned. On <ref n="1805-04-07" type="related">April 7, 1805</ref>, when the captains and the permanent party left <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name> headed up the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, they were able to send back this return group in the keelboat and one canoe. An exact list exists for the group bound for the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>, but for the returning body there remain some mysteries. <name type="person" key="Warfington, Richard">Corporal Richard Warfington</name> was in charge of the party, and the captains both say that he had with him in the keelboat six soldiers and two Frenchmen, with two more Frenchmen in the canoe.</p>
            <p>
	Among the six soldiers were <name type="person" key="Reed, Moses B.">Reed</name> and <name type="person" key="Newman, John">Newman</name>, expelled from the permanent party. Four other soldiers were intended from the first for the return party, probably Privates <name type="person" key="Boley, John">John Boley</name>, <name type="person" key="Dame, John">John Dame</name>, <name type="person" key="Tuttle, Ebenezer">Ebenezer Tuttle</name>, and <name type="person" key="White, Isaac">Isaac White</name>. It seems possible, if unlikely, that the mysterious <name type="person" key="Robertson, John">John Robertson</name>, or <name type="person" key="Robertson, John">Robinson</name>, was one of them, instead of either <name type="person" key="Tuttle, Ebenezer">Tuttle</name> or <name type="person" key="White, Isaac">White</name> (see the sketch of <name type="person" key="Robertson, John">Robertson</name>).<ref target="n05" n="5"/>
            </p>
            <p>
	Most of the returning Frenchmen were certainly <hi rend="italic">engagés—</hi>hired boatmen—who had been with the expedition from the start. It is quite clear from the records that the captains regarded their status to be entirely different from that of the enlisted men. They were not soldiers and did not require the same care in record keeping as that demanded by the army. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> usual difficulties in spelling were compounded with French names, and <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> spelling of French names was not much better.</p>
            <p>
Another factor complicating the records was the custom of the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name> valley French of giving <hi rend="italic">dit</hi> names, nicknames by which a man might be better known than by his surname. Unlike English nicknames, these might be passed on from father to son and were considered significant enough to be used in official records. Commonly they referred either to a personal characteristic or to a place of origin or residence. Thus we have Louis Blanchette, <hi rend="italic">dit le Chasseur</hi> (the hunter), founder of <name type="place" key="Saint Charles, Mo.">St. Charles</name>, <name type="place" key="Missouri">Missouri</name>, and Jacques Chauvin, <hi rend="italic">dit Charlesville,</hi> probably after the city in <name type="place" key="France">France</name>. Hence, French names in expedition records may be either surnames or <hi rend="italic">dit</hi> names, and this may account for some of the inconsistencies in the lists.<ref target="n06" n="6"/>
            </p>
            <p>
There are two principal lists of <hi rend="italic">engagés,</hi> which were evidently intended to be complete, one in a detachment order of <ref n="1804-05-26" type="related">May 26, 1804</ref>, the other in <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> Field Notes under <ref n="1804-07-04" type="related">July 4, 1804</ref>. They are inconsistent in both names and numbers, and there is no certainty whether the inconsistencies represent additions or discharges, use of surnames or <hi rend="italic">dit</hi> names, or simple forgetfulness. There is also a record of men paid off in <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> after their return from <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name> in 1805, but it is obviously incomplete. Some of the men may not appear there because they were discharged at the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> or <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> villages in the fall of 1804 and received their pay in cash. It is at least possible that men were added or discharged along the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, recruited from <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>–bound trading parties or leaving the expedition and joining such a party. The captains' lack of attention to the Frenchmen may have extended to failure to note such changes among the <hi rend="italic">engagés.</hi>
               <ref target="n07" n="7"/>
            </p>
            <p>
The purpose of this appendix is to give brief sketches of those known to be associated with the expedition up to August 24, 1804. Individuals are listed alphabetically within groups: the leaders; sergeants; privates, corporal, interpreter, and servant; and <hi rend="italic">engagés.</hi> Sketches of <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name>, <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Toussaint Charbonneau</name>, <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Jean Baptiste">Jean Baptiste Charbonneau</name>, and <name type="person" key="Lepage, Jean Baptiste">Jean Baptiste Lepage</name>, all of whom joined during the winter of 1804–5 at <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name>, will appear in the next volume. For the two captains only a brief biography is necessary. For most of the others it is possible to include most of the principal facts, with an indication of the sources for further study. In most cases there is no new, previously unpublished information, but an effort has been made to draw together the work of previous researchers in the field. In a few cases, doubts and unresolved questions about some men, such as <name type="person" key="Robertson, John">John Robertson</name> and <name type="person" key="La Liberté">La Liberté</name>, have necessitated disproportionately long sketches of men whose actual importance to the expedition was minor.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Meriwether Lewis</name> (1774–1809). Born in <name type="place" key="Virginia">Virginia</name>, he joined the army in 1794 and served in the <name type="place" key="Ohio River">Ohio</name> Valley and the Old Northwest Territory, where he became friends with <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>. He became <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name> private secretary in 1801, while retaining his military rank, and in 1803 the president assigned him the task of conducting the expedition. After the expedition he became governor of <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name> Territory, where he encountered difficulties that caused him severe emotional problems. He died by his own hand on the <name type="place" key="Natchez Trace">Natchez Trace</name> in <name type="place" key="Tennessee">Tennessee</name>. Dillon; Bakeless (LCPD).</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Second Lieutenant William Clark</name> (1770–1838). The younger brother of <name type="person" key="Clark, George Rogers">George Rogers Clark</name>, he moved from <name type="place" key="Virginia">Virginia</name>, where he was born, to <name type="place" key="Kentucky">Kentucky</name> with his family at the age of fourteen. Joining the army in 1792, he participated in the campaigns of <name type="person" key="Wayne, Anthony">General Anthony Wayne</name> in the Northwest, rising to the rank of captain; <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> was under his command for a time. He left the army in 1796 to attend to family business, but he kept in touch with <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and was apparently the other's first choice to share command of the expedition. Because of army red tape, he received only a second lieutenant's rank, but he and <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> concealed this from the men, and he was always referred to as <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain Clark</name>. After the expedition he had a distinguished political career, including the governorship of <name type="place" key="Missouri">Missouri</name> Territory, but for much of the time until his death he was in charge of relations with the Indians west of the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name>, with his headquarters in <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>. The Indians knew that city simply as "Red Head's Town," after him, and he strove to maintain some degree of justice and equity in the relations between Indian and white. Loos; Bakeless (LCPD); Steffen.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Floyd, Charles">Sergeant Charles Floyd</name> (1782–1804). Born in <name type="place" key="Kentucky">Kentucky</name>, he was one of the nine young men from that state on the expedition. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> regarded him as "a young man of much merit," and he was made a sergeant before the start of the expedition. He is remembered principally as the only member lost on the voyage; he died on August 20, 1804, near present <name type="place" key="Sioux City, Iowa">Sioux City</name>, <name type="place" key="Iowa">Iowa</name>, perhaps of a ruptured appendix. He kept his journal until a few days before his death. He may have been a distant relative of <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark</name>. <name type="place" key="Floyd River">Floyd's (or Floyd) River</name> in <name type="place" key="Iowa">Iowa</name> was named for him. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> to <name type="person" key="Dearborn, Henry">Henry Dearborn</name>, January 15, 1807, Jackson (LLC), 1:366, 370 n. 3; Clarke (MLCE), 39; Garver.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Sergeant Patrick Gass</name> (1771–1870). Born in <name type="place" key="Pennsylvania">Pennsylvania</name>, of Irish ancestry, he belonged to <name type="person" key="Bissell, Russell">Captain Russell Bissell's</name> company of the First Infantry, having joined the army in 1799 after service in a volunteer Ranger unit. He was promoted from private to sergeant after <name type="person" key="Floyd, Charles">Floyd's</name> death in August of 1804, having officially joined the expedition on January 1, 1804. His skill as a carpenter was of great value to the expedition. His journal, published in 1807 after considerable alteration, was the first journal from the expedition to see publication. He stayed on in the army and served in the War of 1812, losing an eye in an accident, which caused his discharge. Marrying at the age of sixty, he eventually settled in <name type="place" key="Wellsburg, W. Va.">Wellsburg</name>, <name type="place" key="West Virginia">West Virginia</name>, and died there in 1870, the last known survivor of the expedition. Clarke (MLCE), 39–40; Jacob; Forrest, Smith (SSPG); McGirr.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Sergeant John Ordway</name> (ca. 1775–ca. 1817). One of the journalists of the expedition, he was born and apparently grew up in <name type="place" key="New Hampshire">New Hampshire</name>. He joined from <name type="person" key="Bissell, Russell">Captain Russell Bissell's</name> company of the First Infantry and was placed on the expedition roll on January 1, 1804, but he was already at <name type="place" key="Camp Dubois (Camp Wood, River Dubois) (Ill.)">Camp Dubois</name> some time before that. He was the only one of the original sergeants to come from the regular army, and probably for that reason he often took care of the paperwork and was in charge of the camp when the captains were both absent. <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> kept his journal faithfully throughout the expedition. He seldom appears in the journals except in carrying out some duty, attesting to his reliability. After the expedition he accompanied <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and a party of Indians to <name type="person" key="Washington D.C.">Washington, D.C.</name>, then returned to <name type="place" key="New Hampshire">New Hampshire</name>, having taken his discharge. In 1809 he settled in <name type="place" key="Missouri">Missouri</name>, became prosperous, and married. He and his wife had died by 1817. Clarke (MLCE), 40–41.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Sergeant Nathaniel Hale Pryor</name> (1772–1831). He was born in <name type="place" key="Virginia">Virginia</name> and was a cousin of <name type="person" key="Floyd, Charles">Charles Floyd</name>, also with the expedition. He moved to <name type="place" key="Kentucky">Kentucky</name> with his parents in 1783 and joined the expedition on October 20, 1803, at <name type="place" key="Clarksville, Ind.">Clarksville</name>, <name type="place" key="Indiana">Indiana</name>, as one of the nine young men from <name type="place" key="Kentucky">Kentucky</name>. He was one of the few members already married, having taken a wife in 1798. He may have kept a journal, like the other sergeants, but none has been found. The captains considered him "a man of character and ability" and after the expedition helped him secure an officer's commission in the army. In 1807 he was in charge of the expedition to return the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> chief <name type="person" key="Big White (Sheheke)">Sheheke</name> to his tribe, but he was forced to turn back by the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name>. He resigned from the army in 1810 and entered the Indian trade on the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name>; he rejoined the army in 1813 and rose to captain, serving in the Battle of <name type="place" key="New Orleans, La.">New Orleans</name>. After the War of 1812 he became a trader among the <name type="native_nation" key="Osage Indians">Osages</name> on the <name type="place" key="Arkansas River">Arkansas River</name>, married an <name type="native_nation" key="Osage Indians">Osage</name> woman, and remained with the tribe until his death. He served briefly as government agent for the <name type="native_nation" key="Osage Indians">Osages</name> in 1830–31. <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Pryor</name>, <name type="place" key="Oklahoma">Oklahoma</name>, and the <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Pryor</name> Mountains and town of <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Pryor</name>, both in <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>, bear his name. Clarke (MLCE), 41–42; Settle.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Boley, John">Private John Boley</name> (dates unknown). <name type="person" key="Boley, John">Boley</name>, sometimes "<name type="person" key="Boley, John">Boleye</name>" in the records, was probably born in <name type="place" key="Pittsburgh, Pa.">Pittsburgh</name>, <name type="place" key="Pennsylvania">Pennsylvania</name>, and was living in <name type="place" key="Kaskaskia, Ill.">Kaskaskia</name> when he joined the army in 1803. He came from <name type="person" key="Bissell, Russell">Captain Russell Bissell's</name> company of the First Infantry Regiment. He had some disciplinary trouble at <name type="place" key="Dubois River">River Dubois</name> and was designated for the return party. After returning from <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name> in 1805 he accompanied <name type="person" key="Pike, Zebulon Montgomery">Zebulon M. Pike's</name> expedition to the upper <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name> in that year, and in 1806 he went with <name type="person" key="Pike, Zebulon Montgomery">Pike</name> to the southwest and the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rockies</name>. Part of that group, including <name type="person" key="Boley, John">Boley</name>, returned east down the <name type="place" key="Arkansas River">Arkansas River</name> before <name type="person" key="Pike, Zebulon Montgomery">Pike</name> and the rest were captured by the Spanish. After his discharge he settled in <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> and reportedly accompanied a civilian party to the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rockies</name>. In 1823, he and his wife were living in <name type="place" key="Carondelet, Mo.">Carondelet</name>, near <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>. Jackson (LLC), 1:237 n. 7; Clarke (MLCE), 60.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Bratton, William E.">Private William E. Bratton</name> (1778–1841). Often "<name type="person" key="Bratton, William E.">Bratten</name>" in the journals, he was born in <name type="place" key="Virginia">Virginia</name> and moved to <name type="place" key="Kentucky">Kentucky</name> with his family in about 1790. He enlisted with the expedition on October 20, 1803, as one of the nine young men from <name type="place" key="Kentucky">Kentucky</name>. <name type="person" key="Bratton, William E.">Bratton</name> was useful to the expedition as a hunter and blacksmith. During the spring of 1806 he was incapacitated for some weeks by a mysterious back ailment, perhaps the longest spell of serious illness experienced by any member of the expedition, finally being cured by an Indian sweat bath. After the expedition he lived in <name type="place" key="Kentucky">Kentucky</name> and <name type="place" key="Missouri">Missouri</name>, served in the War of 1812, married in 1819, and lived in <name type="place" key="Ohio">Ohio</name> and <name type="place" key="Indiana">Indiana</name>. He died and was buried at <name type="place" key="Waynetown, Ind.">Waynetown</name>, <name type="place" key="Indiana">Indiana</name>. Clarke (MLCE), 43–45; Chuinard, 348–76; Lange (WB).</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Collins, John">Private John Collins</name> (?–1823). Born in <name type="place" key="Maryland">Maryland</name>, <name type="person" key="Collins, John">Collins</name> officially joined the expedition on January 1, 1804, although he was probably at the <name type="place" key="Dubois River">River Dubois</name> camp before that; he may have transferred from <name type="person" key="Bissell, Russell">Captain Russell Bissell's</name> company of the First Infantry. <name type="person" key="Collins, John">Collins</name> was involved in disciplinary troubles as often as any other man in the expedition, leading <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> to call him a "black gard"; at <name type="place" key="Dubois River">River Dubois</name> he stole a local farmer's hog and was frequently drunk and disobedient. On the first summer of the voyage he was court-martialed for stealing whiskey from the official supply while detailed to guard it. Nonetheless, he was from the first a member of the permanent party, presumably because of redeeming qualities perceived by the captains. He may have settled in <name type="place" key="Missouri">Missouri</name> after the expedition. Later he was with <name type="person" key="Ashley, William">William Ashley's</name> trapping venture to the upper <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> and was killed in <name type="person" key="Ashley, William">Ashley's</name> battle with the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> in 1823. Clarke (MLCE), 45.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Private John Colter</name> (ca. 1775–1813). <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name>, probably the only member of the Corps whose fame does not rest primarily on his service with the expedition, was born in <name type="place" key="Virginia">Virginia</name>. As a youth, he and his family moved to <name type="place" key="Maysville, Ky.">Maysville</name>, <name type="place" key="Kentucky">Kentucky</name>, where he intercepted <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> on the captain's voyage down <name type="place" key="Ohio River">the Ohio</name>, becoming one of the nine young men from <name type="place" key="Kentucky">Kentucky</name>. His enlistment dates from October 15, 1803. After some disciplinary difficulties during the winter at <name type="place" key="Dubois River">River Dubois</name>, he proved useful to the expedition as a hunter. On the return journey he received permission to leave the party at the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> villages to join a small trapping expedition headed back up the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>. He spent an additional four years in the mountains as an independent trapper and working for <name type="person" key="Lisa, Manuel">Manuel Lisa's</name> Missouri Fur Company. In his wanderings he was apparently the first white man to see the region of present <name type="place" key="Yellowstone National Park">Yellowstone Park</name>, and his tales of hot springs and geysers led to derisive jokes about "<name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter's</name> Hell." His escape, naked, from the <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name> near the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Three Forks of the">Three Forks of the Missouri</name> has become a western legend. On his return to civilization in 1810 he was able to add information to <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> great map of the West. Settling in <name type="place" key="Missouri">Missouri</name>, <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name> married; he died in 1813 of jaundice. Clarke (MLCE), 46–48; Haines; Vinton; Harris.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Private Pierre Cruzatte</name> (dates unknown). Often referred to as "<name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Peter Cruzat</name>" and other variations in the journals, he was half French and half <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Omaha</name>. His official enlistment date was May 16, 1804, at <name type="place" key="Saint Charles, Mo.">St. Charles</name>, <name type="place" key="Missouri">Missouri</name>, but he may have been recruited earlier. He was an experienced <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri River</name> boatman who had already participated in the Indian trade as far as <name type="place" key="Nebraska">Nebraska</name> and was hired for his skill and experience. Unlike the other French boatmen, he and <name type="person" key="Labiche, François">Fran<seg n="u231">ç</seg>ois Labiche</name> were enlisted as members of the permanent party. He was one-eyed and nearsighted, and his fiddle playing often entertained the party. At times he also acted as an interpreter. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> paid tribute during the expedition to his skill and experince as a riverman and to his integrity, but in the postexpedition list of members he receives no special recommendation; this is perhaps because the myopic <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Cruzatte</name> had accidentally wounded <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> while the two were hunting in August 1806. Speculation places him with <name type="person" key="McClallen, John">John McClellan's</name> expedition to the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rockies</name> in 1807. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> lists him as "killed" by 1825–28. Clarke (MCLE), 62–63; Jackson (LLC) 1:371 n. 8; <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> List of Expedition Members [ca. 1825–28], ibid., 2:638; Majors 573.
</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Dame, John">Private John Dame</name> (1784–?). <name type="person" key="Dame, John">Dame</name>, born in <name type="place" key="New Hampshire">New Hampshire</name>, joined the army in 1801; he was assigned to the expedition from <name type="person" key="Stoddard, Amos">Captain Amos Stoddard's</name> artillery company and designated for the return party. He is mentioned once in the journals, August 8, 1804, for killing a pelican. Jackson (LLC), 1:237 n. 7; Clarke (MLCE), 60.</p>
            <p>
Interpreter <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">George Drouillard</name> (?–1810). Generally "<name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name>" or some variant in the journals, he was probably born in <name type="place" key="Canada">Canada</name>, the son of a French-Canadian father and a <name type="native_nation" key="Shawnee Indians">Shawnee</name> mother, and migrated as a youth to the <name type="place" key="Cape Girardeau, Mo.">Cape Girardeau</name> district of <name type="place" key="Missouri">Missouri</name> with his mother's people. He met <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> at <name type="place" key="Fort Massac (Ill.)">Fort Massac</name>, <name type="place" key="Illinois">Illinois</name>, in November 1803, possibly while employed by the army there, and agreed to serve the expedition as an interpreter. He was apparently considered a civilian employee, not an enlisted man, during the expedition. His skill with the Indian sign language was of great value to the captains, and he was also one of the Corps's best hunters; whenever one of the captains set out to scout ahead of the party, <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name> was likely to be chosen to accompany him, because of those abilities and his general skill as a scout and wilderness man. After the expedition's return he became a partner in <name type="person" key="Lisa, Manuel">Manuel Lisa's</name> fur trading ventures on the upper <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> and the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone</name>. On a return trip to <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> he was able to contribute information to <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> map of the West. <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name> was with the party of <name type="person" key="Lisa, Manuel">Lisa's</name> men who established a fur post at the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Three Forks of the">Three Forks of the Missouri</name> in 1810, and near there in that year he died at the hands of the <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name>. Clarke (MLCE), 40; Skarsten (GD) and (GDLC); <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> to <name type="person" key="Dearborn, Henry">Henry Dearborn</name>, January 15, 1807, Jackson (LLC), 1:368–69; Lange (GD).</p>
            <p>
* Privates <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Joseph Field</name> (ca. 1772–1807) and <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">Reubin Field</name> (ca. 1771–1823?). The two brothers, called "Field" or "Fields" at various times in the journals, were born in <name type="place" key="Virginia">Virginia</name> and came to <name type="place" key="Kentucky">Kentucky</name> at an early age; they were among the nine young men from <name type="place" key="Kentucky">Kentucky</name>, and their official enlistment date was August 1, 1803, indicating that they were among the first men recruited by <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> in the neighborhood of his home. <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">Reubin</name> had some disciplinary difficulties at <name type="place" key="Dubois River">River Dubois</name>, but both were chosen for the permanent party. They were among the best shots and hunters in the Corps of Discovery and with <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">George Drouillard</name> were often chosen to accompany the captains on special reconnaissances; both were with <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> in his fight with the <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name> on July 27, 1806. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> wrote, "It was their peculiar fate to have been engaged in all the most dangerous and difficult scenes of the voyage, in which they uniformly acquited themselves with much honor." <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Joseph</name> apparently died less than a year after the return of the expedition; <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> listed him as "killed," as distinguished from those who died a natural death. One theory suggests that he was with the mysterious expedition of <name type="person" key="McClallen, John">John McClellan</name> to the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rockies</name> when his death occurred, but in that case it hardly seems that word of his death could have reached <name type="place" key="Kentucky">Kentucky</name> by October 1807, when it was officially recorded. <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">Reubin</name> settled in <name type="place" key="Kentucky">Kentucky</name>, married, and died by early 1823. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> to <name type="person" key="Dearborn, Henry">Henry Dearborn</name>, January 15, 1807, Jackson (LLC), 1:367; <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> List of Expedition Members [ca. 1825–28], ibid, 2:638; Clarke (MLCE), 48–49; Appleman (JRF); Majors, 573; Lange (EB).</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">Private Robert Frazer</name> (?–1837). "<name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">Frazer</name>" is the accepted form of his name, but in the journals he is often "<name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">Frazier</name>," "<name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">Frasure</name>," and other forms that probably indicate how his comrades pronounced his name. Accounts saying that he was born in <name type="place" key="Vermont">Vermont</name> and was once a fencing master are apparently in error; he was probably born in <name type="place" key="Virginia">Virginia</name>. There is no information on when he joined or if he had previously been in the army. <name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">Frazer</name> was not at first part of the permanent party but was transferred from the intended return party on October 8, 1804, to replace <name type="person" key="Reed, Moses B.">Moses Reed</name> after the latter's expulsion. <name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">Frazer</name> kept a journal and received special permission from the captains to publish it, but the publication never took place and the journal is apparently lost. His map of the expedition, far below the standard set by <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, has survived (<hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 124). He accompanied <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> to <name type="place" key="Washington D.C.">Washington, D.C.</name>, after the expedition, then returned to <name type="place" key="Missouri">Missouri</name> and settled there. He died in <name type="place" key="Franklin County, Mo.">Franklin County</name>, <name type="place" key="Missouri">Missouri</name>. Clarke (MLCE), 61; Cutright (HLCJ), 20 and n. 4.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Gibson, George">Private George Gibson</name> (?–1809). Born in <name type="place" key="Pennsylvania">Pennsylvania</name>, he was one of the nine young men from <name type="place" key="Kentucky">Kentucky</name>. He was a good hunter and played the fiddle for the party on occasion. He served as an interpreter, probably through the medium of sign language. He may have been with <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Nathaniel Pryor's</name> party attempting to return the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> chief <name type="person" key="Big White (Sheheke)">Sheheke</name> to his home in 1807 and was perhaps wounded then. He died in <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>. Clarke (MLCE), 49.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Goodrich, Silas">Private Silas Goodrich</name> (dates unknown). <name type="person" key="Goodrich, Silas">Goodrich</name>, sometimes "<name type="person" key="Goodrich, Silas">Guterage</name>" or some variation in the journals, was born in <name type="place" key="Massachusetts">Massachusetts</name>. The time and place of his joining the Corps are unknown, although he was officially enrolled in January 1, 1804; possible he was then a resident of <name type="place" key="Missouri">Missouri</name>, and he may already have been in the army. He was one of the expedition's best fishermen. He reenlisted in the army after the expedition. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> lists him as dead by 1825–28. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> List of Expedition Members [ca. 1825–28], Jackson (LLC), 2:638; Clarke (MLCE), 50.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Hall, Hugh">Private Hugh Hall</name> (ca. 1772–?). <name type="person" key="Hall, Hugh">Hall</name> was born in <name type="place" key="Massachusetts">Massachusetts</name>, joined the army in 1798, and was transferred to the expedition from <name type="person" key="Campbell, John">Captain John Campbell's</name> company of the Second Infantry Regiment in November 1803. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> notes that he drank. He and <name type="person" key="Collins, John">John Collins</name> were court-martialed in June 1804 for tapping the official ration whiskey and getting drunk, <name type="person" key="Collins, John">Collins</name> having been detailed to guard the supply. <name type="person" key="Hall, Hugh">Hall</name> was in the <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> area in 1809, when he borrowed money from <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>; <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> apparently had no information to record about him in 1825–28. Jackson (LLC), 1:371 n. 15; <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> List of Expedition Members [ca. 1825–28], ibid., 2:638; Clarke (MLCE), 50.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Howard, Thomas P.">Private Thomas Proctor Howard</name> (1779–?). <name type="person" key="Howard, Thomas P.">Howard</name> was born and reared in <name type="place" key="Massachusetts">Massachusetts</name> and joined the army in 1801; he was assigned to the expedition from <name type="person" key="Campbell, John">Captain John Campbell's</name> company of the Second Infantry Regiment, officially enrolling on January 1, 1804. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> noted at <name type="place" key="Dubois River">River Dubois</name> that <name type="person" key="Howard, Thomas P.">Howard</name> "never Drinks water." On February 9, 1805, returning to <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name> from the Indian villages after the gate was closed, he climbed over the wall. The next day he was tried for setting a "pernicious example" to the Indians by showing them that the wall was easily scaled. The sentence was fifty lashes, remitted on the recommendation of the court. This was the last recorded court-martial of the expedition. A <name type="person" key="Howard, Thomas P.">Thomas Howard</name> was again serving in the army in 1808. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had no information to record on him in 1825–28. Jackson (LLC), 1:371 n. 14; <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> List of Expedition Members [ca. 1825–28], ibid., 2:638; Clarke (MLCE), 50.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Labiche, François">Private Fran<seg n="u231">ç</seg>ois Labiche</name> (dates unknown). He is referred to as "<name type="person" key="Labiche, François">La Buish</name>," "<name type="person" key="Labiche, François">Leebice</name>," and other spellings in the journals. Though traditionally regarded as half French and half <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Omaha</name>, he may be the "mulatto" mentioned by <name type="person" key="McKenzie, Charles">Charles McKenzie</name> as interpreting French for the captains at <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name>. (The only other possible mulatto would have been <name type="person" key="York">York</name>, who surely spoke no French). <name type="person" key="Labiche, François">Labiche</name> was apparently recruited at <name type="person" key="Kaskaskia, Ill.">Kaskaskia</name>, though the official date of his enlistment is May 16, 1804, at <name type="place" key="Saint Charles, Mo.">St. Charles</name>, <name type="place" key="Missouri">Missouri</name>. Like <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Cruzatte</name> he was an enlisted member of the permanent party, not a hired boatman, undoubtedly chosen for his experience as a boatman and Indian trader. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> took special note of his services as an interpreter, recommending that he receive a bonus; he went with <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> to <name type="place" key="Washington D.C.">Washington, D.C.</name>, after the expedition to interpret for the Indian chiefs. He may be the <name type="person" key="Labiche, François">Fran<seg n="u231">ç</seg>ois Labuche</name> who lived in or near <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> and baptized seven children there between 1811 and 1834. It is possible that "<name type="person" key="Labiche, François">Labiche</name>" may have been a nickname, the family name being Milhomme. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> listed him as living in <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> in 1825–28. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> to <name type="person" key="Dearborn, Henry">Henry Dearborn</name>, January 15, 1807, Jackson (LLC), 1:367, 371 n. 16; <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> List of Expedition Members [ca. 1825–28], ibid., 2:638; Masson, 1:336–37; Clarke (MLCE), 64.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="McNeal, Hugh">Private Hugh McNeal</name> (dates unknown). He was born and reared in <name type="place" key="Pennsylvania">Pennsylvania</name> and may have been in the army before joining the expedition. A man of that name was on the army rolls as late in 1811. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> lists him a dead by 1825–28. Jackson (LLC), 1:371 n. 17; <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> List of Expedition Members [ca. 1825–28], ibid., 2:639.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Newman, John">Private John Newman</name> (ca. 1785–1838). <name type="person" key="Newman, John">Newman</name> was born in <name type="place" key="Pennsylvania">Pennsylvania</name> and joined the expedition from <name type="person" key="Bissell, Daniel">Captain Daniel Bissell's</name> company of the First Infantry Regiment. He avoided the disciplinary troubles of some of the others at <name type="place" key="Dubois River">River Dubois</name>, and his record was apparently good until October 1804, when he was confined for "having uttered repeated expressions of a highly criminal and mutinous nature." Tried by court-martial, he received seventy-five lashes and was expelled from the party. His offense may have consisted of angry, defiant words uttered in a moment of bad temper, or he may have been involved in something more serious in collusion with <name type="person" key="Reed, Moses B.">Moses Reed</name>. Since he could not be abandoned in the wilderness, he accompanied the party to <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name>, doing hard labor, then went back with the return party in April 1805. During the intervening months he worked hard to redeem himself, in the hope of being restored to the permanent party, but although the captains were pleased with his conduct, they did not deem it wise to alter their verdict. After the expedition <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> suggested that Congress allow <name type="person" key="Newman, John">Newman</name> the pay for his period of service up to his expulsion. He did receive some pay and a land warrant as a member of the expedition, and he may have settled in <name type="place" key="Missouri">Missouri</name>. He married at least once but had no children of record. In the 1830s he trapped on the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> in the Dakotas for some years and was killed by the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Yankton">Yankton</name>
               <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name> in the summer of 1838. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> included him in his list of 1825–28, indicating some interest in <name type="person" key="Newman, John">Newman's</name> welfare, although he had no information to record. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> to <name type="person" key="Dearborn, Henry">Henry Dearborn</name>, January 15, 1807, Jackson (LLC), 1:365–66, 372 endnote; <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> List of Expedition Members [ca. 1825–28], ibid., 2:639; Clarke (JN); Clarke (MLCE), 51.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Potts, John">Private John Potts</name> (1776–1808?). <name type="person" key="Potts, John">Potts</name> was born in <name type="place" key="Germany">Germany</name> and had been a miller; he joined the U. S. Army in 1800. He was with <name type="person" key="Purdy, Robert">Captain Robert Purdy's</name> company in <name type="place" key="Tennessee">Tennessee</name> when ordered to join the expedition in November 1803. In 1807 he joined <name type="person" key="Lisa, Manuel">Manuel Lisa's</name> fur-trading venture to the upper <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>. He was with his old comrade <name type="person" key="Colter, John">John Colter</name> when the two were ambushed by <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name> near the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Three Forks of the">Three Forks of the Missouri</name>; <name type="person" key="Potts, John">Potts</name> was killed and <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name> narrowly escaped. Jackson (LLC), 1:371 n. 20; Clarke (MLCE), 51; Harris, 133–34.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Reed, Moses B.">Private Moses B. Reed</name> (dates unknown). <name type="person" key="Reed, Moses B.">Reed's</name> antecedents and the point at which he joined the expedition are unknown. He was a member of the permanent party as it was originally constituted, but in August 1804 he attempted to desert; apprehended, he was tried, convicted, and expelled from the party. He remained with the expedition doing hard labor until sent back with the return party in April 1805. <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> records that <name type="person" key="Reed, Moses B.">Reed</name> was confined on October 12, 1804, at the same time that <name type="person" key="Newman, John">John Newman</name> was arrested for "mutinous expression." This is the only indication that <name type="person" key="Reed, Moses B.">Reed</name> may have been involved in <name type="person" key="Newman, John">Newman's</name> offense, but if so, then <name type="person" key="Newman, John">Newman</name> may have been guilty of something more than a fit of bad-tempered insubordination. Conceivably the two were in collusion to defy the captains' authority in some way, or perhaps <name type="person" key="Reed, Moses B.">Reed</name> tried to induce some other men to support <name type="person" key="Newman, John">Newman's</name> defiance. There is no other record of <name type="person" key="Reed, Moses B.">Reed's</name> confinement at this time or of his being punished; since he had been dishonorably discharged, the captains may have doubted their legal authority to punish him. After his return to <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>, he dropped out of sight. When <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> made up his list of party members in 1825–28, he included <name type="person" key="Newman, John">Newman</name> but not <name type="person" key="Reed, Moses B.">Reed</name>, evidence of his total lack of interest in the latter's fate. Clarke (MLCE), 52; <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> List of Expedition Members [ca. 1825–28], Jackson (LLC), 2:638–39.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Robertson, John">Private John Robertson</name> (ca. 1780–?). Also "<name type="person" key="Robertson, John">Roberson</name>" in the journals, he is thought to be the <name type="person" key="Robertson, John">Corporal John Robinson</name>, born in <name type="place" key="New Hampshire">New Hampshire</name>, who was serving with <name type="person" key="Stoddard, Amos">Captain Amos Stoddard's</name> artillery company at the time of the expedition. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> refers to him as a corporal on December 26, 1803, but in subsequent references where rank is given he is a private; apparently he was demoted for some reason. Perhaps he was the unnamed corporal <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> criticized on January 4, 1804, for having "no authority" over his men; this is even more likely because the captains were so completely satisfied with <name type="person" key="Warfington, Richard">Corporal Richard Warfington</name>, the only other corporal with the expedition. <name type="person" key="Robertson, John">Robertson</name> had some difficulties involving drinking during the <name type="place" key="Dubois River">River Dubois</name> winter. In an undated list in <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> Field Notes (placed under April 12, 1804) he is designated for the return party. The last dated mention of his name is in the Orderly Book for April 1, 1804, where he is also designated as one of those to return from somewhere up the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>. There is no subsequent dated reference to his name, and he is not in the detachment order of May 26, 1804, concerning the organization of squads. On June 12, 1804, <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Joseph Whitehouse</name> wrote that a man from <name type="person" key="Stoddard, Amos">Captain Stoddard's</name> company was sent back to <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> with a trading party encountered coming down the river; no one else bothered to record the incident, and <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse</name> gives no name and no reason for his return. If <name type="person" key="Robertson, John">Robertson</name> was with the expedition until June 12, it is peculiar that he is not mentioned in the May 26 detachment order. If he was not the man from <name type="person" key="Stoddard, Amos">Stoddard's</name> company sent back, then there are only two men known to have been from this company who are not mentioned in the journals after June 12, and if one of them was sent back, and <name type="person" key="Robertson, John">Robertson</name> had left some time earlier, then there exist problems in accounting for the six soldiers who were with the return party from <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name> under <name type="person" key="Warfington, Richard">Corporal Warfington</name> in 1805. No reason is anywhere indicated why <name type="person" key="Robertson, John">Robertson</name> would be taken along yet not included in the detachment order of May 26. A purely speculative possibility may be mentioned. The detachment order of May 26 specifically exempts <name type="person" key="Howard, Thomas P.">Thomas P. Howard</name> from duty with the pirogues without giving any reason, such as a special assignment. It could be that <name type="person" key="Howard, Thomas P.">Howard</name>, designated for the permanent party, was temporarily incapacitated by some illness or injury but was expected to recover in a short time. <name type="person" key="Robertson, John">Robertson</name> might then have been taken along to replace <name type="person" key="Howard, Thomas P.">Howard</name>, the preferred man, if the latter did not recover as quickly as anticipated. However having improved as hoped, the less desirable <name type="person" key="Robertson, John">Robertson</name> was sent home. Difficulties with this hypothesis are that no such illness of <name type="person" key="Howard, Thomas P.">Howard's</name> is mentioned, and the party with which the unnamed man returned was not the first one met coming down the river. Presumably <name type="person" key="Robertson, John">Robertson</name> returned to his original unit, but there is no further record of him. Clarke (MLCE), 61–62; Jackson (LLC), 1:373 endnote.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Private George Shannon</name> (1785–1836). The youngest member of the party, <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name> was born in <name type="place" key="Pennsylvania">Pennsylvania</name> and moved to <name type="place" key="Ohio">Ohio</name> with his family in 1800. He joined <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> at <name type="place" key="Maysville, Ky.">Maysville</name>, <name type="place" key="Kentucky">Kentucky</name>, with an official enlistment date of October 19, 1803, and is usually listed with the nine young men from <name type="place" key="Kentucky">Kentucky</name>. In the fall of 1804 he as lost for over two weeks and nearly starved; some sources state that he was continually getting lost, which is unjust, since the only other time he was separated from the party for a few days, on the headwaters of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> in 1805, was hardly his fault. In 1807 he was with <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Nathaniel Pryor's</name> party in the attempt to return the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> chief <name type="person" key="Big White (Sheheke)">Sheheke</name> to his people and was wounded in the encounter with the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name>; the wound cost him his leg. Eventually he received a government pension for his injury. In 1810 he assisted <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Nicholas Biddle</name> in the preparation of his history of the expedition. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> offered him an opportunity to join him in the fur trade, but <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name> chose to study law, and by 1818, after university training, he was practicing in <name type="place" key="Lexington, Ky.">Lexington</name>, <name type="place" key="Kentucky">Kentucky</name>. He pursued the legal and political career common on the frontier in his day, eventually serving as senator from <name type="place" key="Missouri">Missouri</name>. He died and was buried in <name type="place" key="Palmyra, Mo.">Palmyra</name>, <name type="place" key="Missouri">Missouri</name>. Clarke (MLCE), 52–53; Lange (PGS).</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Shields, John">Private John Shields</name> (1769–1809). Born in <name type="place" key="Virginia">Virginia</name>, <name type="person" key="Shields, John">Shields</name> emigrated with his family to <name type="place" key="Tennessee">Tennessee</name> in 1784; in 1790 he married and was thus one of the few married men with the expedition. He enlisted on October 19, 1803, and is usually listed as one of the nine young men from <name type="place" key="Kentucky">Kentucky</name>; in fact, he was the oldest member of the permanent party whose age is known, with the exception of <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Toussaint Charbonneau</name>. <name type="person" key="Shields, John">Shields</name> was involved in a virtual mutiny against <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Sergeant Ordway's</name> authority at <name type="place" key="Dubois River">River Dubois</name>, greatly disappointing the captains, who evidently expected him as the oldest to display a greater sense of responsibility. During the expedition, however, his skills as a blacksmith, gunsmith, and carpenter were invaluable. "Nothing was more peculiarly useful to us, in various situations," wrote <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, "than the skill and ingenuity of this man as an artist, in repairing our guns, accoutrements, &amp;c." <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> recommended that Congress give <name type="person" key="Shields, John">Shields</name> a bonus for his services. After the expedition <name type="person" key="Shields, John">Shields</name> trapped in <name type="place" key="Missouri">Missouri</name> for a time with <name type="person" key="Boone, Daniel">Daniel Boone</name>, a kinsman, then settled in <name type="place" key="Indiana">Indiana</name>, where he died and was buried. Clarke (MLCE), 53–54; <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> to <name type="person" key="Dearborn, Henry">Henry Dearborn</name>, January 15, 1807, Jackson (LLC), 1:367; Lange (JS).</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Thompson, John B.">Private John B. Thompson</name> (dates unknown). His place of birth and date of joining the expedition are unknown, but he may have lived in <name type="place" key="Indiana">Indiana</name>. He seems to have had some experience as a surveyor. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> refers to him during the expedition as "a valuable member of our party." His postexpedition career is equally obscure; <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> listed him in 1825–28 as "killed." Speculation places him with <name type="person" key="McClallen, John">John McClellan's</name> expedition in the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rockies</name> in 1807. Clarke (MLCE), 354; Majors, 573; <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> List of Expedition Members [ca. 1825–28], Jackson (LLC), 2:639.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Tuttle, Ebenezer">Private Ebenezer Tuttle</name> (1773–?). <name type="person" key="Tuttle, Ebenezer">Tuttle</name> was born in <name type="place" key="Connecticut">Connecticut</name> and joined the army in 1803. He was a member of <name type="person" key="Stoddard, Amos">Captain Amos Stoddard's</name> artillery company. The only mention of him in the journals is in a detachment order of May 26, 1804. Possibly he was the unnamed man from <name type="person" key="Stoddard, Amos">Stoddard's</name> company sent back on June 12, 1804; otherwise he was with the return party from <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name> in 1805, as originally planned. Jackson (LLC), 1:237 n. 7; Clarke (MLCE), 62.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Warfington, Richard">Corporal Richard Warfington</name> (1777–?). In the journals his name appears as "<name type="person" key="Warfington, Richard">Warpenton</name>," "<name type="person" key="Warfington, Richard">Worthington</name>," "<name type="person" key="Warfington, Richard">Wortheyton</name>," and other versions. He was born in <name type="place" key="North Dakota">North Carolina</name>, joined the army in 1799, and was transferred to the Corps of Discovery from <name type="person" key="Campbell, John">Captain John Campbell's</name> company of the Second Infantry Regiment on November 24, 1803, holding the rank of corporal. The captains apparently found him reliable and efficient and decided to put him in charge of the party they intended to send back from some point on the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>. That party was not dispatched nearly as soon as originally intended, and on August 4, 1804, <name type="person" key="Warfington, Richard">Warfington's</name> enlistment expired. Believing that he was the only one of the intended return party who was really trustworthy, the captains asked <name type="person" key="Warfington, Richard">Warfington</name> not to take his official discharge at that time, so that he could retain his rank and authority over the return group and ensure the safety of the dispatches, journals, and specimens sent back. <name type="person" key="Warfington, Richard">Warfington</name> remained with the group at <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name>, conducted the return party to <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> in 1805, and carried out his command of that body to the captains' complete satisfaction; he even managed to keep alive a prairie dog and four magpies <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> sent to <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> recommended that <name type="person" key="Warfington, Richard">Warfington</name> receive a bonus beyond his regular pay. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> apparently had no information about him in 1825–28. Clarke (MLCE), 59–60; <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> to <name type="person" key="Dearborn, Henry">Henry Dearborn</name>, January 15, 1807, Jackson (LLC), 1:364–65, 372 endnote; <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> List of Expedition Members [ca. 1825–28], ibid., 2:639; Cutright (LCPN), 377.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Weiser, Peter">Private Peter M. Weiser</name> (1781–?). <name type="person" key="Weiser, Peter">Weiser</name>, descended from the noted frontier diplomat <name type="person" key="Weiser, Conrad">Conrad Weiser</name>, was born and apparently reared in <name type="place" key="Pennsylvania">Pennsylvania</name>. He was probably a member of <name type="person" key="Bissell, Russell">Captain Russell Bissell's</name> company of the First Infantry Regiment, stationed at <name type="place" key="Kaskaskia, Ill.">Kaskaskia</name>, before joining the expedition. In spite of some minor disciplinary trouble at <name type="place" key="Dubois River">River Dubois</name> he was made a member of the permanent party. In 1807 he joined <name type="person" key="Lisa, Manuel">Manuel Lisa's</name> fur-trading venture up the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, and for the next few years he was on the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone</name> and the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> headwaters with <name type="person" key="Lisa, Manuel">Lisa's</name> men, including some old comrades from the expedition. It has been conjectured that he also crossed the <name type="place" key="Continental Divide">Continental Divide</name> to the <name type="place"
                     key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Snake River</name> valley in <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>; at any rate, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> map of the West (<hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 126), published in 1814, shows "Wiser's R." as a tributary of the <name type="place"
                     key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Snake</name> in western <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>, in country not visited by the expedition. It is not known whether <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> received the information from <name type="person" key="Weiser, Peter">Weiser</name> himself or from one of his associates, such as <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name> or <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name>. The river, with the correct spelling, and an <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name> town, still bear his name. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> listed him in 1825–28 as "killed"; he may have been one of those killed by the <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name> while operating out of <name type="person" key="Lisa, Manuel">Lisa's</name> post at the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Three Forks of the">Three Forks of the Missouri</name> in 1810, or perhaps he fell in some later fur-trade skirmish. Clarke (PW); Clarke (MLCE), 59; <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> List of Expedition Members [ca. 1825–28], Jackson (LLC), 2:639.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Werner, William">Private William Werner</name> (dates unknown). Often "<name type="person" key="Werner, William">Warner</name>" in the journals, he may have been born in <name type="place" key="Kentucky">Kentucky</name> and may have been in the army before joining the Corps; his actual date of joining is uncertain. He fought with <name type="person" key="Potts, John">John Potts</name> during the <name type="place" key="Dubois River">River Dubois</name> winter, and he was convicted of being absent without leave at <name type="place" key="Saint Charles, Mo.">St. Charles</name>, <name type="place" key="Missouri">Missouri</name>, at the outset of the expedition. Otherwise his service was apparently satisfactory but unremarkable. He appears briefly in the records after the expedition, having been advanced some money in 1807 by <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and allowed the use of a government horse. In 1825–28 <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> understood him to be living in <name type="place" key="Virginia">Virginia</name>. Clarke (MLCE), 54; <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> List of Expedition Members [ca. 1825–28], Jackson (LLC), 2:639.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="White, Isaac">Isaac White</name> (ca. 1774–?). <name type="person" key="White, Isaac">White</name> was born in <name type="place" key="Massachusetts">Massachusetts</name> and joined the army in 1801. He was a member of <name type="person" key="Stoddard, Amos">Captain Amos Stoddard's</name> artillery company. The only mention of him in the journals is in a detachment order of May 2, 1804. Possibly he was the man of <name type="person" key="Stoddard, Amos">Stoddard's</name> company sent back on June 12, 1804; otherwise he was with the return party from <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name> in 1805. Jackson (LLC), 1:237 n. 7; Clarke (MLCE), 62.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Private Joseph Whitehouse</name> (ca. 1775–?). An expedition journalist, <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse</name> was probably born in <name type="place" key="Virginia">Virginia</name> and went to <name type="place" key="Kentucky">Kentucky</name> with his family in about 1784. He enlisted officially on January 1, 1804, transferring from <name type="person" key="Bissell, Daniel">Captain Daniel Bissell's</name> company of the First Infantry Regiment, stationed at <name type="place" key="Kaskaskia, Ill.">Kaskaskia</name>. He was in some sort of disciplinary difficulty during the winter at <name type="place" key="Dubois River">River Dubois</name> but was allowed to remain with the expedition. During the expedition he often acted as a tailor for the other men. In 1807 in <name type="place" key="Missouri">Missouri</name> he was ordered arrested for debt. He later rejoined the army, served in the War of 1812, and deserted in 1817. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> apparently had no information about him in 1825–28. Clarke (MLCE), 55–56; <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> List of Expedition Members [ca. 1825–28], Jackson (LLC), 2:639; Cutright (HLCJ), 242–64.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Willard, Alexander">Private Alexander Hamilton Willard</name> (1778–1865). Born in <name type="place" key="New Hampshire">New Hampshire</name>, he was living in <name type="place" key="Kentucky">Kentucky</name> when he enlisted in <name type="person" key="Stoddard, Amos">Captain Amos Stoddard's</name> artillery company in 1800. He was tried and convicted on July 12, 1804, of sleeping while on sentry duty; the offense, under the military regimen of the Corps, was punishable by death, but instead he was given one hundred lashes. He was a blacksmith and apparently assisted <name type="person" key="Shields, John">John Shields</name> in this work during the expedition. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> hired him as government blacksmith for the <name type="native_nation" key="Sac and Fox Indians">Sauk and Fox Indians</name> in 1808, and the next year he held the same position with the <name type="native_nation" key="Delaware Indians">Delawares</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Shawnee Indians">Shawnees</name>. He served in the War of 1812 and lived in <name type="place" key="Missouri">Missouri</name> and <name type="place" key="Wisconsin">Wisconsin</name>. His marriage in 1807 produced twelve children. In 1852 he emigrated with his family to <name type="place" key="California">California</name> and there died and was buried near <name type="place" key="Sacramento, Cal.">Sacramento</name>. There is some suggestion that he kept a journal on the expedition, but if so, it is lost. Jackson (LLC), 1:372 n. 26; Clarke (MLCE), 56.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Windsor, Richard">Private Richard Windsor</name> (dates unknown). Often "<name type="person" key="Windsor, Richard">Winser</name>" or <name type="person" key="Windsor, Richard">Winsor</name>" in the journals, he may have come from <name type="person" key="Bissell, Russell">Captain Russell Bissell's</name> company of the First Infantry Regiment. Like many of the other soldiers detailed to the expedition, he officially enlisted for the expedition on January 1, 1804. During the trip he was often assigned as a hunter. He settled in <name type="place" key="Missouri">Missouri</name> after the expedition but rejoined the army and served until 1819. In 1825–28 <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> listed him as living on the <name type="place" key="Sangamon River">Sangamon River</name> in <name type="place" key="Illinois">Illinois</name>. Clarke (MLCE), 59; <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> List of Expedition Members [ca. 1825–28], Jackson (LLC), 2:628.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="York">York</name> (ca. 1770–?). <name type="person" key="York">York</name> is the only name given for <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> slave in the journals or any primary document. He seems to have been about the same age as <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, or a few years younger, and to have been <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> companion from childhood, in the fashion of the slaveholding South. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> legally inherited <name type="person" key="York">York</name> from his father in 1799. The journals and other primary sources indicate that he was large and strong and perhaps overweight. He seems to have carried a gun and to have performed his full share of the duties with other members of the party; a body servant who could neither defend himself nor carry his share of the load would have been an unacceptable luxury on the expedition. Tales of his sexual prowess among Indian women or of his being the expedition's buffoon rest largely on the racial bias of later historians, not on evidence in the journals. <name type="person" key="York">York</name> received his freedom sometime after 1811 and then operated a wagon freight business in <name type="place" key="Tennessee">Tennessee</name> and <name type="place" key="Kentucky">Kentucky</name>. By <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> account, the business failed, and <name type="person" key="York">York</name> then decided to rejoin his old master in <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> but died of cholera on the way, sometime before 1832. An alternative account has it that he made his way west to the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rockies</name> and was living with the <name type="native_nation" key="Crow Indians">Crows</name> in the 1830s; the tale is unlikely but not wholly impossible. Betts (SY); Clarke (MLCE), 38.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">Engagé</hi>
               <name type="person" key="Cann, E.">E. Cann</name> (dates unknown). He appears in <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> list of <hi rend="italic">engagés</hi> under <ref n="1804-07-04" type="related">July 4, 1804</ref>. Elsewhere in the journals that name appears in versions that have been deciphered as "<name type="person" key="Cann, E.">Carr</name>," "<name type="person" key="Cann, E.">Cane</name>," and "<name type="person" key="Cann, E.">Carn</name>"; some of the variation may be due to <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> handwriting, not his spelling. <name type="person" key="Cann, E.">Cann</name> was presumably with the return party of 1805. He has been identified as <name type="person" key="Cann, E.">Alexander Carson</name> (ca. 1775–1836), a relative of <name type="person" key="Carson, Kit">Christopher "Kit" Carson</name>, on the basis of a second-hand account stating that <name type="person" key="Carson, Kit">Carson</name> claimed to have come to the mountains with <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>; there is no more direct evidence. <name type="person" key="Cann, E.">Cann</name> was perhaps born in <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name> and wintered with the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> in 1809–10. In 1811 he joined the overland Astorians led by <name type="person" key="Hunt, Wilson Price">Wilson Price Hunt</name>, crossing the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rockies</name> with them, and spent a number of years trapping in the mountains and on the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>, working for the North West Company and the Hudson's Bay Company. In 1833 he settled permanently in the <name type="place" key="Willamette (Multnomah) River">Willamette</name> Valley in <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name> and was killed by Indians in 1836. Clarke (MLCE), 68–69; Jackson (LLC), 1:373 endnote; Stoller.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">Engagé</hi>
               <name type="person" key="Cougee, Charles">Charles Caugee</name> (dates unknown). He is mentioned in a list of <hi rend="italic">engagés</hi> under <ref n="1804-07-04" type="related">July 4, 1804</ref>, and may have been with the return party from <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name> in 1805. Nothing else is known of him. Clarke (MLCE), 68.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">Engagé</hi>
               <name type="person" key="Collin, Joseph">Joseph Collin</name> (dates unknown). He should not be confused with <name type="person" key="Collins, John">John Collins</name>, an enlisted man with the permanent party. <name type="person" key="Collin, Joseph">Collin</name> is listed as an <hi rend="italic">engagé</hi> on <ref n="1804-05-26" type="related">May 26, 1804</ref>, and in no other list. Because there is no record of his being paid, he may have been paid in cash when discharged in the fall of 1804, at either the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> or <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> villages. He may also be the man picked up at the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> villages on the expedition's return in 1806. A <name type="person" key="Collin, Joseph">Joseph Collin</name> from the <name type="place" key="Montreal">Montreal</name> area in <name type="place" key="Canada">Canada</name> was married at <name type="place" key="Portage des Sioux, Mo.">Portage des Sioux</name>, <name type="place" key="Missouri">Missouri</name>, in 1818. See also the sketch of <name type="person" key="La Liberté">La Liberté</name>, below. Clarke (MLCE), 69–70.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">Engagé</hi>
               <name type="person" key="Deschamps, Jean Baptiste">Jean Baptiste Deschamps</name> (dates unknown). He was the "patroon"—foreman—of the French boatmen, presumably because of his experience and maturity. Virtually nothing is known of him, though he may have been residing with his wife at <name type="place" key="Saint Charles, Mo.">St. Charles</name>, <name type="place" key="Missouri">Missouri</name>, in 1792. Clarke (MLCE), 63.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">Engagé</hi>
               <name type="person" key="Hérbert, Charles (Chalo?)">Charles Hebert</name> (dates unknown). He is listed as an <hi rend="italic">engagé</hi> on <ref n="1804-05-26" type="related">May 26, 1804</ref>, and nowhere else. Possibly he is the "Charlo" of <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> list of <ref n="1804-07-04" type="related">July 4, 1804</ref>. He has been identified as a Canadian who married in <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> in 1792 and may have lived near <name type="place" key="Saint Charles, Mo.">St. Charles</name> or <name type="place" key="Portage des Sioux, Mo.">Portage des Sioux</name>, <name type="place" key="Missouri">Missouri</name>. Since there is no record of his being paid, he may have been discharged at the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> villages in the fall of 1804 and paid in cash. Perhaps he returned with the return party of 1805, having wintered with the expedition at <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name>. Clarke (MLCE), 69.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">Engagé</hi>
               <name type="person" key="La Jeunesse, Jean Baptiste">Jean Baptiste La Jeunesse</name> (?–1806?). He is also "<name type="person" key="La Jeunesse, Jean Baptiste">La Guness</name>" and, apparently, "<name type="person" key="La Jeunesse, Jean Baptiste">Lasones</name>," in the journals. He was probably from <name type="place" key="Saint Rose, Canada">St. Rose</name>, <name type="place" key="Quebec">Quebec</name>, <name type="place" key="Canada">Canada</name>. In 1797 in <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> he married the sister of <name type="person" key="Malboeuf (Mabbauf), Etienne">Etienne Malboeuf</name>, another expedition <hi rend="italic">engagé.</hi>
               <name type="person" key="La Jeunesse, Jean Baptiste">La Jeunesse</name> was discharged, and presumably paid off, at the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> villages in the fall of 1804 and set off with <name type="person" key="Primeau, Paul">Paul Primeau</name> downriver in a canoe on November 6. He may have stopped off at the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> villages or elsewhere for the winter. He was apparently dead by September 1807, when his wife remarried. Clarke (MLCE), 64–65.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">Engagé</hi>
               <name type="person" key="La Liberté">La Liberté</name> (dates unknown). An <hi rend="italic">engagé</hi> of this name was sent on <ref n="1804-07-29" type="related">July 29, 1804</ref>, to the <name type="native_nation" key="Oto Indians">Oto Indians</name> in northeastern <name type="place" key="Nebraska">Nebraska</name> to invite them to confer with the captains. He took the opportunity to quit the expedition, and though a party was sent to apprehend him, he escaped and appears no more in the expedition record. Attempts to identify him further have mired in confusion about his actual name. <name type="person" key="La Liberté">La Liberté</name> seems to have been a common name among the French Canadians and <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name> Valley French involved in the fur trade and river travel at the time. Thus, a <name type="person" key="La Liberté">La Liberté</name> was working for the North West Company in <name type="place" key="Canada">Canada</name> in 1799 and might be the same man. The <hi rend="italic">engagé</hi> who left the party spoke the <name type="native_nation" key="Oto Indians">Oto</name> language to some extent, so he must have lived among them for a while. His singularly appropriate name may be only a <hi rend="italic">dit</hi> name, not a formal surname. He does not appear under that name in the list of <hi rend="italic">engagés</hi> in the detachment order of May 26, 1804; this could mean that he was hired later, perhaps picked up from some party of traders headed down the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>. However, he may only be concealed on the May 26 list under another name, especially if <name type="person" key="La Liberté">La Liberté</name> is only a <hi rend="italic">dit</hi> name. The list of <ref n="1804-07-04" type="related">July 4, 1804</ref>, in <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> Field Notes gives "<name type="person" key="La Liberté">Joseph La bartee</name>," and also "<name type="person" key="La Liberté">J. Le bartee</name>"; each time the name has an asterisk beside it. On the first occurrence, "Le bartee" is assigned to a pirogue, the second time to the large keelboat. Did <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> err and list the same man twice, or were there two men with the same surname or <hi rend="italic">dit</hi> name? Did the asterisk indicate the error, or refer to the similarity of names? <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> refers to the deserter first on July 29, 1804; Quaife gives the name as "Jo Barter," but <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway's</name> manuscript version can as readily be interpreted as "Bartee." At any rate, <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> later calls him "<name type="person" key="La Liberté">La Liberty</name>," confirming that he is one of the possible two "Le bartees." Donald Jackson has uncovered, in an 1819 <name type="place" key="Illinois">Illinois</name> legal document, a reference to "Joseph Callin <hi rend="italic">dit</hi>
               <name type="person" key="La Liberté">La Liberty</name> of portage des <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Scioux</name>." This could easily be the <hi rend="italic">engagé</hi>
               <name type="person" key="Collin, Joseph">Joseph Collin</name> of the expedition, especially since he is not mentioned by the name <name type="person" key="Collin, Joseph">Collin</name> in the Field Notes list of July 4. This could explain how <name type="person" key="La Liberté">La Liberté</name> became "<name type="person" key="La Liberté">Joseph Le bartee</name>" in that list.</p>
            <p>	The question remains, however, whether there were two men with this <hi rend="italic">dit</hi> name or only one, and whether, if there were two, <name type="person" key="Collin, Joseph">Collin</name> was the deserter. (Technically, he was not a deserter in the military sense because he was a hired boatman rather than an enlisted man.) There is no record of <name type="person" key="Collin, Joseph">Collin's</name> having been paid, which would have been the case if he had deserted, but it could also mean that, like some other <hi rend="italic">engagés,</hi> he was discharged at the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> or <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> villages and paid in cash. A man picked up at the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> in 1806, who had perhaps been with the expedition in 1804, could have been <name type="person" key="Collin, Joseph">Collin</name>; this man, in any case, could hardly have been the deserter, since he would have avoided the expedition, and they would not have given him a ride home. Thus it is quite possible that <name type="person" key="Collin, Joseph">Joseph Collin</name> bore the <hi rend="italic">dit</hi> name <name type="person" key="La Liberté">La Liberté</name> and is referred to as "<name type="person" key="La Liberté">Joseph Le bartee</name>" by <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> because of this. It is also possible, however, that there was another <hi rend="italic">engagé</hi> with that same <hi rend="italic">dit</hi> name, and if so, either might have been the deserter. Since he was a civilian employee, not an enlisted soldier, his desertion was not quite so serious as that of <name type="person" key="Reed, Moses B.">Moses Reed</name>, which occurred at about the same time, although <name type="person" key="La Liberté">La Liberté</name> did take a "public horse" with him when he was sent to the <name type="native_nation" key="Oto Indians">Otos</name>. A <name type="person" key="La Liberté">Joseph La Liberté</name> was married in <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> in 1835, and a <name type="person" key="La Liberté">La Liberté</name>, aged 60, was buried there in 1837.</p>
            <p>	If there are two <name type="person" key="La Liberté">La Libertés</name>, and <name type="person" key="Collin, Joseph">Collin</name> is one of them, which other <hi rend="italic">engagé</hi> is concealed under this name? One is clearly named Joseph, while the initial of the other appears to be "J." Besides <name type="person" key="Collin, Joseph">Collin</name> there is no other "Joseph" among the known <hi rend="italic">engagés.</hi> The only other whose initial might be "J." is <name type="person" key="La Jeunesse, Jean Baptiste">Baptiste La Jeunesse</name>, whose actual given name was presumably <name type="person" key="La Jeunesse, Jean Baptiste">Jean-Baptiste</name>. However, he apparently appears as "<name type="person" key="La Jeunesse, Jean Baptiste">Lasones</name>" in the same July 4 list as the two Le bartees. The discrepancies in both name and number between the principal lists of <hi rend="italic">engagés</hi> do not allow any certainty on this matter. Quaife (MLJO), 102; Clarke (MLCE), 63–64, 69–70; Jackson, "<name type="person" key="La Liberté">La Liberté</name> Identified," typescript.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">Engagé</hi>
               <name type="person" key="Malboeuf (Mabbauf), Etienne">Etienne Malboeuf</name> (ca. 1775–?). He was from <name type="place" key="Lac de Sable, Canada">Lac de Sable</name>, <name type="place" key="Canada">Canada</name>, and his mother may have been an Indian; he was baptized in <name type="place" key="Saint Charles, Mo.">St. Charles</name>, <name type="place" key="Missouri">Missouri</name>, in 1792. In 1804, he was residing in <name type="place" key="Kaskaskia, Ill.">Kaskaskia</name>, <name type="place" key="Illinois">Illinois</name>. Like most of the other <hi rend="italic">engagés,</hi> he returned from <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name> in 1805. Clarke (MLCE), 65.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">Engagé</hi>
               <name type="person" key="Pinaut, Peter">Peter Pinaut</name> (ca. 1776–?). Undoubtedly <name type="person" key="Pinaut, Peter">Pierre</name> to his fellow Frenchmen, he is presumably the "<name type="person" key="Pinaut, Peter">Charles pineau</name>" of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> financial accounts. He may also be the "Charlo" mentioned in one list in <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> Field Notes. Pinaut was the illegitimate son of a French father and a <name type="native_nation" key="Missouri Indians">Missouri Indian</name> mother, and was baptized in <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> in 1790, suggesting that he grew up in the Indian country on the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>. The only mention of him in the journals is in the detachment order of <ref n="19804-05-26" type="related">May 26, 1804</ref>. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> Account [August 5, 1807], Jackson (LLC), 2:422; Clarke (MLCE), 65–66.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">Engagé</hi>
               <name type="person" key="Primeau, Paul">Paul Primeau</name> (dates unknown). He is variously "<name type="person" key="Primeau, Paul">Primaut</name>," "<name type="person" key="Primeau, Paul">Preemau</name>," and "<name type="person" key="Primeau, Paul">Premor</name>" in the journals. He came from <name type="place" key="Chateauguay, Canada">Chateauguay</name>, <name type="place" key="Canada">Canada</name>, and was married in <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> in 1799. He was discharged, and presumably paid off, at the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> villages in the fall of 1804, and on November 6, with <name type="person" key="La Jeunesse, Jean Baptiste">Jean-Baptiste La Jeunesse</name>, set out downriver in a canoe for <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>. He may have wintered with the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> or elsewhere. In 1807 he was probably in <name type="place" key="Missouri">Missouri</name>. Clarke (MLCE), 66.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">Engagé</hi>
               <name type="person" key="Rivet, François">Fran<seg n="u231">ç</seg>ois Rivet</name> (ca. 1757–1852). Born at <name type="place" key="Montreal">Montreal</name>, <name type="person" key="Rivet, François">Rivet</name>, also referred to as "<name type="person" key="Rivet, François">Reevey</name>" and such variations, came to the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name> Valley at an early age and engaged in hunting and trading in <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name>. He may have left the return party of 1805 at the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> villages. He soon headed up the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> again, perhaps with <name type="person" key="Lisa, Manuel">Manuel Lisa's</name> trading company, for about 1809 he was in the <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Flathead</name> country of northwest <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>, where he married and fathered two sons. In 1813 he was employed by the North West Company among the <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Flatheads</name>, and was still there in 1824, working as both trapper and interpreter. In 1829 he transferred to <name type="place" key="Fort Colville (Mont.)">Fort Colville</name> on the upper <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>, and in 1832, at the age of seventy-five, he was placed in charge of the post by the Hudson's Bay Company. After retiring in 1838 he settled in the <name type="place" key="Willamette (Multnomah) River">Willamette</name> Valley in <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>. Clarke (MLCE), 66–67; Munnick (FR).</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">Engagé</hi>
               <name type="person" key="Roi (Roie, Rokey), Peter">Peter Roi</name> (dates unknown). There were many early settlers in the "<name type="place" key="Illinois">Illinois</name> country" with the surname Roi or Roy, descended from pioneers of French and Indian blood who were there even before the founding of <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>, having come from <name type="place" key="Canada">Canada</name>. <name type="person" key="Roi (Roie, Rokey), Peter">Pierre Roy</name>, born in 1786 at <name type="place" key="Sainte Genevieve, Mo.">Ste. Genevieve</name>, <name type="place" key="Missouri">Missouri</name>, may be the man, but there is no evidence. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> also gives the name as "<name type="person" key="Roi (Roie, Rokey), Peter">Roie</name>." On August 21, 1806, at the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> villages in <name type="place" key="South Dakota">South Dakota</name>, the returning expedition encountered one of their former <hi rend="italic">engagés,</hi> whom <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> identifies as "<name type="person" key="Roi (Roie, Rokey), Peter">Rokey</name>"; he had probably stayed behind when the return party of 1805 went down to <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> and now returned to <name type="place" key="Missouri">Missouri</name> with the expedition. It has been suggested that his name was Rocque, a name that appears on no expedition roster. <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">John Ordway</name> also refers to this man by name, and in Quaife's edition the name is given as "Ross." Examination of the manuscript shows that <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway's</name> letters can easily be interpreted as "<name type="person" key="Roi (Roie, Rokey), Peter">Roie</name>" or even "Roei." "<name type="person" key="Roi (Roie, Rokey), Peter">Rokey</name>" was therefore probably <name type="person" key="Roi (Roie, Rokey), Peter">Peter Roi</name>, and there is no need to search for Rocque or Ross. This interpretation is strengthened by the fact that <name type="person" key="Roi (Roie, Rokey), Peter">Roi</name> was not among the expedition <hi rend="italic">engagés</hi> who received their pay in <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> in 1805. Clarke (MLCE), 67, 70; Quaife (MLJO), 392; Jackson (LLC), 1:237 n. 7.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n01" n="1">Cutright (HLCJ), 237–38.</note>
            <note xml:id="n02" n="2">
               <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> List of Expedition Members [ca. 1825–28], Jackson (LLC), 2:638–39.</note>
            <note xml:id="n03" n="3">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> to <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, June 19, 1803, and August 3, 1803, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, August 21, 1803, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> to <name type="person" key="Dearborn, Henry">Henry Dearborn</name>, January 15, 1807, ibid., 1:57–60, 115–17, 117–18, 369–73 nn. The remaining seven of the nine are: <name type="person" key="Floyd, Charles">Floyd</name>; <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Pryor</name>; <name type="person" key="Bratton, William E.">Bratton</name>; the <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph and Reubin">Field brothers</name>, <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Joseph</name> and <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">Reubin</name>; <name type="person" key="Gibson, George">Gibson</name>; and <name type="person" key="Shields, John">Shields</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n04" n="4">Ibid., 369–73 nn.; Appleman (LC), 62–64, 366 n. 54. No muster roll for <name type="person" key="Bissell, Russell">Russell Bissell's</name> company has been found; such a document would clarify some of the doubts about several men.</note>
            <note xml:id="n05" n="5">The question of the composition of the return party will be considered at greater length under April 7, 1805, in the appropriate volume of this edition.</note>
            <note xml:id="n06" n="6">McDermott (FS), 28–30; Clarke (MLCE), 21–22, 63 n. 23.</note>
            <note xml:id="n07" n="7">Jackson (LLC), 1:237 n. 7, 2:422.</note>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
