<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-04-22">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
April 22, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 7</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">March 23–June 9, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1991</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">155-159</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">295-296</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">214</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
         <geoDecl datum="WGS" xml:id="lc.geo.1806-04-22.01">
            <placeName/>
            <geo>45.7 -120.6833</geo>
            <note>Camped in a Tenino Indian village, Klickitat County, WA, near John Day Dam.</note>
         </geoDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="category">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-10-06</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1806-04-22">April 22, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-04-22.01" n="lc.geo.1806-04-22.01">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Tuesday April 22cd 1806</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
Last night two of our horses broke loos from the picquits and straggled off some little distance, the men who had charge of them fortunately recovered them early.    at 7 A. M. we set out having previously sent on our small Canoe with <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name> and <name type="person" key="Potts, John">Potts</name>.    we had not arrived at the top of a hill over which the road leads opposite the village before <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbono's</name> horse threw his load, and taking fright at the saddle and robe which still adhered, ran at full speed down the hill, near the village he disengaged himself from the saddle and robe, an indian hid the robe in is lodge. I sent our guide and one man who was with me in the rear to assist <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbono</name> in retaking his horse which having done they returned to the village on the track of the horse in surch of the lost articles    they found the saddle but could see nothing of the robe the indians denyed having seen it; they then continued on the track of the horse to the place from whence he had set out with the same success.    being now confident that the indians had taken it I sent <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">the Indian woman</name> on to request <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. C.</name> to halt the party and send back some of the men to my assistance being determined either to make the indians deliver the robe or birn their houses. they have vexed me in such a manner by such repeated acts of villany that I am quite disposed to treat them with every severyty, their defenseless state pleads forgiveness so far as rispects their lives.    with this resolution I returned to their village which I had just reached as <name type="person" key="Labiche, François">Labuish</name> met me with the robe which he informed me he found in an Indian lodg his behind their baggage. I now returned and joined <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt Clark</name> who was waiting my arrival with the party.    <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">the Indian woman</name> had not reached <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt C.</name> untill about the time I arrived and he returned from a position on the top of a hill<ref target="n32042201" n="1"/> not far from where he had halted the party.    from the top of this emmenense <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. C.</name> had an extensive view of the country.    he observed the range of mountains in which <name type="place" key="Mount Hood (Timm, Falls Mountain)">Mount Hood</name> stands to continue nearly south as far as the eye could reach.    he also observed the snow clad top of <name type="place" key="Mount Jefferson">Mount Jefferson</name> which boar S. 10 W. <name type="place" key="Mount Hood (Timm, Falls Mountain)">Mount Hood</name> from the same point boar S. 30 W.    the tops of the range of western mountains are covered with snow. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt C.</name> also discovered some timbered country in a Southern direction from him at no great distance. <name type="place" key="Deschutes (Clark's, Towanahiook's) River">Clarks river [<hi rend="italic">NB: Towarnahiooks</hi>]</name> which mouths immediately opposite this point of view forks at the distance of 18 or 20 miles form hence, the wright hand fork takes its rise in <name type="place" key="Mount Hood (Timm, Falls Mountain)">mount Hood</name>, and the main branch continues it's course to the S. E. [<hi rend="italic">NB: 10 or 12 miles higher up another fork comes in from <name type="place" key="Mount Jefferson">Mt. Jefferson</name>
                  </hi>]<ref target="n32042202" n="2"/>    we now made the following regulations as to our future order of march (viz) that <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. C.</name> &amp; myself should devide the men who were disencumbered by horses and march alternately each day the one in front and the other in rear.    haveing divided the party agreeably to this arrangement, we proceeded on through an open plain country about 8 miles to a village of 6 houses of the <name type="native_nation" key="Tenino Indians">Eneshur</name> nation,<ref target="n32042203" n="3"/> here we observed our 2 canoes passing up on the opposite side; the wind being too high for them to pass the river they continued on.    we halted at a small run just above the village where we dined on some dogs which we purchased of the inhabitants and suffered our horses to graize about three hours.    there is no timber in this country we are obliged to purchase our fuel of the natives, who bling it from a great distance.    while we halted for dinner we purch a horse.    after dinner we proceeded on up the river about 4 miles to a village of 7 mat lodges of the last mentioned nation.<ref target="n32042204" n="4"/>    here our <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Chopunnish</name> guide informed us that the next village was at a considerable distance and that we could not reach it tonight.    the people at this place offered to sell us wood and dogs, and we therefore thought it better to remain all night.    a man blonging to the next village above proposed exchanging a horse for one of our canoes, just at this moment one of our canoes was passing.<ref target="n32042205" n="5"/>    we hailed them and ordered them to come over but the wind continued so high that they could not join us untill after sunset and the Indian who wished to exchange his horse for the canoe had gone on. <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonoe</name> purchased a horse this evening.    we obtained 4 dogs and as much wood as answered our purposes on moderate terms.    we can only afford ourselves one fire, and are obliged to lie without shelter, the nights are cold and days warm.—    <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name> and <name type="person" key="Potts, John">Pots</name> had passed on with their canoe.
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-04-22.02" n="lc.geo.1806-04-22.01">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Tuesday 22nd of April 1806</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
last night 2 of our horses broke loose and Strayed of at a Short distance.    at 7 oClock we loaded up and Set out, haveing previously Sent off the Canoe with <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name> and <name type="person" key="Potts, John">Potts</name>    we had not arived at the top of the hill which is 200 feet before <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Shabonos</name> horse threw off his load and went with great Speed down the hill to the Village where he disengaged himself of his Saddle &amp; the robe which was under it, the Indians hid the robe and delayed <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name> and the rear party Some time before they found the robe which was in a lodge hid behind their baggage, and took possession of it.    dureing the time the front of the party was waiting for <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Cap Lewis</name>, I assended a high hill from which I could plainly See the range of Mountains which runs South from <name type="place" key="Mount Hood (Timm, Falls Mountain)">Mt. Hood</name> as far as I could See. I also discovered the top of <name type="place" key="Mount Jefferson">Mt. Jefferson</name> which is Covered with Snow and is S 10° W. <name type="place" key="Mount Hood (Timm, Falls Mountain)">Mt. Hood</name> is S. 30° W.    the range of mountains are Covered with timber and also <name type="place" key="Mount Hood (Timm, Falls Mountain)">Mt Hood</name> to a sertain hite. The range of Mountains has Snow on them. I also discovered some timbered land in a S. derection from me, Short of the mountains. <name type="place" key="Deschutes (Clark's, Towanahiook's) River">Clarks river</name> which mouthes imedeately opposit to me forks at about 18 or 20 miles, the West fork runs to the <name type="place" key="Mount Hood (Timm, Falls Mountain)">Mt Hood</name> and the main branch Runs from S. E.    after <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt Lewis</name> Came up we proceeded on through a open ruged plain about 8 miles to a Village of 6 Houses on the river.    here we observed our 2 Canoes passing up on the opposit Side and the Wind too high for them to join us. I halted at the mouth of a run<ref target="n32042206" n="6"/> above the village near Some good grass to let the horses graze and for the party to dine. Sent to the huts and purchased a dog &amp; Some wood.    dureing the time the party was takeing diner we purchased one horse.    after we proceeded on up the river about 4 miles to a village of 7 mat Lodges.    here our <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Chopunnish</name> guide informed me that the next villg. was at Some distance and that we Could not get to it to night, and that there was no wood to be precured on this Side.    a man offered to Sell us a horse for a Canoe.    just at the moment we discovered one of our Canoes on the opposit Side.    we concluded to Camp here all night with the expectation of precureing some horses. Sent and purchased Some wood and 4 dogs 〈with〉 &amp; Shapillele. <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Shabono</name> purchased a hors for which he gave a red rapper, Shirt, ploom &amp; Tomahawk &amp;c.    the party purchased a great quantity of Chapellell and Some berries for which they gave bits of Tin and Small pieces of Cloth &amp; wire &amp;c.    had our horses led out and held to grass untill dusk when they were all brought to Camp, and pickets drove in the ground and the horses tied up.    we find the horses very troublesom perticularly the Stud which Compose 10/13 of our number of horses.    the air I find extreemly Cold which blows Continularly from <name type="place" key="Mount Hood (Timm, Falls Mountain)">Mt. Hoods</name> Snowey regions.    those Indians reside in Small Lodges built of the mats of Grass, flags &amp;c.<ref target="n32042207" n="7"/> and Crouded with inhabitents, who Speak a language Somewhat different from those at the falls.<ref target="n32042208" n="8"/>    their dress habits and appearance appear to be very much the Same with those below.    we made 14 miles to day with the greatest exirtion. <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Serjt. Gass</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">R. Fields</name> joined us with one Canoe this evening.    the other Canoe with <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name> &amp; pots is a head.

</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-04-22.03" n="lc.geo.1806-04-22.01">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Tuesday 22nd of April 1806.    a clear pleasant cold morning.    we loaded up our horses &amp; Set out.    assended a high hill    one of the horses threw his load &amp; Scattered it    one of the Indians Stole a robe &amp; hid it in one of their lodges.    we found it &amp; proced on the high Smooth plain which is extensive &amp; Smooth back from the river    about noon we halted at a village<ref target="n32042209" n="9"/> of the <name type="native_nation" key="Walula Indians">Wal-a-wal</name> tribe where we bought a dog and a little firewood.    the wind So high from the N. W. that the canoes being on the opposite Side of the river could not cross    we purchased a horse.    took a light dinner and proceed. on about 6 miles and Camped<ref target="n32042210" n="10"/> at a village where we purchased a horse 5 dogs and a little wood and considerable of new chappalell &amp;c.    in the evening Sergt. <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">R. Fields</name> came across the river &amp; joined us with one of the Small canoes


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-04-22.04" n="lc.geo.1806-04-22.01">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Tuesday 22nd.</hi>    This was a pleasant morning and high wind. We proceeded on about 3 miles, when the wind became so violent, that we could not proceed any further, and halted an unloaded our canoes. Having remained here two hours, the other canoe came up, and we proceeded on though the wind was high and river rough. At sunset I crossed over, where the party going by the land came in sight, and halted at a small village on the north side<ref target="n32042211" n="11"/> but the other canoe<ref target="n32042212" n="12"/> kept on along the southern shore. In the course of this day two more horses were procured, and at this small village 
we got some more dogs and shapaleel.



</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n32042201" n="1">The hill on which <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> made his survey may have been <name type="place" key="Haystack Butte">Haystack Butte</name>, <name type="place" key="Klickitat County, Wash.">Klickitat County</name>, <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>, directly opposite <name type="place" key="Deschutes (Clark's, Towanahiook's) River">Deschutes (Towarnihiooks, Clark's) River</name>. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 77.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32042202" n="2">Perhaps the <name type="place" key="Metolius River">Metolius River</name>, in <name type="place" key="Jefferson County, Oreg.">Jefferson County</name>, <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>, a tributary of the <name type="place" key="Deschutes (Clark's, Towanahiook's) River">Deschutes</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32042203" n="3">In <name type="native_nation" key="Klickitat County, Wash.">Klickitat County</name>, in the vicinity of present <name type="place" key="Maryhill Museum">Maryhill Museum</name>. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 77.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32042204" n="4">In <name type="place" key="Klickitat County, Wash.">Klickitat County</name>, in the vicinity of present <name type="place" key="John Day Dam">John Day Dam</name>, the camp for the night. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 77 shows two camps for this date. The first is noted as "encampd. 22d April 1806," while the second, a short distance upriver, is listed as "Campd. 22d April 1806."</note>
            <note xml:id="n32042205" n="5">In it were <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name> and <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">Reubin Field</name>, according to <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32042206" n="6">Perhaps <name type="place" key="Harley Canyon">Harley Canyon</name> in <name type="place" key="Klickitat County, Wash.">Klickitat County</name>. It does not appear on <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 77.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32042207" n="7">The textile plants used most commonly for weaving of large mats were bulrush, <hi rend="italic">Scirpus</hi> sp. (perhaps Clark's grass), and common cat-tail ("flag"), <hi rend="italic">Typha latifolia</hi> L. Hitchcock et al. 1:731.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32042208" n="8">
               <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> is probably here referring to a dialect difference within the Shahaptian language.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32042209" n="9">In <name type="native_nation" key="Klickitat County, Wash.">Klickitat County</name>, <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>, in the vicinity of <name type="place" key="Maryhill Museum">Maryhill Museum</name>. It was at a village
of <name type="native_nation" key="Tenino Indians">Tenino Indians</name> (called "Eneshur" by the captains) and not <name type="native_nation" key="Walula Indians">Walula Indians</name> as <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> seems to indicate.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32042210" n="10">In the vicinity of <name type="place" key="John Day Dam">John Day Dam</name>, <name type="place" key="Klickitat County, Wash.">Klickitat County</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32042211" n="11">A <name type="native_nation" key="Tenino Indians">Tenino Indian</name> village in <name type="place" key="Klickitat County, Wash.">Klickitat County</name>, <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>, in the vicinity of <name type="place" key="John Day Dam">John Day
Dam</name>, where they camped for the night.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32042212" n="12">In it were <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name> and <name type="person" key="Potts, John">Potts</name>; <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">Reubin Field</name> was in the same canoe with <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name>. See journal 
entries of the captains and of <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> for this day.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-04-21" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-04-23" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
