<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-04-26">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
April 26, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 7</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">March 23–June 9, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1991</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">169-173</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">298</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">216</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
         <geoDecl datum="WGS" xml:id="lc.geo.1806-04-26.01">
            <placeName/>
            <geo>45.9333 -119.3333</geo>
            <note>Camped in Benton County, WA, near present Plymouth and opposite the mouth of the Umatilla River.</note>
         </geoDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="category">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-10-06</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1806-04-26">April 26, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-04-26.01" n="lc.geo.1806-04-26.01">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Saturday April 26th 1806.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
This morning early we set forward and at the distance of three miles entered a low level plain country of great extent.    here the river hills are low and receede a great distance from the river this low country commence on the S. side of the river about 10 miles below our encampment of last evening.    these plains are covered with a variety of herbatious plants, grass, and three speceis of shrubs specimines of which I have preserved.<ref target="n32042601" n="1"/>    at the distance of twelve miles we halted near a few willows which afforded us a sufficient quantity of fuel to cook our dinner which consisted of the ballance of the dogs we had purchased yesterday evening and some jirked Elk.    we were overtaken today by several families of the natives who were traveling up the river with a number of horses; they continued with us much to our annoyance as the day was worm the roads dusty and we could not prevent their horses from crouding in and breaking our order of mach without using some acts of severity which we did not wish to commit.    after dinner we continued our march through the level plain near the river 16 Ms. and encamped about a mile below three lodges of the <name type="native_nation" key="Walula Indians">Wollah wollah</name> nation,<ref target="n32042602" n="2"/> and about 7 Ms. above our encampment of the 19 of October last.    after we encamped a little Indian boy caught several chubbs with a bone in this form<ref target="n32042603" n="3"/> which he substituted for a hook.    these fish were of about 9 inches long small head large abdomen, small where the tail joined the body, the tail wide long is proportion and forked.    the back and ventral fins were equadistant from the head and had each 10 bony rays, the fns next the gills nine each and that near the tail 12.    the upper exceeded the under jaw, the latter is truncate at the extremity and the tonge and pallet are smooth.    the colour is white on the sides and belley and a blewish brown on the back.    the iris of the eye is of a silvery colour and puple black.—    we covered ourselves partially this evening from the rain by means of an old tent.
</p>
               <p>
                  <figure rend="aps">
                     <p>Bone Fishhook, April 26, 1806, Codex K, p. 83
<bibl>
                           <orgName>(American Philosophical Society library, </orgName>
                           <note place="inline"> used with permission.)</note>
                        </bibl>
                     </p>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-04-26.02" n="lc.geo.1806-04-26.01">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Saturday April 26th 1806</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
This morning early we proceeded on and at the distance of three miles entered a low leavel plain Country of great extent.    here the river hills are low and receed a great distance from the river    this low Country Comenced on the South Side about 10 miles below our Encampment of the last night, those plains are Covered with a variety of herbatious plants, Grass and 3 Species of Shrubs.    at the distance of 12 miles halted near Some willows which afforded us a Sufficient quantity of fuel to cook our dinner which Consisted of the ballance of the dogs we had purchased yesterday evening and Some jerked Elk.    we were over taken to day by Several families of the nativs who were traveling up the river with a Numr. of horses; they Continued with us much to our ennoyance as the day was worm the roads dusty and we Could not prevent their horses Crouding in and breaking our order of March without useing Some acts of Severty which we did not wish to Commit.    after dinner we Continued our march through a leavel plain near the river 16 miles and encamped about a mile below 3 Lodges of the fritened band of the <name type="native_nation" key="Walula Indians">Wallah wallah</name> nation, and about 7 miles above our encampment of the 19th of Octr. last.    after we encampd a little Indian boy Cought Several Chubbs with a bone in this form<ref target="n32042604" n="4"/> which he Substituted for a hook.    those fish were of about 9 inches long.    we Covered our Selves perfectly this evening from the rain by means of an old tent. Saw a Goat and a Small wolf at a distance to day.    made 28 miles</p>
               <p>
                  <figure rend="mhs">
                     <p>Bone Fishhook, April 26, 1806, Voorhis No. 3
<bibl>
                           <orgName>Missouri Historical Society</orgName>
                        </bibl>
                     </p>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-04-26.03" n="lc.geo.1806-04-26.01">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Saturday 26th of April 1806.    we got up our horses.    took a light breakfast of a little dry Elk meat and Set out    proced on over a low level Smooth Sandy plain about 12 miles &amp; halted &amp; dined on a little dry Elk meat as we have nothing else.    the day warm.    we delayed about 1 hour and proceed. on    a number of the natives followed us who are mooveing up the river &amp; Some of them are going over the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">rockey mountn.</name> to kill buffaloe. Saw considerable of Snow on the mountains to the South &amp; S East.    came 20 odd miles this day &amp; Camped<ref target="n32042605" n="5"/> on the bank of the river.    only small willows to burn &amp;C—


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-04-26.04" n="lc.geo.1806-04-26.01">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Saturday 26th.</hi>    Last night <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clarke</name> got each a horse, and we set out early, had a fine morning, and proceeded on very well, most of the men having their knapsacks carried on the horses. At noon we halted and took a little of our dried meat, which is the only food we have. At 2 o'clock we continued our journey, and the officers were obliged to go on foot again, to let some of the men ride whose feet were very sore. The country is level and has a most beautiful appearance. On the plains there is a species of clover,<ref target="n32042606" n="6"/> as large as any I have seen, and has a large red handsome blossom. The leaves are not quite so large as those of the red clover cultivated in the Atlantic States, but has seven and eight leaves on a branch. We were overtaken and passed by a great number of the natives, with large droves of horses, that look well and are in good order. We travelled about 25 miles and encamped at a small grove of willows.



</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n32042601" n="1">No pressed specimens exist from this date. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> must have been referring to species he had collected earlier. The three most common shrubs that characterize the shrub-steppe vegetation of the <name type="place" key="Columbia Basin">Columbia Basin</name>, the most xeric of all the vegetation types encountered so far, include big sagebrush; rubber, or whitestem gray, rabbitbrush, <hi rend="italic">Chrysothamnus nauseosus</hi> (Pall.) Britt. var. <hi rend="italic">albicaulis</hi> (Nutt.) Rydb.; and twisted leaf, mountain, or tall green rabbit-brush, <hi rend="italic">C. viscidiflorus</hi> (Hook.) Nutt. See also <ref n="1806-04-30" type="related">April 30, 1806</ref>. Franklin &amp; Dyrness, 211–16; Hitchcock et al., 5:128–30.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32042602" n="2">This camp does not appear on <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> maps 75 or 76; it would be in <name type="place" key="Benton County, Wash.">Benton County</name>, <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>, perhaps below or in the vicinity of present <name type="place" key="Plymouth, Wash.">Plymouth</name> and opposite the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Umatilla (Youmalolam) River">Umatilla River</name>. The site conforms with the location of the camp of October 19, 1805. Works by Alexander; Gough (RIP); Lothson &amp; Lindeman (PB); Lothson &amp; Lindeman (PK); Rice &amp; Lindeman; and Wilke &amp; Dalan report surveys or testing in the <name type="place" key="Plymouth, Wash.">Plymouth</name>, <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>, area but none of these studies show evidence of the expedition. Alexander's map shows one Indian site very close to the location of this night's camp and he suggests that the village could have been occupied by <name type="native_nation" key="Umatilla Indians">Umatillas</name>, <name type="native_nation" key="Cayuse Indians">Cayuses</name>, or <name type="native_nation" key="Walula Indians">Walulas</name>. Alexander, 63–67. The village would probably have been at or near a site described by Drucker (ARMR), 11. A brief description of the area as part of an overview of <name type="place" key="McNary Reservoir">McNary Reservoir</name> is found in Shiner (MR), 197–200, 210–17. The most recent and competent archaeological report concerned with the confluence of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Umatilla (Youmalolam) River">Umatilla</name> rivers is Schalk (IMD).</note>
            <note xml:id="n32042603" n="3">Here apepars a sketch of the implement in Codex K, p. 83 (fig. 12). A similar drawing is in Codex Q, p. 111, apparently by an unknown copyist. See Moulton (SJ), 196–98. The fish was probably a <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name> chub, <hi rend="italic">Mylocheilus lateralis,</hi> a new species. Cutright (LCPN), 426; Burroughs, 265. <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name> was probably the one who drew a line through this passage to nearly the end of the entry.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32042604" n="4">A sketch of the fishing implement in Voorhis No. 3 (fig. 13).</note>
            <note xml:id="n32042605" n="5">In <name type="place" key="Benton County, Wash.">Benton County</name>, <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>, below or near <name type="place" key="Plymouth, Wash.">Plymouth</name>, roughly opposite the mouth of the <name type="native_nation" key="Umatilla (Youmalolam) River">Umatilla River</name>. The captains note that it was seven miles above the camp of <ref n="1805-10-19" type="related">October 19, 1805</ref>. See their entries for this date.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32042606" n="6">Large-head clover, <hi rend="italic">Trifolium macrocephalum</hi> (Pursh) Poiret. This species was collected by <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> on <ref n="1806-04-17" type="related">April 17</ref>. The red clover used for comparison is <hi rend="italic">T. pratense</hi> L., an introduced European species.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-04-25" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-04-27" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
