<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-01-03">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
January 3, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 6</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">November 2, 1805–March 22, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1990</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">162-164</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">264</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">185-186</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jw">Joseph Whitehouse</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 11</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of Joseph Whitehouse, May 14, 1804–April 2, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1997</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">409-410</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="category">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-08-05</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1806-01-03">January 3, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-01-03.01" n="">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Friday January 3d 1806.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
At 11 A. M. we were visited by our near neighbours, Chief or Tiá,<ref target="n26010301" n="1"/>
                  <name type="person" key="Coboway">Co-mo-wool</name>; alias <name type="person" key="Coboway">Conia</name> and six <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsops</name>.    the[y] brought for sale some roots buries and three dogs also a small quantity of fresh blubber.    this blubber they informed us they had obtained from their neighbours the <name type="native_nation" key="Tillamook Indians">Callamucks</name>
                  <ref target="n26010302" n="2"/> who inhabit the coast to the S. E. near whose vilage a whale had recently perished.    this blubber the Indians eat and esteeme is excellent food.    our party from necessaty have been obliged to subsist some length of time on dogs have now become extreemly fond of their flesh; it is worthy of remark that while we lived principally on the flesh of this anamal we were much more healthy strong and more fleshey than we had been since we left the Buffaloe country.    for my own part I have become so perfectly reconciled to the dog that I think it an agreeable food and would prefer it vastly to lean Venison or Elk.    a small Crow,<ref target="n26010303" n="3"/> the blue crested Corvus and the smaller corvus with a white brest,<ref target="n26010304" n="4"/> the little brown ren,<ref target="n26010305" n="5"/> a large brown sparrow,<ref target="n26010306" n="6"/> the bald Eagle and the beatifull Buzzard of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">columbia</name> still continue with us.—    Sent <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Sergt. Gass</name> and <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">George shannon</name> to the saltmakers who are somewhere on the coast to the S. W. of us, to enquire after <name type="person" key="Willard, Alexander">Willard</name> and <name type="person" key="Weiser, Peter">Wiser</name> who have not yet returned. <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">Reubin Fields</name>
                  <name type="person" key="Collins, John">Collins</name> and <name type="person" key="Potts, John">Pots</name> the hunters who set out on the 26th [<hi rend="italic">EC?: 28</hi>] Ulto. returned this evening after dark.    they reported that they had been about 15 Miles up the river at the head of the bay just below us and had hunted the country from thence down on the East side of the river, even to a considerable distance from it and had proved unsuccessful having killed one deer and a few fowls, barely as much as subsisted them.    this reminded us of the necessity of taking time by the forelock,<ref target="n26010307" n="7"/> and keep out several parties while we have yet a little meat beforehand.— I gave the Chief <name type="person" key="Coboway">Commowooll</name> a pare of sattin breechies with which he appeared much pleased.—
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-01-03.02" n="">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">January</hi> 3rd Friday 1806</date>
               </ab>
               <p>
The Sun rose fair this morning for the first time for Six weeks past, the Clouds Soon obscure it from our view, and a Shower of rain Suckceeded— last night we had Sharp lightening a hard thunder Suckceeded with heavy Showers of hail, and rain, which Continud with intervales of fair moon Shine dureing the night. Sent out <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Sergt. Gass</name> &amp; 2 men to the Salt makers with a vew to know what is the Cause of the delay of 2 of our party <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="person" key="Willard, Alexander">Willard</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Weiser, Peter">Wiser</name>
                  </hi> who we are uneasy about, as they were to have been back 6 days ago.
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-01-03.03" n="">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Friday the 3rd January 1806</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
At 11 A. m. we were visited by our near neighbour Chief (or <hi rend="italic">Tiá</hi>)<ref target="n26010308" n="8"/>
                  <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="person" key="Coboway">Co mo wool</name>
                  </hi> alis <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="person" key="Coboway">Conia</name>
                  </hi> [<hi rend="italic">NB: <name type="person" key="Coboway">Coôné</name>‚</hi>] and Six <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clat sops</name>.    they brought for Sale Some roots berries and 3 Dogs also a Small quantity of fresh blubber.    this blubber they informed us they had obtained from their neighbours the <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Tillamook Indians">Cal lá mox</name>
                  </hi> who inhabit the coast to the S. E near one of their Villages a Whale had recently perished.    this blubber the Indians eat and esteem it excellent food.    our party from necescity have been obliged to Subsist Some length of time on dogs have now become extreamly fond of their flesh; it is worthey of remark that while we lived principally on the flesh of this animal we wer much more helthy Strong and more fleshey then we have been Sence we left the Buffalow Country.    as for my own part I have not become reconsiled to the taste of this animal as yet.    a Small Crow, the blue Crested Corvus and the Smaller Corvus with a white breast, the little brown ren, and a large brown Sparrow, the bald Eagle, and the butifull Buzzard of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> Still Continue with us,<ref target="n26010309" n="9"/> Send <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Sarjt. Gass</name> and <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">G. Shannon</name> to the Salt makers who are on the Sea Coast to the S, W of us, to enquire after <name type="person" key="Willard, Alexander">Willard</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Weiser, Peter">Wiser</name> who have not yet returned. <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">R. Field</name>, <name type="person" key="Potts, John">potts</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Collins, John">Collins</name> the hunters who Set out on the 28th ulto. returned this evening after dark.    they reported that they had been about 15 miles up the river which falls into <name type="place" key="Youngs (Meriwether's) Bay">Meriwethers Bay</name> to the East of us,<ref target="n26010310" n="10"/> and had hunted the Country a considerable distance to East, and had proved unsucksesfull haveing killed one Deer and a fiew fowls, bearly as much as Subsisted them.    this reminded us of the necessity of takeing time by the forelock, and keep out several parties while we have yet a little meat before hand. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt Lewis</name> gave the Cheif <name type="person" key="Coboway">Cania</name> a par of Sattin breechies with which he appeared much pleased.—
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-01-03.04" n="">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Friday 3rd Jany. 1806.    hard Thunder hail and rain the greater part of last night    one of the hunters caught a large otter. <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Sergt. Gass</name> went over to the <name type="place" key="Saltmaking Camp (Oreg.)">Salt Camps</name>, about 10 oClock a number of the natives<ref target="n26010311" n="11"/> came to the fort.    in the evening three of our hunters<ref target="n26010312" n="12"/> came to the Fort    had killed nothing but one Deer one Swan and 4 ducks, also a raven which they eat on new years day to Satisfy their hunger.—


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-01-03.05" n="">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Friday 3rd.</hi>    The weather is still cloudy and wet. I set out this morning with one of the men<ref target="n26010313" n="13"/> to go to the <name type="place" key="Saltmaking Camp (Oreg.)">salt-works</name>, to see what progress those engaged in that business had made; and why some of them had not returned, as they had been expected for some time. We proceeded along a dividing ridge,<ref target="n26010314" n="14"/> expecting to pass the heads of some creeks, which intervened. We travelled all day and could see no game; and the rain still continued. In the evening we arrived at a place where two of the men had killed an elk some time ago.<ref target="n26010315" n="15"/> Here we struck up a fire, supped upon the marrow-bones and remained all night.


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-01-03.06" n="">
            <sp who="jw">
               <speaker>Whitehouse</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Friday Janry 3rd    We had hard thunder, hail &amp; Rain the greater part of last night, &amp; light showers of rain this morning; Two of our Men left the fort to go out hunting.    <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Serjeant Gass</name> went over to the Ocean in order to go to the <name type="place" key="Saltmaking Camp (Oreg.)">Camp</name> where some of our party 〈are〉 were making Salt.    About 10 o'Clock A. M. a number of Indians<ref target="n26010316" n="16"/> came to our Fort on a visit; they belonged to the <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsop</name> nation.    In the Evening three of our hunters<ref target="n26010317" n="17"/> returned to the Fort, &amp; had killed 1 Deer, 1 Swan, 2 Geese 4 Ducks &amp; a Raven.    The Raven they had eaten on New Years day, &amp; the remainder of the Game they brought in with them, but mentioned they had seen no Elk.    One of our hunters caught an Otter during last night.



</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n26010301" n="1">In <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookan</name> the term is <hi rend="italic">tia</hi>.  In the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinook</name> jargon it is <hi rend="italic">táyi</hi> which is borrowed from the Nootkan word <hi rend="italic">ta·yi,</hi>; all mean "chief."</note>
            <note xml:id="n26010302" n="2">The <name type="native_nation" key="Tillamook Indians">Tillamooks</name>; the direction should be southwest.</note>
            <note xml:id="n26010303" n="3">Probably the northwestern crow, <hi rend="italic">Corvus caurinus</hi> [AOU, 489], a new species. See also <ref n="1806-03-03" type="related">March 3, 1806</ref>. Cutright (LCPN), 273, 432; Holmgren, 29. Perhaps it was <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name> who drew a red vertical line through this passage about birds.</note>
            <note xml:id="n26010304" n="4">Probably the gray jay; see above, <ref n="1805-12-18" type="related">December 18, 1805</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n26010305" n="5">Perhaps the winter wren.</note>
            <note xml:id="n26010306" n="6">Possibly the golden-crowned sparrow, <hi rend="italic">Zonotrichia atricapilla</hi> [AOU, 557]. Burroughs, 258. The fox sparrow, <hi rend="italic">Passerella iliaca</hi> [AOU, 585], has also been suggested. Holmgren, 33.</note>
            <note xml:id="n26010307" n="7">In Roman mythology Opportunity, or Time (Saturn), was represented as having hair on the front of the head, but being bald behind. The expression has been used by Rabelais, Spenser, and Shakespeare.</note>
            <note xml:id="n26010308" n="8">Perhaps it was <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name> who added the red-inked parentheses around "or Tiá."</note>
            <note xml:id="n26010309" n="9">
               <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name> may have drawn the red vertical line through this passage about birds.</note>
            <note xml:id="n26010310" n="10">
               <name type="place" key="Youngs (Kilhow-a-nah-kle) River">Youngs River</name>, <name type="place" key="Clatsop County, Oreg.">Clatsop County</name>, <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 82.</note>
            <note xml:id="n26010311" n="11">Including <name type="person" key="Coboway">Coboway</name> and six other <name type="person" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsops</name>, according to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n26010312" n="12">
               <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">Reubin Field</name>, <name type="person" key="Collins, John">Collins</name>, and <name type="person" key="Potts, John">Potts</name>, according to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, but <name type="person" key="Potts, John">Potts</name> was not included in <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> enumeration of <ref n="1805-12-28" type="related">December 28</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n26010313" n="13">
               <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name>, according to <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n26010314" n="14">
               <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass's</name> account of his journey to the <name type="place" key="Saltmaking Camp (Oreg.)">saltworks</name> is not altogether clear, no directions or names being given, but the dividing ridge must be the high ground between <name type="place" key="Lewis and Clark (Fort, Netul) River">Lewis and Clark River</name> and the coast, <name type="place" key="Clatsop County, Oreg.">Clatsop County</name>, <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>. Various small streams run from the ridge toward the river, and it was the heads of these he hoped to clear, apparently without success. He was going generally south, and west toward the coast.</note>
            <note xml:id="n26010315" n="15">Somewhere along the ridge in <name type="place" key="Clatsop County, Oreg.">Clatsop County</name>, probably north of <name type="place" key="Cullaby Creek">Cullaby Creek</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n26010316" n="16">Including <name type="person" key="Coboway">Coboway</name> and six other <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsops</name>, report <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n26010317" n="17">
               <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">Reubin Field</name>, <name type="person" key="Collins, John">Collins</name>, and <name type="person" key="Potts, John">Potts</name>, but <name type="person" key="Potts, John">Potts</name> was not included in <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> list of <ref n="1805-12-28" type="related">December 28</ref>.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-01-02" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-01-04" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
