<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.introduction.v03">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">Introduction to Volume 3</title>
            <title type="sub">August 24, 1804-April 6, 1805</title>
            <author>Gary E. Moulton</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 3</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">August 25, 1804–April 6, 1805</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1987</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">1-4</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="category">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-03-03</date>
            <date/>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>
            <name/>Initial creation Transcribed</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="main">Introduction to Volume 3<lb/>
            <name type="place" key="Vermillion (White Stone) River (S. Dak.)">Vermillion River</name>, <name type="place" key="South Dakota">South Dakota</name> through Winter at <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name>, <name type="place" key="North Dakota">North Dakota</name>
         </head>
         <head type="sub">August 24, 1804–April 6, 1805</head>
         <div type="introduction">
            <p>
On August 25, 1804, while their three boats proceeded upriver, the two captains and several men went ashore near the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Vermillion (White Stone) River (S. Dak.)">Vermillion River</name> in present southeast <name type="place" key="South Dakota">South Dakota</name> to visit a hill which the Indians of the vicinity insisted was haunted by evil spirits. Moving on upstream past the mouth of the <name type="place" key="James (Jacque) River (S. Dak.)">James River</name>, they paused from August 28 to 31 at the <name type="place" key="Calumet Bluff (Nebr.)">Calumet Bluff</name> on the present <name type="place" key="Nebraska">Nebraska</name> side of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> to council with the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Yankton">Yankton</name>
               <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>, the first of this numerous tribe and the first of the truly nomadic Plains Indians they had met.</p>
            <p>
The captains were pleased with the council, but as they moved on they were increasingly anxious about <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">George Shannon</name>, the youngest member of the Corps of Discovery, who had been missing since August 27, when he was sent out to locate two stray horses. Mistakenly believing that the boats had gone ahead of him, <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name> hurried up the river trying to overtake them, although they were actually behind him. Not until September 11 did they overtake the young man, now weak from hunger.</p>
            <p>
The party was now entering the semi-arid High Plains, previously unknown to Anglo-Americans, and they were encountering some of the region's characteristic plant and animal species. In present northeast <name type="place" key="Nebraska">Nebraska</name> they first saw a prairie dog "town" and obtained a specimen of that animal. In modern <name type="place" key="South Dakota">South Dakota</name>, as September wore on, they also discovered the coyote, the pronghorn, the mule deer, the jackrabbit, and the magpie.</p>
            <p>
Some miles north of the <name type="place" key="White River">White River</name>, on September 16 and 17, they paused for two days to rest, dry out their baggage, and perhaps to make some decisions. From the first, the captains had intended to send back, before winter, a small party of men carrying dispatches, journals, and specimens to be shipped to <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">President Jefferson</name>. They had never found an opportune time, and it was here that they decided not to send out the return party until the following spring. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> wrote several pages of journals during the two days halt, the first such daily journal-keeping he appears to have done since May.</p>
            <p>
Leaving the rest camp, they traveled around the remarkable <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Big Bend of the">"Grand Detour" of the Missouri River</name> and arrived on September 24 at the mouth of the present <name type="place" key="Bad (Teton) River (S. Dak.)">Bad River</name>, which they called the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name>, for it was there that they met a large number of the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name>
               <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>. Here they had their first really hazardous and potentially violent encounter with Indians on the journey, arising from the arrogance of some of the chiefs, disagreements among the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name> leaders, and very likely confusion resulting from the lack of a <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name> interpreter. The <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name> attempted to bully the Corps of Discovery as they did trading parties, but the captains were not prepared to submit. As they saw it, they represented the dignity of the United States, and their pride and a military conception of security required that they show a readiness to fight. Rightly or wrongly they believed that the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Tetons</name> planned a surprise attack on their boats and they remained uneasy until they left those bands behind.</p>
            <p>
A few days later, on October 8, they reached the villages of the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> in what is now northern <name type="place" key="South Dakota">South Dakota</name>. Their reception by these sedentary farmers was far more encouraging than that of the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Tetons</name>, and the party remained until the eleventh. The captains hoped to serve as peacemakers between the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> and the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name> farther upriver and as they departed they took an <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> chief with them to act as ambassador to the two tribes. On October 13 <name type="person" key="Newman, John">Private John Newman</name> was arrested and tried for "having uttered repeated expressions of a highly criminal and mutinous nature"; the verdict was guilty and he received seventy-five lashes and was dishonorably discharged, although he remained with the party until spring doing hard labor. <name type="person" key="Newman, John">Newman</name> was repentant, but the captains refused to reinstate him.</p>
            <p>
The party arrived on October 25 at the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> villages, 164 days and about 1,510 miles out from <name type="place" key="Camp Dubois (Camp Wood, River Dubois) (Ill.)">Camp Dubois</name>. Here they were met with a mixed reception and informed the Indian leaders of the change in official sovereignty. Winter was near and the Indians and various white traders told the captains that the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> would soon freeze; they decided, therefore, to discharge some of their French boatmen and make their winter quarters in the vicinity of these friendly tribes, from whom they could obtain corn to supplement the results of their hunting. On November 3 the party began the construction of <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name>, on the eastern side of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> a few miles below the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Knife River">Knife River</name> in west-central <name type="place" key="North Dakota">North Dakota</name> and nearly opposite the lower <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> village.</p>
            <p>
The stockaded log fort would be their home for five months, during a bitter Northern Plains winter in which temperatures sometimes dropped to over forty degrees below zero Fahrenheit and venturing outside was likely to result in frostbite. Nevertheless, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> describes the party as being in good spirits. It was by no means a period of idleness, although <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> notes playing backgammon at least once. Hunting, in spite of the fierce cold, was frequently necessary to provide meat. Indians visited the fort constantly and the chiefs, at least, expected to be entertained by the captains. The smiths were kept busy making tomahawks for the visiting warriors, in exchange for corn. The men visited the villages regularly and some of them contracted venereal disease as a result.</p>
            <p>
For the captains the period was occupied not only with diplomacy but with attempts to counter <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name> attacks on the village tribes, with preparations for continuing their journey in the spring, and with evaluating what they had already learned. Traders and Indians provided information that went into the large map of the West that <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> prepared, still largely conjectural beyond <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name> but now incorporating Indian information about rivers and mountains west to the <name type="place" key="Continental Divide">continental divide</name>. The <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> villages were a center of intertribal trade, and the captains met members of the <name type="native_nation" key="Cheyenne Indians">Cheyenne</name>, <name type="native_nation" key="Assiniboine Indians">Assiniboine</name>, and <name type="native_nation" key="Cree Indians">Cree</name> tribes.</p>
            <p>
Soon after the Corps of Discovery settled in for the winter, more traders arrived from <name type="place" key="Canada">Canada</name> representing the competing Hudson's Bay and North West companies. The captains had no objections to the British engaging in legitimate trade with the Indians on what was now American soil, but they suspected that the traders were trying to win the political allegiance of the village tribes away from the United States. The traders consistently denied such intrigues, but the Americans were not convinced and even believed that the British were trying to sabotage the expedition itself.</p>
            <p>
At <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name> other persons were added to the party. <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Toussaint Charbonneau</name>, an independent Canadian trader living at one of the <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> villages (now called <name type="place" key="Sakakawea, N. Dak.">Sakakawea</name>), had two <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshone</name> wives, natives of the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky Mountains</name> along the <name type="place" key="Continental Divide">continental divide</name> and later captives of the <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name>. <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name> hired out his services and those of his consorts as interpreters for the trip across the mountains; in fact, only one of his wives, <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name>, who gave birth to a son during the winter, actually made the trip. In time she became the most famous member of the party after the two leaders themselves. <name type="person" key="Lepage, Jean Baptiste">Baptiste Lepage</name>, another Frenchman living with the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>, also joined up as an enlisted soldier to replace <name type="person" key="Newman, John">Newman</name>.</p>
            <p>
In March the ice began breaking up in the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, and the Corps of Discovery started preparations for a departure in early April. Having decided to send the keelboat back to <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> with the returning soldiers and discharged <hi rend="italic">engagés</hi>, they built several new canoes from cottonwood logs and prepared specimens, journals, and maps to send back to <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, including a live prairie dog and several live birds. The permanent party now consisted of the two captains, three sergeants, twenty-three privates, <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name>, <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name>, <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name> and her infant, and <name type="person" key="York">York</name>. Up to <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name> the route had been known to whites and even mapped to some degree, but now the party faced a long journey through country known only in part from sketchy Indian information. Just five weeks short of a year after leaving <name type="place" key="Camp Dubois (Camp Wood, River Dubois) (Ill.)">Camp Dubois</name>, they set out on April 7, with still half a continent to cross before they reached the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>.
</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
