<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.about.projectteam">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">Project Team</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2005</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
              <term>About</term>
            </keywords>
           <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>About the Site</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-11-07</date>
            <date>2006-06-07</date>
            <date>2005-11-18</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>
            <name>Becky Potter</name>Update content Update content Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-11-23</date>
            <name>Jessica Dussault and Laura Weakly</name>
            Updated staff involvement
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="additional">
            <head type="main">Principal Investigators</head>
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <hi rend="bold">Katherine Walter</hi> (2003-present), co-director of the Center for Digital Research in the Humanities at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln and chair of Digital Initiatives and Special Collections at UNL Libraries, is co-principal investigator of the Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online project.<lb/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="additional">
            <head type="main">Project Team</head>
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <hi rend="bold">Jason Bougger </hi>(2002-present) is lead systems administrator in Computing Operations and Research Services at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln Libraries.<lb/>
               </item>
               <item>
                 <hi rend="bold">Erica Corwin</hi> (2002-present) is Electronic Marketing Coordinator at the University of Nebraska Press. She analyzes Web traffic and responds to users' e-mails.<lb/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi rend="bold">Karin Dalziel</hi> (2016-present) is the Digital Design / Development Specialist for the Center for Digital Research in the Humanities at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln. In 2016, she redesigned the website and contributed to the migration of the site into a new framework.<lb/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi rend="bold">Jessica Dussault</hi> (2016-present) is a programmer and analyst for the Center for Digital Research in the Humanities at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln. She contributed to the 2016 migration of the site into a new framework.<lb/>
               </item>
               <item>
                 <hi rend="bold">Jana Faust</hi> (2002-present) is co-project manager for the Journals of Lewis and Clark Online edition and Digital Assets and IT Manager at the University of Nebraska Press.<lb/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi rend="bold">Brian Pytlik Zillig</hi> (2002-present) is co-project manager for the Journals of Lewis and Clark Online edition and digital initiatives librarian at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln. Brian has spearheaded development of the XSLT stylesheet and XML search.<lb/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi rend="bold">Greg Tunink</hi> (2016-present) is a programmer and analyst for the Center for Digital Research in the Humanities at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln. He contributed to the 2016 migration of the site into a new framework.<lb/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi rend="bold">Laura Weakly</hi> (2003-present) is metadata encoding specialist in Digital Initiatives and Special Collections at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln. Laura is primarily responsible for the encoding of the journals of Lewis, Clark, Ordway, Floyd, Gass, and Whitehouse, as well as the supplemental materials.<lb/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="additional">
            <head type="main">Past Project Team Members</head>
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                 <hi rend="bold">Gary Dunham</hi> (2003-2007) was co-principal investigator of the Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online project and was director of the University of Nebraska Press.<lb/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi rend="bold">Zach Bajaber</hi> (2002-2007) is a digital resources designer in Digital Initiatives and Special Collections at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln. Zach assisted in prototype and special character encoding, database development and searchability features.<lb/>
               </item>
               <item>
                 <hi rend="bold">Ann Baker</hi> (2005-2007) is an Editorial, Design, and Production Manager at the University of Nebraska Press. Ann is responsible for copyediting and proofreading new content.<lb/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi rend="bold">Brett Barney</hi> (2002-2007) is research assistant professor in Digital Initiatives and Special Collections at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln. Brett developed the model encoding and Document Type Definition and worked on the system for finding personal, place, and Native nation names.<lb/>
               </item>

               <item>
                  <hi rend="bold">Beth Burke</hi> (2005-2007) is a text encoding specialist in Digital Initiatives and Special Collections at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln. Beth is primarily responsible for acquiring necessary permissions to add supplementary material, such as additional reference books, articles, and multimedia, to the website. She also works on scanning and encoding the additional material.<lb/>
               </item>
               <item>
                 <hi rend="bold">Courtney Burkholder</hi> (2002-2004) is the Director at Texas Tech University Press. Before the site launched, Courtney created the initial flyout menu system and coordinated the multimedia portion of the Web site.<lb/>
               </item>


               <item>
                 <hi rend="bold">Elizabeth Demers</hi> (2002-2005) is Senior Acquisitions Editor at Johns Hopkins University Press. During the project, Elizabeth recommended additional texts and represented the project at academic conferences.<lb/>
               </item>

               <item>
                  <hi rend="bold">Andy Jewell</hi> (2004-2007) is assistant professor of digital projects at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln Libraries. He encodes the supplementary scholarly texts.<lb/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi rend="bold">Renae Morehead</hi> (2004-2005) is a freelance copyeditor living in Lincoln, Nebraska. Renae copyedited new content and verified that all corrections had been made to new material before it went live.<lb/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi rend="bold">Rebecca Potter</hi> (2005) was a text encoding specialist in Digital Initiatives and Special Collections at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln. Rebecca was responsible for adding supplementary material, such as additional reference books, articles, and multimedia, to the website. She also worked on transforming HTML files to XML.<lb/>
               </item>

               <item>
                 <hi rend="bold">Annie Shahan </hi>(2002-2007) is Senior Designer at the University of Nebraska Press. Throughout the project, Annie has been responsible for the overall visual design of the online edition.<lb/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi rend="bold">Melissa Sinner</hi> (2002-2003) is digital resources editor for the University of Nebraska-Lincoln Libraries. Melissa worked on the pilot stage of the project.<lb/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi rend="bold">Jamie Tallman</hi> (2006-2007) is a text encoding specialist in Digital Initiatives and Special Collections at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln. Jamie is primarily responsible for adding supplementary material, such as additional reference books, articles, and images, to the website. He has worked extensively on the name key index file.<lb/>
               </item>

               <item>
                 <hi rend="bold">Joeth Zucco</hi> (2003-2007) is Senior Project Editor at the University of Nebraska Press. Over the course of the project, Joeth proofread the Journals text for errors and inconsistencies.<lb/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="additional">
            <head type="main">Former Student Workers and Interns</head>
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <hi rend="bold">Gretchen Albers</hi> (2003) was an acquisitions assistant at the University of Nebraska Press. She worked on standardized spelling and reciprocal links.<lb/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi rend="bold">Matthew Pearson</hi> (2005-2007) is a graduate research assistant in Digital Initiatives and Special Collections at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln. He digitized the map images and encoded supplementary texts.<lb/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi rend="bold">Abigail Sedlacek</hi> (2004) was a student worker at the University of Nebraska Press. In the early stages of the project, Abigail researched permissions issues and reciprocal links.<lb/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi rend="bold">Anastasia Smallcomb</hi> (2005-2007) is a student worker in Digital Initiatives and Special Collections at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln.  She proofread the name key index file. <lb/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
