<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1803-09-11">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">September 11, 1803</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2003</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               
               
               
               
               
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml" n="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc" n="Clark, William">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 2</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">August 30, 1803–August 24, 1804</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1986</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">79-80</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
         <geoDecl datum="WGS" xml:id="lc.geo.1803-09-11.01">
            <placeName/>
            <geo>39.5094 -81.0709</geo>
            <note>South of Grandview Island, East shore</note>
         </geoDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Journal Entries</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2003-12-10</date>
            <date/>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>
            <name/>Initial creation Transcribed</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1803-09-11">September 11, 1803</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1803-09-11.01" n="lc.geo.1803-09-11.01">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>11th September</date>
               </ab>
               <p>
Set out about sunrise, passed <name type="place" key="Sunfish Creek">Sunfish creek</name> 1 mile &amp;c &amp;c    entered the long reach, so called from the <name type="place" key="Ohio River">Ohio</name> running in strait direction for 18 miles    in this reach there are 5 Islands from three to 2 miles in length each—<ref target="n02091101" n="1"/>  observed a number of squirrels<ref target="n02091102" n="2"/> swiming the <name type="place" key="Ohio River">Ohio</name> and universally passing from the W. to the East shore    they appear to be making to the south; perhaps it may be mast or food which they are in serch of but I should reather suppose that it is climate which is their object as I find no difference in the quantity of mast on both sides of this river it being abundant on both except the beach nut which appears extreemly scarce this season, the walnuts and Hickory nuts the usual food of the squirrell appears in great abundance on either side of the river—<ref target="n02091103" n="3"/>  I made my dog<ref target="n02091104" n="4"/> take as many each day as I had occation for, they wer fat and I thought them when fryed a pleasent food—    many of these squirrils wer black,<ref target="n02091105" n="5"/> they swim very light on the water and make pretty good speed—  <name type="person" key="Seaman">my dog</name> was of the newfoundland breed very active strong and docile, he would take the squirel in the water kill them and swiming bring them in his mouth to the boat. we lay this night below the fifth Island in the long reach on the E. side of the river having come 26 miles<ref target="n02091106" n="6"/>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n02091101" n="1">The islands today along the <name type="place" key="Long Reach Island">Long Reach</name> are <name type="place" key="Paden Island">Paden</name>, <name type="place" key="Williamson Island">Williamson</name>, <name type="place" key="Wells Island">Wells</name>, <name type="place" key="Mill Creek Island">Mill Creek</name>, and <name type="place" key="Grand View Island">Grand View</name> islands.</note>
            <note xml:id="n02091102" n="2">These would be gray squirrels, <hi rend="italic">Sciurus carolinensis;</hi> such migrations are rare today, the squirrel population having been much reduced. Hall, 1:417; Cutright (HLCJ), 140. Apart from two brief lists of trees and fish, this is the first of the many natural history observations in <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> journals. His interest in plants and animals, which he shared with <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, dated from childhood. His command of technical terms, especially in his botanical descriptions, was impressive, but he seldom used the Linnaean system of Latin names for species, nor did he attempt to bestow such names on the many new species observed during the expedition. He carried several reference works with him that assisted him in writing his descriptions. These included <name type="person" key="Barton, Benjamin Smith">Benjamin Smith Barton's</name>
               <hi rend="italic">Elements of Botany; or, Outlines of the Natural History of Vegetables</hi> (<name type="place" key="Philadelphia, Pa.">Philadelphia</name>, 1803); John Miller, <hi rend="italic">An Illustration of the Sexual System of Linnaeus,</hi> Vol. 1 (London, 1779); and Miller's <hi rend="italic">An Illustration of the Termini Botanici of Linnaeus,</hi> Vol. 2 (London, 1789). Jackson (SBLC), 5–8; Cutright (LCPN), 1–25, 31.</note>
            <note xml:id="n02091103" n="3">The "beach" nut is <hi rend="italic">Fagus grandifolia</hi> Ehrh., beech nut; the walnuts could be <hi rend="italic">Juglans nigra</hi> L., black walnut, and/or <hi rend="italic">J. cinerea</hi> L., butternut, white walnut, found on river terraces; the hickory nuts can be several species of <hi rend="italic">Carya.</hi> Fernald, 540, 526; Braun, 95–97.</note>
            <note xml:id="n02091104" n="4">The first mention of <name type="person" key="Seaman">Seaman</name>, or <name type="person" key="Seaman">Scannon</name>, whose name appears infrequently in the journals. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> may have purchased him before reaching <name type="place" key="Pittsburgh, Pa.">Pittsburgh</name> and he served as hunter, watchdog, and companion. Though not mentioned after July 1806, it has been supposed that he was still with the party on its return in September 1806. A stream in <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name> was apparently named for him, leading Don Jackson to conjecture the latest spelling of his name. Jackson (DS); Osgood (ODS).</note>
            <note xml:id="n02091105" n="5">A melanistic color phase. Cutright (HLCJ), 141 n. 48; Hall, 1:417.</note>
            <note xml:id="n02091106" n="6">This camp, from <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> description, would be below present <name type="place" key="Grand View Island">Grand View Island</name>, opposite <name type="place" key="Grand View, Ohio">Grand View</name>, <name type="place" key="Ohio">Ohio</name>, in <name type="place" key="Tyler County, W. Va.">Tyler County</name>, <name type="place" key="West Virginia">West Virginia</name>. But see below, <ref n="lc.jrn.1803-09-12" type="related">September 12</ref>, n. 1. Thwaites (EWT), 4:121.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1803-09-10" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1803-09-12" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
