<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-03-10">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
March 10, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 6</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">November 2, 1805–March 22, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1990</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">398-401</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">276</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">197</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jw">Joseph Whitehouse</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 11</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of Joseph Whitehouse, May 14, 1804–April 2, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1997</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">427</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc/>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-09-01</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1806-03-10">March 10, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-03-10.01" n="">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Monday March 10th 1806.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
About 1 P. M. it became fair and we sent out two parties of hunters on this side of the <name type="place" key="Lewis and Clark (Fort, Netul) River">Netul</name> the one below and the other above.    we also directed a party<ref target="n28090101" n="1"/> to set out early in the morning and pass the bay and hunt beyond the <name type="place" key="Youngs (Kilhow-a-nah-kle) River">Kilhowanackkle</name>.    from the last we have considerable hope as we have as yet hunted but little in that quarter.    it blew hard all day.    in the evening the Indians departed. The hunters who were over the <name type="place" key="Lewis and Clark (Fort, Netul) River">Netull</name> the other day informed us that they measured a pine tree, (or fir No 1)<ref target="n28090102" n="2"/> which at the hight of a man's breast was 42 feet in the girth about three feet higher, or as high as a tall man could reach, it was 40 feet in the girth which was about the circumpherence for at least 200 feet without a limb, and that it was very lofty above the commencement of the limbs.    from the appearance of other trees of this speceis of fir and their account of this tree, I think it may be safely estimated at 300 feet.    it had every appearance of being perfectly sound. The black and white duck are small abut the size of the blue-winged teal, or reather larger.    the male is beautifully variagated with black and white.    the white occupys the sides of the head, breast and back, black, the tail feathers of the wings two tufts of feathers which cover the upper part of the wings when foalded, the neck and head.    the female is darker or has much less white about her. I take this to be the same speceis of duck common to the <name type="place" key="Atlantic Ocean">Atlantic</name> coast, and frequently called the butterbox.    the beak is wide and short, and as well as the legs, of a dark colour.    the flesh of this duck is very well flavored.    the brown duck<ref target="n28090103" n="3"/> is much in form like the duckinmallard, tho' not much more than half it's size.    the colour is an uniform mixture of yellowish and dark brown.    there is nothing remarkable in the appearance of this duck it generally resorts the same kind of grassey marshes with the duckinmallard and feeds in a similar manner, on grass seed, and roots.    both these ducks are common to the river for some distance above tide water as well as below. The black duck<ref target="n28090104" n="4"/> is about the size of the bluewinged teal.    their colour is a duskey black the breast and belley somewhat lighter than the other parts, or a dark brown.    the legs stand longitudinally with the body, and the bird when on shore stands of cours very erect.    the legs and feet are of a dark brown, the toes are four on each foot, a short one at the heel and three long toes in front, which are unconnected with a web.    the webs are attatched to each sides of the several joints of the toe, and divided by deep sinuses at each joint.    the web assuming in the intermediate part an eliptical figure.    the beak is about two inches long, streight, flated on the sides, and tapering to a sharp point.    the upper chap somewhat longest, and bears on it's base at the joining of the head, a little conic protuberance of a cartelagenous substace, being redish brown at the point.    the beak is of an ivory white colour.    the eye dark.    these ducks usually associate in large flocks, and are very noisey; their note being a sharp shrill whistle.    they are usually fat and agreeably flavored; and feed principally on moss, and other vegitable productions of the water.    we did not meet with them untill we reached tide-water, but I believe them not exclusively confined to that district at all seasons, as I have noticed the same duck on many parts of the Rivers <name type="place" key="Ohio River">Ohio</name> and <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name>.    the gizzard and liver are also remarkably large in this fowl.    the divers are the same with those of the Atlantic States.    the smaller species<ref target="n28090105" n="5"/> has some white feathers about the rump with no perceptable tail and is very active and quck in it's motion; the body is of a redish brown.    the beak sharp and somewhat curved like that of the pheasant.    the toes are not connected but webed like those discribed of the black duck.    the larger speceis<ref target="n28090106" n="6"/> are about the size of the teal and can flye a short distance which the small one scarcely ever attapts.    they have a short tail.    their colour is also an uniform brickredish brown, the beak is streight and pointed.    the feet are of the same form of the other speceis and the legs are remarkably thin and flat one edge being in front.    the food of both speceis is fish, and the flesh unfit for uce.    the bluewinged teal are a very excellent duck, and are the same with those of the <name type="place" key="Atlantic Ocean">Atlantic</name> coast.— There are some other speceis of ducks which shall be hereafter discribed as I may hereafter have an opportunity to examine them.—
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-03-10.02" n="">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Monday March 10th 1806</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
about 1 P. M. it became fair and we Sent out two parties of hunters on this Side of the <name type="place" key="Lewis and Clark (Fort, Netul) River">Netul</name>, one above and the other below, we also derected a party to Set out early in the morning and pass <name type="place" key="Youngs (Meriwether's) Bay">Meriwethers Bay</name> and hunt beyond the <name type="place" key="Youngs (Kilhow-a-nah-kle) River">Kilhow anak kle</name>.    from the last we have considerable hope, as we have as yet hunted but little in that quarter.    it blew hard all day, in the evening the Indians  departed. The Hunters, S. R. F. &amp; F.<ref target="n28090107" n="7"/> who were over the netul the other day informed us that they measured a 2d tree of the fir Speces (No. 1) as high as a man Could reach, was 39 feet in the girth; it tapered but very little for about 200 feet without any Considerable limbs, and that it was a very lofty above the Commencement of the limbs.    from the appearance of other Species of fir, and their account of this tree, I think it might safely estimated at 300 feet.    it had every appearance of being perfectly Sound in every part—.</p>
               <p>
The brown Duck is much in form like the Duckinmallard, tho' not much more than half it's Size.    the colour is one uniform mixture of yellowish and dark brown.    there is nothing remarkable in the colour of this duck; it resorts the Same kind of grassy marshes with the Duckinmallard, and feeds in a Similar manner, on grass, Seeds &amp; roots.    both these ducks are common to the river for Some distance above tide water as well as below. The black Duck is about the Size of the bluewinged teel.    their colour is a duskey black the breast and belly Somewhat lighter than the other parts, or a dark brown.    the legs Stand longitudianally with the body, and the Bird when on Shore Stands very erect.    the legs and feet are of a dark brown, the toes are four on each foot, a short one on the heel and three long toes in front which are unconnected with a web.    the web is atached to each Side of the Several joints of the toes, and devided by deep Sinuses at each joint.    the web assumeing in the intermediate part an elipticle figure.    the beak is about two inches long, Streight, flated on the Sides, and tapering to a Sharp point.    the upper chap Somewhat longest and bears on its base at the joining of the head, a little conic protuberance of a cartelaganous Substance, being redish brown.    the beak is of a ivery white colour.    the eye dark.    these ducks usially associate in large flocks, and are very noisey; their note being a Sharp shrill whistle.    they are usially fat and tolerably flavoured; and feed on moss and other vegitable productions of the water.    we did not meet with them untill we reached tide water, I have noticed the Same duck on maney parts of the ohio an <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name>.    the Gizzard and liver are also remarkably large in this fowl—. The Divers are the Same with those of the atlantic States.    the Smaller Species has some white feathers about the rump and no perceptable tail and is very active and quick in its motion; the body is of a redish brown.    the beak sharp and Somewhat curved like that of the Pheasant the toes are not connected but webd. like those discribed of the black duck. The large Species are about the Size of the teal &amp;c.    the food of both those Species is fish.    and their flesh is unfit for use.</p>
               <p>
The bluewinged teal are a very excellent duck, and are the Same with those of the <name type="place" key="Atlantic Ocean">atlantic</name> coast.— There are some other Species of ducks which Shall be hereafter discribd. as I may hereafter have an oppertunity of exameneing them.

</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-03-10.03" n="">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Monday 10th March 1806. Showers of hail and a little Snow intermixed. Several men<ref target="n28090108" n="8"/> went out a hunting.    high winds &amp;C.


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-03-10.04" n="">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
On the 10th, we had changeable weather, with snow showers. At noon two more hunters went out.


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-03-10.05" n="">
            <sp who="jw">
               <speaker>Whitehouse</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Monday March 10th    We had Showers of rain, with Snow and hail.    several of our Men went out a hunting.    the wind blew hard this day.    Our party are engaged at the fort in repairing the Canoes &amp; dressing of Skins &amp;ca.


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n28090101" n="1">Including <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name>, <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Joseph Field</name>, and <name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">Frazer</name>, as <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> notes in the next entry.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28090102" n="2">Sitka spruce; see above, <ref n="1806-02-04" type="related">February 4, 1806</ref>. Two red vertical lines go through several lines about the spruce and bufflehead, perhaps done by <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28090103" n="3">See <ref n="1806-03-05" type="related">March 5, 1806</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28090104" n="4">The American coot. Another red vertical line here.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28090105" n="5">The pied-billed grebe, <hi rend="italic">Podilymbus podiceps</hi> [AOU, 6]. Burroughs, 178; Holmgren, 29.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28090106" n="6">The red-necked grebe, <hi rend="italic">Podiceps grisegena</hi> [AOU, 2], or the horned grebe, <hi rend="italic">P. auritus</hi> [AOU, 3]. Burroughs, 177–78; Holmgren, 29.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28090107" n="7">
               <name type="person" key="Shields, John">Shields</name>, <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">Reubin Field</name>, and <name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">Frazer</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28090108" n="8">Two parties, according to the captains, along the <name type="place" key="Lewis and Clark (Fort, Netul) River">Lewis and Clark River</name>, and another, 
consisting of <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name>, <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">Reubin Field</name>, and <name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">Frazer</name>, to go beyond <name type="place" key="Youngs (Kilhow-a-nah-kle) River">Youngs River</name>. See the captains' entries for March 10 and <ref n="1806-03-11" type="related">11</ref>.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-03-09" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-03-11" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
