<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-03-18">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
March 18, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 6</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">November 2, 1805–March 22, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1990</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">429-432</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">278</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">199</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jw">Joseph Whitehouse</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 11</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of Joseph Whitehouse, May 14, 1804–April 2, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1997</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">429</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc/>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-09-02</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1806-03-18">March 18, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-03-18.01" n="">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Tuesday March 18th 1806.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name> was taken last night with a violent pain in his side. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name> blead him.    several of the men are complaining of being unwell.    it is truly unfortunate that they should be sick at the moment of our departure.    we directed <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Sergt. Pryor</name> to prepare the two Canoes which <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name> brought last evening for his mess.    they wanted some knees to strengthen them and several cracks corked and payed.    he completed them except the latter operation which the frequent showers in the course of the day prevented as the canoes could not be made sufficiently dry even with the assistance of fire. <name type="person" key="Coboway">Comowooll</name> and two <name type="native_nation" key="Cathlamet Indians">Cathlahmahs</name> visited us today; we suffered them to remain all night.    this morning we gave <name type="person" key="Delashelwilt">Delashelwilt</name> a certificate of his good deportment &amp;c. and also a list of our names, after which we dispatched him to his village with his female band. These lists of our names we have given to several of the natives and also paisted up a copy in our room.    the object of these lists we stated in the preamble of the same as follows (viz)<ref target="n29031801" n="1"/> "The object of this list is, that through the medium of some civilized person who may see the same, it may be made known to the informed world, that the party consisting of the persons whoes names are hereunto annexed, and who were sent out by the government of the U' States in May 1804 to explore the interior of the Continent of North America, did penetrate the same by way of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> and <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> Rivers, to the discharge of the latter into the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific Ocean</name>, where they arrive on the 14th November 1805, and from whence they departed the [<hi rend="italic">blank</hi>] day of March 1806 on their return to the United States by the same rout they had come out."—    on the back of some of these lists we added a sketch of the connection of the upper branches of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> with those of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Columbia</name>, particularly of it's main <name type="place"
                        key="Salmon (Lewis's, Main Fork Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">S. E. branch</name>, on which we also delineated the track we had come and that we meant to pursue on our return where the same happened to very. There seemed so many chances against our government ever obtaining a regular report, though the medium of the savages and the traders of this coast that we declined making any.    our party are also too small to think of leaving any of them to return to the U' States by sea, particularly as we shall be necessarily divided into three or four parties on our return in order to accomplish the objects we have in view;<ref target="n29031802" n="2"/> and at any rate we shall reach the United States in all human probability much earlier than a man could who must in the event of his being left here depend for his passage to the United States on the traders of the coast who may not return immediately to the U' States or if they should, might probably spend the next summer in trading with the natives before they would set out on their return.    this evening <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name> went in quest of his traps, and took an Otter. <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Joseph Fields</name> killed an Elk.— The Indians repeated to us the names of eighteen distinct tribes residing on the S. E. coast who spoke the <name type="native_nation" key="Tillamook Indians">Killamucks</name> language,<ref target="n29031803" n="3"/> and beyound those six others who spoke a different language which they did not comprehend.
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-03-18.02" n="">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Tuesday March 17th 1806</hi>
                     <ref target="n29031804" n="4"/>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name> was taken last night with a violent pain in his Side. I bled him. Several of the men are complaining of being unwell.    it is truly unfortunate that they Should be Sick at the moment of our departure. Derected <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Sergt. Pryor</name> to prepare the two Indian Canoes which we had purchased for his mess.    they wanted Some knees to Strengthen them, and Several cracks corked and payed.    he compleated them except paying.    the frequent Showers of rain prevented the Canoes drying Sufficient to pay them even with the assistance of fire.—</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Coboway">Commorwool</name> and two <name type="native_nation" key="Cathlamet Indians">Cathlahmahs</name> visited us to day; we Suffered them to remain all night.    this morning we gave <name type="person" key="Delashelwilt">Delashelwilt</name> a certificate of his good deportment &amp;c. and also a list of our names, after which we dispatched him to his village with his female band. Those list's of our Names we have given to Several of the nativs, and also pasted up a Copy in our room.    the Object of these lists we Stated in the preamble of the Same as follows Viz: "The Object of this list is, that through the medium of Some civilized person who may See the Same, it may be made known to the informed world, that the party consisting of the persons whose names are hereunto annexed, and who were Sent out by the Government of the United States in May 1804, to explore the interior of the Continent of North America, did penetrate the Same by way of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> and <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> rivers, to the discharge of the latter into <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">the Pacific Ocian</name>, where they arrived on the 14th of November 1805, and from whence they departed the [<hi rend="italic">blank</hi>] day of March 1806 on their return to the United States by the Same rout they had come out."</p>
               <p>
On the back of lists we added a Sketch of the continent of the upper branches of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> with those of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>, particularly of its <name type="place"
                        key="Salmon (Lewis's, Main Fork Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">upper N. E. branch or Lewis's River</name>, on which we also delineated the track we had Came and that we ment to pursue on our return, when the Same happened to vary. There Seemes So many chances against our governments ever obtaining a regular report, through the medium of the Savages, and the traders of this Coast that we decline makeing any. Our party are too small to think of leaveing any of them to return to the Unt. States by Sea, particularly as we Shall be necessarily devided into two or three parties on our return in order to accomplish the Object we have in View; and at any rate we Shall reach the U, States in all humain probabillity much earlier than a man Could who must in the event of his being left here depend for his passage to the U, State on the traders of the Coast, who may not return imediately to the U, States.    or if they should, might probably Spend the next Summer in tradeing with the nativs before they would Set out on their return. This evening <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name> went in quest of his traps, and took an otter. <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Joseph Field</name> killd and Elk.— The Indians repeated to us Eighteen distinct Nati[ons?] resideing on the S S. E Coast who Speak the <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Tillamook Indians">Kil a mox</name>
                  </hi> language or understand it.    and beyend those Six other Nations which Speak a different language which they did not comprehend.</p>
               <p>
The 2d Species of Seawreck<ref target="n29031805" n="5"/> which I saw on the coast to the S. S. E. near the <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Tillamook Indians">Kil â mox</name>
                  </hi> nation.    it resembles a large pumpkin, it is Solid and it's Specific Gravity reather greater than the water, tho' it is Sometimes thrown out by the waves.    it is of a pale yellowish brown colour.    the rhind Smooth and consistency harder than that of the pumpkin, tho' easily cut with a knife.    there are Some fibers of a lighter colour and much harder than any other part which pass Longitudinally through the pulp or fleshey Substance which forms the interior of this marine production.—.—.
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-03-18.03" n="">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Tuesday 18th March 1806.—    a Showery morning of rain and hail. Some Thunder.    we repair the Small canoes.    4 men went over to the prarie near the coast to take a canoe which belongd to the <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clotsop Indians</name>, as we are in want of it.<ref target="n29031806" n="6"/>    in the evening they returned 2 of them by land and killd. an Elk.<ref target="n29031807" n="7"/>    the others took the canoe near the fort and concealed it, as the chief of the <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clotsops</name> is now here.


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-03-18.04" n="">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Tuesday 18th.</hi>    The weather was much like that of yesterday, and some hail fell in the course of the day. Some of the men are repairing the small canoes, and making preparations to return up the river, as soon as the weather will permit. One of the hunters<ref target="n29031808" n="8"/> killed an elk.


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-03-18.05" n="">
            <sp who="jw">
               <speaker>Whitehouse</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Tuesday March 18th    We had showers of rain, some hail &amp; thunder this morning.    the hands were employ'd in repairing our small Canoe, &amp; getting everything in readiness in order to ascend the River on our way homewards.—    Our officers sent 4 Men over the River, to a Priari which lay near the Ocean in order to get a small Canoe which belonged to the <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsop Indians</name>.    They returned in the Evening with the Canoe.<ref target="n29031809" n="9"/>    They had put 2 Men of the party on shore who also returned having killed an Elk on their way to the Fort.



</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n29031801" n="1">While the party was preparing to leave, the Russian ship <hi rend="italic">Juno,</hi> out of <name type="place" key="New Archangel, Alaska">New Archangel (Sitka)</name> in <name type="place" key="Alaska">Alaska</name>, commanded by <name type="person" key="Rezanov, Nicolai">Nicolai Rezanov</name>, was attempting to cross the <name type="place" key="Columbia Bar">Columbia bar</name>. It was finally driven off by the storm of March 21. <name type="person" key="Rezanov, Nicolai">Rezanov</name> was seeking a more hospitable place than <name type="place" key="Alaska">Alaska</name> for a Russian settlement. His failure at this time not only prevented a possible confrontation with <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> but kept the Russians from gaining a foothold on the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>. On June 12, 1806, Captain <name type="person" key="Hill, Samuel">Samuel Hill's</name>
               <hi rend="italic">Lydia,</hi> of <name type="place" key="Boston, Mass.">Boston</name> (see above, <ref n="1805-11-06" type="related">November 6</ref> and <ref n="1805-11-24" type="related">24</ref>, 1805), entered the mouth of the river. The Indians told him about their American visitors, showed him medals given them, and gave him at least one copy of the declaration and muster roll. The news did not reach the United States by this route until after the party's safe return to <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>. The ultimate fate of the documents is unknown. Jewitt, 174; Ruby &amp; Brown (CITC), 108–10; Chevigny, 105–24; Jackson (LLC), 2:300.</note>
            <note xml:id="n29031802" n="2">The first indication of the captains' intention to divide the party on the return journey, which they did on leaving <name type="place" key="Lolo (Travelers' Rest) Creek (Mont.)">Travelers' Rest</name> in <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name> on <ref n="1806-07-03" type="related">July 3, 1806</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n29031803" n="3">These "Nations" may well be villages belonging to some larger group, as on <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> maps of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>. The coast of <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name> and northern <name type="place" key="California">California</name> was the home of peoples speaking a medley of languages of several major language families. The <name type="native_nation" key="Tillamook Indians">Tillamooks</name> (<name type="native_nation" key="Tillamook Indians">Kilamox</name>) were of the Salishan family. South of them were <name type="native_nation" key="Alsea Indians">Alseas</name>, <name type="native_nation" key="Yaquina Indians">Yaquinas</name>, <name type="native_nation" key="Coos Indians">Coos</name>, <name type="native_nation" key="Siuslaw Indians">Siuslaws</name>, and <name type="native_nation" key="Umpqua Indians">Umpquas</name>, speaking languages sometimes grouped into the Penutian phylum. In southwest <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name> and northwest <name type="place" key="California">California</name> were various groups speaking Athapascan languages. The <name type="native_nation" key="Yurok Indians">Yuroks</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Wiyot Indians">Wiyots</name> of northwest <name type="place" key="California">California</name> spoke Algonquian languages, while the Karok language is difficult to relate to any others. <name type="person" key="Thompson, John B.">Thompson</name> (NW); Drucker, 104, 107–8. A red vertical line runs through this sentence, perhaps done by <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n29031804" n="4">Actually March 18.</note>
            <note xml:id="n29031805" n="5">See note at <ref n="1806-03-17" type="related">March 17, 1806</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n29031806" n="6">The captains gave little notice to the incident; see their entries for <ref n="1806-03-17" type="related">March 17</ref> and accompanying notes.</note>
            <note xml:id="n29031807" n="7">
               <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Joseph Field</name> killed the elk.</note>
            <note xml:id="n29031808" n="8">
               <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Joseph Field</name>, say the captains. <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name>, or <name type="person" key="McKeehan, David">McKeehan</name>, does not choose to mention, as <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> and <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse</name> do, that on this date the captains sent a party to steal a canoe from the <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsops</name>, since the captains could not afford to buy another at the asking price. They justified the action because some elk were stolen from them earlier. See <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> entries of <ref n="1806-03-17" type="related">March 17</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n29031809" n="9">In plainer language, they stole the canoe. See <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> for this day, and the captains' 
entries for <ref n="1806-03-17" type="related">March 17</ref>.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-03-17" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-03-19" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
