<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.sup.ronda.01.08">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> among the Indians</title>
            <title type="sub" level="a">8. The <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsop</name> Winter</title>
            <title type="sub"/>
            <author>James P. Ronda</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2005</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title level="m" type="main">
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> among the Indians</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">8. The <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsop</name> Winter</title>
               <author>James P. Ronda</author>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1984</date>
               <idno type="ISBN">0-8032-8990-1</idno>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-11-01</date>
            <date>2005-02-01</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>File splitting Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="ch8" type="chapter" n="8">
            <quote>
               <lg type="linegroup">
                  <l>"They are generally cheerfull but never gay. With us their conversation generally</l>
                  <l>turns upon the subjects of trade, smoking, eating or their women; about the latter</l>
                  <l>they speak without reserve in their presents, of their every part, and of the most</l>
                  <l>formiliar connection."</l>
                  <l/>
               </lg>
               <bibl>—<name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name>, 1806</bibl>
            </quote>
            <div type="section">
               <p>
As the Corps of Discovery settled into winter quarters along the <name type="place" key="Lewis and Clark (Fort, Netul) River">Netul (Lewis and Clark) River</name>, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark</name> described the site of <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name> as "the most eligable Situation for our purposes of any in its neighbourhood."<ref target="n0801" n="1"/> But neither <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> nor his fellow explorers seemed quite able to fix those purposes clearly in mind. It was as if once reaching the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name> the expedition lost a sense of direction and purpose. The reasons for raising <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name> seemed less compelling than those that had brought <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name> to life. On the coast the expedition needed time to prepare itself for a demanding return across the continent. The store of notes and maps from the outbound journey had to be consolidated. In the spruce and fir forests and marshlands around the fort, plants and animals new to eastern eyes required observation, description, and cataloging. To continue their ethnography, the explorers would have to question Indians and court their chiefs. And, as always, they looked at the land and its peoples with the needs of an expanding American trade empire in mind. From natural history and economic geography to salt boiling and moccasin making—these seemed to qualify as "our purposes." But none of these could spark the excitement and anticipation that had run through life a winter before at <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name>. In the predictable procession of wind, storm, and fog, the months ahead loomed as an endless round of rain-soaked days. A season at <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name> seemed to promise mildew, spoiled meat, and numbing boredom.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> "eligable Situation" would have pleased any <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookan</name> band seeking a winter village site. They might have quickly appreciated the advantages provided by the river and surrounding forests and wetlands. But what any native of the lower <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> knew to be a bountiful country was soon perceived by <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> as a damp prison stocked with meager fare. That there could be two such divergent ways of evaluating the Pacific Northwest is fundamental in understanding expedition-Indian relatins during the winter at <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name>. Americans and <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookans</name> saw themselves, each other, and the physical environment in profoundly different ways.</p>
               <p>
Symbolic of those differences was the expedition's obvious disgust with coastal weather. A powerful entry in <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> journal for December 16, 1805, captured a sense of awe and fear. "The rain continues, with Tremendious gusts of wind, which is Tremendious. The winds violent    Trees falling in every direction, whorl winds, with gusts of rain    Hail &amp; Thunder, This kind of weather lasted all day, Certainly one of the worst days that ever was!" Less memorable but perhaps more typical were the string of phrases "we are all wet and disagreeable," "cold and a dreadful day," and most common of all, "the rain continued as usual"<ref target="n0802" n="2"/> While explorers huddled in their dank quarters and cursed the foul weather, the Indians went about their daily routine knowing that wind, rain, and thunder were but spirit forces making their powers known for all to see. Paddling canoes that defied the worst waves and wearing hats and capes admirably suited to wet days, the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookans</name> may have paused to wonder why the bearded men in the log lodge feared the weather and hid from it.</p>
               <p>
Those Indians perplexed by the strange behavior of their neighbors on the <name type="place" key="Lewis and Clark (Fort, Netul) River">Netul</name> had not lacked contact with other whites or their fascinating metals and textiles. A decade before <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> wintered at <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name>, Europeans had come to the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> with stocks of tea kettles, copper sheets, and blue beads. By 1805 the annual spring visits of British and American ships to a rendezvous on the waters of <name type="place" key="Baker (Haley's) Bay">Bakers Bay</name> had become an eagerly anticipated event in the lower <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookans'</name> year. European-manufactured objects quickly pervaded native life. Guns, brass bracelets, and iron pots took an honored place among the goods in burial vaults up the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> and along the coast. As if to emphasize that outside contact, the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinook</name> trade jargon was amply filled with salty English words and phrases.</p>
               <p>
The contacts lower <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookans</name> had with whites before <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> determined a substantial part of their reaction to the expedition. Those experiences had their recorded beginnings in 1792 when three distinct parties crossed the treacherous bar of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> and entered the world of the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinooks</name> and their neighbors. In May of that year, <name type="person" key="Gray, Robert">Captain Robert Gray</name> and his ship <hi rend="italic">Columbia Rediviva</hi> sailed upriver on a merchant excursion that lasted until the end of the month. <name type="person" key="Gray, Robert">Gray</name>, who had already made a journey to the coast, was intent on capturing some of the sea otter trade that had drawn so many ships farther north. The American captain found the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinooks</name> anxious to exchange skins for a wide variety of hardware and cloth. In the fall of the same year, the river had its second caller. The Royal Navy ship <hi rend="italic">Chatham,</hi> under the command of <name type="person" key="Broughton, William Robert">Lt. W. R. Broughton</name> and part of the <name type="person" key="Vancouver, George">Vancouver</name> expedition, explored far up the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>. <name type="person" key="Broughton, William Robert">Broughton's</name> purpose was not overtly commercial, but he did note the interest of river people in manufactured goods, an observation not lost on English maritime investors. The last visitor in that busy year was the British trader <name type="person" key="Baker, James">Captain James Baker</name> in the ship <hi rend="italic">Jenny.</hi>
                  <name type="person" key="Baker, James">Baker</name> pursued a brisk trade with the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinooks</name> at the bay named for him. The ships on the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> in 1792 were just the beginning of a whole fleet yet to come.<ref target="n0803" n="3"/>
               </p>
               <p>
By the mid-1790s, traders were making the lower reaches of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> a regular stop on the sea otter network that now stretched from <name type="place" key="Boston, Mass.">Boston</name> and Bristol to <name type="place" key="Nootka Sound">Nootka Sound</name> and on to <name type="place" key="China">China</name>. Captains like those the Indians later listed for <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> were attracted not only by sea otters and beavers but by arrowproof moosehide armor called clamons. These "leather war dresses" were then exchanged for pelts with the warriors of what is now <name type="place" key="British Columbia">British Columbia</name>. Typical of those trading ventures and the relations between merchants and Indians was the voyage of the Bristol ship <hi rend="italic">Ruby</hi> and her captain <name type="person" key="Bishop, Charles">Charles Bishop</name>. Late in May 1795, the <hi rend="italic">Ruby</hi> braved the vicious currents of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> bar to anchor at <name type="place" key="Baker (Haley's) Bay">Bakers Bay</name>. Already familiar with the trading routine, scores of <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinooks</name> paddled out to the ship and asked <name type="person" key="Bishop, Charles">Bishop</name> to fire a gun announcing the start of business. If <name type="person" key="Bishop, Charles">Bishop</name> believed that his fine store of merchandise would tempt <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinooks</name> to hand over quickly valuable skins and clamons, he was quite mistaken. The Indians had already learned about supply and demand. They had become, in <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> colorful phrase, "great higlers in trade."<ref target="n0804" n="4"/> Even if <name type="person" key="Bishop, Charles">Bishop's</name> array of kettles, brass rods, and brightly colored cloth tempted them, the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinooks</name> knew the value of tantalizing delay. "In the Evening," recalled the British skipper, "the whole of them took to their cannoes and paddled to shore, leaving us not more disappointed than surprized." Thinking they had made their point, the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinooks</name> returned the next day and began to set prices. But <name type="person" key="Bishop, Charles">Bishop</name> was equally willing to play the waiting game, and it was not until the following day that he "broke trade with the Natives." By June 5 the <hi rend="italic">Ruby</hi> had on board more than one hundred sea otter pelts of fine quality. If the captain ws pleased, so were the Indians. The rituals of trade had been properly observed and both peoples had increased personal wealth, a cherished goal that united traders on both sides of the cultural divide.<ref target="n0805" n="5"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Out of the sorts of encounters with ships like the <hi rend="italic">Ruby,</hi> the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookans</name> developed a set of expectations about Europeans. The whites were a trading people who came from the sea in large canoes to exchange valuable metal and cloth for skins. Traders could be violent, but their touchy tempers might be softened by having women do much of the bargaining for both goods and services. The <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookans</name> were convinced, at least by 1805, that whites would eventually pay any price for sea otter pelts. Trading became a ritual game enjoyed as much for sport as for material reward. But material rewards were never far from the center of all native coastal cultures, and when <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> refused to play the trading game there was some confusion and considerable misunderstanding. The whites were traders from the sea, hungry for skins and occasional sex. That a party of them might come overland bringing neither large supplies of goods nor a passion for pelts gave Indians pause to wonder what manner of <hi rend="italic">pâh-shish'-e-ooks</hi> or "cloth men" these were.</p>
               <p>
Maritime traders like <name type="person" key="Gray, Robert">Robert Gray</name> and <name type="person" key="Bishop, Charles">Charles Bishop</name> saw only a small segment of the Indian village world. At <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name>, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had been quite close to their Indian hosts. Such was not the case during the 1805–1806 winter. The decision to establish <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name> two miles up the <name type="place" key="Lewis and Clark (Fort, Netul) River">Netul River</name> meant that the expedition was at some distance from any substantial Indian settlements. Situated northwest from the fort across the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> around <name type="place" key="Baker (Haley's) Bay">Bakers Bay</name> were several villages occupied by the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinooks</name>-proper. At the time of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, the most important <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinook</name> village was <name type="place" key="Qwatsa'mts village">Qwatsa'mts</name>, at the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Wallacut (Chinook) River">Chinook River</name> on <name type="place" key="Baker (Haley's) Bay">Bakers Bay</name>. This plank-house settlement was home to the powerful chief <name type="person" key="Comcomly">Comcomly</name>. Although the explorers gave no village-by-village population figures for the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinooks</name>-proper, they did estimate the total number of houses at twenty-eight and the population at some four hundred.</p>
               <p>
Still on the north shore and northeast from <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name> were the two villages of people <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> called "<name type="native_nation" key="Wahkiakum Indians">Wackiakums</name>." As was so often the case, the explorers had a difficult time separating the names of villages, bands, tribes, and linguistic divisions. The <name type="native_nation" key="Wahkiakum Indians">Wahkiakums</name> lived in two villages at the mouth of <name type="place" key="Elochoman River">Elochoman River</name>. The larger one, containing seven houses, was called <name type="place" key="Wa'qaiya·qam village">Wa'qaiya·qam</name>; the smaller, only four houses, was called <name type="place" key="Lo'xumin village">Lo'xumin</name>. The <name type="native_nation" key="Wahkiakum Indians">Wahkiakums</name> were part of the Chinookan dialect division known as <name type="native_nation" key="Cathlamet Indians">Kathlamet</name>, but were not part of the political world of those <name type="native_nation" key="Cathlamet Indians">Cathlamet</name> villagers who lived on the south side of the great river—a fact that proved especially confusing for <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>. <name type="native_nation" key="Cathlamet Indians">Kala amat or Cathlamet</name> was the native name for a town of nine large plank houses located on the south side of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> about four miles below <name type="place" key="Puget (Sea Otter, Sturgeon) Island">Puget Island</name>. The <name type="native_nation" key="Cathlamet Indians">Cathlamets</name> remained at this site until about 1810, when they moved across the river and joined the <name type="native_nation" key="Wahkiakum Indians">Wahkiakums</name> at <name type="place" key="Wa'qaiya·qam village">Wa'qaiya·qam</name>.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> closest neighbors were the <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsop Indians</name>. The explorers knew and mapped three of their villages. Nearest to the fort was <name type="place" key="Lä't'cap village">Lä't'cap</name>, a name that meant "dried salmon" and provided Europeans with the name <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsop</name>. The "dried salmon" village was about seven miles southwest from <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name>. Situated on a branch of the <name type="place" key="Skipanon River">Skipanon River</name> near the ocean, the village had three houses with twelve families. To this village <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark</name> traveled in December and met <name type="person" key="Cus-ka-lah">Cuscalar</name>, a prominent headman. It may also have been home to the <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsop</name> headman <name type="person" key="Coboway">Coboway</name>. North from "Dried Salmon" on <name type="place" key="Point Adams">Point Adams</name> was the largest <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsop</name> settlement known to the expedition. <name type="place" key="Neahkeluk village">Neahkeluk</name> had eight large wooden houses; later in the nineteenth century, it would be palisaded for protection against hostile attack. For reasons that are now unclear, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> never visited this village nor had any recorded contact with its leaders. Farther down the coastal plain at the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Necanicum (Clatsop) River">Necanicum River</name> was a cluster of seven houses. Three of those were occupied by the <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsops</name>; the remainder of the <name type="native_nation" key="Tillamook Indians">Tillamooks</name>. So at least fourteen houses in the area contained some two hundred <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsops</name>.</p>
               <p>
The most distant of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> neighbors were the <name type="native_nation" key="Tillamook Indians">Tillamooks</name>. Their villages along the coast began at the <name type="place" key="Necanicum (Clatsop) River">Necanicum</name>, with most centered around <name type="place" key="Tillamook (Kilamox) Bay">Tillamook Bay</name>. Because the <name type="native_nation" key="Tillamook Indians">Tillamooks</name> spoke the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinook</name> jargon to strangers, the explorers did not realize that these Indians were not Chinookan speakers but belonged to the Salish language family. Early in the winter, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> believed that villages like <name type="place" key="Necost village">Necost</name>, <name type="place" key="Natti village">Natti</name>, and those around <name type="place" key="Tillamook (Kilamox) Bay">Tillamook Bay</name> represented distinct nations. Only gradually did this confusion clear. It was to the village of <name type="place" key="Necost village">Necost</name>, at the mouth of <name type="place" key="Elk Creek">Elk Creek</name>, that <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> traveled on his way to see a beached whale. In their "estimate of Western Indians," the explorers recorded that there were fifty <name type="native_nation" key="Tillamook Indians">Tillamook</name> houses with a population totaling one thousand.<ref target="n0806" n="6"/>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>
In a disconcerting way, the winter at <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name> has no narrative history. The winter at <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name> had been a dramatic series of alarms and confusions punctuated by buffalo hunts, holiday celebrations, and occasional personal escapades. At <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name> the major events were <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> trip to see a beached whale, <name type="person" key="McNeal, Hugh">Hugh McNeal's</name> brush with death at the hands of a dangerous <name type="native_nation" key="Tillamook Indians">Tillamook</name>, and the ill-advised decision to steal a <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsop</name> canoe. None of these can compare with the dangers of threatened <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> attacks or the tensions of a diplomatic mission to a hostile <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> town. At <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name>, there were only the elemental tasks of hunting, cooking, and mending. Even these had a timeless quality about them as they were repeated day after day. It was more than dampness and slow rot that pervaded life on the coast. Boredom was rife, to be fought off by every means available. Journal entries took on an almost copybook quality, while busy fingers turned out more moccasins than would ever be needed for the return journey. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> captured that sense of time in suspension when he wrote, "Every thing moves on in the old way."<ref target="n0807" n="7"/> Because Indian relations at <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name> do not follow a chronological pattern, this chapter uses topical categories such as visiting, trading, diplomacy, and ethnography to suggest the ways explorers and Indians dealt with each other.</p>
               <p>
The <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> expedition was one of the greatest tourist attractions the native West had ever seen. Generally, crowds of Indians were attracted by the strangers and their fascinating array of weapons, clothing, and camp gear. Almost everywhere, visiting the explorers became a source of endless diversion and interesting conversation. Each visit had an element of personal discovery as both Indians and explorers eyed each other and then perhaps shared food or trade. At <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name> there had been scarcely a day without a visit by Indians bent on seeing just what went on behind those log walls. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> encouraged visiting, knowing that it brought rewards in food, information, and security. During the winter with the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Mandan.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>
                  </ref>, visiting was a two-way affair. Members of the expedition regularly paid calls at the earth-lodge villages. On New Year's Day, 1805, the explorers made especially festive trips to their Indian neighbors. Music, dancing, and hearty food marked that holiday fling. Although it would be too much to claim that the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri River</name> villagers and the explorers made lasting friendships, the rituals of visiting in lodge and fort softened the rigors of a plains winter.</p>
               <p>
That kind of visiting, so characteristic of an earlier season, did not occur at <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name>. For all sorts of reasons, the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookans</name> and the Americans did not share much of each other's company. When Indians came to the fort it was for business, not for companionship or curiosity. When <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name> had been under construction, dozens of Indians had watched at every stage of the building. At <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name> there were far fewer riverbank superintendents. Early in December, four Indians appeared at the fort site and spent the better part of the day staring at the explorers. Later in the month, as work moved slowly on the huts, two other Indians came to observe the project. Social visits were so unusual that when one did happen it was sure to be noted in the expedition's journals. One of those rare calls took place on January 20, when three <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsops</name> came to the fort and spent the day. As if to underscore how remarkable this was, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> wrote, "The object of their visit is mearly to smoke the pipe."<ref target="n0808" n="8"/>
               </p>
               <p>
If only a handful of <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookans</name> bothered to pay friendly visits at <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name>, there were even fewer white guests in plank houses. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> journey to the "Dried Salmon" village on December 9 and 10 and his later trip to the <name type="native_nation" key="Tillamook Indians">Tillamooks</name> were not so much social calls as reconnaissance probes for a good salt-boiling site or a supply of whale blubber. Members of the expedition did not visit their neighbors. Perhaps blocked by the strong currents in the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> estuary, no explorer ventured to the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinook</name> villages at <name type="place" key="Baker (Haley's) Bay">Bakers Bay</name>. Even more surprising, there is no record of anyone in the expedition visiting the largest <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsop</name> village, <name type="place" key="Neahkeluk village">Neahkeluk</name>, located on <name type="place" key="Point Adams">Point Adams</name>. Not even the usual holiday spirit moved men like <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Pierre Cruzatte</name> to take his fiddle outside <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop's</name> gates. New Year's Day, always a time in the French and English traditions to visit neighbors, did not see any noisy greetings shared with <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsop</name> villagers. The only members of the expedition who may have visited in Indian homes were those who, like <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Joseph Field</name>, <name type="person" key="Bratton, William E.">William Bratton</name>, and <name type="person" key="Gibson, George">Geroge Gibson</name>, spent many days at the salt-boiling camp. At that site there were seven Indian houses, and it is possible that the men found them better shelter than their tents.</p>
               <p>
It was not from a lack of conviviality that Indians paid so few social calls at <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name>. When <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> first entered a <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsop</name> village he was treated with "extrodeanary friendship." His host, a man named <name type="person" key="Cus-ka-lah">Cuscalar</name>, had new mats placed on the floor and presented the captain with platters of food. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> readily admitted that their neighbors could be "very loquacious and inquisitive."<ref target="n0809" n="9"/> But the social distance between them could not be overcome. Part of the explanation rests with the increasing commercialization of coastal life. Trade and the acquisition of material wealth had always been an important part of <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookan</name> life. With the coming of white merchants and the influx of manufactured goods, that facet became even more prominant. Contacts with whites were commercial, not social. The Indians found nothing at <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name> that was especially strange or interesting. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> airgun might have drawn an extra look and <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard's</name> marksmanship was impressive, but coastal people were already familiar with firearms, even if they did not own many. <name type="person" key="York">York</name> was no attraction. Since American ships out of New England often brought black sailors, a man like York was not going to draw the kind of attention paid on the Upper <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>. Few trade goods, language problems, and an isolated location served to make <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name> a place remote from the centers of Indian activity.</p>
               <p>
Perhaps the central reason for the lack of sociability during the second winter rested with the expedition's Indian policy. As noted above, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> distrusted and disliked the peoples of the region. The explorers viewed them as habitual thives tainted with avarice and treachery. A long series of incidents and misunderstandings beginning with the expedition's descent of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> seemed to justify such suspicion and ill-concealed hostility. The explorers might well have asked how one could find friends among badly clad, ill-shaped people who squatted like frogs and tied the ankles of their young women. They did not want such Indians as part of the expedition's daily life.</p>
               <p>
The captains' desire to keep the Indians at bay was made plain in special orders written at <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name>. Issued on January 1, 1806, they established strict procedures for dealing with Indians who came to the fort. Sentries were instructed to watch carefully for "the designs or approach of the savages." Once an Indian was seen coming toward the fort, sentries were required to inform the sergeant of the guard, who in turn was to notify either captain. The specific orders for the treatment of those Indians permitted inside the fort are important enough to be quoted in full.
<quote>
	The Commanding Officers require and charge the Garrison to
	treat the natives in a friendly manner; nor will they be
	permitted at any time, to abuse, assault or strike them;
	unless such abuse assault or stroke be first given by the
	natives. Nevertheless it shall be right for any individual,
	in a peaceable manner, to refuse admittance to, or put out of
	his room, any native who may become troublesome to him; and
	should such native refuse to go when requested, or attempt to
	enter their rooms after being forbidden to do so; it shall be
	the duty of the sergeant of the guard on information of the
	same, to put such native out of the fort and see that he is
	not again admitted during the day unless specially permitted;
	and the Sergeant of the guard may for this purpose imploy such
	coercive measures (not extending to the taking of life) as
	shall at his discretion be deemed necessary to effect the
	same.
</quote>
One further section of the regulation calls for some attention. At <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name>, staying overnight had been an honor freely extended to many Indians. At <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name>, the sergeant of the guard, accompanied by <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name> and two armed sentries, was required to "collect and put out of the fort, all Indians except such as may be permitted to remain by the Commanding Officers."<ref target="n0810" n="10"/> Only rarely was that permission granted and even visiting chiefs found themselves unceremoniously ejected from the compound at sunset. Such restrictions on hospitality were not lost on the Indians. Accustomed to considerable freedom in dealing with white traders, they could only resent the suspicion directed toward them from the fort on the <name type="place" key="Lewis and Clark (Fort, Netul) River">Netul</name>.</p>
               <p>
Although the restrictions on hospitality at <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name> and the natives' economic expectations of whites limited the number of social visits, there were nonetheless fairly regular meetings between the explorers and the Indians. Trading for objects made by native skill or gathered from the land or sea had always been a point of contact between Indians and Europeans. Even though both parties sometimes believed they were being shortchanged, the lure of furs and iron pots kept them coming back for more.</p>
               <p>
At <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name> the corn trade had been essential for the expedition's survival. Establishing the war-axe forge had been a measure of how far <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> were willing to stretch their diplomacy to ensure a reliable food supply. But at <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name> there was a conscious effort to achieve self-sufficiency. The south side of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> was chosen as a wintering site because it was reported to have a plentiful game supply. Led by <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">George Drouillard</name>, hunters in the expedition were expected to provide staples for the winter diet. But the scarcity of game, its often poor quality, and the difficulty in preserving meat in a warm, damp climate made self-sufficiency an impossible goal. It was plain that the expedition's larders would be bare or at least its diet monotonous unless an Indian food trade was established.</p>
               <p>
As their closest neighbors, the <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsops</name> were most often the expedition's trading partners. <name type="person" key="Coboway">Coboway's</name> people soon realized that <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> were not ordinary traders in search of fur. Quickly readjusting their own marketing strategies, the Indians were ready to provide produce, not pelts. Beginning in early December 1805, Indian canoes came up the <name type="place" key="Lewis and Clark (Fort, Netul) River">Netul</name> loaded with a wide variety of foodstuffs. Believing that the explorers' tastes were much like their own, native merchants brought quantities of wappato, fish, salal berry cakes, shannetahque (cured edible thistle root), and culhomo (seashore lupine root). Those same canoes also held stacks of hats, bags, mats, and an occasional dog. Sea otter and elk skins were usually offered for sale by traders not familiar with the market conditions. Shrewd dealers as they were, the <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsops</name> quickly grasped the expedition's needs and increasingly offered what would sell.</p>
               <p>
The <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name> market was never as busy or as noisy as the corn exchange at <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name>. During the nearly four months the explorers lived on the coast, Indians came to trade on only twenty-four days. The fort was never a major market stop, something a party of <name type="native_nation" key="Wahkiakum Indians">Wahkiakums</name> made plain when they refused to sell all their wappato there, preferring to vend it at the <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsops</name> for whale blubber.<ref target="n0811" n="11"/> If native sellers tried to cater to <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name> needs without abandoning traditional trade patterns, white buyers were equally selective in what they purchased. Prices too high or quality too low were sure grounds for no sale. On well over half of the trading days, goods offered by Indians were rejected or a partial purchase was made. Selective buying meant that <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> obtained foodstuffs that were reasonably priced and of good quality while rejecting higher-priced items. In all this there must have been a great deal of haggling conducted by signs and an occasional phrase in the trade jargon.</p>
               <p>
It did not take <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> long to learn that "those people ask generally double and tribble the value of what they have to sell, and never take less than the real value of the article in such things as is calculated to do them service." At that rate, the expedition's stock of merchandise was bound to diminish with alarming speed. Once lavish in their gifts to Indians along the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, the explorers were reduced to a very short supply of trade goods. Gone were the calico shirts, brass combs, and "small cheap looking glasses" that so charmed the Indians up the big river and across the <name type="place" key="Continental Divide">Great Divide</name>. What remained was a motley collection of fishhooks, brass wire and armbands, moccasin awls, worn files, and beads of various colors. By early January 1806, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> complained, "Our merchandize is reduced to a mear handfull." Despite an inventory that could fit into two handkerchiefs, trade continued. Throughout the dismal winter months, the expedition purchased roots, berries, and fish. The rain-shedding qualities of <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookan</name> hats so impressed <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> that they had some made especially to their own head measurements. Unfortunately, the journals are silent on the price paid to Indian women for such custom-fitted articles. Wappato continued a major item, so important that <name type="person" key="Coboway">Coboway</name> made at least one special trip upriver just to locate a fresh supply of the roots.<ref target="n0812" n="12"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Even with the limited number of trade contacts, there were problems. Those difficulties were not so much disagreements about price or quality as misunderstandings over trading protocol and etiquette. Each partner had rules and believed they should be obeyed, even if his opposite number neither understood nor agreed to those rules. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> expected the Indians to follow the new orders about leaving the fort at sunset. Four <name type="native_nation" key="Wahkiakum Indians">Wahkiakums</name> who had been trying to sell roots at rather high prices proved "very forward" and left the fort "with relictiance" when confronted with the new orders.<ref target="n0813" n="13"/> Perhaps the most memorable case of trade involved the <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsop</name>
                  <name type="person" key="Cus-ka-lah">Cuscalar</name> and his family. It was <name type="person" key="Cus-ka-lah">Cuscalar</name> who welcomed <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> to "Dried Salmon" village in December 1805, and the two men soon struck up something of a friendship. When the Indian was sick, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> thoughtfully sent a piece of cinnamon to cheer him. On the day before Christmas 1805, <name type="person" key="Cus-ka-lah">Cuscalar</name>, his younger brother, and two women appeared at the fort. Seated on the ground before the captains, the Indian ceremoniously laid out a supply of mats and roots. Whether this was a gift or goods offered for trade is not clear now and may not have been so to the explorers. Later in the evening <name type="person" key="Cus-ka-lah">Cuscalar</name> asked for several metal files. If the mats and roots were gifts, then the Indian had every reason to think that a reciprocal present would be offered. Plainly confused by what was going on, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> announced that no files were available and abruptly returned <name type="person" key="Cus-ka-lah">Cuscalar's</name> goods. Undaunted, the Indian then offered the captains the services of the two women in his party. When this gesture was rebuffed, <name type="person" key="Cus-ka-lah">Cuscalar</name> was displeased and the women "highly disgusted."<ref target="n0814" n="14"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Whether or not sales were made, and cultural confusions aside, trading did provide the Indians and the explorers a small space of common ground in an otherwise suspicious atmosphere. The cultures of both groups shared many economic values and practices. Each placed great emphasis on acquiring material wealth and measured personal status by that wealth. Individuals who excelled as traders were praised for their skill and rewarded for their enterprise. Yankee capitalists, no less than <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookans</name>, expected every business contact to have an almost balletlike quality in which both buyer and seller spent hours dancing around each other offering price and counterprice. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> learned that lesson when he spent a full day dickering with an Indian over the relative values of a watch and some sea otter pelts, only to have the whole transaction come to naught. Like the New England shopkeeper or the backcountry merchant, the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookan</name> trader knew when to hold his ground and when to sell quickly. Sea otter pelts that cost fathoms of blue beads one day might go the next for half a twist of tobacco or some castoff clothing. Had circumstances been different and the traders his own cultural kin, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> might have meant as praise his description of Indian merchants as "close dealers" who would "Stickle for a very little, never close a bargin except they think they have the advantage."<ref target="n0815" n="15"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Although <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> called <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name> "the most eligable Situation for our purposes," no expeditionary assignment proved harder to define or more elusive to execute than diplomatic relations with the coastal peoples. When the Corps of Discovery struggled up the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> and wintered at <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name> its diplomatic agenda was very plain. It included proclaiming United States sovereignty, establishing legal relations with native peoples, and surveying the northern and western boundaries of the Louisiana Purchase. Equally important was extending the <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>-based American trade empire, something essential in <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name> vision of a West more commercial than colonial. The tactics <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> employed in pursuing those goals ranged from confronting Canadian traders and meeting with native leaders to forming, ever so slowly, an alliance of villagers against pro-British nomads. Flags, medals, presents, client chiefs, and full-dress parades—all this <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> inherited from a long tradition of Indian-white diplomacy that stretched back to eastern forests.</p>
               <p>
But what seemed so clear on the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> and within the bounds of the newly purchased lands became less plain on the other side of the mountains. Despite <name type="person" key="Gray, Robert">Robert Gray's</name> effective discovery of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name> in 1792, the infant American Republic had neither the power to proclaim sovereignty in the Northwest nor was this <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name> immediate intention. The president did explain to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> in 1803 his desire to shift control of the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name> fur trade out of British hands at <name type="place" key="Nootka Sound">Nootka Sound</name> to an America post near the headwaters of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>.<ref target="n0816" n="16"/> On the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, American efforts aimed at diminishing British influence involved complex attempts to rearrange Indian-trader alliances and recast tribal politics. Promoting peace among tribes, offering weapons and American military protection, promising to bring vast stores of trade goods—all were diplomatic strategies toward that end. But down the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>, American interests were less clear. Thinking that their <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri River</name> diplomacy had succeeded, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> may have attempted to create similar economic alliances on the coast. The effort to patch up quarrels between Sahaptian and Chinookan speakers at <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The Dalles</name> suggests such diplomacy had not been entirely abandoned. But at <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name>, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> found no open tensions to resolve, nor were they certain of their own authority. And, of course, if most Indians did not think the writ of the young Republic ran even as far as the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Mandan.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>
                  </ref>, it surely could not cross the mountains to touch the lives of the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinooks</name> and the <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsops</name>.</p>
               <p>
What passed for diplomacy during the winter among the <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsops</name> began even before the expedition settled along the <name type="place" key="Lewis and Clark (Fort, Netul) River">Netul</name>. Contacts with the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinooks</name>-proper started in mid-November 1805 on something less than a friendly note. Angered by an attempt to steal guns from the expedition, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> bluntly informed the Indians that anyone seen near the baggage would be shot. Two days later, on November 17, a man identified only as "the principal chief of the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinnooks</name>" appeared at the American camp. Since neither the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinooks</name> nor any of their neighbors were tribes with unified political leadership but were autonomous villages, this man could have been any one of several headmen. The expedition's records are equally unhelpful in revealing what took place between the captains and their visitor except that the explorers now knew the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinooks</name> to be "noumerous" and "well armed with fusees."<ref target="n0817" n="17"/>
               </p>
               <p>
It was not until later in November, with the expedition still camped on the north side of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>, that any recorded diplomatic exchanges with the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinooks</name> took place. On November 20, as <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> and his party returned from their <name type="place" key="Cape Disappointment">Cape Disappointment</name> reconnaissance, they found the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinook</name> chiefs <name type="person" key="Comcomly">Comcomly</name> and <name type="person" key="Shelathwell">Chillarlarwil</name> with <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>. There are no journal entries by <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> for this period, so what passed between the explorer and the chiefs is not known. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> reported only that the two Indians were given medals and one was additionally favored with a flag. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> usually linked such objects to accepting American sovereignty and the essentials of federal Indian policy. But neither at this meeting nor at any other during the winter did the explorers make any promises or require the Indians to submit to American control. Hindered by language problems and mutual wariness, diplomacy with the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinooks</name> proceeded at a glacial pace.<ref target="n0818" n="18"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Despite the fact that the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinooks</name> were the largest, best-armed, and most influential native group at the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> made no effort to build on their initial talks. They did not venture across the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> to visit <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinook</name> villages, nor did they invite chiefs like <name type="person" key="Comcomly">Comcomly</name>, <name type="person" key="Shelathwell">Chillarlawil</name>, or <name type="person" key="Tah-cum">Taucum</name> to council at <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name>. For explorer-diplomats who had been instructed to redirect the fur trade toward American posts, this was a strangely passive way to go about it.</p>
               <p>
Throughout the long winter on the coast there was only one other formal meeting with a <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinook</name> chief. Near the end of February 1806, <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop's</name> routine was interrupted by the arrival of <name type="person" key="Tah-cum">Taucum</name> and some twenty-five <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinook</name> men. This was the largest Indian delegation to come to the fort, and no doubt some in the expedition nervously fingered their weapons during their stay. Any fears about <name type="person" key="Tah-cum">Taucum's</name> intentions, however, were quickly laid to rest. The <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinook</name> chief had been dealing peacefully with white traders for more than a decade, and he was not about to endanger such good relations or to attack well-armed men. <name type="person" key="Tah-cum">Taucum</name> evidently came to the fort more out of curiosity than a serious interest in negotiation. There was, after all, nothing to negotiate, nor were the white strangers real traders. Whatever his motives, the chief made it plain that his was a friendly call. Impressed by his good looks and taller-than-average stature, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> gave <name type="person" key="Tah-cum">Taucum</name> as warm an official welcome as they ever offered any costal chief. The Indian and his entourage were fed and "plyed plentifully with smoke." Throughout the afternoon <name type="person" key="Tah-cum">Taucum</name> and his friends enjoyed food and tobacco but evidently had no interest in hearing about the ideas of the "great chief of the Seventeen great nations." Almost as an afterthought, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> presented the chief with a medal. <name type="person" key="Tah-cum">Taucum</name> "seemed much gratified" but many have believed that it was no more than his just due. If the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinook</name> thought the medal was a sign of the expedition's trust and good will, he was quite mistaken. At sunset <name type="person" key="Tah-cum">Taucum</name> an his party were hustled unceremoniously out of the fort as if they were an unwelcome set of traders selling rotten fish. As if to justify such inhospitable conduct, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> wrote a long, vindictive journal entry filled with frightening images of treacherous Indians lurking around the fort ready to pounce on unsuspecting explorers. <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name> may have been secure that night, but closing the gates at dusk was hardly a way to impress important and powerful neighbors.<ref target="n0819" n="19"/>
               </p>
               <p>
If <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> diplomatic relations with neighbors across the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> proved oddly inconclusive, much the same was the case in their dealings with the nearby <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsops</name>. Those Indians, some four hundred strong living in three autonomous villages, had several chiefs, including <name type="person" key="Coboway">Coboway</name>, <name type="person" key="Sha-no-ma">Shanoma</name>, and <name type="person" key="War-ho-lote">Warhalott</name>. <name type="person" key="Coboway">Coboway</name>, known to the explorers as <name type="person" key="Coboway">Comowooll or Conia</name>, was the only <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsop</name> chief who had any recorded contact with the expedition. Early in December, with <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name> still under construction, <name type="person" key="Coboway">Coboway</name> led two canoes of his folk to pay a call on the white newcomers. The chief exchanged some wappato, shannetahque, and a small sea otter pelt for some fishhooks and a small sack of <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Shoshoni.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name>
                  </ref> tobacco. Despite the bustle of construction, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> treated the <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsop</name> delegation "with as much attention as we could." <name type="person" key="Coboway">Coboway</name> was given a medal, but with trade goods already in short supply, others in the delegation probably found American hospitality somewhat meager on the material side. <name type="person" key="Coboway">Coboway's</name> visit predated the regulations limiting overnight stays, so the chief spent the night with the explorers.<ref target="n0820" n="20"/> From <name type="person" key="Coboway">Coboway's</name> point of view, the visit had mixed results. He must have been pleased with the attention paid to him, but the evident poverty of the explorers was disappointing. If <name type="person" key="Coboway">Coboway</name> thought he had scored a victory in having <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name> on his side of the river, he never pressed that advantage, nor did the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinooks</name> see the expedition's wintering place as a slight aimed at them. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> made no promises to any chief and evidently sought nothing more than a friendly but distant relationship.</p>
               <p>
During the winter, the explorers were visited by two other delegations from nearby villages. In each case, the Indians took the initiative in making contact with the Americans. At the end of December, a young <name type="native_nation" key="Wahkiakum Indians">Wahkiakum</name> chief and several people from his village came up the <name type="place" key="Lewis and Clark (Fort, Netul) River">Netul</name> for trade and talk. Once again, expedition records do not reveal what, if any, official words passed between the chief and the captains. The <name type="native_nation" key="Wahkiakum Indians">Wahkiakum</name> was given a small medal and, like the <name type="native_nation" key="Assiniboine Indians">Assinboin</name> band chief <name type="person" key="Chechank">Chechank</name> at <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name>, a piece of ribbon to put on his hat.<ref target="n0821" n="21"/> Early in January, the <name type="native_nation" key="Cathlamet Indians">Cathlemat</name> chief <name type="person" key="Shâh-hâr-wâr-cap">Shahharwarcap</name> and eleven men ventured to the fort. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> gave the chief a medal of the smallest size and in return received some wappato and tobacco. Following protocol, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> then offered some twine for a skimming net. After some time in trading, <name type="person" key="Shâh-hâr-wâr-cap">Shahharwarcap</name> was escorted out of the fort at sunset and spent the night in the woods.<ref target="n0822" n="22"/> These contacts with <name type="native_nation" key="Wahkiakum Indians">Wahkiakum</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Cathlamet Indians">Cathlamet</name> chiefs hardly qualify as talks, but they did round out a network of reasonably friendly relations between <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name> and the surrounding villages.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> diplomacy at <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name> was characterized by modest goals and relative inaction. At <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name> there had been a sense of urgency in talks with the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Mandan.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>
                  </ref> and <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name>. The captains had had a clear picture of United States interests on the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, even if their grasp of tribal politics had been less sure. But similar clarity was lacking at <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name>. American interests in <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">the Pacific</name> Northwest were as yet unformed. The trade empire <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> represented was centered in the <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> of the Chouteau brothers and <name type="person" key="Lisa, Manuel">Manuel Lisa</name>, not the <name type="place" key="New York">New York</name> of <name type="person" key="Astor, John Jacob">John Jacob Astor</name>. Here the explorers were uncertain of and uninterested in village and band rivalries. It is revealing that <name type="person" key="Comcomly">Comcomly</name>, the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinook</name> headman who emerged in the period after <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> as the most powerful political leader in the area, never visited <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name>. Whatever diplomatic initiatives there were during the winter came from the Indians themselves. It was very rare for whites to winter in the region, and the natives' visits to the fort may be interpreted as an effort to determine the intentions of the expedition. If there was a network of "understandings" binding the Indians and the explorers, it was the result of action by the former. By the second winter, the explorers had expended not only the material substance of diplomacy but much of their intellectual capital as well. Perhaps it seemed enough to fulfill the forms of diplomacy with the few remaining flags and medals, leaving the substance to others.</p>
               <p>
If <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> were reluctant traders and inactive diplomats, they better fulfilled their ethnographic responsibilities. The <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name> diaries are enlivened with a wealth of information on lower <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookan</name> life, including drawings of weapons, canoes, and the tools of daily life. At <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name>, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had used a wide variety of techniques to gather and preserve information about the Indians: interviews, direct observation, participation in ceremonies, and collection of artifacts. The results of that considerable effort were recorded in journals, maps, and the impressive "Estimate of the Eastern Indians." Knowing what they did well and what was possible, the expedition's ethnographers centered on describing Indian material culture. If past experience meant anything, the expedition was admirably prepared to document the lives of the coastal people. That the <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name> ethnographic achievement proved somehow less major than expected was the result of a whole battery of information gathering problems, some beyond the expedition's control and others of its own making.</p>
               <p>
It has become a historical commonplace to describe the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookans</name> encountered by <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> as "a decadent stock." In a burst of rhetoric more colorful than accurate, Bernard De Voto branded the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinooks</name> and their kin as "dullwitted, thievish, lying, [and] rotten with gonorrhoea and the pox"<ref target="n0823" n="23"/> Although others have not written such powerful slander, students of the expedition have often assumed that <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookan</name> life was somehow a "culture in decline." This latter-day estimate would have astonished everyone from white traders and explorers to the Indians themselves. When <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> came to the coast in 1805, they found a thriving people fully at one with a bountiful physical environment. Arguments about cultural decline to the contrary, the maritime fur trade had dramatically enhanced the wealth and power of the coastal people. As one story describing the advent of metal trade goods put it, "the people bought this and the <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsop</name> became rich."<ref target="n0824" n="24"/> Like those ingenious <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Mandan.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>
                  </ref> who dismantled a corn grinder to make tools more suited to their own needs, the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookans</name> bought only certain European goods and then quickly made them part of native life. The assertion that the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookans</name> were "dull-witted" would have brought looks of disbelief from white merchants who knew firsthand the talents of Indian traders. To be fair, it must be said also that there was probably no more veneral disease on the coast than at <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name>. The expedition's experience suggests that more men had the ailment at <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name> than at <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name>. And as for the charge that the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookans</name> were liars, it is revealing that the only serious case of deception during the winter involved the expedition and not the natives. <name type="person" key="Coboway">Coboway</name>, <name type="person" key="Cus-ka-lah">Cuscalar</name>, <name type="person" key="Tah-cum">Taucum</name>, and the women who worked for <name type="person" key="Delashelwilt">Delashelwilt's</name> wife was neither noble nor savage. Their lives moved to a pattern often difficult for the explorers to discern. It was just as hard for the natives to comprehend the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> expedition.<ref target="n0825" n="25"/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> were always drawn to the characteristic objects of Indian life. Few items more fully symbolized native cultures on the Northwest Coast than the canoe. From the first time they saw such canoes on the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> admired their way in the water and the skill of those who paddled them through heaving river swells. From the <name type="native_nation" key="Tlingit Indians">Tlingits</name> of <name type="place" key="British Columbia">British Columbia</name> down to the coastal <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Salish</name> of <name type="native_nation" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>, there were five distinctive canoe styles in use. Ranging south from <name type="place" key="British Columbia">British Columbia</name> to the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name> and then up to the <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Cascades (Great Rapids, Great Shute)">Cascades</name>, the Chinook or Nootka canoe was a dominant style. The Chinook canoe, typically twenty to thirty-five feet long with a flat bottom, was quickly recognizable by its separate wood piece fitted over an undercut prow and a sharp, vertical stern. The cutwater canoe, common among lower <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookans</name>, obtained its name from the use of a board cutwater placed on the prow. Cutwaters were often thirty to thirty-five feet long and carried ten to twelve persons and considerable cargo. Also widespread in coastal <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name> and <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name> and on the lower <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> was the shovel-nose canoe. This style was the only kind used above <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The Dalles</name>. Shovel-noses could be recognized by their distinctive sharply undercut prow and stern. This canoe was usually some fifteen feet long and maneuvered by two or three paddlers. Perhaps the most impressive and certainly the most memorable canoe in lower <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookan</name> waters was the double cutwater style. This very large canoe, usually thirty-five feet or longer, had cutwater boards at both bow and stern. More important, both ends were decorated with large carved totem animals. Finally, there were several kinds of simple hunting canoes.<ref target="n0826" n="26"/>
               </p>
               <p>
In a long, illustrated journal entry dated February 1, 1806, both <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> presented detailed descriptions of four of the five canoe styles of the Northwest Coast. The first canoe in the sequence of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> drawings was the shovel-nose. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had often seen the <name type="native_nation" key="Cathlamet Indians">Cathlamets</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Wahkiakum Indians">Wahkiakums</name> use these small canoes around the "<name type="place" key="Marsh (Seal) Island">marshey Islands</name>" near their villages. Second in <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> illustrated entry was the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinook</name>, the sort of canoe that may have been frequently drawn up on the banks of the <name type="place" key="Lewis and Clark (Fort, Netul) River">Netul</name>. The third drawing depicted the cutwater canoe. Both explorers noted its use up to <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The Dalles</name> as well as its unmistakable cutwater board. That feature of native naval design was something neither man had ever seen, and both admitted that on first sight they had confused the bow for the stern, perhaps thinking the board was a simple rudder. Like every outsider who ever saw the double cutwater, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> were impressed by its size and ornamentation. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> drawing shows a large double cutwater with what may be a human figure on the prow and a carving, clearly of an animal, at the stern. When <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> visited the <name type="native_nation" key="Tillamook Indians">Tillamook</name>-<name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsop</name> village at present-day <name type="place" key="Seaside, Oreg.">Seaside</name>, <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>, he measured a double cutwater but evidently either forgot or mislaid the figures when writing his entry.<ref target="n0827" n="27"/>
               </p>
               <p>
The explorers knew that there was more to say about canoes beyond simple physical characteristics. Like James G. Swan who spent three years among the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinooks</name> in the 1850s, they understood that "the manufacture of a canoe is a work of great moment with these Indians." A brief but accurate discussion of construction techniques and materials completed the captains' journal entry. Impressed by the canoe themselves, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> were even more taken with the skill of their builders. With a chisel made from a worn file embedded in a wooden handle, Indian craftsmen made boats marked by easy handling and graceful lines. "A person would suppose," wrote the captains, "that the forming of a large canoe like this was the work of several years; but these people make then in several weeks." It was no wonder that canoes were prized possessions not to be traded away except at the highest prices.<ref target="n0828" n="28"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Some of the best of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> ethnography responded to <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name> requirement that they describe Indian "food, clothing, &amp; domestic accomodations." Throughout its journey, the expedition took careful note of Indian architecture, recording the designs and construction principles of earth lodges, tepees, brush wickiups, and on the Northwest Coast, plank houses. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> first encountered plank houses around <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The Dalles</name> and saw them with increasing frequency downriver. Drawing on observations made during the winter, they were able to describe in considerable detail the size, shape, and materials for a <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookan</name> plank dwelling.</p>
               <p>
Although there was some variety in the plank house's size and shape, depending on local circumstances and the status of the inhabitants, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> found a common overall plan and structure. After finding a proper location with good access to water and enough sunlight, Indian builders excavated a pit some three to five feet deep. When finished, the pit measured anywhere from fourteen by twenty to forty by one hundred feet on its sides. A strong framework of cedar timber posts and gables was then erected over the pit. Split cedar boards were then driven into the ground vertically so that the tops of these planks could be attached to the gable rafters and eave poles. Roofs were made with thin planks, sometimes laid in a double thickness. Oval door openings often provided a place for <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookan</name> craftsmen to demonstrate their considerable carving abilities. Entrances were made to appear as animal or human mouths. When <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> visited the <name type="native_nation" key="Cathlamet Indians">Cathlamet</name> village on the return journey, they noted such designs, "some of these which represented human figures setting and supporting the burthen on their shoulders."<ref target="n0829" n="29"/>
               </p>
               <p>
The insides of those houses were filled with the domestic clutter of <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookan</name> daily life. Sleeping mats, bowls, knives, bags, digging sticks, and clothing were only some of the items in a typical coastal household inventory. It was not until the drawings and paintings of John Webber, an artist with <name type="person" key="Cook, James">Captain Cook</name> at <name type="place" key="Nootka Sound">Nootka Sound</name>, and Paul Kane, a nineteenth-century artist, became better known that there was visual confirmation of what <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> first described. The explorers provided a catalog of the utensils that the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookans</name> used every day. Their journals contain accurate descriptions of wooden bowls, reed mats, different sizes of woven rush bags, and "neet trenchers made of wood." There is a fine account of root-digging sticks with a simple sketch to illustrate the tool. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> also made drawings of several weapons, including clubs, swords, and the common double-bladed handknife.<ref target="n0830" n="30"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Food and clothing did not escape the ethnographer's eyes. In a long journal entry written on a dismal, rainy day in January, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> took pains to describe "the Culinary articles of the Indians in our neighbourhood." Handsomely carved bowls, water baskets that doubled as hats, and horn spoons were all duly noted, as was the proper way to roast fish on a skewer. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> would not have recognized the word <hi rend="italic">ethnobotany,</hi> but their observations on the natives' use of plants as a major food source has no equal in the literature of early exploration. The captains were no less attentive to <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookan</name> clothing. Despite <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> ill-tempered outburst proclaiming <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookan</name> female dress and ornament as "the most disgusting sight I have ever beheld," the journals contain remarkably precise descriptions of native dress. At one point, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> summarized: "All go litely dressed ware nothing below the waist in the coldest weather, a pice of fur around their bodies and a short robe composes the sum total of their dress, except a fiew hats, and beads about their necks arms and lets."<ref target="n0831" n="31"/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> were especially fascinated by the unique and skillfully made hats worn by Indians up and down the coast. Made of cedar and bear grass, these brimless, cone-shaped hats were often decorated with geometric or pictorial figures woven into them. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> saw a common Nootka design and described it as "faint representations of the whales, the Canoes, and the harpooners Strikeing them." <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> was impressed with their practical design, writing, "They are nearly waterproof, light, and I am convinced are much more durable than either chip or straw." The explorers found such hats so well-suited to endless days of rain that they purchased several for themselves, drew four pictures of them, and took one back for <name type="person" key="Peale, Charles Willson">Charles Willson Peale's</name>
                  <name type="place" key="Philadelphia, Pa.">Philadelphia</name> museum.<ref target="n0832" n="32"/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> ethnography was never an end in itself, but was always intended for the service of government policy or commercial expansion. When <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> instructed <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> to learn about the "ordinary occupations" of native people, he had in mind the ways that Indian economic patterns might fit into an American trade system. Knowing that an essential part of their mission was to lay the foundations of future "commercial intercourse," the explorers paid special attention to Indian trade routes and the kinds of goods that passed along them. By the time <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> got to <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The Dalles</name>, they were experienced in analyzing trade networks and their potential for the eager merchants of <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>. The Northwest Coast contained an exchange system every bit as extensive as that at the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> villages. Had <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> been farther north, they might have had a closer look at the maritime fur trade, but their location near the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> nonetheless provided a good place to watch a stream of brass tea kettles, blue beads, wappato, and pelts pass around a circle of Indian and white hands.<ref target="n0833" n="33"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Despite the fact that more than one hundred American ships had been engaged in fur operations on the Northwest Coast between 1788 and 1803, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> knew very little about the organization or the schedule of that trade. When he gathered his notes and began writing about coastal trade, he did not know whether traders who visited the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> came from <name type="place" key="Nootka Sound">Nootka Sound</name> or made the river their first stop on voyages direct from <name type="place" key="England">England</name> or the United States. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> was equally unsure about the existence of a trading post somewhere on the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name> coast south of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>. Strangely enough, the explorer did not even appear aware of the role of <name type="place" key="Hawaii">Hawaii</name> as an important resupply point, although he speculated that "some island in the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">pacific ocean</name>" was perhaps being used in the trade. From Indians, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> learned that traders came to the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> in April, anchored at <name type="place" key="Baker (Haley's) Bay">Bakers Bay</name>, and stayed some six or seven months. More important, he was able to learn what sort of goods the Indians were anxious to obtain. Those goods ranged from high quality two- and three-point blankets and coarse cloth to sheet copper and brassware. Also in demand were knives, fishhooks, pots, kettles, and firearms. The <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookans</name> enjoyed sporting European fashions, making castoff sailors' clothing an item for exchange. Of course, there was always a market for blue beads, known in the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinook</name> trade jargon as <hi rend="italic">tyee-kamosuk</hi> or "chief beads." In return, the maritime traders obtained dressed and undressed elk skins, sea otter and beaver pelts, and so <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> thought, dried salmon. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> knew that vast quantities of pounded fish came down from <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The Dalles</name> market but frankly could not understand why white traders wanted it. Later he discovered that he had misinterpreted Indian information. The salmon was not meant for the sailors but was part of a large domestic trade of which the tall ships were only a small part.<ref target="n0834" n="34"/>
               </p>
               <p>
The extensive native trade network also got the expedition's attention. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> knew about the role of <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The Dalles</name> as "the great mart for all the country." After further investigation, he better understood the flow of pounded salmon and European goods up and down the river. Typical of the exchanges that <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> was able to trace were a variety of products from blubber and whale oil to wappato and beads. On one day in January, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> watched <name type="native_nation" key="Cathlamet Indians">Cathlamet</name> canoes loaded with upriver wappato destined for the <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsop</name> towns. At those towns the wappato would be traded for blubber and oil, items the <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsops</name> obtained from their <name type="native_nation" key="Tillamook Indians">Tillamook</name> neighbors. The <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsops</name>, rich in European trade goods, paid for the whale products with beads and metal. "In this manner," explained <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, "is a trade continually carryed on by the natives of the river each trading some article or other with their neighbors above and below them; and thus articles which are vended by the whites at the enterence of this river, find their way to the most distant nations enhabiting its waters."<ref target="n0835" n="35"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Whenever <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> ventured beyond describing objects to write about the "character" of an Indian group they ran afoul of powerful stereotypes that had long been a part of the Euro-American frontier experience. The explorers could and did have good relations with individual Indians, but when they tried to evaluate whole cultures, traditional attitudes and categories almost always came to the surface. Until they reached the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> made do with two stereotypes for Indians. There were the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri River</name> villagers, potential American customers and allies. In the explorers' eyes, these were the good Indians, sometimes childlike and potentially dangerous but good nonetheless. Baptized by reason of their trade potential, cultural salvation was extended to the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Shoshoni.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshonis</name>
                  </ref>, <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Flathead.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Flatheads</name>
                  </ref>, and <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perces</name>
                  </ref>. The <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> and the <name type="native_nation" key="Assiniboine Indians">Assinboins</name> formed a second image. These natives <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> judged harshly, not necessarily because they were nomads but for their links to British traders. This negative evaluation was not unchangeable. If <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo's</name> warriors abandoned their English friends, they might be redeemed and welcomed into the American congregation. Such attitudes were intellectually satisfying and practically useful; they provided quick reference points as the expedition moved through a maze of Indians in an unknown land. Facial features, treatment of women and the elderly, differing traditions of hospitality toward strangers, economies of hunting and farming, even the sounds of language—all of these could be put into familiar mental pictures that made the world comprehensible.</p>
               <p>
But in the Northwest those reassuring images were challenged in disturbing ways. Here were people who made graceful caneos but flattened the heads of their children, carved beautiful designs on wooden bowls but squatted like frogs, and bargained with Yankee skill but had a language that sounded like hens clucking. The <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookans</name> simply did not fit into any convenient mental category. They were villagers who did not farm and warriors who preferred trade to combat. How could they be "Indians" when they did not look or act like any "Indian" the expedition had yet encountered? Confronted with human beings and cultural patterns that did not conform to the familiar categories, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> fell back on intellectual positions prepared by previous generations of Indian-white contact. At a moment when it might have been possible to escape the thrall of perceptions that had held Europeans since the Age of Reconnaissance, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> chose to reassert the familiar themes of native treachery and brutality. Language more suited to the bloody engagements in the <name type="place" key="Ohio River">Ohio</name> country of the 1790s was conferred on the coastal people. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had a singular chance to see the Indians beyond stereotype; to see them as inventive, adaptable men and women living prosperous lives between the mountains and the sea. That the explorers failed to transcend their own past is a measure of how deeply rooted those mental categories had become for white Americans.</p>
               <p>
When <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> offered negative evaluations of the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookans</name> they usually focused on two features of coastal life, one physical and the other behavioral. There is no doubt that they found the shape of <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> and coastal peoples unattractive. Like other Euro-Americans, the explorers were conditioned to admire tall, slender bodies. Thin lips, narrow noses, and small feet were all essential parts of the body beautiful. Although the plains and plateau Indians came close to that image, the river and coastal folk surely did not. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> repeatedly used the words "low," "illy formed," and "badly made" to describe <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookan</name> bodies. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> wrote, "They are low in stature, rather diminutive and illy shapen; possessing thick broad flat feet, thick ankles, crooked legs, wide mouths, thick lips, nose moderately large, fleshey, wide at the extremity with large nostrils, black eyes and black coarse hair."<ref target="n0836" n="36"/> Although its unflattering aspects were surely intended, this physical portrait is generally accurate. More important, it does not directly engage in the kinds of racial typing common later in the century, nor is its language as harsh as that used by later travelers to the coast. It is worth recalling that the most vindictive thing said about Indians in the extant journals—<name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> cruel characterization of hungry men eating uncooked meat as savage brutes—described <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Shoshoni.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshonis</name>
                  </ref>, not <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookans</name>.</p>
               <p>
But the behavior of some coastal Indians was hardly endearing. From <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The Dalles</name> down to the coast, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> were troubled by repeated incidents of theft. Those thefts posed two quite distinct problems. Plainly the expedition could not afford to lose tools, weapons, and valuable trade goods. But on another level, the explorers found persistent theft a habit hard to understand. Differing concepts of property, notions of communal sharing, increased commercialization of native life, and theft as an attention-getting tactic were all explanations that did not occur to the ethnographers in the expedition. Instead, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> speculated that thievery was an irreducible part of the coastal Indians' psyche. "I therefore believe," he wrote, "this trait in their character proceeds from an avaricious all grasping disposition."<ref target="n0837" n="37"/>
               </p>
               <p>
The captains may not have liked their <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name> neighbors nor wanted their constant company, but at the same time, they said very positive things that must not be overlooked. Indeed, they had as many favorable things to say about the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookans</name> as they had about plains or plateau Indians. For all the talk about "badly made," thievish natives, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> found <name type="person" key="Coboway">Coboway</name> and his kin "mild inoffensive people." Hospitality toward strangers was evident when <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> visited a <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsop</name> house and was treated with "extrodeanary friendship." The explorers were equally impressed with <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookan</name> family life, noting that "the greatest harmoney appears to exist among them." "Cheerful but never gay," possessed with "good memories," "very loquacious and inquisitive," the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookans</name> may have sometimes seemed like transplanted Yankee peddlars—not a wholly flattering estimate, come to think of it, from men with <name type="place" key="Virginia">Virginia</name> and backcountry roots.<ref target="n0838" n="38"/>
               </p>
               <p>
By the time <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> wintered at <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name>, they had settled on several ways to record ethnographic information. Journals, maps, vocabularies, artifacts, and tabular estimates were all familiar parts of their ethnography. At <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name>, the bulk of material about the Indians was written by <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> in long journal entries. Each entry was a miniature essay on a particular aspect of Indian material culture or behavior. On subjects ranging from trade routes and hunting techniques to clothing styles and burial practices, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> essays represent a substantial achievement in the history of ethnography. They reflect his keen powers of observation and a remarkable ability to bring objects alive with words.<ref target="n0839" n="39"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Although the journals of the captains hold much valuable information about the Indians, the same cannot be said of the diaries kept by Sergeants <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> and <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name>. Earlier in the voyage, <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> often had recorded telling bits of native life. The look of an <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> cornfield or the unique sound of the <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Salish</name> language were things that he would not miss putting in his journal. <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name> could be equally observant, especially about Indian houses. But during the winter on the coast, the sergeants' powers of observation declined. For reasons that are not clear, their journals are thin and without significant ethnographic value.</p>
               <p>
Perhaps the greatest advance in ethnographic recording at <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name> was the inclusion of illustrations in the journals. Drawings had appeared briefly when the party spent time with the <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians, Lemhi">Lemhi</name>
                  <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Shoshoni.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshonis</name>
                  </ref>, but at <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name> the illustrative art flowered. Whatever the cause for the drawings, whether sheer boredom or genuine interest in new subjects, these visual records provide a new dimension to the expedition's ethnography. Sketches of North Coast hats, swords, clubs, knives, and arrows dot the journal pages, as do drawings of fishhooks, digging sticks, canoes, and paddles. These drawings continue to enliven our understanding of <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookan</name> life. Most striking is <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> simple but powerful set of sketches depicting <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookan</name> heads and a head-flattening cradleboard.<ref target="n0840" n="40"/> The quality and perceptiveness in the <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name> drawings makes one wish that the captains had discovered their artistic gifts earlier and practiced them longer.</p>
               <p>
The comprehensive "Estimate of the Eastern Indians" had been the lasting ethnographic accomplishment to come out of <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name>. At <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name>, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> attempted a similar estimate for western Indians but with far less success. Abandoning the interrogative and comparative structure that made the eastern estimate so valuable and remarkable, the explorers settled for a simple list of tribes, bands, and villages with populations given in numbers of lodges and persons. The "Estimate of Western Indians" was begun at <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name>, revised during the return journey, and further annotated by <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> when the expedition had ended. In organization, the western estimate is a straightforward recital of native groups, moving from the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Shoshoni.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshonis</name>
                  </ref>, <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Flathead.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Flatheads</name>
                  </ref>, and several <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> bands to the <name type="native_nation" key="Yakima Indians">Yakimas</name>, <name type="native_nation" key="Wanapam Indians">Wanapams</name>, and <name type="native_nation" key="Walula Indians">Walulas</name> encountered at the junction of the <name type="place"
                        key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Snake</name> and <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> rivers. The estimate enumerates the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name> Sahaptians and <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookans</name>, reaching east to the <name type="place" key="Cascade Indians">Shahala or Cascade Indians</name>. Then applying an unusual economic or botanical standard, the explorers list bands from the <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Cascades (Great Rapids, Great Shute)">Cascades of the Columbia</name> to the <name type="place" key="Cowlitz (Coweliskee) River">Cowlitz River</name> as "wappato Indians." These include the <name type="native_nation" key="Clatskanie Indians">Clatskanies</name>, a number of groups living around <name type="place" key="Sauvie (Wapato) Island">Wappato or Sauvies Island</name>, and the <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skilloots</name>. Moving to the coast, the estimate records the <name type="native_nation" key="Wahkiakum Indians">Wahkiakums</name>, <name type="native_nation" key="Cathlamet Indians">Cathlamets</name>, <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinooks</name>-proper, and <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsops</name>.</p>
               <p>
Because <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> never traveled farther south along the <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name> coast than the <name type="native_nation" key="Tillamook Indians">Tillamook</name> village of <name type="place" key="Necost village">Necost</name>, their information on groups much past <name type="place" key="Cape (Lookout) Meares">Cape Lookout</name> was very sketchy. The explorers knew the names and locations of the <name type="native_nation" key="Tillamook Indians">Tillamook</name> towns around <name type="place" key="Tillamook (Kilamox) Bay">Tillamook Bay</name>. Perhaps based on information gathered during <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> visit, the estimate contains a list of Salish and Yakonan speakers south to <name type="place" key="Cape Blanco">Cape Blanco</name> and the <name type="place" key="Rogue River">Rogue River</name>. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had even less information from the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinooks</name>-proper north along the coast. The few contacts with <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinooks</name> during the winter made the estimate of those in the northern reaches meager indeed. Under one entry, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> listed a number of groups along the <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name> coast as far north as the <name type="native_nation" key="Quinault Indians">Quinaults</name> on the <name type="place" key="Olympic Peninsula">Olympic Peninsula</name>. When <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> made his brief reconnaissance up the <name type="place" key="Willamette (Multnomah) River">Willamette River</name> on the return journey, listings were added for bands and peoples commonly known as the <name type="native_nation" key="Mult-no-mah Indians">Multnomahs</name>. Also noted were groups of Sahaptian speakers living on the middle <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> above the <name type="place"
                        key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Snake</name>-<name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> junction. For all the care <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> took with it, the western estimate has a barebones quality. Whether it was a failure of energy, imagination, or information, the document did not meet the standard set at <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name>.<ref target="n0841" n="41"/>
               </p>
               <p>
The weaknesses in the "Estimate of the Western Indians" reflect the deeper problems that made <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name> ethnography less successful than the studies undertaken a winter earlier. The explorers had not abandoned their commitment to "name the nations," nor had they suddenly lost their descriptive skills. At <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name>, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> were up against a battery of information-gathering problems, some of their own making and others simply beyond remedy.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name> had been ideally situated for ethnographic field work. Two <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> villages and three <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> ones were close by. Because these villages were the center for northern plains trade, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had access to Indian information far beyond the range of their own travels. If <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name> was set at what geographer John Allen has aptly termed "the keystone of the upper <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> region," <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name> was isolated in a cultural backwater.<ref target="n0842" n="42"/> Only one small <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsop</name> village was within easy walking distance. The <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinook</name> villages on the north side of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> seemed as remote as the <name type="native_nation" key="Tillamook Indians">Tillamook</name> towns to the south.</p>
               <p>
Compounding the physical isolation at <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name> was the restrictive visiting policy discussed above. Unfortunately, the evening curfew was enforced in an atmosphere of fear and distrust. Then, too, the coastal Indians did not find the white men a novelty and were disappointed by their slim store of trading goods. The result was far fewer Indian visitors than there had been at <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name> and a sketchier ethnographic record. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> may have felt more secure with fewer Indians about, but their cultural isolation yielded a written record long on objects and short on those who made and used them.<ref target="n0843" n="43"/>
               </p>
               <p>
That mental and physical distance from Indians meant fewer native informants. Even with Indians like <name type="person" key="Coboway">Coboway</name>, <name type="person" key="Cus-ka-lah">Cuscalar</name>, and <name type="person" key="Delashelwilt">Delashelwilt</name>—men who visited the fort fairly regularly—<name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> never developed the sort of rapport they had had with <name type="person" key="Black Cat (Posecopsahe)">Black Cat</name>, <name type="person" key="Big White (Sheheke)">Sheheke</name>, or many other <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> Indians. Some of that difficulty was a matter of language. However difficult and time-consuming the translations at <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name>, at least the words and sentences had been forthcoming. At <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name>, translation was much more difficult. No one in the party could speak the Chinookan language, and the explorers evidently picked up only a rudimentary knowledge of the trade jargon. Over and over, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> lamented: "I cannot understand them sufficiently to make any enquiries."<ref target="n0844" n="44"/>
               </p>
               <p>
During the winter at <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name>, many of the gaps in Indian information could be filled by traders like <name type="person" key="Jusseaume, René">Jusseaume</name>, <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name>, and <name type="person" key="Heney, Hugh">Heney</name>. At <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name>, there was no comparable group of knowledgeable whites for <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> to question. Already hemmed in by inhospitable weather, miserable food, and a strange language, the absence of helpful traders deepened the expedition's isolation and ignorance.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>
The winter at <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name> wore on in days of cold drizzle. The men habitually noted in their journals that "nothing worthy of notice occurred today." No sooner had the fort been built than the whole party began "counting the days which seperate us from the 1st of April and which bind us to <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">fort Clatsop</name>."<ref target="n0845" n="45"/> In the routine of hunting, cooking, mending, and salt-boiling, several incidents stand out to reveal the lights and shadows of personal relations between the explorers and the Indians. Some of these are no more than snapshots from the <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name> family album, but at least two might be short films on the subject of friendship betrayed.</p>
               <p>
At <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name>, Indians and explorers had been allies in a struggle to survive a plains winter. But at <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name> their relationship was at best an armed truce. Yet there must have been moments, especially at trading times, when something like the atmosphere of that plains winter crept into the <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name> compound. The <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinooks</name> were convivial folk who enjoyed storytelling and good company. Their zest for life was reflected in a delight with bargaining that went beyond business into the realm of sport. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> never recorded any of the arresting tales in coastal oral tradition, nor do their journals contain any hints of the actual words that passed between Indians and whites. But in a memorable entry written by <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, there is a hint of those brief times when neighbors shared trade and food. "With us," he recalled, "their conversation generally turns upon the subjects of trade, smoking, eating or their women; about the latter they speak without reserve in their presents, of their every part, and of the most formiliar connection."<ref target="n0846" n="46"/> In journal entries usually empty of an Indian presence, this is an especially vivid picture. Earthy talk, a sly wink or pointed finger, and the forceful way the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookans</name> blew smoke from their lungs—all lent a flash of color to otherwise gray days.</p>
               <p>
Talk about that "most formiliar connection" is a reminder that sexual liaisons with Indian women had been part of the life of the expedition at least since the time at the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> villages. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> certainly was not surprised, and he wisely purchased the proper medical supplies in <name type="place" key="Philadelphia, Pa.">Philadelphia</name> to cope with venereal disease. The captains simply accepted sexual relations as part of frontier life and were worried only if they endangered the expedition's health or security. It is probably safe to say that "Louis Veneris" was an unpaid, unenlisted, but ever-present member of the Corps of Discovery throughout its long voyage.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> once wrote that <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinook</name> women were "lude and carry on sport publickly," and added that "the <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clotsops</name> and others appear deffident, and reserved."<ref target="n0847" n="47"/> His unflattering assessment of <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinook</name> morals and the differences in behavior of women on either side of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> brings us closer to understanding why sex was so freely offered to the Americans. With the coming of white traders in the mid-1790s, <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinook</name> women began to play an increasingly important role in an expanding native economy. Trusted by whites who perhaps feared males, <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinook</name> women soon became the principal intermediaries between fur merchants and their own kin. Women operated their own business canoes and were regularly consulted on trade matters by men on both sides of the counter. In a culture that frowned on sexual intercourse only if it involved incest, it was reasonable for these women to use their own sexual favors and those of others to make and seal trade agreements. Women who made personal and business alliances with traders enhanced the wealth of their own families. Certainly the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinook</name> who was reported to be "<name type="person" key="Hill, Samuel">Mr. Haley's</name> favorite woman" brought influence and material rewards to her family. The young woman who had "J. Bowmon" tattooed on her arm probably had a similar relationship with that trader. The plains people, concerned with acquiring spirit power, had used sex as one means to gain that end. The <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookans</name>, whose lives focused on trading and material wealth, saw sex as an equally valid way to amass the goods that signaled power and prestige.<ref target="n0848" n="48"/> In a telling set of remarks made in a speech to the Mercantile Library Association of <name type="place" key="Boston, Mass.">Boston</name> in 1846, one-time coastal trader William Sturgis observed, "Among a portion of the Indians, the management of trade is entrusted to the women. The reason given by the men was, that women could talk with white men <hi rend="italic">better</hi> than they could, and were willing to talk <hi rend="italic">more.</hi>"<ref target="n0849" n="49"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Encounters with <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinook</name> women began while the expedition was still on the north side of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>. Toward evening on November 21, 1805, the wife of the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinook</name> chief <name type="person" key="Delashelwilt">Delashelwilt</name> brought six women to the American camp. Their arrival prompted a brisk exchange of goods and services between young men and women who <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> admitted were "handsome." "The young women sport openly with our men" was <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> understated way of reporting what must have been quite a romp. In fact, their men were giving away goods at such alarming speed that <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> were forced to call a temporary halt to the good times. Finding a ready solution, the captains "divided some ribbon between the men of our party to bestow on their favorite Lasses, this plan to save the knives and more valuable articles."<ref target="n0850" n="50"/> These sexual contacts produced many venereal complaints, belatedly recorded by <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> the following spring.</p>
               <p>
Just how often the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinook</name> woman, now known as "the old baud," brought her following to <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name> is not clear. Although <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> remained silent on the subject, there are some clues to suggest that sexual contacts were fairly regular. Exchanging goods for sex may have led to the stern prohibition against selling "any tool or iron or steel instrument, arms, accoutrements or ammunicion," issued as part of the General Order dealing with Indian-expedition relations. More specific and less circumstantial is the evidence from <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Patrick Gass</name>. The sergeant reported that "the old baud" and nine girls "frequently visited our quarters." He noted that sex was available at any "easy rate," and <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Nicholas Biddle</name> later commented that payment rates were fixed on the basis of female appearance. Medical evidence for all this activity is not wanting. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> alluded to "many" venereal complaints after the initial <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinook</name> meeting. Although there do not appear to have been as many cases at <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name> as at <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name>, by January at least two men—<name type="person" key="McNeal, Hugh">Hugh McNeal</name> and <name type="person" key="Goodrich, Silas">Silas Goodrich</name>—had contracted the malady.<ref target="n0851" n="51"/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="McNeal, Hugh">McNeal's</name> case of "the pox" was certainly uncomfortable, but his "connection" to one <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinook</name> woman saved his life and probably rescued the expedition from involvement in a nasty confrontation. On the evening of January 9, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> and several men were smoking with Indians at a cluster of <name type="native_nation" key="Tillamook Indians">Tillamook</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsop</name> houses on the <name type="place" key="Necanicum (Clatsop) River">Necanicum River</name> near the coast. At ten o'clock the quiet was shattered by loud calls from houses across the river. As many Indians rushed to investigate, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsop</name> guide told him that rumor had it someone's throat had been cut. When <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> discovered that <name type="person" key="McNeal, Hugh">Hugh McNeal</name> was missing, he quickly sent <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Sergeant Pryor</name> and four armed men to find him. <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Pryor</name> had no sooner set out than he met <name type="person" key="McNeal, Hugh">McNeal</name> coming "in great haste." Regaining his composure, <name type="person" key="McNeal, Hugh">McNeal</name> explained that he had been invited to one of the houses by a <name type="native_nation" key="Tillamook Indians">Tillamook</name> man. After sampling some blubber at one lodge, the two men had gone on to another. <name type="person" key="McNeal, Hugh">McNeal</name> did not know that the Indian was intent on killing him for his blanket and personal effects. A <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinook</name> woman described only as "an old friend of <name type="person" key="McNeal, Hugh">McNeals</name>" knew of the plot and seized the American by his blanket cape in an effort to thwart the scheme. Still unaware that his life was at risk, <name type="person" key="McNeal, Hugh">McNeal</name> pushed the woman away. Undaunted, she then alerted the village. In the commotion that followed, <name type="person" key="McNeal, Hugh">McNeal's</name> would-be assassin escaped. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> provided a proper ending to the whole escapade when he dubbed the <name type="person" key="Necanicum (Clatsop) River">Necanicum</name> "<name type="place" key="Ecola Creek (McNeal's Folly)">McNeal's Folly Creek</name>."<ref target="n0852" n="52"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Sex sometimes had comic overtones. When a <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsop</name> man brought his sister as payment for medical attention, the offer was swiftly rejected. Not to be denied, the woman took up residence with the <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name> family. Once her presence was known, a number of men in the expedition came knocking on her door only to find their "solicitations" turned down. After two or three days of sulking around the fort, the woman finally realized that medical bills were easier to incur than to pay.<ref target="n0853" n="53"/> In mid-March, as the party prepared to leave <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name>, <name type="person" key="Delashelwilt">Delashelwilt</name>, "the old baud," and six girls made camp outside the stockade and laid "close seige" to the expedition's affections. Fearing that the "winning graces" of the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinooks</name> might touch off another epidemic of venereal disease like that in November 1805 and endanger the return journey, the captains delivered a stiff lecture on the dangers that waited outside the fort. The lecture ended, at least so claimed <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, with the entire party giving "the vow of celibacy." In what must be the most inappropriate gesture in expedition history, <name type="person" key="Delashelwilt">Delashelwilt</name> was then given a certificate of "good deportment." <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> might as well have gone one step further and awarded his wife and her retinue a citation for meritorious service.<ref target="n0854" n="54"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Friendly talk and intimate encounters made a dismal winter bearable for at least some of the explorers. At those times the distances that separated explorer from Indian was, if not bridged, at least narrowed. But there was a darker side to Indian relations at <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name>, something that went beyond the indignity of the password "no <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinook</name>" or the inhospitable treatment afforded visiting chiefs. During February and March, the expedition played out a particularly sordid tale of deception and friendship betrayed. It involved a premeditated theft of a <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsop</name> canoe in plain violation of Indian legal practice and expedition policy. Writers of detective fiction later in the century might have entitled it "The Case of the Purloined Canoe." Whatever the label, it proved a cautionary tale—one that revealed the brand of white morality confronted by the Indians in the grim years to come.</p>
               <p>
What later became a blot on the expedition's honor began simply enough in early February when some <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsop Indians</name> took six elk from <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">George Drouillard's</name> cache. Short on food, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> properly complained to <name type="person" key="Coboway">Coboway</name> about the theft. Following traditional practice, the chief sent a man to the fort on February 12 with three dogs to pay for the stolen meat. This well-intentional and legally correct act went momentarily awry when the dogs bolted and ran off. But all was put right when <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name> went to the <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsop</name> village and retrieved the animals. As far as the Indians were concerned, the case was now closed; proper restitution had been made and accepted. There was every reason to believe that the unpleasantness at the elk cache would be forgotten.<ref target="n0855" n="55"/>
               </p>
               <p>
But in March, with preparations underway for the journey home, the incident suddenly took on new life. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> knew they would need several Indian canoes to flesh out the expedition's flotilla. <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name> was therefore sent to the <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsop</name> village to purchase what craft he could find. He returned with some <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsops</name> and an "indifferent" canoe; the Indians refused to part with it even when offered <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> fancy-dress uniform coat. Indians remained at the fort throughout the day but would not sell their canoes "at a price which it was in our power to give consistently with the state of our stock of merchandize."<ref target="n0856" n="56"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Stymied in their efforts to obtain the necessary canoes by honest trade, a plan surfaced that was at worst criminal and at best a terrible lapse of judgment. One of the interpreters—either <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name> or <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name>—and several other men proposed the revival of the elk theft case as a pretext for taking a <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsop</name> canoe. As <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> blandly put it, "We yet want another canoe, and as the <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsops</name> will not sell us one at a price which we can afford to give we will take one form them in lue of the six elk which they stole from us in the winter." <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> were not up against the wall of survival, nor was this a food emergency. The captains were abandoning a two-year tradition of never stealing from the Indians. The essential honesty that distinguished <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> from explorers like Hernando DeSoto and Francisco Pizarro had been tarnished. Expedition goods were in short supply, but experience always proved that patience in coastal trade usually yielded a satisfactory exchange. Unfortunately, patience was not the order of the day.<ref target="n0857" n="57"/>
               </p>
               <p>
On the next day, March 18, an unsuspecting <name type="person" key="Coboway">Coboway</name> spent the whole day at the fort. While the chief was there, four of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> men slipped away toward his village. Knowing where the canoes were beached, they took one and brought it up near the fort. Because <name type="person" key="Coboway">Coboway</name> was still there, the thieves concealed their prize nearby until he left. It had been one thing for <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> to trick <name type="person" key="Cameahwait">Cameahwait</name> into thinking that <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> party was close at hand when the fate of the expedition hung in the balance at <name type="place" key="Shoshone Cove">Shoshoni Cove</name>. Even then <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> admitted his deception "set a little awkward." It was another thing to cheat <name type="person" key="Coboway">Coboway</name>—a man <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> described as "friendly and decent," "kind and hospitable"—and not even feel a pang of conscience.<ref target="n0858" n="58"/>
               </p>
               <p>
That singular betrayal of friendship begins to make sense when projected against remarks made by <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> during the period between the stealing of the elk and the stealing of the canoe. After a visit on February 20 by <name type="person" key="Tah-cum">Taucum</name> and a large <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinook</name> delegation, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> launched into a vitriolic attack on the natives. Dredging up language and images rooted in two centuries of white frontier experience, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> branded the Indians as treacherous savages beyond redemption. Brushing aside any thought that the two peoples might ever be linked in genuine friendship, the explorer maintained that kindness from whites had always been repaid with brutality from Indians. "The too great confidence of our countrymen in their sincerity and friendship," exclaimed <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, "has caused the destruction of many hundreds of us." Turning his attention to the expedition, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> admitted that long months of good relations with Indians made it difficult to believe the party could fall victim to attack. Against that general good feeling, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> charged that the Indians did not deserve the expedition's confidence, no matter how helpful they had been. About all Indians, he declared, there was something fundamentally treacherous. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> was determined to do everything in his power to undermine any favorable impression his men had of the Indians. The central theme of Indian treachery had to be drilled into their minds. The Corps of Discovery had to be taught to hate. In phrases reminiscent of Puritan fears of the howling wilderness and savage devils, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> repeated his conviction "that our preservation depends on never loosing sight of this trait [treachery] in their character, and being always prepared to meet it in whatever shape it may present itself."<ref target="n0859" n="59"/> With those words <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> moved from common-sense vigilance of the sort required of every explorer to a dangerous flirtation with paranoia.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> ranting was not typical of either the language or the practice of the expedition. It was not even typical of events during the <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsop</name> winter. But those were powerful words that demand the historian's attention and explanation. A long way from home, the expedition felt hemmed in by a strange environment and seemingly unpredictable people. Isolation, loneliness, and fear—all extract a high price from even the strongest and most moral. Such conditions often release pent-up feelings of hostility toward outsiders. <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name> always had an atmosphere of "us versus them," unlike the "we" of <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name>. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> were not the first Europeans who had their moral sensibilities challenged and then eroded by the new American land. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> outburst and the theft of the canoe mark a low point in expedition-Indian relations.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>
The winter at <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name> ended as it had begun—with overvcast skies and splatters of rain. On March 23, 1806, after giving <name type="person" key="Coboway">Coboway</name> possession of their winter quarters, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> "bid a final adieu to <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name>." <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> claimed that with the exception of not meeting any white traders, all the expedition's goals had been achieved.<ref target="n0860" n="60"/> In most particulars his evaluation was accurate. Secured in carefully sewn elkskin bags was what amounted to a virtual catalog of western North America—its land, peoples, plants, and animals. The face of a vast portion of the continent now would be disclosed for all to see in journals, drawings, maps, vocabularies, botanical specimens, and artifacts. If <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> were disturbed that their primary mission—finding a passage through the American garden—had not yielded the result <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> hoped for, they did not show it. For now there was only the hurry to sever those ties that for a winter had bound them to the North Coast.</p>
               <p>
Some eight years later there was a disquieting and sad postscript to the <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatop</name> winter. On May 21, 1814, <name type="person" key="Coboway">Coboway</name> brought to the North West Company trader <name type="person" key="Henry, Alexander (younger)">Alexander Henry</name> a piece of paper the chief had carefully preserved through all those damp winters. Dated March 19, 1806, it was a list of the members of the Corps of Discovery of the Northwest. Despite their ill treatment of him, the chief obviously cherished this reminder of those his people called <hi rend="italic">pâh-shish-e-ooks,</hi> the "cloth men." <name type="person" key="Coboway">Coboway's</name> rude introduction to the world of imperial rivalries came when <name type="person" key="Henry, Alexander (younger)">Henry</name> abruptly threw the document into a fire and then presented the chief with a British replacement.<ref target="n0861" n="61"/>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had done their work well. Lured by what the captains saw, those eight years had brought a flood of Astorians, Nor'-Westers, and empire builders to the Northwest. And <name type="person" key="Coboway">Coboway's</name> world had been transformed in ways hard to understand and difficult to predict.

</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="section">
            <head rend="center">Abbreviations</head>
            <p>
B A E       Bureau of American Ethnology</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">Field Notes.</hi>        Osgood, Ernest, S., ed. <hi rend="italic">The Field Notes of <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain William Clark</name>, 1803–1805.</hi> New Haven: Yale University Press, 1964.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal.</hi>        <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass, Patrick</name>. <hi rend="italic">A Journal of the Voyages and Travels of a Corps of Discovery.</hi> Edited by <name type="person" key="McKeehan, David">David McKeehan</name>. 1807. Reprint, with preface by Earle R. Forrest. Minneapolis: Ross and Haines, 1958.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal.</hi>        Quaife, Milo M., ed. <hi rend="italic">The Journals of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Meriwether Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Sergeant John Ordway</name>.</hi> Madison: Historical Society of Wisconsin, 1916.</p>
            <p>
Thw.       Thwaites, Reuben G., ed. <hi rend="italic">The Original Journals of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition.</hi> 8 vols. New York: Dodd, Mead &amp; Co., 1904–1905.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal.</hi>        "The Journal of <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Private Joseph Whitehouse</name>." In Thw. 7:29–190.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="notes" type="notes">
            <head rend="center">Notes</head>
            <note xml:id="n0801" n="1">Thw. 3:270.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0802" n="2">
               <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> pp. 317, 322, 326; Thw. 3:267, 285, 291.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0803" n="3">Barry Gough, <hi rend="italic">Distant Dominion: Britain and the Northwest Coast of North America, 1579-1809</hi> (Vancouver: University of British Columbia Press, 1980), pp. 116–34; Derek Pethick, <hi rend="italic">First Approaches to the Northwest Coast</hi> (Vancouver: J. J. Douglas, 1976), pp. 77–133; Robert H. Ruby and John A. Brown, <hi rend="italic">The <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinook Indians</name>: Traders of the Lower <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>
               </hi> (Norman: University of Oklahoma Press, 1976), pp. 40–58. An important oral tradition relating the first <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsop</name> sighting of a European ship is in Franz Boas, ed., <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinook</name> Texts,</hi> Smithsonian Institution, BAE Bulletin no. 20 (Washington, D.C., 1894), pp. 277–78. Lower <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookan</name> perceptions of <name type="person" key="Gray, Robert">Capt. Robert Gray</name> can be found in Philip Ashton Rollins, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Discovery of the Oregon Trail: Robert Stuart's Narratives of His Overland Trip Eastward from <name type="place" key="Astoria, Oreg.">Astoria</name> in 1812–13</hi> (New York: Edward Eberstadt and Sons, 1935), pp. 15–16.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0804" n="4">Thw. 3:311.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0805" n="5">T. C. Elliott, ed., "The Journal of the Ship <hi rend="italic">Ruby,</hi>" <hi rend="italic">Oregon Historical Quarterly</hi> 28 (1927):261–63.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0806" n="6">Berreman, <hi rend="italic">Tribal Distribution in <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>,</hi> pp. 13–15; Verne F. Ray, <hi rend="italic">Lower <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinook</name> Ethnographic Notes,</hi> University of Washington Publications in Anthropology, vol. 7 (Seattle, 1938), pp. 37–41; Leslie Spier, <hi rend="italic">Tribal Distribution in <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>,</hi> General Series in Anthropology, no. 3 (Menasha, Wisconsin, 1936), pp. 21-23, 42; John R. Swanton, <hi rend="italic">The Indian Tribes of North America,</hi> Smithsonian Institution, BAE Bulletin no. 145 (Washington, D.C., 1952), pp. 414, 417–18, 458, 471–73; Thw. 3: map between 281–82, 294–95, 6:117. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> spatial understanding of the Indians around them is portrayed in <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> map in Moulton, ed., <hi rend="italic">Atlas,</hi> plates 81–85.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0807" n="7">Thw. 4:128.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0808" n="8">
               <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> p. 316; Thw. 3:286, 362.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0809" n="9">Thw. 3:315.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0810" n="10">Ibid. 3:302–4.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0811" n="11">Ibid. 3:296–97.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0812" n="12">Ibid. 3:286, 316, 4:94–95.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0813" n="13">Ibid. 3:299.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0814" n="14">Ibid. 3:289</note>
            <note xml:id="n0815" n="15">
               <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> p. 325; Thw. 3:245, 278, 289, 4:105.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0816" n="16">
               <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, "Instructions to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>," 1:65.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0817" n="17">Thw. 3:226, 229–30.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0818" n="18">Ibid. 3:238.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0819" n="19">Ibid. 4:89–90. <name type="person" key="Tah-cum">Taucum's</name> earlier dealings with traders are traced in Elliott, ed., "Journal of the Ship <hi rend="italic">Ruby,</hi>" pp. 267–78. In the list of chiefs prepared early in the <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name> winter, <name type="person" key="Tah-cum">Taucum</name> is called Stock-home. See Thw. 3:294.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0820" n="20">Thw. 3:278.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0821" n="21">Ibid. 3:296.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0822" n="22">Ibid. 3:332.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0823" n="23">DeVoto, <hi rend="italic">Course of Empire,</hi> pp. 508–9.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0824" n="24">Boas, ed., <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinook</name> Texts,</hi> p. 278.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0825" n="25">Erna Gunther, <hi rend="italic">Indian Life on the Northwest Coast of North America</hi> (Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1972), pp. 55–90; Susan Kardas, "'The People Bought This and the <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsop</name> Became Rich.' A View of Nineteenth-Century Fur Trade Relationships on the Lower <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> between <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookan</name> Speakers, Whites, and <name type="native_nation" key="Kanaka Indians">Kanakas</name>" (Ph.D. diss., Bryn Mawr College, 1971), chap. 2; Ray, <hi rend="italic">Lower <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinook</name> Ethnographic Notes, passim;</hi> Verne F. Ray, "The <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinook</name> Indians in the Early 1800s," in <hi rend="italic">The Western Shore: <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name> Country Essays Honoring the American Revolution,</hi> ed. Thomas Vaughan (Portland: Oregon Historical Society, 1976), pp. 138–39.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0826" n="26">Philip Drucker, <hi rend="italic">Indians of the Northwest Coast</hi> (New York: McGraw-Hill Co., 1955), pp. 63–67; Ronald L. Olson, <hi rend="italic">Adze, Canoe, and House Types of the Northwest Coast,</hi> University of Washington Publications in Anthropology, no. 2 (Seattle, 1927), pp. 18–23; Ray, <hi rend="italic">Lower <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinook</name> Ethnographic Notes,</hi> pp. 101–6.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0827" n="27">
               <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> entry, Thw. 4:35, has five canoe drawings. The first two are both shovel-noses of different sizes. The succeeding drawings follow the same sequence as in the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> entry. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> also has drawings of two different canoe paddles, the pointed type used exclusively with shoven-nose canoes and the more common notched style.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0828" n="28">James G. Swan, <hi rend="italic">The Northwest Coast, or, Three Years' Residence in <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name> Territory</hi> (1857; reprint, Seattle: University of Washington Press, 1969), p. 80; Thw. 4:30–36. See also Gabriel Franchère, <hi rend="italic">A Voyage to the Northwest Coast of America,</hi> ed. Milo Quaife (1854; reprint, Chicago: The Lakeside Press, 1954), pp. 186–87; Ross, <hi rend="italic">Adventures on the <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>,</hi> pp. 72–74.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0829" n="29">Thw. 3:356–57, 4:198–99. See also Franchère, <hi rend="italic">Voyage to the Northwest Coast,</hi> pp. 187–88; Ray, <hi rend="italic">Lower <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinook</name> Ethnographic Notes,</hi> pp. 124–26; Swan, <hi rend="italic">Northwest Coast,</hi> pp. 110–11, 339.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0830" n="30">Thw. 3:274, 288, drawings between 326 and 327, 4:9, 24; J. Russell Harper, ed., <hi rend="italic">Paul Kane's Frontier</hi> (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1971), plate 37, figs. 158, 192, 194; John Webber, "Interior of a house at Yuquot, <name type="place" key="Nootka Sound">Nootka Sound</name>, 1778," J. C. Beaglehole, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Voyage of the Resolution and Discovery, 1776–1780</hi> (Cambridge: The Hakluyt Society, 1967), plate 38.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0831" n="31">Thw. 3:297; 4:185–87. Cutright, <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>: Pioneering Naturalists,</hi> pp. 264–71 has a superb treatment of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> ethnobotany at <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0832" n="32">Thw. 3:294, 296, 360, 4:23, 94–95. Hats identical to those described in the journals can be seen in Drucker, <hi rend="italic">Indians of the Northwest Coast,</hi> p. 75, and J. C. H. King, "The <name type="native_nation" key="Nootka Indians">Nootka</name> of <name type="place" key="Vancouver Island">Vancouver Island</name>," in <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="person" key="Cook, James">Cook's</name> Voyages and the Peoples of the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>,</hi> ed. Hugh Cobbe (<name type="place" key="London">London</name>: British Museum Publications, 1979), p. 94.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0833" n="33">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> did record in both words and pictures Indian hunting and fishing techniques but along with <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> tended to define "ordinary occupations" in a way most suited to American business interests. See Thw. 3:346–47, 350.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0834" n="34">Thw. 3:327–28. See also Frederic W. Howay, <hi rend="italic">A List of Trading Vessels in the Maritime Fur Trade, 1785–1825</hi> (Kingston, Ontario: Limestone Press, 1973), pp. 1–57. On several occasions Indians gave the expedition detailed information about ships and traders on the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>. Those names were probably garbled in transmission since only one, <name type="person" key="Moore, Hugh">Capt. Hugh Moore</name> of the <hi rend="italic">Phoenix,</hi> can be identified from Howay's master list. See Thw. 3:306–7, 4:200.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0835" n="35">Ths. 3:338, 343. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> never suggested building a permanent post on the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>, although <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> noted the good location of <name type="place" key="Baker (Haley's) Bay">Bakers Bay</name> as an anchorage, Thw. 3:340–41.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0836" n="36">Thw. 4:184.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0837" n="37">Ibid. 3:311.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0838" n="38">Ibid. 3:274, 311, 315, 360. Practices such as head flattening and ankle binding, which were certainly beyond the experience of the explorers, were given remarkably value-free descriptions in the journals.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0839" n="39">Perhaps the best of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> essays written during the winter at <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name>: a comparison of the treatment of the elderly in the coastal and plains culture areas, Thw. 3:315; coastal burial practices, Thw. 3:326–27; hunting techniques, Thw. 3:346–47; house construction, Thw. 3:356–57; canoes, Thw. 4:30–36; clothing and physical appearance, Thw. 4:183–88.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0840" n="40">Thw. 4: between 10 and 11. See also Harper, ed., <hi rend="italic">Paul Kane's Frontier,</hi> figs. 170, 171.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0841" n="41">Thw. 6:114–20. Early attempts at listing western Indians can be seen in Thw. 3:294–95 and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> "A List of the Nations and Tribes of Indians residing West of the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky Mountains</name>," <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Papers, Missouri Historical Society, box 5. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> map of the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name> coast from <name type="place" key="Cape Disappointment">Cape Disappointment</name> to <name type="place" key="Cape (Lookout) Meares">Cape Lookout</name> in Moulton, ed., <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi>, plates 81–85, gives some spatial dimension to the western estimate as does his 1810 map. See also Berreman, <hi rend="italic">Tribal Distribution in <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>,</hi> fig. 1; Sapir, <hi rend="italic">Tribal Distribution in <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>,</hi> map at p. 42; Swanton, <hi rend="italic">Indian Tribes of North America,</hi> map facing p. 186.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0842" n="42">Allen, <hi rend="italic">Passage through the Garden,</hi> p. 207.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0843" n="43">
               <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> p. 174; Thw. 3:302–4.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0844" n="44">Thw. 3:327, 4:74. In <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> entry for April 11, 1806, there is an interline note reporting that the explorers learned some jargon during the winter. Such words and phrases would have been enough to carry on trade talks but insufficient for a discussion of social beliefs and practices.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0845" n="45">Ibid. 4:128.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0846" n="46">Ibid. 3:315.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0847" n="47">Ibid. 3:294.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0848" n="48">"<name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name> Notes," 2:504; Coues, ed., <hi rend="italic">New Light,</hi> 2:837–38, 859; Ruby and Brown, <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinooks</name>,</hi> pp. 64–66; Swan, <hi rend="italic">Northwest Coast,</hi> p. 154.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0849" n="49">Ruby and Brown, <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinooks</name>,</hi> p. 75.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0850" n="50">Thw. 3:339–41.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0851" n="51">
               <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>-Coues, <hi rend="italic">History,</hi> 2:779; <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> p. 229; Thw. 3:304, 4:16, 27. <name type="person" key="McNeal, Hugh">McNeal</name> and <name type="person" key="Goodrich, Silas">Goodrich</name> continued to suffer the effects of their sexual adventures as late as July, 1806. See Thw. 5:255.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0852" n="52">
               <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> p. 321; Thw. 3:328–29.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0853" n="53">
               <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>-Coues, <hi rend="italic">History,</hi> 2:779; "<name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name> Notes," 2:503.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0854" n="54">Thw. 4:170, 176, 180.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0855" n="55">Ibid. 4:39, 45, 61, 94, 102.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0856" n="56">Ibid. 4:162, 168, 173.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0857" n="57">Ibid. 4:177, 179.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0858" n="58">
               <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> p. 329; Thw. 4:138, 195. <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> was the only expedition member to record details of the theft.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0859" n="59">Thw. 4:89–90.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0860" n="60">Ibid. 4:197. R. G. Thwaites and others have claimed that Indians, especially "the crafty <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinook</name>
               <name type="person" key="Comcomly">Concomly</name>," knowingly kept from the expedition knowledge of the presence of the brig <hi rend="italic">Lydia.</hi> See Thw. 3:328n. John Jewitt, a sailor rescued by the <hi rend="italic">Lydia</hi> from captivity at <name type="place" key="Nootka Sound">Nootka Sound</name>, indicates that the ship entered the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> at an unspecified date and its crew learned that <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had left <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name> some two weeks before. Thwaites believed that the <hi rend="italic">Lydia</hi> was on the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> before mid-March 1806, an assumption not based on any evidence in Jewitt's account, which is very unclear on dates. However, there seems no reason to doubt Jewitt's two-week information. Equally significant, there is no reason for the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookans</name> to keep this sort of information from <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>. See Robert F. Heizer, ed., <hi rend="italic">Narrative of the Adventures and Sufferings of John R. Jewitt</hi> (1820; reprint, Ramona, Calif.: Ballena Press, 1975), p. 88.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0861" n="61">Coues, ed., <hi rend="italic">New Light,</hi> 2:915; Thw. 4:185, 188.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.ronda.01.07" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.ronda.01.00" type="contents"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.ronda.01.09" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
