<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.sup.lavender.01.03">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Way to the Western Sea</title>
            <title type="sub">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> across the Continent</title>
            <title type="sub" level="a">Chapter 3</title>
            <author>David Lavender</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2005</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Way to the Western Sea</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">Chapter 3</title>
               <author>David Lavender</author>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>2001</date>
               <idno type="ISBN">0-8032-8003-3</idno>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-11-09</date>
            <date>2005-04-20</date>
            <name>Becky Potter</name>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Split into chapters Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="three" type="chapter">
            <head rend="center">THREE. Grappling with Logistics</head>
            <div type="section">
               <p>
After weeks of paperwork, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name> at last felt the touch of the future when, in mid-March, 1803, he reached the U.S. arsenal at <name type="place" key="Harpers Ferry, W. Va.">Harpers Ferry</name>, <name type="place" key="Virginia">Virginia</name> (now <name type="place" key="West Virginia">West Virginia</name>). There, on the rifle range, above the placid junction of the <name type="place" key="Shenandoah River">Shenandoah</name> and <name type="place" key="Potomac River">Potomac</name> rivers, he was handed one of the brand-new Model 1803, short-barreled, .54-caliber flintlocks that <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name> secretary of war, <name type="place" key="Dearborn, Henry">Henry Dearborn</name>, had just adopted as the army's official rifle. He hefted it. Good balance. He tamped in powder, dropped in a ball. Quick, easy loading. Aim. Fire. Commendable accuracy in spite of the short barrel. He must have nodded satisfaction, for the livelihood of his party might depend in large part on the rifles the men carried.</p>
               <p>
He ordered fifteen guns for fifteen men, together with powder horns, pouches, bullet molds, wipers, and, of utmost importance, spare parts and the special tools needed for repairs. To this requisition he added two dozen large knives and three dozen pipe tomahawks, some for his own party, some as gifts for important Indians. The tomahawks could be used for a peaceful smoke as well as for splitting heads. Handles were hollow and a tobacco bowl was 
molded solidly onto the heel of the hatchet blade.<ref target="n0301" n="1"/>
               </p>
               <p>
What turned into a real monster was the iron boat frame he had designed earlier in <name type="place" key="Washington D. C.">Washington</name>. The problem revolved around the detachable sections forming bow and stern. Each had to curve inward to a point while also creating the "sheer line," a curve that runs from the end of a boat's keel up to the tip of the bow and, in the case of the iron nightmare, to the tip of the stern as well. The keel of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> boat was thirty-two feet long. The overall length 
was thirty-six feet. Therefore each sheer line had to rise two feet two inches, the depth of the boat, within a horizontal distance of two feet even. He used a cord suspended in a curve between two points to show the arsenal boatwrights the line to strive for.</p>
               <p>
The blacksmiths heated bars of wrought iron until they glowed cherry red and then hammered out long, thin slats that would be supported at intervals by iron stanchions. Bolt holes had to fit exactly so the sections could be assembled and disassembled. Eyelets were also bored along the gunwales and other parts of the frame. After the craft had been put together at a launching point, a lattice of sticks could be added to the frame as support for a cover of bark and/or buffalo hides; the whole could then be drawn tight by cords run through the eyelets. Whether or not the boat was also fitted for a mast, as wooden pirogues were, does not appear.</p>
               <p>
The construction demanded more time and care than <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> had anticipated. He hovered anxiously around the arsenal's foundry while the workmen built and fit together one curved end section and one semicylindrical midsection, the latter four feet ten inches of beam and twenty-six inches wide at the bottom. From this partial work he calculated that the completed frame would weigh, without a sheathing, a mere ninety-nine pounds, an easy carriage. Feeling cocky, he named the boat Experiment, ordered it finished, and moved on.<ref target="n0302" n="2"/> But in the meantime he had not written a single line to the man who was most interested in hearing from him.</p>
               <p>
One wonders about the six weeks' delay. <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, and hence <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, hoped the expedition would be several hundred miles up the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> before winter set in. With that as a goal, they had allotted one week for the work at <name type="place" key="Harpers Ferry, W. Va.">Harpers Ferry</name>. The president would be expecting regular reports, and <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> knew it. He sent none, perhaps because he did not wish to create worries while success seemed elusive. He may have feared, too, that if <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> learned of the setbacks he would order the experiment abandoned. Or conceivably, the troubles may have put him into such a fit of 
depression that for a time he could not rouse himself to do much of anything.</p>
               <p>
Whatever the cause, the president was worried. On April 23, expecting <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> would be in <name type="place" key="Philadelphia, Pa.">Philadelphia</name> by then, he addressed a letter to him there, complaining of not having had word of him since March 7. "I have no doubt you have used every possible exertion to get off, and therefore we have only to lament what cannot be helped, as a delay of a month now may lose you a year in the end."<ref target="n0303" n="3"/>
               </p>
               <p>
By that time <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> was in <name type="place" key="Lancaster, Pa.">Lancaster</name>, <name type="place" key="Pennsylvania">Pennsylvania</name>, home of the surveyor <name type="person" key="Ellicott, Andrew">Andrew Ellicott</name>. His first move on arriving was to write <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> a long explanation of what he had been up to. Among other things, he stated, he had written many long, important memos to boat builders, recruiting officers, supply agents. (But none to the president.) He had, moreover, triumphed over the difficulties of the iron boat. Yes, he was late, but there was no need to worry. "I still think it practicable to reach the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> by the 1st of August."<ref target="n0304" n="4"/>
               </p>
               <p>
His host, <name type="person" key="Ellicott, Andrew">Andrew Ellicott</name>, was one of the friends <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> had called on to prepare <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> for what lay ahead. He was an able cartographer. When <name type="place" key="Virginia">Virginia</name> and <name type="place" key="Maryland">Maryland</name> had ceded the <name type="place" key="Washington D. C.">District of Columbia</name> to the United States to be the new seat of government, <name type="person" key="Ellicott, Andrew">Ellicott</name> had surveyed and mapped the area. He had acted as assistant to the city's planner, <name type="person" key="L'Enfant, Pierre Charles">Pierre Charles L'Enfant</name>, and afterwards had taken several trips to the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name>, whose course from the 
mouth of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> to the gulf he had surveyed more accurately than it had been done before. <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> had learned its definitive place on the globe from his calculations.</p>
               <p>
He did not believe in the kind of crash course <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> wanted him to give <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>. The young man would need patience and practice, he told <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>—lots of practice, especially with the instruments used for determining latitude and longitude. This practice he proceeded to give him, working him hard for seventeen 
days, often after dark. Once again this was more time than <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> had counted on when drawing up his schedule. And <name type="place" key="Philadelphia, Pa.">Philadelphia</name>, where he would purchase the bulk of his supplies and receive more tutoring in different subjects, still lay ahead.</p>
               <p>
He reached the thriving city about May 9 and straightaway began spending the twenty-five hundred dollars Congress had appropriated for the trip. His indispensable helper was <name type="person" key="Whelen, Israel">Israel Whelen</name>, the government purchasing agent stationed in the city. Working together, they bought upwards of two hundred different items from twenty-eight vendors. More material came from the <name type="place" key="Schuylkill, Pa.">Schuylkill</name> arsenal just outside the city. Altogether, it was a staggering accumulation, including a $250 chronometer needed for calculating longitude, rough clothing for his men, books on botany and navigation for himself, tools and gun flints, and articles for the Indians they would meet. Though the last-named items were ostensibly good-will offerings, the heterogeny (its total cost came to $669.50) would also serve as a traveling showcase of the wares the United States was prepared to deliver to the Western tribes in 
exchange for furs<ref target="n0305" n="5"/>—2,800 fishhooks, 12 dozen pocket mirrors, 22 yards of scarlet cloth, 130 rolls of tobacco, 73 bunches of assorted beads (not enough of them blue, the Indians' favorite color), and on and on. Packing it properly for equitable distribution among an unknown number of potential customers would turn out to be a major problem.</p>
               <p>
The whites would take along a few specialties of their own. One was 193 pounds of soup concentrate, ordered from cook <name type="person" key="Baillet, Francois">Francois Baillet</name> at a cost of $289.50. <name type="person" key="Baillet, Francois">Baillet</name> boiled hunks of beef down to a thick liquid, clarified it with the whites of eggs, added chopped vegetables, and continued boiling until he had obtained a thick paste. He then sealed the stiff goo into lead canisters; after the contents were diluted and eaten, the containers could be melted 
down and molded into bullets.</p>
               <p>
Another of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> inspirations was an air rifle specially made for him by <name type="person" key="Lukens, Isaiah">Isaiah Lukens</name>, manufacturer of machine tools, dies, medals, watches, and so on. Though the weapon, novel at the time (but not to boys with BB guns today), looked like a long-barreled Kentucky rifle, it was activated by air pumped under pressure into a reservoir in the gun's butt. Firing produced no smoke and only a pop—useful characteristics if one wished to be secretive or to awe the Indians with what seemed another example of "white man's powerful medicine."<ref target="n0306" n="6"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Even more curious than soup or airguns to modern readers are the medical supplies on which <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> spent $94.49, for they reveal the abysmal state of medicine at the opening of the nineteenth century. The captain's adviser in this field was <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name> friend, <name type="person" key="Rush, Benjamin">Dr. Benjamin Rush</name>. A native of <name type="place" key="Pennsylvania">Pennsylvania</name>, <name type="person" key="Rush, Benjamin">Rush</name> had graduated from Princeton at the age of fifteen. After a hard five-year apprenticeship under a <name type="place" key="Philadelphia, Pa.">Philadelphia</name> doctor, he crossed the <name type="place" key="Atlantic Ocean">Atlantic</name> to the
University of Edinburgh, where he won his M.D. at the age of twenty-two. Returning home, he became the first professor of chemistry in the United States. His institution: the College of <name type="place" key="Philadelphia, Pa.">Philadelphia</name>, soon to be absorbed by the University of <name type="place" key="Pennsylvania">Pennsylvania</name>, which appointed him head of its medical department. He was one of the four doctors who signed the Declaration of Independence; he helped found the country's first antislavery league and was a leading member of the American Philosophical Society. He wrote prodigiously on all manner of subjects. A fluent and 
popular lecturer, he helped prepare an estimated three thousand doctors for the young United States. The harm they inflicted on the populace is incalculable.<ref target="n0307" n="7"/>
               </p>
               <p>
In those days no one had the foggiest notion of bacterial or viral infective agents. An ailing body was cured by draining away the morbidities that had invaded it. "Bad" blood was <name type="person" key="Rush, Benjamin">Rush's</name> particular <hi rend="italic">bête noir</hi>, as it had been for most physicians since the days of ancient <name type="place" key="Greece">Greece</name>. Using a lancet (a small, sharp-edged, folding knife), he slit a sufferer's vein and let the blood flow into a bowl,where he studied its "diseased" state. Very ill patients were bled until they fainted. Bleeding was also resorted to in the case of dislocated and broken bones; it supposedly reduced muscular tension, thereby making manipulations easier. He practiced what he preached. During <name type="place" key="Philadelphia, Pa.">Philadelphia's</name> yellow fever epidemic in 1793, he ranged heroically through the city's hospitals, a knife-wielding technician at his heels. When he caught the disease, he bled himself. On other occasions he bled one of his daughters when she was six weeks old and had twice bled a son by the time the infant was two months old. Both children survived—because of the remedies, <name type="person" key="Rush, Benjamin">Rush</name> was sure.<ref target="n0308" n="8"/>
               </p>
               <p>
He treated syphilis by applying mercury compounds to lesions in the mouth. (Mercury, we now know, is a poison.) The resulting painful salivations, he believed, took away the ailment. Making a patient vomit was a cure for a wide variety of ills, and was often accompanied by bleeding. He ended constipation with his famed bilious pills, compounded out of calomel (which contains mercury) and jalap. The concoctions were popularly, and appropriately, 
known as <name type="person" key="Rush, Benjamin">Rush's</name> Thunderbolts.</p>
               <p>
In following his recommendations, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> filled a specially made chest with 1,300 doses of physic, 1,100 doses of emetics designed to induce vomiting, 3,500 pills to cause sweating, and various drugs for increasing salivation and kidney output. Less harmful were 15 pounds of pulverized Peruvian bark, at a cost of $30 (it contained quinine for soothing malaria), and 30 gallons of strong spirit wine that could be diluted and spooned into patients as medicine. Instruments included lancets, a clyster syringe for enemas, and four pewter penis syringes for urethral irrigations for the relief of gonorrhea.<ref target="n0309" n="9"/>
               </p>
               <p>
To these cures <name type="person" key="Rush, Benjamin">Rush</name> added written suggestions for maintaining health. Do not march when indisposed (though the men had a continent to cross) but rest in a <hi rend="italic">horizontal</hi> position (Rush's emphasis). Use spirits for washing tired feet; take internally no more than three tablespoonfuls of liquor to refresh a chilled or weary body. At mealtime try water laced with molasses and a few drops of sulphuric acid. During difficult and laborious enterprises, <hi rend="italic">eat sparingly</hi>. Wash your feet every morning with cold water. Beware of 
constipation.<ref target="n0310" n="10"/> In the event, the last admonition was the only one followed.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Rush, Benjamin">Rush</name> also suggested, at <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name> request, some of the things <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> should concentrate on while studying Indians. What diseases did they have? ("Is the bilious fever ever attended by a black vomit?") What remedies do they use? At what age do women begin and cease to menstruate? Take a sampling of pulse rates of both children and adults morning, noon, and night. What about their bathing habits? Do they ever commit suicide for love? Is murder common? Do they sacrifice animals during their worship? How do they dispose of their dead?<ref target="n0311" n="11"/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Patterson, Robert">Robert Patterson's</name> advice about surveying—he was professor of mathematics at the University of <name type="place" key="Philadelphia, Pa.">Philadelphia</name>—was far more practical than <name type="person" key="Rush, Benjamin">Rush's</name> about health. Only a hint of it has survived, however, in a problem in astronomy he sent <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, saying it was a sample of the training he would give <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>. Elementary, he described it, "easy even to boys or common sailors of but moderate capacity," whereupon he filled several sheets of paper with figures and formulas. He also recommended certain statistical tables the explorer should take with him to speed his calculations.<ref target="n0312" n="12"/> Just learning to use those was something of a feat for a young man already overloaded with considerations.</p>
               <p>
At <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name> behest two more of the university's professors added their bits, <name type="person" key="Barton, Benjamin Smith">Dr. Benjamin Smith Barton</name>, a physician and naturalist, and <name type="person" key="Wistar, Caspar">Caspar Wistar</name>, the professor of anatomy. <name type="person" key="Barton, Benjamin Smith">Barton</name> presumably helped <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> with taxonomy and recommended texts, including his own famed Elements of Botany, which <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> purchased for six dollars, a high price for a book in those days. <name type="person" key="Wistar, Caspar">Wistar</name> perhaps made suggestions about fossils, a field in which he was skilled, but since neither man's offerings were put into writing, this is mostly guesswork. Nor is it written anywhere that <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> visited, for purposes of study, <name type="person" key="Peale, Charles W.">Charles Willson Peale's</name> natural history museum, the first of its kind in the United States and located, at that time, in <name type="place" key="Independence Hall">Independence Hall</name>, but it would be most uncharacteristic if he had overlooked the opportunity.</p>
               <p>
In spite of, perhaps because of, his busy days, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> enjoyed <name type="place" key="Philadelphia, Pa.">Philadelphia</name>. He was associated with important men who clearly liked him, and he was in charge of an enterprise whose successful completion conceivably could bring him lasting fame. When night fell, he was able to turn to diversions he had grown accustomed to in <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name> household—stimulating company, handsome women, good talk. His guide to <name type="place" key="Philadelphia, Pa.">Philadelphia's</name> social scene was <name type="person" key="Dickerson, Mahlon">Mahlon Dickerson</name>, an entertaining young lawyer and future senator (1817–33) whom he had first met at the White House. They dined together several times, paid calls on various young ladies, and were guests two or three times at the home of <name type="person" key="McKean, Thomas">Thomas McKean</name>, governor of <name type="place" key="Pennsylvania">Pennsylvania</name>. There <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> again encountered <name type="person" key="McKean, Thomas">McKean's</name> handsome, curly-haired son-in-law, the <name type="person" key="Yrujo, Marqués de Casa">Marqués de Casa Yrujo</name>, <name type="place" key="Spain">Spain's</name> minister to the United States.<ref target="n0313" n="13"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Undoubtedly <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> learned that largely through <name type="person" key="Yrujo, Marqués de Casa">Yrujo's</name> efforts the right of shippers to deposit their cargoes at <name type="place" key="New Orleans, La.">New Orleans</name>, a right whose revocation had helped precipitate the expedition, had been restored. It is less certain whether <name type="person" key="Yrujo, Marqués de Casa">Yrujo</name> learned from <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> that the expedition into Upper <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name>, for which he had refused to grant passports, was going ahead anyway. In time to come the ambassador would object so constantly to <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> about his actions concerning <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name> that the exasperated president would demand his recall.<ref target="n0314" n="14"/> Affairs had not reached that pass in May, however, and the meetings passed without jangle, though perhaps with cat-and-mouse games for information that <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, holding the upper hand, would have enjoyed.</p>
               <p>
Another satisfaction came from the solution of a nagging problem about transportation. His initial plan had been to launch the expedition from <name type="place" key="South West Point, Tenn.">South West Point</name>, <name type="place" key="Tennessee">Tennessee</name>, close to the <name type="place" key="Cumberland River">Cumberland River</name>, a major tributary of the <name type="place" key="Ohio River">Ohio</name>. But Congressman <name type="person" key="Dickson, William">William Dickson</name> of <name type="place" key="Tennessee">Tennessee</name>, whom he had counted on to arrange for a keelboat and pirogue, had not answered his letters, and <name type="person" key="McRae, William">Major William McRae</name>, who had been delegated to enlist, on approval, personnel for the expedition, wrote that a sufficient number of qualified men could not be found among the riffraff at the
Point.</p>
               <p>
Meanwhile supplies were piling up in <name type="place" key="Philadelphia, Pa.">Philadelphia</name>—twenty-seven hundred pounds, with another eight hundred or so waiting to be picked up at <name type="place" key="Harpers Ferry, W. Va.">Harpers Ferry</name> for transport across the mountains. The agent responsible, under government contract, for moving all public freight from the <name type="place" key="Atlantic Ocean">Atlantic</name> to the trans-<name type="place" key="Appalacian Mountains">Appalachian</name> area was one <name type="person" key="Linnard, William">William Linnard</name>. He knew roads, boatyards, and military installations. During discussions about the supplies, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and he decided to switch the expedition's departure point from <name type="place" key="Tennessee">Tennessee</name> to <name type="place" key="Pittsburgh, Pa.">Pittsburgh</name>, where the <name type="place" key="Allegheny River">Allegheny</name> and <name type="place" key="Monongahela River">Monongahela</name> rivers join to form the <name type="place" key="Ohio River">Ohio</name>. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> ordered a five-horse outfit for the hauling, and dashed off a letter to the boatyard <name type="place" key="Linnard, William">Linnard</name> recommended, specifying the kind of craft he wanted and asking, overoptimistically, that it be ready for departure by July 20.<ref target="n0315" n="15"/>
               </p>
               <p>
By this time he was eager to be on the move. Except for a few more astronomical lessons from <name type="person" key="Patterson, Robert">Robert Patterson</name>, he had completed what he had been ordered to do, and instructions from <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> about the aims of the expedition as a whole were already at hand. Ostensibly a guide for <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> as he marched west, this remarkable document was also the president's statement to history about the purpose of the quasi-secret, quasi-illegal mission he was about to send on its way. Into it he poured all that had piqued his encyclopedic curiosity during decades of interest in the American West. He did not let the orders rest on his musings alone. Having finished a rough draft, he sent copies to his cabinet members for suggestions.</p>
               <p>
Only <name type="person" key="Gallatin, Albert">Albert Gallatin</name> and <name type="person" key="Lincoln, Levi">Levi Lincoln</name>, the attorney general, had responded at length. <name type="person" key="Gallatin, Albert">Gallatin</name>, remembering military reconnaisance as the original motive behind the expedition, did not want that element dropped, even though the right of deposit had been restored. The antagonistic nations of Europe still might carry their warfare into the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name> Valley. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, therefore, should acquire "a perfect knowledge of the posts, establishments &amp; force 
kept by <name type="place" key="Spain">Spain</name> in upper <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name>," and of the trails British traders used in reaching the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>. For the day might come when the United States would have to seize the area from its French owners and Spanish caretakers to "prevent G.B. from doing the same." His reasoning? The <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> country was bound to be settled eventually "by the people of the U. States." It followed that <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> should determine the area's boundaries, particularly southward 
toward Spanish <name type="place" key="New Mexico">New Mexico</name>, and then examine the land not only for military purposes and scientific knowledge but also for its ability to support a large population. Here indeed was the voice of manifest destiny, unnamed yet but ringing clear.<ref target="n0316" n="16"/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Lincoln, Levi">Levi Lincoln</name> was more concerned with practical politics. <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name> opponents, the Federalists, remained "perverse, hostile, and mali[g]nant." To blunt their barbs, which would be especially sharp if the expedition failed, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> instructions should be given, so far as was possible, a high moral tone. He should be advised, for 
instance, to determine how the Indians' religious and ethical standards could be improved—that is, made more like those of white Protestants. Who could fail to approve of that? Then he added a cautionary note. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name> was inclined to be rash and stubborn. He should be warned that if crises arose along the way, he should retreat rather than charge headlong.<ref target="n0317" n="17"/>
               </p>
               <p>
After incorporating both men's ideas into a new draft, <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> sent it to <name type="place" key="Philadelphia, Pa.">Philadelphia</name> for further comments by <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> tutors and by <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> himself. Reactions were enthusiastic. The only suggestion from any Philadelphian, and that one by implication only, was for the addition of <name type="person" key="Rush, Benjamin">Dr. Rush's</name> queries to the other Indian material.</p>
               <p>
The primary object of the mission, the president wrote (his instructions are printed in full in appendix I) was to explore the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> and any adjoining <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name> stream that offered "direct and practicable communication across the continent for the purpose of commerce." Mapping was to be detailed and exact. To prevent loss of valuable material, copies of the celestial observations were to be entrusted to several trustworthy men; ". . . one of those copies 
[should] be on the paper of the birch, as less liable to injury from the damp than common paper." (There is no indication that such a copy was made; birch bark was not handy in the regions the men traversed.)</p>
               <p>
Since another aim of the expedition was to lay the groundwork for a profitable commerce with the Western Indians, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> should take pains to learn as much as he could about them—tribal names, vocabularies, populations, tribal boundaries, relations with other groups of Indians, occupations, diseases, life styles, and morals. He
should always deal with the natives in a conciliatory manner, assuring them of the desire of the United States "to be neighborly, friendly &amp; useful to them. . . . Confer with them on the points most convenient as mutual emporiums"—by which the president meant government-operated trading factories. He should arrange, if possible, to have influential chiefs visit the United States to see for themselves its power and richness. He should take with him "kine pox," a vaccine for smallpox, a disease to which Native Americans were particularly susceptible, and explain its use. In event of opposition by any "nation" (did <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> mean <name type="place" key="Spain">Spain</name> or <name type="place" key="England">England</name> as 
well as Indian tribes?) he must give way. "In the loss of yourselves, we should lose also the information you will have acquired."</p>
               <p>
Back to commerce: <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> should investigate the possibility of diverting down the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> and into the U.S. the furs currently being sent to the West Coast for barter with ship traders. Most of those fur gatherers were Americans, but a cross-country route would be preferable to the long sea voyages around <name type="place" key="Cape Horn">Cape Horn</name> or the <name type="place" key="Cape of Good Hope">Cape of Good Hope</name>.</p>
               <p>
And the end was not yet. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> was to bring back scientifically oriented reports on the topography, soil, climate, vegetation, animals, and minerals of the land he crossed. He should learn what he could of the southern tributaries of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> and their connection, if any, with the <name type="place" key="Rio Grande">Rio Grande</name> and the <name type="place" key="Colorado River">Colorado River</name>. He should discover, too, the routes Canadian traders used in reaching the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>.</p>
               <p>
As for getting home again, he should consider retracing his outward path, checking his original observations along the way, but only after sending two couriers East by sea—if a ship turned out to be available. If the outward journey had been "eminently dangerous," all could return by sea, again if a trading ship could be contacted. He would be given open letters of credit with which to buy fresh new clothes for his men and pay for the long ocean 
voyage. Lastly, after becoming acquainted with his group, he should name the most dependable among them to be his successor in the event of his being incapacitated or dying along the way.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>
With those awesome charges in mind—the final draft would be drawn up after the last suggestions had been received—<name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> returned to <name type="place" key="Washington D. C.">Washington</name>, arriving sometime in early June.<ref target="n0318" n="18"/> There he learned of astounding news from <name type="place" key="France">France</name>, where the American ambassador, <name type="person" key="Livingston, Robert">Robert Livingston</name>, and <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name> special envoy, <name type="person" key="Monroe, James">James Monroe</name>, had been seeking to obtain <name type="place" key="New Orleans, La.">New Orleans</name> and West <name type="place" key="Florida">Florida</name> from <name type="place" key="Bonaparte, Napoleon">Napoleon</name>. During the talks the <name type="person" key="Talleyrand, Charles">Duc de Talleyrand</name> and <name type="person" key="Barbé-Marbois, François de">François de Barbé-Marbois</name>, head of the French treasury, had suddenly asked whether the United States would be interested in acquiring not pieces of <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name> but <hi rend="italic">all</hi> of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Bonaparte, Napoleon">Napoleon's</name> affairs had come to a crisis. His <name type="place" key="Santo Domingo">Santo Domingo</name> adventure, during which his brother-in-law, <name type="person" key="Leclerc, Charles">General Charles Le-clerc</name>, had died of yellow fever, had collapsed. A renewal of war with <name type="place" key="England">England</name> was imminent. Finally, <name type="person" key="Bonaparte, Napoleon">Bonaparte</name> wanted to impress history by reforming the unwieldy structure of the French government. Restoring <name type="place" key="France">France's</name> New World empire, in short, had become irrelevant, and the first consul was willing to give up the enormous territory he had wrenched from <name type="place" key="Spain">Spain</name> only two and a half years earlier for a mere one hundred and twenty million francs—this despite his promise to <name type="person" key="Carlos IV">Carlos IV</name> that he would never sell the territory, least of all to the United States.</p>
               <p>
Unable to conceal their astonishment, the American envoys stammered they had no authority to make such a purchase. How sad, <name type="person" key="Barbé-Marbois, François de">Barbé-Marbois</name> murmured to <name type="place" key="Livingston, Robert">Livingston</name>. For when war broke out, as assuredly it would, British naval forces in the Caribbean most probably would seize <name type="place" key="New Orleans, La.">New Orleans</name> for their nation, as a step toward <name type="place" key="Canada">Canada</name> and the eventual boxing in of the Americans between the <name type="place" key="Atlantic Ocean">Atlantic</name> and the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name>. In order to prevent such a disaster would it not be well to seize the initiative—and quickly, since <name type="person" key="Bonaparte, Napoleon">Napoleon</name> would not wait?</p>
               <p>
Late in the night of April 12, 1803, <name type="person" key="Livingston, Robert">Livingston</name> hurried to his desk in the American legation, and, writing feverishly until 3:00 <hi rend="smallcaps">A.M.</hi> on the 13th, described the situation in a long dispatch to <name type="person" key="Madison, James">Secretary of State James Madison</name>. He and <name type="person" key="Monroe, James">Monroe</name>, he said in effect, had no choice but to go ahead with the negotiations, holding 
the price to as low a figure as they could.<ref target="n0319" n="19"/>
               </p>
               <p>
So affairs stood when <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name> reached <name type="place" key="Washington D. C.">Washington</name>. Luck again! Pure, shining luck! His expedition, which had been designed to pussyfoot ambiguously around in someone else's territory, showing off its wares to Indians attached commercially to other nations, suddenly was on the edge of achieving real historic status as the first Americans to explore officially the almost totally unknown lands beyond the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name>. American lands, for surely 
<name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> would not repudiate the negotiations now. The purchase completed, a new gloss would inform every mile <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> traveled. Every item of knowledge he acquired would be American knowledge, for the use of generations of Americans still to come.</p>
               <p>
Americans as far west as the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>? Why not? <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name> certainly embraced the headwaters of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> in the north and possibly reached even to the <name type="place" key="Rio Grande">Rio Grande</name> in the south. Territory beyond these limits might well fall into his country's hands through what was sometimes called the principle of contiguity—especially if he and his handful of men found a river that would let them link their overland discoveries to those made eleven years
earlier by <name type="person" key="Gray, Robert">Robert Gray</name>, when he had sailed his ship into the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> on May 11, 1792.</p>
               <p>
Sea to shining sea! And he was on hand with his head crammed with astronomical formulas, his medicine chest with pills, and his packing boxes with Indian goods, ready to make the most of his fortune . . . provided something had not happened in <name type="place" key="Paris">Paris</name> to end the negotiations before the purchase was completed. Suspense gnawed at him. If only transatlantic communications weren't so slow!</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="notes" type="notes">
            <head rend="center">Notes</head>
            <div type="section">
               <note xml:id="n0301" n="1">Russell, 37–43, 278–85. Figures from Jackson, Letters, 70, 72.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0302" n="2">
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> account of the boat building is by no means clear. Jackson, Letters, 39–40. For dimensions: Cutright, <hi rend="italic">Pioneering Naturalists</hi>, 165; <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>, II, 245.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0303" n="3">Jackson, <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, 43, and <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> and Stony Mountains</hi>, 135.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0304" n="4">Jackson, <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, 40.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0305" n="5">Ronda, 9.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0306" n="6">Jackson, <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, II, 735. Chatters, 4–6.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0307" n="7">Chuinard, 121–44.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0308" n="8">Ibid., 68–69.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0309" n="9">Cutright, "I Gave Him Barks." Jackson, <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, 80, 88, 93.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0310" n="10">Jackson, <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, 53.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0311" n="11">Ibid., 50.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0312" n="12">Ibid., 28–31, 56.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0313" n="13">Dickerson, "Diary," in ibid., 679–81.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0314" n="14">Malone, V, 78–79.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0315" n="15">Jackson, <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, 53–54.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0316" n="16">Ibid., 32–34.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0317" n="17">Ibid., 34–36. <name type="person" key="Lincoln, Levi">Lincoln's</name> suggestions "sharpened focus on the approach the expedition should take to the tribes, which in too many cases was roughshod and calculated to produce hostility." Ronda, 2, 7.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0318" n="18">It is possible <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> did not reach <name type="place" key="Washington D. C.">Washington</name> until June 17, 1803. (See his letter to <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> in Jackson, <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, 57.) However, he seems to have left <name type="place" key="Philadelphia, Pa.">Philadelphia</name> before June 11. (Note dates referring to his trip in ibid., 54, 51.) A young man on horseback could easily cover the 130 miles separating <name type="place" key="Philadelphia, Pa.">Philadelphia</name> from <name type="place" key="Washington D. C.">Washington</name> in four days, and three if he pushed himself. A stagecoach, traveling by night as well as by day, would be still faster. So I imagine <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> reached the White House by June 12 and "day before yesterday" refers to the day he penned the first draft of his carefully prepared letter to <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> (see <ref type="editorial" n="lc.lavender.01.04">chapter 4</ref>) and not to the date, June 19, attached to the final draft.</note>
               <note xml:id="n0319" n="19">The negotiations about <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name> have been summarized in DeConde, 148–75; Sprague, 299–313; and Malone, IV, 286–96.</note>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.lavender.01.02" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.lavender.01.00" type="contents"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.lavender.01.04" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
