<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-06-16">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
June 16, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 8</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">June 10–September 26, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1987</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">27-31</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">323</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">240</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
         <geoDecl datum="WGS" xml:id="lc.geo.1806-06-16.01">
            <placeName/>
            <geo>45.8667 -116.0833</geo>
            <note>Camped on a branch of Fish Creek, Idaho County, ID.</note>
         </geoDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Journal Entries</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-11-02</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1806-06-16">June 16, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-06-16.01" n="lc.geo.1806-06-16.01">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Monday June 16th 1806.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
We collected our horses very readily this morning, took breakfast and set out at 6 A. M.; proceeded up the creek about 2 miles through some handsom meadows of fine grass abounding with quawmash, here we passed the creek<ref target="n36061601" n="1"/> &amp; ascended a ridge which led us to the N. E. about seven miles when we arrived at a small branch of <name type="place" key="Hungery Creek">hungry creek</name>.<ref target="n36061602" n="2"/>    the difficulty we met with from the fallen timber detained us untill 11 oC before we reached this place.    here is a handsome little glade in which we found some grass for our horses    we therefore halted to let them graize and took dinner knowing that there was no other convenient situation for that purpose short of the glaids on <name type="place" key="Hungery Creek">hungry creek</name> where we intended to encamp, as the last probable place, at which we shall find a sufficient quantity of grass for many days.    this morning <name type="person" key="Windsor, Richard">Windsor</name> busted his rifle near the muzzle.    before we reached this little branch on which we dined we saw in the hollows and N. hillsides large quatities of snow yet undisolved; in some places it was from two to three feet deep.    vegetation is proportionably backward; the dogtooth violet<ref target="n36061603" n="3"/> is just in blume, the honeysuckle,<ref target="n36061604" n="4"/> huckburry<ref target="n36061605" n="5"/> and a small speceis of white maple<ref target="n36061606" n="6"/> are beginning to put fourth their leaves; these appearances in this comparatively low region augers but unfavourably with rispect to the practibility of passing the mountains, however we determined to proceed, accordingly after taking a haisty meal we set out and continued our rout though a thick wood much obstructed with fallen timber, and intersepted by many steep ravines and high hills.    the snow has increased in quantity so much that the greater part of our rout this evening was over the snow which has become sufficiently firm to bear our horshes, otherwise it would have been impossible for us to proceed as it lay in immence masses in some places 8 or ten feet deep.    we found much difficulty in pursuing the road as it was so frequently covered with snow.    we arrived early in the evening at the place that <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. C.</name> had killed and left the flesh of a horse for us last September.<ref target="n36061607" n="7"/>    [<hi rend="italic">EC?: 19th they got there</hi>]    here is a small glade in which there was some grass, not a sufficiency for our horses but we thought it most advisable to remain here all night as we apprehended if we proceeded further we should find less grass.    the air is pleasent in the course of the day but becomes very cold before morning notwithstanding the shortness of the nights. <name type="place" key="Hungery Creek">Hungry creek</name> is but small at this place but is deep and runs a perfect torrent; the water is perfectly transparent and as cold as ice.    the pitch pine, white pine some larch and firs constite the timber; the long leafed pine extends a little distance on this side of the main branch of <name type="place" key="Lolo (Collins's) Creek (Idaho)">Collins's creek</name>, and the white cedar not further than the branch of <name type="place" key="Hungery Creek">hungry creek</name> on which we dined. I killed a small brown pheasant today,<ref target="n36061608" n="8"/> it feeds on the tender leaves and buds of the fir and pitch pine.    in the fore part of the day I observed the Cullumbine<ref target="n36061609" n="9"/> the blue bells<ref target="n36061610" n="10"/> and the yelow flowering pea<ref target="n36061611" n="11"/> in blume.    there is an abundance of a speceis of anjelico<ref target="n36061612" n="12"/> in these mountains, much stonger to the taist and more highly scented than that speceis common to the U' States.    know of no particular virtue or property it possesses; the natives dry it cut it in small peices which they string on a small cord and place about their necks; it smells very pleasantly.    we came 15 miles today.
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-06-16.02" n="lc.geo.1806-06-16.01">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Monday June 16th 1806</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
Collected our horses early and Set out 7 A M  proceeded on up the Creek through a gladey Swompy bottom with grass and quawmash Crossed the Creek to the East and proceeded on through most intolerable bad fallen timber over a high Mountain on which great quantity of Snow is yet lying premisquissly through the thick wood, and in maney places the banks of snow is 4 feet deep.    we noned it or dined on a Small Creek in a small open Vally where we found Some grass for our horses to eate, altho Serounded by Snow    no other Convenient Situation Short of the glades on <name type="place" key="Hungery Creek">Hungery Creek</name> where we intended to encamp, as the last probable place, at which we Shall find a Sufficent quantity of grass for maney days. This morning <name type="person" key="Windsor, Richard">Windsor</name> bursted his rifle near the Muzzle. Vigitation is propotionable backward; the dog tooth Violet is just in blume, the honeysuckle, huckleberry and a Small Species of white maple are beginning to put foth their leaves, where they are clear of the Snow, those appearances in this comparratively low region augers but unfavourably with respect to the practibility of passing the Mountains, however we deturmine to proceed, accordingly after takeing a hasty meal we Set out and Continued our rout through a thick wood much obstructed with fallen timber, and interupted by maney Steep reveins and hills which wer very high.    the Snow has increased in quantity So much that the great part of our rout this evening was over the Snow which has become Sufficently firm to bear our horses, otherwise it would have been impossible for us to proceed as it lay in emince masses in Some places 8 or ten feet deep. We found much dificulty in finding the road, as it was So frequently covered with Snow.    we arived early in the evening at the place I had killed and left the flesh of a horse for the party in my rear last Septr.    here is a Small glade in which there is Some grass, not a Sufficency of our horses, but we thought it adviseable to remain here all night as we apprehended if we proceeded further we should find less grass. The air is pleasant in the Course of the day, but becomes very cold before morning not withstanding the Shortness of the night. <name type="place" key="Hungery Creek">Hungary Creek</name> is but Small at this place but is deep and runs a perfect torrent; the water is perfectly transparent and as Cold as ice.    the titch pine, white pine Some Larch and firs consists the timber, the long leafed pine extends but a Short distance on the Mts. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. L.</name> killed a Small brown pheasant today, it feeds on the tender leaves and buds of the fir and pitch pine.    in the forepart of the day I observed the Cullumbine the blue bells and the Yellow flowering pea in blume.    there is an abundance of a Species of Anjelico in the mountains much Stronger to the taiste, and more highly Scented than that Species common to the U' States. I know of no particular virtue or property it posesses    the nativs dry it Cut it in Small pieces which they string on a Small Cord and place about the necks; it Smells pleasently.    we Come 15 Ms. today.
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-06-16.03" n="lc.geo.1806-06-16.01">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Monday 16th June 1806.    two of our hunters went on to a glade a Short distance to hunt    we took an eairly breakfast    the morning fair.    we Set out    proced on    overtook the hunters who had killed nothing.    folled up the glade and mountains Some distance then took the hills on to a ridge of falling timber    towards noon we passed over high banks of Snow which bore
up our horses. Some places 5 or 6 feet deep    about noon we halted at a Small branch<ref target="n36061613" n="13"/> &amp; green to dine    the grass is verry Short and in the woods jest Starting up.    delayed about 2 hours and Set forward again.    light Showers of rain this afternoon    the Snow is more Common and much deeper.    towards evening we came on <name type="place" key="Hungery Creek">hungry creek</name>
                  <ref target="n36061614" n="14"/>    followed down it to a green where <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name> killed a horse last fall for the party to eat.    here we Camped.<ref target="n36061615" n="15"/>    the young grass verry Short.    the bushes are all bent flat down by the deep Snow lying on them.    the Snow must fall in these hollars in the winter 15 or 20 feet deep and perhaps the Snow drifts in and fills the hollars full.


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-06-16.04" n="lc.geo.1806-06-16.01">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Monday 16th.</hi>    We had a pleasant morning, and renewed our journey; went up a handsome creek about three miles, and then took to the hills which are very rough, with a great many banks of snow, some of them four or five feet deep. These banks are so closely packed and condensed, that they carry our horses, and are all in a thawing state. We halted for dinner at a handsome stream where there was some grass for our horses; and in about two hours proceeded on again, and had some rain. In the afternoon we found the snow banks more numerous, extensive and deep: in some of them the snow as much as eight feet deep. In the evening we came to <name type="place" key="Hungery Creek">Hungry
creek</name> (where Capt. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clarke</name> killed a horse last fall and left it for the party) and encamped,<ref target="n36061616" n="16"/> that our horses might get some grass as we do not expect they will get any soon again; and there is not much here.



</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n36061601" n="1">
               <name type="place" key="Eldorado Creek">Eldorado Creek</name>, in <name type="place" key="Idaho County, Idaho">Idaho County</name>, <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>. Space, 31; Peebles (RLC), 22.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36061602" n="2">Actually a branch of <name type="place" key="Fish Creek (Idaho County, Idaho)">Fish Creek</name>, in <name type="place" key="Idaho County, Idaho">Idaho County</name>, not named on <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 70. Space, 31.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36061603" n="3">Dogtooth violet, also called fawn, or glacier, lily, <hi rend="italic">Erythronium grandiflorum</hi> Pursh. It was an undescribed western species that <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> had collected at lower elevations twice earlier (<ref n="1806-05-08" type="related">May 8</ref> and <ref n="1806-06-05" type="related">June 5, 1806</ref>). Hitchcock et al., 1:787–88; Cutright (LCPN), 301, 308, 408.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36061604" n="4">Orange honeysuckle, <hi rend="italic">Lonicera ciliosa</hi> (Pursh) DC.; he preserved a specimen of this undescribed species on this day and two weeks earlier at <name type="place" key="Camp Chopunnish (Idaho)">Camp Chopunnish</name>. Hitchcock et al., 4:458; Cutright (LCPN), 308, 410.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36061605" n="5">Mountain huckleberry, <hi rend="italic">Vaccinium membranaceum</hi> Dougl. ex Hook. Hitchcock et al., 4:32; Cutright (LCPN), 212, 422.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36061606" n="6">Rocky Mountain maple, <hi rend="italic">Acer glabrum</hi> Torr., the only species of maple in this part of the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky Mountains</name>. Hitchcock et al., 3:412.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36061607" n="7">At what is now called <name type="place" key="Horsesteak Meadow">Horsesteak Meadow</name>, on <name type="place" key="Hungery Creek">Hungery Creek</name>, just below <name type="place" key="Windy Saddle">Windy Saddle</name> in <name type="place" key="Idaho County, Idaho">Idaho County</name>. The location is marked "Small prarie, Killed a horse," on <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 70. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> party killed the horse on <ref n="1805-09-19" type="related">September 19, 1805</ref> (as Elliott Coues correctly noted it), and <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> found it the following day. Space, 32.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36061608" n="8">Perhaps the Oregon ruffed grouse, <hi rend="italic">Bonasa umbellus sabini,</hi> but see <ref n="1806-03-03" type="related">March 3, 1806</ref>. The red vertical line from here through the remainder of the entry was apparently drawn by <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36061609" n="9">The columbine in this area is the red, or Northwest crimson, columbine, <hi rend="italic">Aquilegia formosa</hi> Fisch. Hitchcock et al., 2:333; Cutright (LCPN), 306, 402.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36061610" n="10">Tall bluebells, <hi rend="italic">Mertensia paniculata</hi> (Ait.) G. Don, is common in this region. Hitchcock et al., 4:225.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36061611" n="11">Mountaon thermopsis, <hi rend="italic">Thermopsis montana</hi> Nutt., is common in this habitat and has bright yellow "pea" flowers. Ibid., 3:352.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36061612" n="12">The angelica-like plant abundant here is licorice-root, <hi rend="italic">Ligusticum verticillatum</hi> (Geyer) Coult. &amp; Rose. Ibid., 3:540. It is highly scented as noted. Lewis would have difficulty distinguishing between <hi rend="italic">Angelica</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Ligusticum</hi> without fruits, which would not have been present on this date.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36061613" n="13">On a branch of <name type="place" key="Fish Creek (Idaho County, Idaho)">Fish Creek</name>, <name type="place" key="Idaho County, Idaho">Idaho County</name>, <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36061614" n="14">
               <name type="place" key="Hungery Creek">Hungery Creek</name>, <name type="place" key="Idaho County, Idaho">Idaho County</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36061615" n="15">At <name type="place" key="Horsesteak Meadow">Horsesteak Meadow</name> on <name type="place" key="Hungery Creek">Hungery Creek</name> just below <name type="place" key="Windy Saddle">Windy Saddle</name>, <name type="place" key="Idaho County, Idaho">Idaho County</name>. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> party killed the horse on <ref n="1805-09-19" type="related">September 19, 1805</ref>, and <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> group found it the next day.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36061616" n="16">Apparently on a branch of <name type="place" key="Fish Creek (Idaho County, Idaho)">Fish Creek</name>, <name type="place" key="Idaho County, Idaho">Idaho County</name>, <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>, although <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> also identifies the main stream as <name type="place" key="Hungery Creek">Hungery Creek</name>.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-06-15" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-06-17" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
