<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1804-05-20">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
May 20, 1804</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 2</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">August 30, 1803–August 24, 1804</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1986</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">240-244</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">6, 374</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jw">Joseph Whitehouse</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 11</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of Joseph Whitehouse, May 14, 1804–April 2, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1997</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">10</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Journal Entries</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-01-08</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1804-05-20">May 20, 1804</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1804-05-20.01" n="">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Sunday May 20th 1804</hi>
                     <ref target="n04052001" n="1"/>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
The morning was fair, and the weather pleasent; at 10 oCk A M. agreably to an appointment of the preceeding day, I was joined by <name type="person" key="Stoddard, Amos">Capt. Stoddard</name>, Lieuts. <name type="person" key="Mulford, Clarence">Milford</name>
                  <ref target="n04052002" n="2"/> &amp; <name type="person" key="Worrell, Stephen">Worrell</name>
                  <ref target="n04052003" n="3"/> together with Messrs. <name type="person" key="Chouteau, René Auguste">A. Chouteau</name>, <name type="person" key="Gratiot, Charles">C. Gratiot</name>, and many other respectable inhabitants of <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>, who had engaged to accompany me to the Vilage of <name type="place" key="Saint Charles, Mo.">St. Charles</name>; accordingly at 12 Oclk after bidding an affectionate adieu to <name type="person" key="Chouteau, Brigitte Saucier">my Hostis</name>, that excellent woman the spouse of <name type="person" key="Chouteau, Jean Pierre">Mr. Peter Chouteau</name>,<ref target="n04052004" n="4"/> and some of my fair friends of <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>, we set forward to that village in order to join my friend companion and fellow labourer <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. William Clark</name> who had previously arrived at that place with the party destined for the discovery of the interior of the continent of North America    the first 5 miles of our rout laid through a beatifull high leavel and fertail prarie which incircles the town of <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> from N. W. to S. E.    the lands through which we then passed are somewhat broken up fertile    the plains and woodlands are here indiscriminately interspersed untill you arrive within three miles of the vilage when the woodland commences and continues to the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>    the latter is extreamly fertile. At half after one P. M. our progress was interrupted [<hi rend="italic">hole</hi>]    the near approach of a violent thunder storm from the N. W. and concluded to take shelter in a little cabbin hard by untill the rain should be over; accordingly we alighted and remained about an hour and a half and regailed ourselves with a could collation which we had taken the precaution to bring with us from <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>.</p>
               <p>
The clouds continued to follow each other in rapaid succession, insomuch that there was but little prospect of it's ceasing to rain this evening; as I had determined to reach <name type="place" key="Saint Charles, Mo.">St. Charles</name> this evening and knowing that there was now no time to be lost I set forward in the rain, most of the gentlemen continued with me, we arrived at half after six and joined <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt Clark</name>, found the party in good health and sperits.    suped this evening with <name type="person" key="Tayon, Charles">Charles Tayong</name> a Spanish Ensign &amp; late Commandant of <name type="place" key="Saint Charles, Mo.">St. Charles</name>    at an early hour I retired to rest on board the barge—    <name type="place" key="Saint Charles, Mo.">St. Charles</name> is situated on the North bank of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> 21 Miles above it's junction with the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name>, and about the same distance N. W. from <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>; it is bisected by one principal street about a mile in length runing nearly parrallel with the river, the plain on which it stands—is narrow tho' sufficiently elivated to secure it against the annual inundations of the river, which usually happen in the month of June, and in the rear it is terminated by a range of small hills, hence the appellation of <hi rend="italic">petit Cote,</hi> a name by which this vilage is better known to the French inhabitants of the <name type="place" key="Illinois">Illinois</name> than that of <name type="place" key="Saint Charles, Mo.">St. Charles</name>. The Vilage contains a Chappel, one hundred dwelling houses, and about 450 inhabitants; their houses are generally small and but illy constructed; a great majority of the inhabitants are miserably pour, illiterate and when at home excessively lazy, tho' they are polite hospitable and by no means deficient in point of natural genious, they live in a perfect state of harmony among each other; and plase as implicit confidence in the doctrines of their speritual pastor, the Roman Catholic priest, as they yeald passive obedience to the will of their temporal master the commandant.    a small garden of vegetables is the usual extent of their cultivation, and this is commonly imposed on the old men and boys; the men in the vigor of life consider the cultivation of the earth a degrading occupation, and in order to gain the necessary subsistence for themselves and families, either undertake hunting voyages on their own account, or engaged themselves as hirelings to such persons as possess sufficient capital to extend their traffic to the natives of the interior parts of the country; on those voyages in either case, they are frequently absent from their families or homes the term of six twelve or eighteen months and alwas subjected to severe and incessant labour, exposed to the ferosity of the lawless savages, the vicissitudes of weather and climate, and dependant on chance or accident alone for food, raiment or relief in the event of malady. These people are principally the decendants of the Canadian French, and it is not an inconsiderable proportian of them that can boast a small dash of the pure blood of the aboriginees of America. On consulting with my friend <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. C.</name> I found it necessary that we should pospone our departure untill 2 P M. the next day and accordingly gave orders to the party to hold themselves in readiness to depart at that hour.—</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captn. Clark</name> now informed me that having gotten all the stores on board the Barge and perogues on the evening of the 13th of May he determined to leave our winter cantainment at the mouth of <name type="place" key="Dubois River">River Dubois</name> the next day, and to ascend the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> as far as the Vilage of <name type="place" key="Saint Charles, Mo.">St. Charles</name>, where as it had been previously concerted between us, he was to wait my arrival; this movement while it advanced us a small distance on our rout, would also enable him to determine whether the vessels had been judiciously loaded and if not timely to make the necessary alterations; accordingly at 4 P. M. on Monday the 14th of May 1804, he embarked with the party in the presence of a number of the neighbouring Citizens who had assembled to witness his departure. during the fore part of this day it rained excessively hard. In my last letter to the President dated at <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> I mentioned the departure of <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name> from <name type="place" key="Dubois River">River Dubois</name> on the 15th Inst,<ref target="n04052005" n="5"/> which was the day that had been calculated on, but having completed the arrangements a day earlyer he departed on the 14th as before mentioned. On the evening of the 14th the party halted and encamped on the upper point of the first Island which lyes near the Larbord shore,<ref target="n04052006" n="6"/> on the same side and nearly opposite the center of this Island a small Creek disimbogues called <name type="place" key="Coldwater (Colewater) Creek">Couldwater</name>.</p>
               <p>
The course and distance of this day was West 4 Miles    the Wind from N. E.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1804-05-20.02" n="">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Sunday 20th May</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
a Cloudy morning    rained and a hard wind last night    I continue to write Rolls, Send 20 men to Church to day<ref target="n04052007" n="7"/>    one man Sick    <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt Lewis</name> and Several Gentlemen arrive from <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St Louis</name> thro a violent Shoure of rain, the most of the party go to the Church</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1804-05-20.03" n="">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Sunday 20th May</hi> [<hi rend="italic">NB: at <name type="place" key="Saint Charles, Mo.">St Charles</name>
                     </hi>]</date>
               </ab>
               <p>
	A Cloudy morning rained and hard wind from the [<hi rend="italic">blank</hi>] last night, The letter George lost yesterday found by a Country man, I gave the party leave to go and hear a Sermon to day delivered by Mr. [<hi rend="italic">blank</hi>] a romon Carthlick Priest    at 3 oClock <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Capt. Lewis</name>
                  <name type="person" key="Stoddard, Amos">Capt. Stoddard</name> accompanied by the Officers &amp; Several Gentlemen of <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St Louis</name> arrived in a heavy Showr of Rain    Mssr. Lutenants <name type="person" key="Mulford, Clarence">Minford</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Worrell, Stephen">Werness</name>. <name type="person" key="Gratiot, Charles">Mr. Choteau Grattiot</name>, <name type="person" key="Delaunay, David">Deloney</name>, <name type="person" key="Labbadie, Sylvester">LaberDee</name>
                  <name type="person" key="Rankin, James">Ranken</name>
                  <ref target="n04052008" n="8"/>
                  <name type="person" key="Saugrain, Antoine François">Dr. SoDrang</name>
                  <ref target="n04052009" n="9"/>
               </p>
               <p>
rained the greater part of this evening. Suped with <name type="person" key="Tayon, Charles">Mr. Charles Tayon</name>, the late Comdt. of <name type="place" key="Saint Charles, Mo.">S: Charles</name> a Spanish Ensign.

	
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1804-05-20.04" n="">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>

Sunday May 20th 1804. I and a nomber of the party went to the Mass, &amp; Saw them perform &amp;C</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1804-05-20.05" n="">
            <sp who="cf">
               <speaker>Floyd</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Sunday may 20th 1804    〈saved    a number of the party went to <name type="place" key="Saint Charles, Mo.">St [Charles]</name> and saw them [illegible] and S〉 nothing worth Relating to day



</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1804-05-20.06" n="">
            <sp who="jw">
               <speaker>Whitehouse</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Sunday 20th May 1804.    Several of the party went to church, which the french call Mass, and Saw their way of performing &amp;c.—</p>
               <p>
Sunday may 20th    This day several of our party went to the Chapel, where Mass was said by the Priest, which was a novelty to them.—


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n04052001" n="1">This entry occupies the major portion of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> fragmentary Codex Aa. See <ref n="introduction.general" type="related">Introduction</ref> and <ref n="v02.appendix.c" type="related">Appendix C</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n04052002" n="2">"<name type="person" key="Mulford, Clarence">Milford</name>" to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and "<name type="person" key="Mulford, Clarence">Minford</name>" to <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, he was <name type="person" key="Mulford, Clarence">Clarence Mulford</name>, first commissioned in 1800, from the state of <name type="place" key="New Jersey">New Jersey</name>. In 1804 he was a lieutenant in <name type="person" key="Stoddard, Amos">Captain Amos Stoddard's</name> artillery company; he resigned in 1811. Heitman, 482.</note>
            <note xml:id="n04052003" n="3">
               <name type="person" key="Worrell, Stephen">Stephen Worrell</name>, of <name type="place" key="Pennsylvania">Pennsylvania</name>, was another of <name type="person" key="Stoddard, Amos">Stoddard's</name> junior officers. He was appointed in 1801 and resigned in 1806. Ibid., 713.</note>
            <note xml:id="n04052004" n="4">Lewis's hostess was <name type="person" key="Chouteau, Jean Pierre">Pierre Chouteau's</name> second wife, <name type="person" key="Chouteau, Brigitte Saucier">Brigitte Saucier Chouteau</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n04052005" n="5">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> last known letter to <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> before leaving <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> does not mention the date of departure; it is simply a list of goods shipped to <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> and is largely in <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> hand. Possibly the list was an enclosure with the letter referred to by <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> to <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, May 18, 1804, Jackson (LLC), 1:192–94 and headnote.</note>
            <note xml:id="n04052006" n="6">The first letter of the word appears to be "<hi rend="italic">L</hi>," but <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> entries for <ref n="1804-05-14" type="related">May 14</ref> clearly locate the island on the starboard side.</note>
            <note xml:id="n04052007" n="7">
               <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> was one of them, and perhaps <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse</name>, although his journal is unclear on the point.</note>
            <note xml:id="n04052008" n="8">
               <name type="person" key="Labbadie, Sylvester">Sylvester Labbadie</name> was related to the Chouteaus by marriage. <name type="person" key="Delaunay, David">David Delaunay</name> became a judge under the new government. <name type="person" key="Rankin, James">James Rankin</name>, identified by Thwaites as "an early settler," was a surveyor and the first sheriff of <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> until removed from office in 1805. Thwaites (LC), 1:22 n. 1; Houck, 2:225, 383.</note>
            <note xml:id="n04052009" n="9">
               <name type="person" key="Saugrain, Antoine François">Dr. Antoine Fran<seg n="u231">ç</seg>ois Saugrain</name> was born in Paris and educated in physics, chemistry, and mineralogy, as well as medicine. After an adventurous career that included travel in <name type="place" key="Mexico">Mexico</name> in the service of <name type="place" key="Spain">Spain</name> and capture by Indians along the <name type="place" key="Ohio River">Ohio River</name>, he brought a party of French immigrants to settle at <name type="place" key="Gallipolis, Ohio">Gallipolis, Ohio</name>, in 1790. In 1800 he settled in <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>, where he was surgeon for the Spanish troops, and in 1805 he received a similar appointment in the U.S. Army from <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">President Jefferson</name>. He was known to <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, who as minister to <name type="place" key="France">France</name> in 1787 had given <name type="person" key="Saugrain, Antoine François">Saugrain</name> a letter of introduction to <name type="person" key="Clark, George Rogers">George Rogers Clark</name>; hence, he was probably also known to <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark</name>, at least by reputation. He apparently gave help and advice to the captains before the expedition, although the story that he scraped the back off his wife's mirror to provide them with mercury for a thermometer is probably untrue. <name type="person" key="Saugrain, Antoine François">Saugrain</name> has been called the "First Scientist in the Mississippi Valley." Chuinard, 195–212; Jackson (TJ), 45, 62 n. 7; <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> to <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>, May 18, 1804, Jackson (LLC), 1:192.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1804-05-19" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1804-05-21" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
