<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.preface.v02">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">Volume 2 Preface</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author>William Clark</author>
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 2</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">August 30, 1803–August 24, 1804</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1986</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">vii-x</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Journal Editorial</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-01-22</date>
            <date/>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>
            <name/>Initial creation Transcribed</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="main">Volume 2 Preface</head>
         <div type="preface">
            <p>An entirely new and complete edition of the journals of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> expedition has been a hope of scholars and enthusiasts for many years. Realizing the deficiencies and incompleteness of the volumes done by Reuben Gold Thwaites in 1904–5, Donald Jackson may have been the first to formally declare the need. In an address to the Centennial Conference of the Missouri Historical Society in March 1967, he pointed out what had been apparent for some time: using the multiple published editions of the journals was becoming increasingly difficult, and "some kind of standard edition" was needed. But, his clarion call for action went unheeded for nearly a decade.</p>
            <p>In 1977, an article recommending reissuing several important historical travel accounts in a modern format, among them <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> epic work, came to the attention of the University of Nebraska Press. Excited about the possibilities for a new edition, members of the press set out to determine if a wider level of interest for such a project existed. They turned first to an organization newly formed at the University of Nebraska, the Center for Great Plains Studies. The center was developed in 1976 out of a desire of several university professors to take an interdisciplinary approach to studying the <name type="place" key="Great Plains">Great Plains</name> region of North America. The activities of the center are directed toward exploring all aspects of the <name type="place" key="Great Plains">Great Plains</name> environment: the land, the people, the wildlife, the institutions, the economy, and the cultures of the <name type="place" key="Great Plains">Great Plains</name>. The board of directors for the center were attracted from the start to the idea of sponsoring a new edition of the journals. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> were the first Americans to cross and describe the <name type="place" key="Great Plains">Great Plains</name>, and much of the territory that the Corps of Discovery were assigned to examine lies within the region. Moreover, through the center a large number of scholars would be available for consultation with the proposed project. The board of directors were ready to accept sponsorship of the project, and members of the press were encouraging about the prospects of publication.</p>
            <p>The Center for Great Plains Studies then moved to discover the scope and dimensions of such a project. Donald Jackson, serving as a consultant sought the cooperation of institutions that hold original <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> materials and ascertained available financial support. His work was a success throughout. Not only did all the institutions with <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> materials agree to share their journals and manuscripts with the anticipated project, but the principal holding institution, the American Philosophical Society, agreed to cosponsor the project should it materialize. In addition, Jackson wrote the first draft of a proposal to be submitted to the National Endowment for the Humanities, which became the basis for the final and successful proposal granted by NEH in July 1980.</p>
            <p>By mid–1979, the project to publish a completely reedited version of the journals was under way under the present editor. The edition is cosponsored by the Center for Great Plains Studies of the University of Nebraska and by the American Philosophical Society, with the encouragement and cooperation of all repositories of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> manuscripts. The National Endowment for the Humanities, a principal funding agency for editorial projects, has continued its financial support, and the National Historical Publications and Records Commission has also endorsed the project.</p>
            <p>The new edition will number eleven volumes, which will include an atlas of maps from the expedition; the journals of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, <name type="person" key="Floyd, Charles">Charles Floyd</name>, <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">John Ordway</name>, <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Patrick Gass</name>, and <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Joseph Whitehouse</name> (all the extant journals associated with the expedition); and a volume of the expedition's natural history materials, including reproductions of the herbarium sheets that <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> gathered on the trip, now at the Academy of Natural Sciences, <name type="place" key="Philadelphia, Pa.">Philadelphia</name>. The first volume of the new edition, <hi rend="italic">Atlas of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition,</hi> was published in 1983. The maps were published first so that they could be used as a resource and reference tool for succeeding volumes. The present volume is the first of the nine journal volumes to follow.</p>
            <p>It is a pleasure to acknowledge the numerous people who have been so helpful during the work on the journals of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>. First, recognition should go to the able and considerate workers at the institutions that hold the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> manuscripts.</p>
            <p>
               <table rows="14" cols="1">
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Academy of Natural Sciences, <name type="place" key="Philadelphia, Pa.">Philadelphia</name>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">    A. E. Schuyler</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">American Philosophical Society, <name type="place" key="Philadelphia, Pa.">Philadelphia</name>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">    Whitfield J. Bell, Jr., Beth Carroll-Horrocks, Stephen Catlett, Murphy D. Smith</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Beinecke Rare Book Library, Yale University, New Haven, Connecticut</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">    Archibald Hanna, George A. Miles</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Missouri Historical Society, St. Louis</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">    Beverly D. Bishop, Anthony R. Crawford, Frances H. Stadler</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Newberry Library, Chicago</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">    John Aubrey, Herbert T. Hoover</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">State Historical Society of Missouri, Columbia</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">    Lynn Wolf Gentzler</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">State Historical Society of Wisconsin, Madison</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">    Josephine L. Harper</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>Numerous scholars in diverse fields have helped clarify the variety of scientific endeavors in which the captains were engaged. Those experts gave much in time and advice, most with little hope of reward other than the advancement of scholarship to which they are so dedicated. Not listed are persons whose published works were so important. Those debts are acknowledged in the bibliography.</p>
            <p>
               <table rows="14" cols="1">
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Anthropology, ethnology, linguistics:</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
    Warren Caldwell, University of Nebraska–Lincoln<lb/>
    Raymond J. DeMallie, Indiana University<lb/>
    Ives Goddard III, Smithsonian Institution<lb/>
    James B. Griffin, University of Michigan<lb/>
    John E. Koontz, University of Colorado<lb/>
    John Ludwickson, Nebraska State Historical Society<lb/>
    Kenneth Miner, University of Kansas<lb/>
    Douglas R. Parks, Indiana University<lb/>
    Robert L. <name type="person" key="Rankin, James">Rankin</name>, University of Kansas<lb/>
    Mildred Mott Wedel, Smithsonian Institution<lb/>
    Waldo R. Wedel, Smithsonian Institution<lb/>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Archaeology:</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
    Donald L. Johnson, University of <name type="place" key="Illinois">Illinois</name>, Champaign–Urbana<lb/>
    Thomas D. Thiessen, Midwest Archeology Center, Lincoln<lb/>
    W. Raymond Wood, University of Missouri–Columbia<lb/>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Astronomical instruments:</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
    Silvio A. Bedini, Smithsonian Institution<lb/>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Botany:</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
    A. T. Harrison, University of Nebraska–Lincoln<lb/>
    Curtis M. Twedt, Nebraska Game and Parks Commission<lb/>
    Kathleen Young, Nebraska State Museum, Lincoln<lb/>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Geology:</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
    T. Mylan Stout, University of Nebraska–Lincoln<lb/>
    Michael R. Voorhis, University of Nebraska–Lincoln<lb/>
    William Wayne, University of Nebraska–Lincoln<lb/>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Miscellaneous subjects:</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
    John L. Allen, University of Connecticut (geography, cartography)<lb/>
    Patrice Berger, University of Nebraska–Lincoln (French)<lb/>
    Paul R. Cutright, Jenkintown, <name type="place" key="Pennsylvania">Pennsylvania</name> (history, natural history)<lb/>
    William E. Foley, Central Missouri State University (history)<lb/>
    Donald Jackson, Colorado Springs (history, editing)<lb/>
    Joseph Porter, Joslyn Art Museum, <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Omaha</name> (history, ethnology)<lb/>
    James P. Ronda, Youngstown State University (history, ethnology)<lb/>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Zoology</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
    James Ducy, <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Omaha</name> (birds)<lb/>
    Patricia Freeman, University of Nebraska–Lincoln (mammals)<lb/>
    Virginia C. Holmgren, Portland, Oregon (birds)<lb/>
    Paul A. Johnsgard, University of Nebraska–Lincoln (birds)<lb/>
    John D. Lynch, University of Nebraska–Lincoln (fishes)<lb/>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>Persons who have supported the project out of devotion to the expedition are legion. Words of encouragement, financial help, and constant good will from them have made this project more pleasant and its success more sure. One organization, the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Trail Heritage Foundation, has been exemplary in its encouragement, but space does not allow naming its nearly eight hundred members.</p>
            <p>
               <table rows="1" cols="2">
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Irving W. Anderson<lb/>
Hazel Bain<lb/>
Robert B. Betts<lb/>
Chanler C. Biggs<lb/>
Harold B. and Jane Billian<lb/>
Robert C. Carriker<lb/>
Marilyn Clark<lb/>
E. G. Chuinard<lb/>
Dale Davidson<lb/>
Clarence H. Decker<lb/>
V. Strode and Beverly Hinds<lb/>
Helen Hetrick<lb/>
Paul L.	Hedren<lb/>
Mildred R. Goosman
</cell>
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
Robert E. and Ruth Lange<lb/>
Arlen J. Large<lb/>
Robert L. and Gladys Levis<lb/>
Margaret Norris<lb/>
Bob Saindon<lb/>
William P. Sherman<lb/>
Bob and Idena Singer<lb/>
Everett L. Sparks<lb/>
Gail M. and Ellie Stensland<lb/>
Bunky Sullivan<lb/>
Robert Taylor<lb/>
Ralph S. Thompson<lb/>
Edrie L. Vinson<lb/>
L. Edwin Wang<lb/>
Wilbur and Marty Werner
</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>			
Also helpful were members of the Center for Great Plains Studies and those associated with the project more directly:</p>
            <table rows="1" cols="1">
               <row role="data">
                  <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Rosemary Bergstrom, Brian W. Blouet, Rosalind Carr, Frederick C. Luebke, Virginia J. Maca
</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
