<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-08-14">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
August 14, 1805</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 5</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">July 28–November 1, 1805</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1989</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">87-95</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">202</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">125</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jw">Joseph Whitehouse</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 11</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of Joseph Whitehouse, May 14, 1804–April 2, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1997</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">267-269</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
         <geoDecl datum="WGS" xml:id="lc.geo.1805-08-14.01">
            <placeName/>
            <geo>45.2305 -112.637</geo>
            <note>Camped in what they called the Rattlesnake Clifts where the river enters the mountains. Beaverhead County, MT</note>
         </geoDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Journal Entries</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-06-03</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1805-08-14">August 14, 1805</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-08-14.01" n="lc.geo.1805-08-14.01">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Wednesday August 14th</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
In order to give <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name> time to reach the forks of <name type="place" key="Beaverhead (Jefferson) River">Jefferson's river</name> I concluded to spend this day at the <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshone</name> Camp and obtain what information I could with rispect to the country.    as we had nothing but a little flour and parched meal to eat except the berries with which the Indians furnished us I directed <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name> and <name type="person" key="Shields, John">Shields</name> to hunt a few hours and try to kill something, the Indians furnished them with horses and most of their young men also turned out to hunt.    the game which they principally hunt is the Antelope which they pursue on horseback and shoot with their arrows.    this animal is so extreemly fleet and dureable that a single horse has no possible chance to overtake them or run them down.    the Indians are therefore obliged to have recorce to strategem when they discover a herd of the Antelope they seperate and scatter themselves to the distance of five or six miles in different directions arround them generally scelecting some commanding eminence for a stand; some one or two now pursue the herd at full speed over the hills vallies gullies and the sides of precipices that are tremendious to view. thus after runing them from five to six or seven miles the fresh horses that were in waiting head them and drive them back persuing them as far or perhaps further quite to the other extreem of the hunters who now in turn pursue on their fresh horses thus 〈finally〉 worrying the poor animal down and finally killing them with their arrows.    forty or fifty hunters will be engaged for half a day in this manner and perhaps not kill more than two or three Antelopes.    they have but few Elk or black tailed deer, and the common red deer they cannot take as they secrete themselves in the brush when pursued, and they have only the bow and arrow wich is a very slender dependence for killing any game except such as they can run down with their horses. I was very much entertained with a view of this indian chase; it was after a herd of about 10 Antelope and about 20 hunters.    it lasted about 2 hours and considerable part of the chase in view from my tent.    about 1 A. M. the hunters returned had not killed a single Antelope, and their horses foaming with sweat.    my hunters returned soon after and had been equally unsuccessfull. I now directed <name type="person" key="McNeal, Hugh">McNeal</name> to make me a little paist with the flour and added some berries to it which I found very pallateable.</p>
               <p>
The means I had of communicating with these people was by way of <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name> who understood perfectly the common language of jesticulation or signs which seems to be universally understood by all the Nations we have yet seen.<ref target="n19081401" n="1"/>    it is true that this language is imperfect and liable to error but is much less so than would be expected.<ref target="n19081402" n="2"/>    the strong parts of the ideas are seldom mistaken.</p>
               <p>
I now prevailed on the Chief to instruct me with rispect to the geography of his country.    this he undertook very cheerfully, by delienating the rivers on the ground.    but I soon found that his information fell far short of my expectation or wishes.    he drew the river on which we now are to which he placed two branches just above us,<ref target="n19081403" n="3"/> which he shewed me from the openings of the mountains were in view; he next made it discharge itself into a large river which flowed from the S. W. about ten miles below us,<ref target="n19081404" n="4"/> then continued this joint stream in the same direction of this valley or N. W. for one days march and then enclined it to the West for 2 more days march, here he placed a number of heeps of sand on each side which he informed me represented the vast mountains of rock eternally covered with snow through which the river passed.<ref target="n19081405" n="5"/>    that the perpendicular and even juting rocks so closely hemned in the river that there was no possibilyte of passing along the shore; that the bed of the river was obstructed by sharp pointed rocks and the rapidity of the stream such that the whole surface of the river was beat into perfect foam as far as the eye could reach.    that the mountains were also inaccessible to man or horse.    he said that this being the state of the country in that direction that himself nor none of his nation had ever been further down the river than these mountains. I then enquired the state of the country on either side of the river but he could not inform me.    he said there was an old man of his nation a days march below who could probably give me some information of the country to the N. W. and refered me to an old man then present for that to the S. W.—    the Chief further informed me that he had understood from the <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">persed nosed Indians</name>
                  <ref target="n19081406" n="6"/> who inhabit this river below the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">rocky mountains</name> that it ran a great way toward the seting sun and finally lost itself in a great lake of water which was illy taisted, and where the white men lived. I next commenced my enquiries of the old man to whom I had been refered for information relative the country S W. of us.    this he depicted with horrors and obstructions scarcely inferior to that just mentioned.    he informed me that the band of this nation to which he belonged resided at the distance of 20 days march from hence not far from the white people<ref target="n19081407" n="7"/> with whom they traded for horses mules cloth metal beads and the shells which they woar as orniment being those of a species of perl oister.    that the course to his relations was a little to the West of South.    that in order to get to his relations the first seven days we should be obliged to climb over steep and <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">rocky mountains</name> where we could find no game to kill nor anything but roots such as a ferce and warlike nation lived on whom he called the <name type="native_nation" key="Tukudika Indians">broken mockersons</name>
                  <ref target="n19081408" n="8"/> or <name type="native_nation" key="Tukudika Indians">mockersons with holes</name>, and said inhabited those mountains and lived like the bear of other countries among the rocks and fed on roots or the flesh of such horses as they could take or steel from those who passed through their country.    that in passing this country the feet of our horses would be so much wounded with the stones many of them would give out.    the next part of the rout was about 10 days through a dry and parched sandy desert<ref target="n19081409" n="9"/> in which no food at this season for either man or horse, and in which we must suffer if not perish for the want of water.    that the sun had now dryed up the little pools of water which exist through this desert plain in the spring season and had also scorched all the grass.    that no animal inhabited this plain on which we could hope to subsist.    that about the center of this plain a large river passed from S. E. to N. W. which was navigable but afforded neither Salmon nor timber.<ref target="n19081410" n="10"/>    that beyond this plain thee or four days march his relations lived in a country tolerable fertile and partially covered with timber on another large river which ran in the same direction of the former.<ref target="n19081411" n="11"/>    that this last discharged itself into a large river<ref target="n19081412" n="12"/> on which many numerous nations lived with whom his relations were at war but whether this last discharged itself into the great lake or not he did not know.    that from his relations it was yet a great distance to the great or stinking lake as they call the Ocean.    that the way which such of his nation as had been to the Stinking lake traveled was up the river on which they lived and over to that on which the white people lived which last they knew discharged itself into the Ocean, and that this was the way which he would advise me to travel if I was determined to proceed to the Ocean but would advise me to put off the journey untill the next spring when he would conduct me. I thanked him for his information and advise and gave him a knife with which he appeared to be much gratifyed.    from this narative I was convinced that the streams of which he had spoken as runing through the plains and that on which his relations lived were southern branches of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>, heading with the <name type="place" key="Rio de los Apostolos">rivers Apostles</name> and <name type="place" key="Colorado River">Collorado</name>, and that the rout he had pointed out was to the <name type="place" key="Gulf of California">Vermillion Sea</name> or <name type="place" key="Gulf of California">gulph of Callifornia</name>.<ref target="n19081413" n="13"/> I therefore told him that this rout was more to the South than I wished to travel, and requested to know if there was no rout on the left of this river on which we now are, by means of which, I could intercept it below the mountains through which it passes; but he could not inform me of any except that of the barren plain which he said joined the mountain on that side and through which it was impossible for us to pass at this season even if we were fortunate enough to escape from the <name type="place" key="Tukudika Indians">broken mockerson Indians</name>. I now asked <name type="person" key="Cameahwait">Cameahwait</name> by what rout the <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Pierced nosed indians</name>, who he informed me inhabited this river below the mountains, came over to the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>; this he informed me was to the north, but added that the road was a very bad one as he had been informed by them and that they had suffered excessively with hunger on the rout being obliged to subsist for many days on berries alone as there was no game in that part of the mountains which were broken rockey and so thickly covered with timber that they could scarcely pass.    however knowing that Indians had passed, and did pass, at this season on that side of this river to the same below the mountains, my rout was instantly settled in my own mind, povided the account of this river should prove true on an investigation of it, which I was determined should be made before we would undertake the rout by land in any direction. I felt perfectly satisfyed, that if the Indians could pass these mountains with their women and Children, that we could also pass them; and that if the nations on this river below the mountains were as numerous as they were stated to be that they must have some means of subsistence which it would be equally in our power to procure in the same country.    they informed me that there was no buffaloe on the West side of these mountains; that the game consisted of a few Elk deer and Antelopes, and that the natives subsisted on fish and roots principally.    in this manner I spent the day smoking with them and acquiring what information I could with respect to their country.    they informed me that they could pass to the Spaniards by the way of the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">yellowstone river</name> in 10 days. I can discover that these people are by no means friendly to the Spaniard    their complaint is, that the Spaniards will not let them have fire arms and amunition,<ref target="n19081414" n="14"/> that they put them off by telling them if they suffer them to have guns they will kill each other, thus leaving them defenceless and an easy prey to their bloodthirsty neighbours to the East of them, who being in possession of fire arms hunt them up and murder them without rispect to sex or age and plunder them of their horses on all occasions.    they told me that to avoid their enemies who were eternally harrassing them that they were obliged to remain in the interior of these mountains at least two thirds of the year where the suffered as we then saw great heardships for the want of food sometimes living for weeks without meat and only a little fish roots and berries.    but this added <name type="person" key="Cameahwait">Cameahwait</name>, with his ferce eyes and lank jaws grown meager for the want of food, would not be the case if we had guns, we could then live in the country of buffaloe and eat as our enimies do and not be compelled to hide ourselves in these mountains and live on roots and berries as the bear do.    we do not fear our enimies when placed on an equal footing with them. I told them that the <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Minnetares</name>
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name> &amp; <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Recares</name> of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> had promised us to desist from making war on them &amp; that we would indevour to find the means of making the <name type="native_nation" key="Atsina Indians">Minnetares of fort d Prarie</name> or as they call them <name type="native_nation" key="Atsina Indians">Pahkees</name> desist from waging war against them also.    that after our finally returning to our homes towards the rising sun whitemen would come to them with an abundance of guns and every other article necessary to their defence and comfort, and that they would be enabled to supply themselves with these articles on reasonable terms in exchange for the skins of the beaver Otter and Ermin<ref target="n19081415" n="15"/> so abundant in their country.    they expressed great pleasure at this information and said they had been long anxious to see the whitemen that traded guns; and that we might rest assured of their friendship and that they would do whatever we wished them.<ref target="n19081416" n="16"/>
               </p>
               <p>
I now told <name type="person" key="Cameahwait">Cameahwait</name> that I wished him to speak to his people and engage them to go with me tomorrow to the forks of <name type="place" key="Beaverhead (Jefferson) River">Jeffersons river</name> where our baggage was by this time arrived with another Chief and a large party of whitemen who would wait my return at that place.    that I wish them to take with them about 30 spare horses to transport our baggage to this place where we would then remain sometime among them and trade with them for horses, and finally concert our future plans for geting on to the ocean and of the traid which would be extended to them after our return to our homes.    he complyed with my request and made a lengthey harrangue to his village.    he returned in about an hour and a half and informed me that they would be ready to accompany me in the morning. I promised to reward them for their trouble. <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name> who had had a good view of their horses estimated them at 400.<ref target="n19081417" n="17"/>    most of them are fine horses.    indeed many of them would make a figure on the South side of <name type="place" key="James (Jacque) River (S. Dak.)">James River</name> or the land of fine horses.—    I saw several with spanish brands on them, and some mules which they informed me that they had also obtained from the Spaniards. I also saw a bridle bit of spanish manufactary, and sundry other articles which I have no doubt were obtained from the same source.    notwithstanding the extreem poverty of those poor people they are very merry they danced again this evening untill midnight.    each warrior keep one ore more horses tyed by a cord to a take near his lodge both day and night and are always prepared for action at a moments warning.    they fight on horseback altogether.    I observe that the large flies<ref target="n19081418" n="18"/> are extreemly troublesome to the horses as well as ourselves.</p>
               <p>
The morning being cold and the men stif and soar from the exertions of yesterday <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name> did not set out this morning untill 7 A. M.    the river was so crooked and rapid that they made but little way    at one mile he passed a bold runing stream on Stard. which heads in a mountain to the North, on which there is snow.    this we called <name type="place" key="Rattlesnake (Track) Creek (Beaverhead County, Mont.)">track Creek</name>.<ref target="n19081419" n="19"/>    it is 4 yard wide and 3 feet deep    at 7 Ms. passed a stout stream which heads in some springs under the foot of the mountains on Lard.    the river near the mountain they found one continued rapid, wich was extreemly laborious and difficult to ascend.    this evening <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbono</name> struck <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">his indian Woman</name> for which <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. C.</name> gave him a severe repremand. <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Joseph</name> and <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">Reubin Fields</name> killed 4 deer and an Antelope, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. C.</name> killed a buck.    several of the men have lamed themselves by various accedents in working the canoes through this difficult part of the river, and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. C.</name> was obliged personally to assist them in this labour.    they encamped this evening on Lard. side near the <name type="place" key="Rattlesnake Cliffs">rattlesnake Clift</name>.<ref target="n19081420" n="20"/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <table rows="2" cols="3">
                     <head>Courses and distances traveled by <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name>.<lb/>
                        <hi rend="italic">August 14th 1805.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 14° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                           <hi rend="underline">7</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">to the gap of the mountain at the <name type="place" key="Rattlesnake Cliffs">rattlesnake Clifts</name> where the<lb/>
river enters the mountains.    the same being 16 miles by the<lb/>
meanders of the river.    the river cold shoally and one con-<lb/>
tinued rapid throughout.    passed a number of small Islands<lb/>
and bayous on either side.    passed bold running stream on<lb/>
Stard. at 1 M. called <name type="place" key="Rattlesnake (Track) Creek (Beaverhead County, Mont.)">track Creek</name>.    also another at 6 M. higher<lb/>
up, on Lard. side and encamped on Lard. 2 Miles by water<lb/>
short of the extremity of this course distance by land scarcely<lb/>
½ a Mile</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                           <hi rend="right">Miles</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                           <hi rend="double underline">7</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-08-14.02" n="lc.geo.1805-08-14.01">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">August 14th Wednesday 1805.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>		
a Cold morning wind from the S. W. The Thermometer Stood at 51° a 0, a Sunrise the morning being cold and men Stiff. I deturmined to delay &amp; take brackfast at the place we Encamped.    we Set out at 7 oClock and proceeded on river verry Crooked and rapid as below Some fiew trees on the borders near the mountain, passed a bold running Stream at 1 mile on the Stard. Side which heads in a mountain to the North on which there is Snow    passed a bold running Stream on the Lard. Side which heads in a Spring undr. a mountain, the river near the mountain is one continued rapid, which requres great labour to push &amp; haul the Canoes 〈over the〉 up. We Encamped on the Lard Side near the place the river passes thro' the mountain. I checked <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">our interpreter</name> for Strikeing <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">his woman</name> at their Dinner.</p>
               <p>
The hunters <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Jo.</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">R. Fields</name> killed 4 Deer &amp; a antilope, I killed a fat Buck in the evening, Several men have hurt themselves pushing up the Canoes. I am oblige to a pole occasionally.

</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-08-14.03" n="lc.geo.1805-08-14.01">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Wednesday 14th August, 1805</hi>.    a clear cold morning.    the 2 hunters Stayed out all last night.    we took an eairly breakfast and Set out.    the [water?] is verry cold. We have to waid in it which makes our feet and legs ake with cold.    we expect it is made of Springs and near the head of the most of them which causes the River water to be as cold as Spring water.    the upper part of this valley is Smooth and pleasant    passed a large Spring run or creek on the Stard. Side    a handsome valley &amp; Small timber Some distance up it.    the hills appear verry high to the West    about 10 oClock A. m. we came up to the hunters Camp at a grove of cotton timber on L. Side.    they have killed 4 Deer and one antelope.    we proceeded on    the current more rapid oblidged us to hall the large canoes up the rapid &amp; Shole places.    the bottom of the River Shores &amp; bars Stoney.    about one oC. P. m. we halted to dine at a dry part of the plain    a fiew groves of cotton timber along the River    the red &amp; yallow currents common.    the black goose berry verry Sower to the taste. The wind high from S W. the current continued rapid all day. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name> killed a buck.    one of the men killed a faun deer.    we Came [<hi rend="italic">blank</hi>] miles and Camped on the upper part of the valley    a little
timber.    the plain high.    the foot of the mountains near.—


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-08-14.04" n="lc.geo.1805-08-14.01">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Wednesday 14th.</hi>    The morning was clear and cold. We embarked after breakfast; passed a small creek on the north side and a beautiful valley on the same side. Timber is very scarce, and only some few scattering trees along the river. Our hunters<ref target="n19081421" n="21"/> came in at noon, who had been out all day yesterday: they had killed 5 deer and a goat. There are a few deer and goats in this part of the country; and otter and beaver in plenty along the river, but no other kind of game that we could discover. There are some fish in the river and trout of a large size, and of the black kind.<ref target="n19081422" n="22"/> We went 15 miles and encamped on the South side where we had great difficulty in procuring a sufficient quantity of wood to cook with.


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1805-08-14.05" n="lc.geo.1805-08-14.01">
            <sp who="jw">
               <speaker>Whitehouse</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Wednesday 14th August 1805</hi>.    a clear cold morning.    we did not Set out untill we took an eairly breakfast.    the 2 hunters Stayed out last night.    the water in the River is clear and Cold    we are now drawing near the Mountains.    the upper part of the valley pleasant.    passed a Spring run or creek on S. Side a handsome valley Some distance up it.    Some Small timber on its Shores.    about 10 oClock A. m. we came up to the hunters Camp.    they had killed 4 Deer &amp; one antelope.    we proceeded on the current more rapid.    obledged to hale the large canoes over Sholes &amp; rapids.    the Shores &amp; banks of the River Stoney.    halted to dine about one oClock at a dry part of the plain a fine groves of cotten trees &amp;c.    proceeded on took on board a deer and a goat which the hunters had hung on a limb of a tree.    the current continues verry rapid all day.    <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clark</name> killed a buck and one of the men killed a faun deer.    we Came [<hi rend="italic">blank</hi>] miles and Camped on the L. Side at the foot of the Mountains, on the Smooth plain at the upper end of the valley.</p>
               <p>
Wednesday August 14th    We had a Clear cold morning, &amp; did not set out on our Voyage, 'till after we had taken an early breakfast; the two hunters did not return to us last night, the River water is here perfectly Clear, and Cool; we are now near the Mountains, The upper part of the Valley is very pleasant.    We continued on, and passed a run of water, which came from a spring lying on the South side of the River &amp; where a handsome Valley lay near it, and some scattering timber; lying, along the Shore of the River on both sides of it; About 10 o'Clock A. M. we came to where our 2 hunters, that were out last night were encamped; they had killed 4 deer &amp; one Antelope.—    We proceeded on, and found the River running again rapid, which oblig'd us to hawl our Canoes over the Shoals &amp; rapids.    We found the Shores &amp; banks of the River very Stony; About One o'Clock A. M. we halted to dine, at a dry part of the plain, in a Grove of Cotton wood trees.—    We took on board our Canoes here, a deer &amp; a Goat which the hunters had killed and hung on the limbs of trees.    <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain Clark</name> and one of our party, had went out hunting this morning; they returned to us, &amp; had killed a Buck Deer &amp; fawn, which was brought to us.    We came 12 Miles this day, and encamped on the South side of the River, at the foot of the Mountains on a smooth plain at the upper end of a Valley.—


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n19081401" n="1">The sign language was common among all the plains tribes, and those mountain tribes in regular communication with the plains. There were some regional variations, but proficient sign-talkers could adjust easily. As <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> notes, the main ideas were readily communicated. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>. Perhaps it was <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name> who drew a red vertical line through this passage.</note>
            <note xml:id="n19081402" n="2">It appears to be <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> who has interlined, "This part to come in the 20th relatd to <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. C</name> thro the intepreter." He also added an asterisk here and at the end of the addition. See note below. We add a paragraph indention to set off the material. Evidently the <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshones</name> gave <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> the following geographical information through <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name> on <ref n="1805-08-20" type="related">August 20, 1805</ref>, indicating that <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> present entry was written some time after that date. The captains were separated from <ref n="1805-08-18" type="related">August 18</ref> to <ref n="1805-08-29" type="related">29</ref>. Ronda (LCAI), 150–51.</note>
            <note xml:id="n19081403" n="3">Perhaps the two branches were <name type="place" key="Hayden Creek">Hayden Creek</name> and the <name type="place" key="Lemhi (East Fork Lewis's) River">Lemhi River</name> itself, merging near the town of <name type="place" key="Lemhi, Idaho">Lemhi</name>, <name type="place" key="Lemhi County, Idaho">Lemhi County</name>, <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>. Information of Robert N. Bergantino, <name type="place" key="Butte, Mont.">Butte</name>, <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>. Allen would place it farther south, near <name type="place" key="Leadore, Idaho">Leadore</name>. Allen (PG), 295 n. 27.</note>
            <note xml:id="n19081404" n="4">The <name type="place"
                     key="Salmon (Lewis's, Main Fork Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">Salmon River</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n19081405" n="5">The <name type="place"
                     key="Salmon (Lewis's, Main Fork Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">Salmon River</name> runs through the <name type="place" key="Salmon River Mountains">Salmon River Mountains</name>, the <name type="place" key="Clearwater Mountains">Clearwater Mountains</name>, and other ranges in central <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>, some of the most rugged country in the United States. It has acquired the nickname "<name type="place"
                     key="Salmon (Lewis's, Main Fork Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">River of No Return</name>."</note>
            <note xml:id="n19081406" n="6">Probably the first written reference to the <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perces</name> by the name and trait by which they became known in history. The question of whether they actually pierced their noses remains unsettled. See below, <ref n="1805-09-20" type="related">September 20, 1805</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n19081407" n="7">These white people were almost certainly Spanish. Wherever <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> informant lived, it was probably a good deal farther from Spanish settlements in <name type="place" key="California">California</name> or <name type="place" key="New Mexico">New Mexico</name> than <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> supposed. Rees, 12, believes the man came from the <name type="place" key="Duck Valley">Duck Valley</name> region between the forks of the <name type="place" key="Owyhee River">Owyhee River</name> in southwest <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>. The contact may have been indirect, since there was an extensive network of intertribal trade. Also, Spanish traders may have ventured north to meet the Indians at established intertribal trade centers, such as that in southwestern <name type="place" key="Wyoming">Wyoming</name>. Terrell; Ewers (ILUM), 14–33; Hyde (IHP), 157.</note>
            <note xml:id="n19081408" n="8">From the location, these could be the <name type="native_nation" key="Tukudika Indians">Tukudikas</name>, a <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshonean</name> group or groups living in various parts of the northern <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rockies</name>, later referred to by whites as "<name type="native_nation" key="Tukudika Indians">Sheepeaters</name>" because they ate the bighorn sheep. As <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> informant indicated, they eked out a subsistence on a scanty food supply. Rees, 12, indicates that the <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshone</name> name arose from their moccasins being worn out by the lava rocks in their home regions. However, the "<name type="native_nation" key="Tukudika Indians">broken moccasins</name>" have also been identified as the <name type="native_nation" key="Northern Paiute Indians">Bannocks, Northern Paiutes</name> closely associated with the Northern <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshones</name>, and as a mythical people. Swanson, 246–64; <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, 334–35; Hyde (IHP), 124, 157–58; Hodge, 1:129–30; Madsen, 41.</note>
            <note xml:id="n19081409" n="9">Probably the arid <name type="place" key="Snake River Plain">Snake River plain</name> of southern <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>. Allen (PG), 296 n. 30.</note>
            <note xml:id="n19081410" n="10">Their first information about the <name type="place"
                     key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Snake River</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n19081411" n="11">Probably the <name type="place" key="Owyhee River">Owyhee River</name>, a tributary of the <name type="place"
                     key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Snake</name> that runs through eastern <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>. Ibid., 296.</note>
            <note xml:id="n19081412" n="12">The <name type="place"
                     key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Snake</name> again.</note>
            <note xml:id="n19081413" n="13">The <name type="place"
                     key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Snake</name> does head relatively near the upper <name type="place" key="Green River">Green River</name>, a principal tributary of the <name type="place" key="Colorado River">Colorado</name>, but otherwise the captains' surmises were wrong. Traveling up the <name type="place" key="Owyhee River">Owyhee</name> would not take one anywhere near a stream running to either <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">the Pacific</name> or the <name type="place" key="Gulf of California">Gulf of California</name>. The <name type="place" key="Rio de los Apostolos">Rio de los Apostolos</name> was a mythical river of the Southwest which appears on <name type="person" key="King, Nicholas">Nicholas King's</name> map of 1803 (<hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 2) and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>
               <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name> map of 1805 (<hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> maps 32<hi rend="italic">a,</hi> 32<hi rend="italic">b,</hi> 32<hi rend="italic">c</hi>). Ibid., 296–97.</note>
            <note xml:id="n19081414" n="14">The Spanish followed a fairly consistent policy of refusing to trade guns to Indians, in contrast to the French, English, and Americans. Having no direct contact with the Canadian or <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri River</name> trade systems, the <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshones</name> were thus at a great disadvantage, compared to their <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name>, <name type="native_nation" key="Atsina Indians">Atsina</name>, and <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> enemies in obtaining firearms. Secoy, 51–59; Hyde (IHP), 175–76; Ronda (LCAI), 152. Perhaps it was <name type="native_nation" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name> who drew a red vertical line through this passage.</note>
            <note xml:id="n19081415" n="15">Long-tailed weasel, <hi rend="italic">Mustela frenata.</hi> Burroughs, 81–82. See also <ref n="1805-08-20" type="related">August 20, 1805</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n19081416" n="16">Here apparently is the end of the geographical information gathered by <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> on August 20. See note above. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> has interlined, "as low as this in the 20th of the mon: Spoken to <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Cap C.</name>" <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> narrative of events on August 14 then resumes. We add a paragraph indention.</note>
            <note xml:id="n19081417" n="17">It may have been <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name> who drew the red vertical line beginning with this sentence to the end of the paragraph.</note>
            <note xml:id="n19081418" n="18">Horse fly.</note>
            <note xml:id="n19081419" n="19">Evidently later <name type="place" key="Rattlesnake (Track) Creek (Beaverhead County, Mont.)">Rattlesnake Creek</name>, rising on <name type="place" key="Bald Mountain">Baldy Mountain</name>, in <name type="place" key="Beaverhead County, Mont.">Beaverhead County</name>, <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name>. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 66.</note>
            <note xml:id="n19081420" n="20">In <name type="place" key="Beaverhead County, Mont.">Beaverhead County</name>, about ten miles southwest of present <name type="place" key="Dillon, Mont.">Dillon</name> and just downstream of <name type="place" key="Barretts Siding, Mont.">Barretts Siding</name>. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 66.</note>
            <note xml:id="n19081421" n="21">The <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph and Reubin">Field brothers</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n19081422" n="22">Probably one species, the cutthroat trout, <hi rend="italic">Oncorhynchus clarki</hi> (formerly <hi rend="italic">Salmo clarkii</hi>).</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-08-13" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1805-08-15" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
