<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1804-1805.winter.part4">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">Part 4: Mineralogical Collections</title>
            <title type="sub"/>
            <author>Gary E. Moulton</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 3</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">August 25, 1804–April 6, 1805</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1987</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">472-478</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
         <geoDecl datum="WGS" xml:id="lc.geo.1804-1805.winter.part4.01">
            <placeName/>
            <geo> </geo>
            <note>No location. Record of mineral specimens from the American Philosophical Society Donation Book.</note>
         </geoDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Journal Entries</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-04-21</date>
            <date/>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>
            <name/>Initial creation Transcribed</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="main">
            <hi rend="italic">Part 4: Mineralogical Collections</hi>
         </head>
         <head type="sub"/>
         <div type="part">
            <p>
The following list of mineralogical specimens is found in the Donation Book of the American Philosophical Society (see <ref n="v02.appendix.b" type="related">Appendices B</ref> and <ref n="v02.appendix.c" type="related">C</ref>). <name type="person" key="Vaughan, John">John Vaughan</name>, librarian of the Society, may have copied these notes into the book from an original list by <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> or he may have taken the notes directly from identifying tags which were once with the specimens. The specimens are apparently the items in box 4 of the goods sent back from <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name> in April 1805, and designated "Specimens of earths, salts, and minerals, numbered 1. to 67." See Jackson (LLC), 1: 235, 239–40 n. 21; <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> entry, <ref n="1805-04-03" type="related">April 3, 1805</ref>, and accompanying notes. The discrepancy in the number of items (<name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> numbers 67, <name type="person" key="Vaughan, John">Vaughan</name> 68) may be attributed to last minute hurrying by <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> or to a clerical error in <name type="place" key="Philadelphia, Pa.">Philadelphia</name>. <name type="person" key="Seybert, Adam">Adam Seybert</name>, a physician, scientist, and member of the Society, added some comments further identifying the specimens. Those additions are italicized and placed in brackets in this section. The "H" following some items may represent an accession check and may stand for "have."</p>
            <p>
Modern identifications of the specimens are nearly impossible because the descriptions here are so slight and because the specimens have been lost. When Thwaites prepared his edition he called on Edwin H. Barbour, curator of the geological museum, University of Nebraska, to identify the specimens, but the professor had little success. It is doubtful that Barbour saw the specimens so he was at the same disadvantage as we and we are unable to advance identifications much beyond him. Readers are referred to journal entries which correspond to specimen dates for possible geologic references and accompanying annotation.</p>
            <p>
The specimens may not have all arrived safely at <name type="place" key="Philadelphia, Pa.">Philadelphia</name> considering that some items have the note "label only." Apparently at some unknown time the specimens were moved to the <name type="place" key="Academy of Natural Sciences">Academy of Natural Sciences</name>, <name type="place" key="Philadelphia, Pa.">Philadelphia</name>, where they were integrated with the <name type="place" key="Academy of Natural Sciences">Academy's</name> general collections and not differentiated as <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> pieces. Only one item (number nine) has been discovered; it had the original tag still attached, so it could easily be associated with the expedition. It is pictured in Jackson (LLC), 2: following 566.</p>
            <milestone unit="editor_end"/>
            <p>
               <hi rend="center">
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">M. Lewis</name>' Donation continued 16 Nov. 1805.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
No. 1. Specimen of compact salt formed by concretion &amp; found adhering to the rocks, thro' which a Salt fountain Issues, Situated on the South Side of the Southern Branch of the <name type="place" key="Arkansas River">Arcansus River</name>, called by the <name type="native_nation" key="Osage Indians">osage</name> Indians <name type="place" key="Arkansas River">Ne-chu-re-thin-gar</name>. [<hi rend="italic">Muriat of Soda. This salt beyond all doubt is formed in a consequence of water, we held it in solution, having been evaporated in consequence of exposure to the Sun's rays &amp; atmosphere. The crystals are small cubes heaped together and in every respect resemble those procured by art</hi>.]</p>
            <p>
2. Found just above the entrance of the <name type="place" key="Cannonball (Bullet) River">cannon Ball river</name>, the butt[e] is principally composed of this sand &amp; strongly impregnanted with 〈a Substance supposed to be blue vitriol〉    [<hi rend="italic">Sulphat of Iron in consequence of the decomposition of Pyrites</hi>.]</p>
            <p>
3. Flint found at the white Chalk Bluffs 1804</p>
            <p>
4—    <ref n="1804-08-23" type="related">23 Aug 1804</ref>, found exuding from a Strata of Sand rock on [one] of the Bluffs—    [<hi rend="italic">Much resembles the "Atrausent Stein" of the Germans found near Goslar, and consists principally of Sulphat of Iron derived from decomposed Sulphuret of Iron, intermixed with Clay</hi>.]</p>
            <p>
5. Specimen of the Sand of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>. [<hi rend="italic">It is Siliceous sand with a mixture of particles of Mica</hi>.]</p>
            <p>
6 <ref n="1804-08-21" type="related">Augt 21, 1804</ref>    In the interstices of a blue clay which forms the majority of the Bluffs, Strata of all earth or Stone make their appearance &amp; Horizontal. [<hi rend="italic">Alum formed in consequence of a decomposition of aluminous Shistus—&amp; Sulphat of Lime on the lower surface crystallized</hi>.]</p>
            <p>
7 Petrefaction on the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, <ref n="1804-05-30" type="related">May 30, 1804</ref>
            </p>
            <p>
8 Found among the loose earth of the Bluff <ref n="1804-08-23" type="related">23 Aug. 1804</ref> [<hi rend="italic">regular crystals of Gypsum or Sulphat of Lime. Trapezoid</hi>]</p>
            <p>
9 a Petrified jawbone of a fish or some other animal found in a cavern a few miles distance from the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> S side of the River. <ref n="1804-08-06" type="related">6 Aug. 1804</ref>, found by <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Searjant Gass</name>
            </p>
            <p>
10. A Specimen of Earth which forms a narrow Strata in the Bluffs above the Sand rock &amp; beneath a large Strata of blue earth <ref n="1804-08-22" type="related">Augt 22, 1804</ref>—    [<hi rend="italic">Tripoli, nearly colourless &amp; shistose</hi>]</p>
            <p>
11. Generally met with in the Surface of the earth in the level plains &amp; is very common from the <name type="place" key="Calumet Bluff (Nebr.)">calumet Bluff</name> to <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort mandan</name> [<hi rend="italic">Clay with aluminous impregnation derived from decomposed Shistus</hi>.]</p>
            <p>
12. Pebble found at the entrance of the <name type="place" key="Niobrara (Quicurre, Rapid) River">River Quicourre</name>. [<hi rend="italic">Agatised Flint</hi>.]</p>
            <p>
13. <ref n="1804-08-22" type="related">22d Aug. 1804</ref>.    found occupying the interstices of a blue clay which forms the middle Strata of the Bluff &amp; is about 15 feet in Depth. [<hi rend="italic">same as No. 6</hi>.]</p>
            <p>
14 Specimen of the granulated Spontaneous Salt, found at the licks on <name type="place" key="Salt River">Salt River</name> bran[ch] of the <name type="place" key="Platte River (Nebr.)">River Platte</name>, obtained from the <name type="native_nation" key="Oto Indians">Oteoes</name>—[<hi rend="italic">Muriat of Soda inform of an efflorescence</hi>.]</p>
            <p>
15 <ref n="1804-09-01" type="related">Sept. 1, 1804</ref>.    found exuding from a Strata of firm blue earth which forms the majority of the River Bluffs—    [<hi rend="italic">a yellowish clay, probably arising from decomposed Slate</hi>.]</p>
            <p>
16 Presented to me by a <name type="person" key="Griffith">Mr. Griffith</name> near the entrance of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>—    This mineral was presented me by a <name type="person" key="Griffith">Mr Griffith</name> who informed me that it had been procured from an earth, found in a cave of limestone rock on the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississipi</name> a few miles from the entrance of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, by the Same process observed in extracting Saltpetre from the earth of Caverns—    [<hi rend="italic">a mixture of different kinds of Salts</hi>.]</p>
            <p>
17</p>
            <p>
18 <ref n="1804-08-22" type="related">Aug. 22</ref>.    on the Upper part of the Bluff</p>
            <p>
19</p>
            <p>
20—    <ref n="1804-08-22" type="related">Aug 22, 1804</ref>. Is usually found incrusting or overlaying a black Rock which crowns the Summits of most of the river Hills in this quarter. [<hi rend="italic">Sulphat Lime?</hi>]</p>
            <p>
21—    a specimen of a firm blue Earth which formed a large Strata of the Bluffs which we passed from <ref n="1804-08-21" type="related">21 Augt.</ref> to <ref n="1804-09-15" type="related">15 Sep 1804</ref> [<hi rend="italic">Aluminous Shistus in a state of decomposition</hi>.]</p>
            <p>
22. found at the <name type="place" key="Calumet Bluff (Nebr.)">Calumet Bluff</name>. [<hi rend="italic">also resembling "Atramentstein" similar to No. 4</hi>.]</p>
            <p>
23. Salt obtained the <ref n="1804-09-17" type="related">17 Sept. 1804</ref> overlaying a dark blue Clay on the Sides of the river hills, it is So abundant that it impregnates the little rivulets in Such a degree that the water is unfit to drink. [<hi rend="italic">Alum intermixed with Clay</hi>.]</p>
            <p>
24 Carbonated wood found on the Std. side of Riv near <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">fort Mandane</name> 60 feet above high water mark in the Bank Strata 6 Inch thick.</p>
            <p>
25. Precipitate of one pint of <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> water weight 80:65 grs [<hi rend="italic">pincipally common Clay</hi>.]</p>
            <p>
26 Pebbles common to the Sand Bars of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>—    [<hi rend="italic">Agatised flint &amp; small quartzose pebbles</hi>.]</p>
            <p>
27 Specimen of lead ore of Bertons mine on the <name type="place" key="Meramec River">Marimeg River</name>—[<hi rend="italic">Galena or sulphuret of Lead</hi>.]</p>
            <p>
28. <hi rend="italic">Green Earth</hi>, Presented by <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Mr Charbono</name>, who informed me that the natives procure this earth in the neighberhood of the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky mountain</name>, but cannot 〈find〉 point out the place.—    The Indians mix this Earth with glue &amp; paint their arrows with it, when thus boiled with Glue it gives a fine green color to wood, but easily yield to Water    the Indians also paint their Skins with it. M. L: Feby. 13, 1804 [<hi rend="italic">Green Clay coloured by Iron</hi>.]</p>
            <p>
29. Specimen of the lead ore of Bertons' mine on the Marrimic River Upper Louisiana [<hi rend="italic">Galena</hi>]</p>
            <p>
30. <ref n="1804-09-15" type="related">Sep. 15, 1804</ref> found in the interstices of a Brown rock which Sometimes makes its appearance in a Strata of 6 or 8 feet usually about half of the Elevation of the Bluffs—    [<hi rend="italic">Similar to 4 &amp; 22</hi>.]</p>
            <p>
31. Specimen of 〈quartz〉 Carbonat of Lime found on many parts of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> common to the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississipi</name> &amp; <name type="place" key="Ohio River">Ohio</name>. 〈probably a mixture of Glauber, common &amp; Epsom Salts with alumine.〉 [<hi rend="italic">Rhomboidal carbonat of Lime</hi>.]</p>
            <p>
32. Specimen of Globar Salts taken in Prairie of Std. Shore <ref n="1804-08-22" type="related">22 Octr. 1804</ref> many bushels could have been obtained.—    [<hi rend="italic">a misture of various kinds of Salt with alumine</hi>.]</p>
            <p>
33 Specimen of the Sand of the <name type="place" key="Niobrara (Quicurre, Rapid) River">river Quicourre</name> or <name type="place" key="Niobrara (Quicurre, Rapid) River">Rapid River</name>. [<hi rend="italic">quartz ore Sand of a greyish white colour</hi>.]</p>
            <p>
34 Obtained at the <name type="place" key="Calumet Bluff (Nebr.)">Calumet Bluffs</name>—    [<hi rend="italic">principally fragments of argillaceous Iron ore</hi>.—]</p>
            <p>
35 Found on the N. Side of the <name type="place" key="Niobrara (Quicurre, Rapid) River">River quicourre</name> just above its entrance [<hi rend="italic">Slate in a State of decomposition—with some Sulphat of Lime</hi>.]</p>
            <p>
36. Found <ref n="1804-09-06" type="related">Sep. 6</ref> on Larbord Shore encrusting a Rock—    [<hi rend="italic">Alumine probably from decomposition of Shistus with Saline impregnation tho' very Slight</hi>.]</p>
            <p>
37. Found at the upper part of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Big Bend of the">Big Bend</name>
            </p>
            <p>
38. found at the base of the Bluffs intermixed with loose earth <ref n="1804-08-22" type="related">22 Aug. 1804</ref> [<hi rend="italic">Pyrites</hi>.]</p>
            <p>
39. Petrefactions obtained on the <name type="place" key="Ohio River">River ohio</name> in 1803</p>
            <p>
40 Specimen of the Sand rock which forms the base of the Limestone Clifts in the neighborhood of the <name type="place" key="Femme Osage (Osage Woman's) River">osage Woman's river</name> on the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>. [<hi rend="italic">fine grained Sand Stone</hi>.]</p>
            <p>
41. Specimen of Earth which constitutes the majority of the Bluffs—<ref n="1804-08-23" type="related">23d Aug 1804</ref>    when taken was in a firmer state than at present—    [<hi rend="italic">Slate decomposed with Pyrites decomposed</hi>.]</p>
            <p>
42. found at the upper Point of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Big Bend of the">Big Bend of the Missouri</name>
            </p>
            <p>
43. found above the white chalk Bluff in the Interstices of the Chalk rock [<hi rend="italic">Shistus decomposing with Small crystals of Gypsum</hi>.]</p>
            <p>
44—    <ref n="1804-08-23" type="related">Aug 23, 1804</ref> Specimen of a bituminous substance found on the face of a Sand rock, from which it appears to exude &amp; forms by exposure to the air. This Strata of Sand rock is about 10 feet thick &amp; forms a proportion of the lower part of the River Bluffs—    [<hi rend="italic">Aluminous Shistus in a state of decomposition</hi>.]</p>
            <p>
45. Specimen of the Earth which forms the base of the Banks of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>    H. [<hi rend="italic">fine grey coloured Sand</hi>.]</p>
            <p>
46. Found at the Burning Cliffs <ref n="1804-08-23" type="related">23 Aug. 1804</ref>—    [<hi rend="italic">Pyrites</hi>.]</p>
            <p>
47 Specimen of the Earth of which the Hills of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> are principally formed from the entrance of the <name type="place" key="Sioux River">river Sioux</name> to <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">fort mandan</name> &amp; if Indian information may be depended upon, for several hundred miles further up—    It is in this tract of country that the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> acquires it coloring matter of which it abates but little to its junction to the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississipi</name>. This earth when saturated by the rains or melting snows becomes so Soft for many feet in depth, that being unable to support its own weight, it Seperates into large masses from the hills, &amp; Slipping down their Sides precipitates itself into the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> &amp; mingles with its waters—    great quantities of this earth are also thrown into the river by its Subsidiary Streams &amp; rivulets which pass thro' or originate in this tract of open Country. M. L. [<hi rend="italic">Slate in a decomposed state</hi>.]</p>
            <p>
48. <ref n="1804-09-10" type="related">Sep. 10th</ref>    found on the side of the Bluffs not very abundant [<hi rend="italic">same as 47-with Streaks of green clay</hi>.]</p>
            <p>
49. <ref n="1804-08-22" type="related">Aug.22, 1804</ref>    found overlaying &amp; intermixed with the Earth which forms the bluffs of the River. [<hi rend="italic">crystallized Sulphat of Lime</hi>.]</p>
            <p>
50 <ref n="1804-08-24" type="related">Aug. 24, 1804</ref>    Specimen of Pirites at the base of the Bluffs on the South side of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>. [<hi rend="italic">Principally cubic Pyrites imbedded in argillaceous Shistus</hi>.]</p>
            <p>
51. Specimen of Pirites found <ref n="1804-08-22" type="related">22 Aug. 1804</ref> at the base of the bluffs on the S. Side of the <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississipi</name>—    only the label</p>
            <p>
52 A Specimen of the Chalk found at the white 〈Chalk〉 Clay Bluffs on the S. Side of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>. [<hi rend="italic">Argill?</hi>]</p>
            <p>
53 Found at the White 〈Chalk〉 Clay Bluffs on S. Side <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> (only the label) [<hi rend="italic">Pyrites in a state of efforescence</hi>]</p>
            <p>
54 from <ref n="1804-08-24" type="related">24 Aug.</ref> to <ref n="1804-09-10" type="related">10 Sept. 1804</ref>    Pyrites found intermixed promiscuously with the earth which form the Bluffs of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> in a great variety of places. [<hi rend="italic">same as 53</hi>.]</p>
            <p>
55 Incrustations of large round masses of rock which appear in a Sand bluff just above the entrance of the <name type="place" key="Cannonball (Bullet) River">Cannonball river</name>. This river derives its name from the appearance of these Stones    many of them are as perfectly globular as art could form them. [<hi rend="italic">Carbonate of Lime be caustious that you do not confound this with the globular Pyrites.    see No. 58 below</hi>.]</p>
            <p>
56 Found on the side of the River bluffs.    <ref n="1804-08-22" type="related">22d Aug. 1804</ref>    Irregularly intermixed with the Earth. [<hi rend="italic">Pyrites</hi>.]</p>
            <p>
57. Pyrites found along the borders of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> from <ref n="1804-08-20" type="related">20 Augt</ref> to <ref n="1804-09-10" type="related">10 Sepr</ref>, they are very common on the borders of all the little Rivulets in this open Country. [<hi rend="italic">Some of these Pyrites are in a state of efflorescence</hi>.]</p>
            <p>
58 Found <ref n="1804-08-23" type="related">23d Aug. 1804</ref> at the base of the Bluff. [<hi rend="italic">Carbonat of Lime indeterminately crystallised &amp; invested by 〈indurated argill〉 compact carbonat of Lime</hi>]</p>
            <p>
59 A Specimen of calcareous rock, a thin Stratum of which is found overlaying a soft Sand rock which makes its appearance in many parts of the bluffs from the entrance of the <name type="place" key="Platte River (Nebr.)">River Platte</name> to <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandon</name>. [<hi rend="italic">Mass of shells</hi>]</p>
            <p>
60. Found on the River Bank <ref n="1804-08-01" type="related">1 Aug. 1804</ref> (petrified [<hi rend="italic">Ed: blank</hi>] Nest)</p>
            <p>
61</p>
            <p>
62 Specimen of the pummice Stone found amongst the piles of drift wood on the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, Sometimes found as low down as the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Osage (Osarge) River">osage river</name>. I can hear of no burning mountain in the neighborhood of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> or its Branches, but the bluffs of the River are now on fire at Several places, particularly that part named in our chart of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>
               <hi rend="italic">The <name type="place" key="Burning Bluffs">Burning Bluffs</name>
               </hi>. The plains in many places, throughout this great extent of open country, exhibit abundant proofs of having been once on fire—    Witness the Specimens of Lava and Pummicestone found in the Hills near <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">fort mandon</name>—    [<hi rend="italic">Pumice</hi>.]</p>
            <p>
63 Specimen of a Substance extremely common &amp; found intermix'd with the loose Earth of all the Cliffs &amp; Hills from the <name type="place" key="Calumet Bluff (Nebr.)">Calumet Bluff</name> to <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandon</name>. [<hi rend="italic">crystallized Gypsum. Sulphated Lim</hi>]</p>
            <p>
64 Specimen of Carbonated wood with the loose Sand of the sand-Bars of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> &amp; <name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississipi</name>, it appears in considerable quantaties in many places—    [<hi rend="italic">carbonated wood</hi>]</p>
            <p>
65. Specimen of Stone commonly met with on the Surface of the Earth thro' 
a great proprotion of the plain open country above the <name type="place" key="Platte River (Nebr.)">River Platte</name>—[<hi rend="italic">Carbonate of Lime</hi>.]</p>
            <p>
66 Found in the Bluffs near <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort mandan</name>. [<hi rend="italic">Petrefied wood</hi>.]</p>
            <p>
67. A Specimen of Lava &amp; pummice Stone found in great abundance on the Sides of the Hills in the Neighborhood of <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name> 1609 miles above the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>—    exposed by the washing of the Hills from the rains &amp; melting Snow.—    These are merely the river Hills which are the banks only of a Valley formed by the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, passing thro' a level plain—    from the tops of these hills the country as far as the eve can reach is a level plain. The tract of Country which furnishes the Pummice Stone seen floating down the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Misouri</name>, is rather burning or burnt plains than burning mountains—    [<hi rend="italic">Lavas</hi>]</p>
            <p>
68 Brought us by one of our hunters, <name type="person" key="Shields, John">John Shields</name> who found it at the Allum Bluff <ref n="1804-08-22" type="related">22 Aug. 1804</ref>. [<hi rend="italic">Pyrites or Slate</hi>.]

</p>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1804-1805.winter.part3" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1804-1805.winter.part5" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
