<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-06-19">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
June 19, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 8</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">June 10–September 26, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1987</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">37-38</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">325</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">242</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Journal Entries</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-11-03</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1806-06-19">June 19, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-06-19.01" n="">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Thursday June 19th 1806.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
Our hunters were out very early this morning, they returned before noon with one deer only.    the Fishermen had been more unsuccessfull, they returned without a single fish and reported they could find but few and those they had tryed to take in vain.    they had broke both their giggs which were of indian fabrication made of bone. I happened to have a pointed peice of iron in my pouch which answered by cuting in two peices to renew boath giggs.    they took one fish this evening which proved to be a salmon trout much to our mortification, for we had hoped that they were the salmon of this spring arrival and of course fat and fine.    these trout are of the red kind they remain all winter in the upper parts of the rivers and creeks and are generally poor at this season. At 2 P. M. J &amp; <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">R Feilds</name> arived with two deer; <name type="person" key="Shields, John">John Sheilds</name> and <name type="person" key="Lepage, Jean Baptiste">LaPage</name> came with them, they had not succeeded in finding their horses.    late in the evening <name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">Frazier</name> reported that my riding horse that of <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt Clark</name> and his mule had gone on towards the <name type="place" key="Weippe Prairie (Camas Flats, Quawmash Flats)">Quawmash flatts</name> and that he had pursued their tracks on the road about 2½ miles.    we determined to send out all the hunters in the morning in order to make a fair experiment of the pactability of our being able to subsist at this place and if not we shall move the day after to the <name type="place" key="Weippe Prairie (Camas Flats, Quawmash Flats)">Quawmash flatts</name>.    the musquetoes have been excessively troublesome to us since our arrival at this place particularly in the evening. <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Cruzatte</name> brought me several large morells<ref target="n36061901" n="1"/> which I roasted and eat without salt pepper or grease    in this way I had for the first time the true taist of the morell which is truly an insippid taistless food.    our stock of salt is now exhausted except two quarts which I have reserved for my tour up <name type="place" key="Marias River">Maria's River</name> and that I left the other day on the mountain.—
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-06-19.02" n="">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Thursday June 19th 1806</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
This morning early <name type="person" key="Collins, John">Collins</name>
                  <name type="person" key="Labiche, François">Labeesh</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Crusat</name> turned out to hunt, and <name type="person" key="Gibson, George">Gibson</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name> fixed two Indian giggs and went in Serch of fish in the Creek. I took my gun and walked up the Creek about 4 Miles Saw some bear Sign and one fish only. <name type="person" key="Gibson, George">Gibson</name> killed only one fish which we found to be the Salmon Trout of the dark Species.    this fish was of the common Size pore, and indifferently flavoured. <name type="person" key="Labiche, François">Labeesh</name> killed one Deer neither of the others killed any thing.    about 1 P. M. <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Jo.</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">R Fields</name>
                  <name type="person" key="Shields, John">Shields</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Lepage, Jean Baptiste">LaPage</name> came up. <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">Reubin</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Joseph Fields</name> brought two Deer which <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">R.</name> had killed in the Small glade on a branch of <name type="place" key="Hungery Creek">Hungary Creek</name> where we had left them yesterday. <name type="person" key="Shields, John">Shields</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Lepage, Jean Baptiste">LaPage</name> did not find the two horses which we lost yesterday morning.    they report that they hunted with great diligence in the vicinity of our camp of the 17th without suckcess.    in my walk of this day up the Creek I observed a great abundance of fine grass<ref target="n36061902" n="2"/> sufficient to Sustain our horses any length of time we chose to Stay at this place. Several Glades of quawmash.    the S W. Sides of the hills is fallen timber and burnt woods, the N. E. Sides of the hills is thickly timbered with lofty pine, and thick under growth    This evening Several Salmon trout were Seen in the Creek, they hid themselves under the banks of the Creek which jutted over in Such a manner as to secure them from the Stroke of our giggs nets and spears which were made for the purpose of taking those Salmon trout.    we concluded to delay at this place another day with a view to give time to the two young Chiefs to arrive in case they set out on the 19th inst. as they informed us they Should    they will have Sufficient time to join us tomorrow or early the next day.    Should we get a guide from this place it will Save us two days march through some of the worst road through those Mountains, crouded with fallin timber mud holes and steep hills &amp;c.    we directed all the hunters to turn out early and kill something for us to live on &amp;c. Musquetors troublesom
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-06-19.03" n="">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Thursday 19th June 1806.    a fair morning. Several men went out a hunting &amp; 2 went at fishing with Indin gigs which Some of the party had with them but could See only now and then a Scattering one, and could not kill any.    about noon <name type="person" key="Labiche, François">Labuche</name> came in with a deer which he had killed. Shortly after all our men who Stayed back came up    <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">R. Fields</name> had killed two deer, but <name type="person" key="Shields, John">Shields</name> had not found the 2 lost horses.    towards evening <name type="person" key="Gibson, George">Gibson</name> giged &amp; killd. one of the fish we took to be Salmon and we found it to be Salmon trout, and poor.    we expect they all are that is in this creek.    the Musquetoes are verry troublesome

</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-06-19.04" n="">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Thursday 19th.</hi>    This was a fine morning; some hunters<ref target="n36061903" n="3"/> went out and we agreed to stay here all day that our horses might rest and feed. At 10 o'clock our hunters came in and had killed a deer. Two men<ref target="n36061904" n="4"/> are trying to take some of the fish with a gig. At noon the two men<ref target="n36061905" n="5"/> who had been left at <name type="place" key="Hungery Creek">Hungry creek</name> to look for the horses came up, but had not found them: and with them the two hunters,<ref target="n36061906" n="6"/> who were left at the place we dined yesterday, and had killed two deer. In the evening one of the large fish was caught, which we found to be a salmon-trout.<ref target="n36061907" n="7"/>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n36061901" n="1">Most likely the black morel, <hi rend="italic">Morchella angusticeps</hi> Pk., a spring mushroom highly prized by people who have access to salt and "grease." Miller (MNA), 214. The word is underlined in red, apparently by <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36061902" n="2">The dominant grasses of the area are Idaho fescue, <hi rend="italic">Festuca idahoensis</hi> Elmer, and bluebunch wheatgrass, <hi rend="italic">Agropyron spicatum</hi> (Pursh) Scribn. &amp; Smith; see <ref n="1805-09-21" type="related">September 21, 1805</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36061903" n="3">
               <name type="person" key="Collins, John">Collins</name>, <name type="person" key="Labiche, François">Labiche</name>, and <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Cruzatte</name>, notes <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36061904" n="4">
               <name type="person" key="Gibson, George">Gibson</name> and <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name>, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> says.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36061905" n="5">
               <name type="person" key="Shields, John">Shields</name> and <name type="person" key="Lepage, Jean Baptiste">Lepage</name>; see <ref n="1806-06-18" type="related">June 18</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36061906" n="6">The <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph and Reubin">Field brothers</name>; see <ref n="1806-06-18" type="related">June 18</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36061907" n="7">Steelhead trout.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-06-18" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-06-20" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
