<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-02-11">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
February 11, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 6</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">November 2, 1805–March 22, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1990</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">296-299</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">271</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">192-193</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jw">Joseph Whitehouse</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 11</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of Joseph Whitehouse, May 14, 1804–April 2, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1997</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">419</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Journal Entries</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-08-25</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1806-02-11">February 11, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-02-11.01" n="">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Tuesday February 11th 1806.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
This morning Sergt. <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name>
                  <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">Reubin Fields</name> and <name type="person" key="Thompson, John B.">Thompson</name> passed the <name type="place" key="Lewis and Clark (Fort, Netul) River">Netul</name> opposite to us on a hunting expedition.    sent <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Sergt Pryor</name> with a party of four men to bring <name type="person" key="Gibson, George">Gibson</name> to the fort.    also sent <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name> and <name type="person" key="Weiser, Peter">Wiser</name> to the <name type="place" key="Saltmaking Camp (Oreg.)">Salt works</name> to carry on the business with <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Joseph Fields</name>; as <name type="person" key="Bratton, William E.">Bratton</name> has been sick we desired him to return to the Fort also if he thought proper; however in the event of his not coming <name type="person" key="Weiser, Peter">Wiser</name> was directed to return.</p>
               <p>
There is a shrub<ref target="n28021101" n="1"/> which grows commonly in this neighbourhood which is precisely the same with that in <name type="place" key="Virginia">Virginia</name> some times called the quillwood.    also another<ref target="n28021102" n="2"/> which grows near the water in somewhat moist grounds &amp; rises to the hight of 5 or 6 feet with a large, peteolate spreading plane, crenate and somewhat woolly leaf like the rose raspberry.    it is much branched the bark of a redish brown colour and is covered with a number of short hooked thorns which renders it extreemly disagreeable to pass among; it does not cast it's foliage untill about the 1st of December.    this is also the case with the black alder. The[re] is also found in this neighbourhood an evergreen shrub<ref target="n28021103" n="3"/> which I take to be another variety of the Shallun and that discribed under that name in mistake on the 26th of January.    this shrub rises to the hight of from four to five feet, the stem simple branching, defuse and much branched.    the bark is of a redish dark brown, that of the mane stem is somewhat rough while that of the boughs is smooth.    the leaves are petiolate the petiole 1/10 of an inch long; oblong, obtuse at the apex and accute angular at the insertion of the petiole; ¾ of an inch in length and ⅜ths in width; convex, somewhat revolute, serrate, smoth and of a paler green than the evergreens usually are; they are also opposite and ascending.    the fruit is a small deep perple berry like the common huckleberry of a pleasent flavor. they are s[e]perately scattered &amp; attatched to the small boughs by short peduncles.—.    the natives eat this berry when ripe but seldom collect it in such quantities as to dry it for winter uce.—
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-02-11.02" n="">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Tuesday February 11th 1806.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
This Morning <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Serjt. Gass</name>
                  <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">R. Field</name> and <name type="person" key="Thompson, John B.">J. Thompson</name> passed the <name type="place" key="Lewis and Clark (Fort, Netul) River">Netul</name> opposit to us on a hunting expedition. Sent <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Serjeant Natl. Pryor</name> with 4 men in a Canoe to bring <name type="person" key="Gibson, George">gibson</name> to the Fort.    also Sent <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Weiser, Peter">P. Weser</name> to the <name type="place" key="Saltmaking Camp (Oreg.)">Salt works</name> to carry on the business with <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Jos. Field</name>; as <name type="person" key="Bratton, William E.">bratten</name> is also Sick we derected that he Should return to the fort if 〈the〉 he continued unwell;</p>
               <p>
There is Shrub which grows Commonly in this neighbourhood which grows on the Steep Sides of the hills and also in low moist grounds, and rise to the hight of 5 or 6 feet with a large peteolate, Spreading plain crenate and Somewhat woolly leaf like the rose raspberry.    it is much branched the bark of a redish brown colour and is covered with a number of Short hooked thorns which renders it extreamly disagreeable to pass among, it does not cast its foliage untill about the 1st of December.</p>
               <p>
There is a Species of <hi rend="italic">bryor</hi>
                  <ref target="n28021104" n="4"/> which is common in this neighbourhood of a green colour which grows most abundant in the rich dry lands near the water courses, but is also found in Small quantities in the piney lands at a distance from the water Courses in the former Situations the Stem is frequently the Size of a mans finger and rise perpendicularly to the hight of 4 or 5 feet when it decends in an arch and becoms procumbent  or rests on Some neighbouring plant or Srubs; it is Simple unbranched and celindric; in the latter Situation it is much Smaller, and usially procumbent.    the Stem is armed with Sharp and hooked bryors.    the leaf is peteolate, ternate and resembles in Shape and appearance that of the purple Raspberry common to the atlantic States. The frute is a berry resembling the Blackberry in every respect and is eaten when ripe and much esteemed by the nativs but is not dryed for winters Consumption.    in the Countrey about the enterance of the <name type="place" key="Sandy (Quicksand) River">quick Sand river</name>
                  <ref target="n28021105" n="5"/> I first discovered this bryor, it grows So abundantly in the furtile Vally of <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> and on the Islands in that part of the river, that the Countrey near the river is almost impenitrable in maney places. This green Bryor retains its leaf or foliage and virdue untill late in December. The Briory bush with a wide leaf is also one of its ascociates.<ref target="n28021106" n="6"/>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-02-11.03" n="">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Tuesday 11th Feby. 1806. <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Sergt. Pryor</name> and five men<ref target="n28021107" n="7"/> Set out with a canoe
to go round to the <name type="place" key="Saltmaking Camp (Oreg.)">Salt works</name> after the Sick men.    2 more men<ref target="n28021108" n="8"/> were to Stay in their places    three men<ref target="n28021109" n="9"/> went out to hunt.    the after part of the day rainy.

</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-02-11.04" n="">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Tuesday 11th.</hi>    This was a fine morning. A sergeant and six men<ref target="n28021110" n="10"/> were sent to bring the sick men to the fort. At the same time myself and two men went out to hunt, and remained out to the 17th during which time there was a great deal of heavy rain, and the weather changeable and disagreeable.— While we were out we killed 8 elk. During one of the most disagreeable nights, myself and another lay out in our shirts and overalls,<ref target="n28021111" n="11"/> with only one elk-skin to defend us from a violent night's rain. We had started a gang of elk, and in order to be light in the pursuit left our clothes where the first was killed, and could not get back before dark. Our shirts and overalls being all of leather made it the more disagreeable.


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-02-11.05" n="">
            <sp who="jw">
               <speaker>Whitehouse</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Tuesday Febry 11th    We had a fine clear day.    <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Serjeant Pryor</name> &amp; four Men, were sent with a Canoe to go round to the <name type="place" key="Saltmaking Camp (Oreg.)">Salt Camp</name> in order to bring the Men that were sick there,<ref target="n28021112" n="12"/> to the Fort; and two more of our men were sent to the Salt works to supply the place of the Men that were sick.    Three of our hunters left the fort to go a hunting.    the latter part of the day was rainey.—    The remainder of our party at the fort, were employ'd dressing Skins, making Cloathes &amp;ca.—



</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n28021101" n="1">Perhaps the Oregon grape which is given a fuller description the next day. Quill wood may be mountain holly of the next day's entry. Thwaites (LC), 4:59 n. 1. Several lines, starting with this paragraph, have a red vertical line through them, perhaps Biddle's work.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28021102" n="2">Probably the Pacific blackberry or perhaps Pacific salmonberry.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28021103" n="3">The evergreen huckleberry of <ref n="1806-01-26" type="related">January 26, 1806</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28021104" n="4">
               <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> description (copied from <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> entry of <ref n="1806-02-13" type="related">February 13</ref>), noting the ternate (trifoliate) leaf, abundance, and green color, confirms the identification of Pacific blackberry as given earlier.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28021105" n="5">
               <name type="place" key="Sandy (Quicksand) River">Sandy River</name>, <name type="place" key="Multnomah County, Oreg.">Multnomah County</name>, <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 79.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28021106" n="6">The "Briory bush" is salmonberry, with bush referring to the upright habit of the species; see <ref n="1805-12-01" type="related">December 1, 1805</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28021107" n="7">Only four, according to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28021108" n="8">
               <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name> and <name type="person" key="Weiser, Peter">Weiser</name>, report the captains.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28021109" n="9">
               <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name>, <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">Reubin Field</name>, and <name type="person" key="Thompson, John B.">Thompson</name>, according to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28021110" n="10">
               <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Pryor</name> and four men went to the <name type="place" key="Saltmaking Camp (Oreg.)">saltworks</name> to carry <name type="person" key="Gibson, George">Gibson</name> back; <name type="person" key="Colter, John">Colter</name> and <name type="person" key="Weiser, Peter">Weiser</name> went 
along to continue the salt-boiling with <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Joseph Field</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28021111" n="11">Heavy trousers worn for protection over regular clothes.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28021112" n="12">
               <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Pryor's</name> party went to the <name type="place" key="Saltmaking Camp (Oreg.)">saltworks</name> to bring <name type="person" key="Gibson, George">Gibson</name> back, and <name type="person" key="Bratton, William E.">Bratton</name> if necessary.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-02-10" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-02-12" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
