<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-06-06">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
June 6, 1806</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 7</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">March 23–June 9, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1991</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">338-343</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">320</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">236</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Journal Entries</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-10-27</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1806-06-06">June 6, 1806</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-06-06.01" n="">
            <sp who="ml">
               <speaker>Lewis</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Friday June 6th 1806.</hi>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
This morning <name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">Frazier</name> returned having been in quest of some roots and bread which had left at the lodg of the <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">Twisted hair</name> when on his way to the fishery on <name type="place"
                        key="Salmon (Lewis's, Main Fork Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">Lewis's river</name>.    the <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">Twisted hair</name> came with him but I was unable to converse with him for the want of an interpreter, <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name> being absent with <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. C.</name> This Cheif left me in the evening and returned to his village. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt C.</name> Visited the <name type="person" key="Broken Arm">Broken Arm</name> today agreeably to his promise; he took with him <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name> and several others.    they were received in a friendly manner. The <name type="person" key="Broken Arm">Broken Arm</name> informed <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt C.</name> that the nation would not pass the mountain untill the latter end of the summer, and that with rispect to the young men whom we had requested should accompany us to the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">falls of the Missouri</name>, were not yet scelected for that purpose nor could they be so untill there was a meeting of the nation in counsil.    that this would happen in the course of ten or twelve days as the whole of the lodges were about to remove to the head of the <name type="place" key="Lawyer (Commearp) Creek">Commeâp Creek</name> in the plain near <name type="place"
                        key="Salmon (Lewis's, Main Fork Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">Lewis's river</name>,<ref target="n35060601" n="1"/> that when they had assembled themselves they would hold a council and scelect the young men.    that if we set out previously to that period the men would follow us.    we therefore do not calculate on any assistance from them as guides, but depend more upon engageing some of the <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Ootlashshoots</name> in the neighborhood of <name type="place" key="Lolo (Travelers' Rest) Creek (Mont.)">Travellers rest C.</name> for that purpose. The broken arm gave <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. C.</name> a few dryed Quawmas roots as a great present, but in our estimation those of cows are much better, I am confident they are much more healthy. The men who were with <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. C.</name> obtained a good store of roots and bread in exchange for a number of little <hi rend="italic">notions,</hi> using the Yanke phrase, with which their own enginuity had principally furnished them.    on examination we find that our whole party have an ample store of bread and roots for our voyage, a circumstance not unpleasing. They retuned at 5 P. M. shortly after which we were visited by <name type="person" key="Hohots Ilppilp">Hohâstillpilp</name> the two young Cheifs who gave us the horses in behalf of the nation some time since and several others, who remained all night. The <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Kooskooske</name> is about 150 Yds. wide at this place and discharges a vast body of water; notwithstanding it high state the water remains nearly transparent, and it's temperature appeas to be quite as cold as that of our best springs.    we meet with a beautifull little bird<ref target="n35060602" n="2"/> [<hi rend="italic">EC: Piranga ludoviciana</hi>] in this neighbourhood about the size and somewhat the shape of the large sparrow.    it is reather longer in proportion to it's bulk than the sparrow.    it measures 7 inches from the extremity of the beek to that of the tail, the latter occupying 2½ inches.    the beak is reather more than half an inch in length, and is formed much like the virginia nitingale;<ref target="n35060603" n="3"/> it is thick and large for a bird of it's size; wide at the base, both chaps convex, and pointed, the uper exceeds the under chap a little 〈and a〉 is somewhat curved and of a brown colour; the lower chap of a greenish yellow.    the eye full reather large and of a black colour both puple and iris.    the plumage is remarkably delicate; that of the neck and head is of a fine orrange yellow and red, the latter predominates on the top of the head and arround the base of the beak from whence it graduly deminishes &amp; towards the lower part of the neck, the orrange yellow prevails most; the red has the appearance of being laid over a ground of yellow.    the breast, the sides, rump and some long feathers which lie between the legs and extend underneath the tail are of a fine orrange yellow.    the tail, back and wings are black, ecept a small stripe of yellow on the outer part of the middle joint of the wing, ¼ of an inch wide and an inch in length.    the tail is composed of twelve feathers of which those in the center are reather shortest, and the plumage of all the feathers of the tail is longest on that side of the quill next the center of the tail.    the legs and feet are black, nails long and sharp; it has four toes on each foot, of which three are forward and one behind; that behind is as long as the two outer of the three toes in front.</p>
               <p>
Observed equal altitudes of the sun with Sextant.</p>
               <p>
                  <table rows="4" cols="11">
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">h</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">m</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">s</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">h</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">m</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">s</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">A. M.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">1</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">55</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">  4.5</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">P.M.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">10</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">17</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">43</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="3" cols="1">}</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="3" cols="1">Altitude 64° 42' 30"</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">"</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">66</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">30</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">"</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">19</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">12</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">"</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">57</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">57</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">"</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">20</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">40</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>					  
Chronometer too slow on M. T.—  [<hi rend="italic">blank</hi>]
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-06-06.02" n="">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>
                     <hi rend="italic">Friday June 6th 1806</hi>
                     <ref target="n35060604" n="4"/>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
I visited the <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="person" key="Broken Arm">Broken Arm</name>
                  </hi> to day agreeable to my promis of the 4th inst. and took with me <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name> &amp; three other men I was receved in the friendly manner. The <name type="person" key="Broken Arm">broken Arm</name> informed me that maney of the Small chiefs of the different Bands of his nation had not heard our word from our own mouths, Several of them were present and was glad to See me &amp;c. I repeeted in part what had been Said in Council before. The <name type="person" key="Broken Arm">Broken arm</name> told me that the nation would not pass the mountains untill the latter part of the Summer, and with respect to the young men who we had requested to accompany us to the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">falls of Missouri</name>, were not yet Selected for that purpose nor could they be So untill they had a Meeting of the Nation in Council.    that this would happen in the Course of ten or 12 days as the whole of the Lodges were about to Move to the head of <name type="place" key="Lawyer (Commearp) Creek">Commeâp Creek</name> in the Plain of <name type="place"
                        key="Salmon (Lewis's, Main Fork Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">Lewis's river</name>, that when they held a council they would Select two young men.    that if we Set out previously to that time the men would follow us.    we therefore do not Calculate any assistance from them as guides, but depend more upon engageing Some of the <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Oatlash-shoots</name> on <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Clark's, Flathead) River">Clarks river</name> in the neighbouringhood of <name type="place" key="Lolo (Travelers' Rest) Creek (Mont.)">Travellers rest C.</name> for that purpose. The <name type="person" key="Broken Arm">Broken Arm</name> gave me a fiew Quawmash roots as a great preasent, but in my estimation those of Cows is much better. I am Confident they are much more healthy. The <name type="person" key="Broken Arm">Broken Arm</name> informed me that they had latterly been informed that a party of the <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshones</name> had arived at the <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Cayuse Indians">Ye-E-al-po</name>
                  </hi> Nation who reside to the South of the enterance of <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Kooskooske</name> into <name type="place"
                        key="Salmon (Lewis's, Main Fork Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">Lewis's river</name>.<ref target="n35060605" n="5"/>    and had informed that people that their nation (the <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshones</name>) had received the talk which was given their relations on the head of the <name type="place"
                        key="Salmon (Lewis's, Main Fork Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">East fork of Lewis's river</name> last fall, and were resolved to pursue our Councils, and had came foward for the purpose of makeing peace with them, and allso with the <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Chopunnish</name> &amp;c.    that they had Sent Several men in Serch of those people with a view to bring them to <name type="place"
                        key="Salmon (Lewis's, Main Fork Lewis's, Southeast Fork of Columbia, West Fork Lewis's) River">Lewis's river</name> at which place the <name type="person" key="Broken Arm">Broken Arm</name> informed me he Should meet them and Smoke the pipe of peace.    which he Should afterwards Send by with Some of his Chiefs in company with those <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshones</name> to their nation and confirm a piece which never Should be broken on his part.    he produced two pipes one of which he said was as a present to me the other he intended to Send to the <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshones</name> &amp;c. and requested me to take one, I receved the one made in the fascion of the Country, the other which was of Stone curiously inlaid with Silver in the common form which he got from the <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshones</name>.<ref target="n35060606" n="6"/> I deckorated the Stem of this pipe with blue ribon and white wampom and informed the Chief this was the emblem of peace with us.</p>
               <p>
The men who accompanied me obtained a good Store of roots and bread in exchange for a number of little <hi rend="italic">notions,</hi> useing the Yanke phrase, with which their own enginuiety had principally furnished them.    on examonation we find our whole party have a Sufficient Store of bread and roots for our Voyage.    a Circumstance not unpleasing—.</p>
               <p>
I returned at 4 P. M followed by <name type="person" key="Hohots Ilppilp">Hohâstillpilp</name> the 2 young Chiefs who gave us the horses in behalf of the nation Some time Sence, the young man who gave us the horse at <name type="person" key="Lolo (Collins's) Creek (Idaho)">Collins Creek</name> to kill as we Came up, and Several others. I met the <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">twisted hair</name> and two other indians with <name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">Frazier</name> on the opposit bank from our Camp this Morning &amp; Sent him over to our Camp. I met him this evening on his return home.    he informed me he could not accompany us across the mountains as his brother was Sick &amp;c.—.
</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-06-06.03" n="">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>[<hi rend="italic">undated, ca. June 6, 1806</hi>]<ref target="n35060607" n="7"/>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <list type="simple">
                     <item>The <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Chopunnish</name> call the <name type="native_nation" key="Crow Indians">Crow Indians</name> Up-shar-look-kar</item>
                     <item>
                        <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Chopunnish</name> name for Sin-sho-cal    <name type="place" key="Dearborn River">Dearbourne R</name>
                     </item>
                     <item>   ditto—    do—    Cal la mar-Sha mosh    <name type="place" key="Madison River (Middle Fork)">Meddesons</name>
                     </item>
                     <item>   ditto—    do—    Co-ma win-nim    <name type="place" key="Marias River">Maria River</name>
                     </item>
                     <item>   ditto    ditto—    Ta-ki-á-ki-á     <name type="place" key="Musselshell (Mah-tush,-ah-zhah, Shell) River">Mescle Shell R</name>
                     </item>
                     <item>   ditto—    ditto    <hi rend="italic">Wah-wo-ko-ye-o-cose</hi> is th    [<hi rend="italic">blank</hi>]</item>
                     <item>   ditto    do—    <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Rockejhone</name>—    <hi rend="italic">
                           <name type="place" key="Elk River">Elk river</name>
                        </hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>   ditto    do—    <hi rend="italic">Koos-koos-an-nim-a</hi>    the <name type="place" key="Little Missouri (E-mâh-tark',-Ah'-zhah) River">little Missouri</name>
                     </item>
                     <item>   ditto—    do—    <hi rend="italic">Walch-Nim-mah</hi>    <name type="place" key="Knife River">Knife R</name>
                     </item>
                     <item>   ditto—    do    <hi rend="italic">Ni-hi-Sir-te—</hi>    <name type="place" key="Heart (Ches-che-tar and similar spellings) River">C. R</name>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-06-06.04" n="">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
Friday 6th June 1806.    a fair morning. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt Clark</name> and five men<ref target="n35060608" n="8"/> went
across the river to Some villages.    one of the party<ref target="n35060609" n="9"/> who Stayed at the <name type="place" key="Commearp Village">commeap village</name> last night riturnd    informed us that 5 of the <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Sho-Sho-nee of Snake nation</name> had come to make peace or treaty with this nation<ref target="n35060610" n="10"/>    towards evening <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt Clark</name> &amp; party returned    the young chief<ref target="n35060611" n="11"/> who gave us Several
horses and Several more of the natives of his village accompanyd them &amp;C.


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1806-06-06.05" n="">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Friday 6th.</hi>    The morning was pleasant, and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Capt. Clarke</name> and five of the party<ref target="n35060612" n="12"/> went over the river to buy some roots at the villages, and in the evening returned with a good supply, accompanied by some of the natives.




</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n35060601" n="1">Near the head of <name type="place" key="Lawyer (Commearp) Creek">Lawyer Creek</name>, in <name type="place" key="Lewis County, Idaho">Lewis County</name>, <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n35060602" n="2">The first description of the western tanager, <hi rend="italic">Piranga ludoviciana</hi> [AOU, 607]. Coues called the description "clear and unmistakable." Coues (HLC), 3:1035–36 n. 26; Cutright (LCPN), 296, 306, 384–87, 437; Holmgren, 31. A red vertical line runs through this descriptive material to about "the eye full," perhaps done by Biddle.</note>
            <note xml:id="n35060603" n="3">Northern cardinal, <hi rend="italic">Cardinalis cardinalis</hi> [AOU, 593]; see also <ref n="1804-06-04" type="related">June 4, 1804</ref>. Holmgren, 32.</note>
            <note xml:id="n35060604" n="4">This entry ends the daily journal material in Voorhis No. 3. The remaining material is written from the back in reverse order to the rest of the journal. It includes weather data for April and May 1806, which is placed in the appropriate location; a map dated April 18, 1806, which is placed with its textual reference at <ref n="1806-04-20" type="related">April 20</ref> (see fig. 11); and a list of <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name> terms (see notes below).</note>
            <note xml:id="n35060605" n="5">The <name type="native_nation" key="Cayuse Indians">Cayuse</name> people, who called themselves <name type="native_nation" key="Cayuse Indians">Waiilatpus</name>, and who lived in northeastern <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name> and southeastern <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>, west of the <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name> homeland. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> term is Shahaptian <hi rend="italic">weyí·letpu·,</hi> being the designation for this group; <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> gives it as "<name type="native_nation" key="Cayuse Indians">Y-e-let-pos</name>" on <ref n="1806-06-08" type="related">June 8</ref>. Their language, Waiilatpuan, was distantly related to the Shahaptian of <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perces</name>, and the two tribes associated and intermarried to a great extent. Hodge, 1:224–25; Ruby &amp; Brown (CIIT).</note>
            <note xml:id="n35060606" n="6">The wording is ambiguous, but the pipe "in the common form" may have been one with the bowl at right angles to the stem, while the one "in the fashion of the country" may have been one with the bowl at the end of the stem, as they had observed among the <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshones</name> (see <ref n="1805-08-13" type="related">August 13, 1805</ref>, and fig. 1 there). Perhaps, however, the silver inlay was the "common form" referred to.</note>
            <note xml:id="n35060607" n="7">The following is a list found on the back flyleaf of <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> Voorhis No. 3 journal. It is undated, so is placed here with the nearest regularly dated daily entry. It is mainly a list of <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name> terms for major tributaries of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri River</name>, going downstream. It indicates the extent of <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name> knowledge of the country east of the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rockies</name>, either from <name type="native_nation" key="Crow Indians">Crow</name> informants or from trips as far as the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>-<name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> villages, perhaps in company with <name type="native_nation" key="Crow Indians">Crows</name>.<lb/>
               <table rows="6" cols="2">
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Up-shar-look-kar, <name type="native_nation" key="Crow Indians">Crow Indians</name>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                        <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Rockejhone</name>, French for <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone</name>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Sin-sho-cal, <name type="place" key="Dearborn River">Dearborn River</name>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Koos-koos-an-nim-a, <name type="place" key="Little Missouri (E-mâh-tark',-Ah'-zhah) River">Little Missouri River</name>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Cal la mar-Sha mosh, <name type="place" key="Sun (Mah-pah-pah,-ah-zhah, Medicine) River">Sun River</name>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Walch-Nim-mah, <name type="place" key="Knife River">Knife River</name>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Co-ma win-nim, <name type="place" key="Marias River">Marias River</name>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Ni-hi-Sir-te, perhaps <name type="place" key="Heart (Ches-che-tar and similar spellings) River">Heart River</name> or <name type="place" key="Cannonball (Bullet) River">Cannon</name>-</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Ta-ki-á-ki-á, <name type="place" key="Musselshell (Mah-tush,-ah-zhah, Shell) River">Musselshell River</name>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                        <name type="place" key="Cannonball (Bullet) River">ball River</name> (see below)</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Wah-wo-ko-ye-o-cose, perhaps</cell>
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                        <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone River</name>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <lb/>
Some of the terms may be linguistically defined as follows: "Up-shar-look-kar" is apparently the <name type="native_nation" key="Crow Indians">Crow</name> self-designation, <hi rend="italic">Apsáalooke;</hi> the present <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name> name for <name type="native_nation" key="Crow Indians">Crow Indians</name> is <hi rend="italic">'isú·<seg n="uxu803">x̣</seg>e;</hi> "Wah-wo-ko-ye-o-cose" may be <hi rend="italic">wewúkiye kú·s,</hi> "elk water," for the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone River</name>; "Walch-Nim-mah" may be <hi rend="italic">walcníma,</hi> from the root <hi rend="italic">wálc</hi> for "knife." <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> cryptic letters "<name type="place" key="Heart (Ches-che-tar and similar spellings) River">C. R.</name>" following the term "Ni-hi-Sir-te," may stand for "<name type="place" key="Heart (Ches-che-tar and similar spellings) River">Ches-che-tar River</name>," the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> name for the <name type="place" key="Heart (Ches-che-tar and similar spellings) River">Heart River</name>, which would be the next stream after the <name type="place" key="Knife River">Knife River</name>. The next tributary below that, however, is the <name type="place" key="Cannonball (Bullet) River">Cannonball River</name>, joining the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri River</name> between <name type="place" key="Morton County, N. Dak.">Morton</name> and <name type="place" key="Sioux County, N. Dak.">Sioux</name> counties, <name type="place" key="North Dakota">North Dakota</name>, and perhaps the designated "<name type="place" key="Heart (Ches-che-tar and similar spellings) River">C. R.</name>"</note>
            <note xml:id="n35060608" n="8">
               <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name> and three others went to the village of <name type="person" key="Broken Arm">Broken Arm</name>, according to <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n35060609" n="9">
               <name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">Frazer</name>, report the captains.</note>
            <note xml:id="n35060610" n="10">This was actually news from <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> about the <name type="native_nation" key="Cayuse Indians">Cayuse Indians</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n35060611" n="11">Again, <name type="person" key="Hohots Ilppilp">Hohots Ilppilp</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n35060612" n="12">Identified only as "<name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drewyer</name> &amp; three other men" by <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-06-05" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1806-06-07" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
