<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.jrn.1804-10-12">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
October 12, 1804</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="ml">Meriwether Lewis</author>
               <author xml:id="wc">William Clark</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>Thomas W. Dunlay,</name>
                  <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 3</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">August 25, 1804–April 6, 1805</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1987</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">160-167</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jo">John Ordway</author>
               <author xml:id="cf">Charles Floyd</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 9</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of John Ordway and Charles Floyd</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1995</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">83-84</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="pg">Patrick Gass</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 10</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journal of Patrick Gass, May 14, 1804–September 23, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1996</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">54</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author xml:id="jw">Joseph Whitehouse</author>
               
               
               <editor role="editor">Gary E. Moulton</editor>
               <title level="m" type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, Volume 11</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">The Journals of Joseph Whitehouse, May 14, 1804–April 2, 1806</title>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1997</date>
               <biblScope type="pages">99</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
         <geoDecl datum="WGS" xml:id="lc.geo.1804-10-12.01">
            <placeName/>
            <geo>45.6975 -100.2933</geo>
            <note>In Campbell County, SD, in an area inundated by the Missouri</note>
         </geoDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Journals</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Journal Entries</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2004-03-18</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-09-26</date>
            <name>Karin Dalziel</name>Added Geo Information from spreadsheet</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="date">
            <date when="1804-10-12">October 12, 1804</date>
         </head>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1804-10-12.01" n="lc.geo.1804-10-12.01">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">12th of October Friday</hi>    after Brackfast we joined the Chiefs &amp; Indians on the bank who wer waiting for us, and proseeded to the 1st village<ref target="n07101201" n="1"/> and Lodge of the <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="person" key="Hay (Pocasse)">Pocasse</name>
                  </hi>, This man Spok<ref target="n07101202" n="2"/> at Some lengths, to the Sam[e] purpote of the 1s Chief, &amp; Declareing his intentions of visiting his great father, Some Doubts as to his Safty in Passing the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>, requested us to take a Chief of their nation and make a good peace with the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> for them, that they Knew that they were the Cause of the war by Killing the 2 <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> Chiefs—    this Chief &amp; people gave us about 7 bushels of Corn, Some Tobacco of their own make,<ref target="n07101203" n="3"/> and Seed Legins &amp; a Robe    We proceeded to the 3rd Chiefs Village which is the largest,<ref target="n07101204" n="4"/> after the usial Seremoney of Eating Smokg. &amp;. he Spoke to near the Same amount of the last Chief, &amp; more pleasently, he gave us 10 bushels of Corn, Some Beens &amp; Simmins, after he had Spoken, and [I] gave Some Sketches of the Power &amp; Magnitude of Our Countrey, we returned to our Boat, I have the rhumetism on my neck [<hi rend="italic">blot</hi>]    the Chiefs accompanied us on board, w[e] gave them Some Sugar Salt and a Sun Glass each, and after eating a little they returned on Shore leaveing one to accompany us to the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>, and we Set out viewed by men womin &amp; children of each village    proceeded on about 9½ miles and Camped on the S S.<ref target="n07101205" n="5"/>    Clear &amp; Cold—    The <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Ricaras</name> Are about 500 men    <name type="person" key="Tabeau, Pierre-Antoine">Mr. Taboe</name> say 600    able to bear arms, and the remains of ten different tribes of Panias    reduced by the Small Pox &amp; wares [wars] with the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>, they are tall Stout men corsily featured, their womin Small &amp; industerous    raise great quantites of corn beans &amp;c also Tobacco for the men to Smoke, they collect all the wood and doe the Drudgery common amongst Savages—    Their language is So corrupted that many lodges of the Same village with dificuelty under Stand all that each other Say—    They are Dirty, Kind, pore, &amp; extravegent; possessing natural pride, no begers, rcive what is given them with pleasure, Thier houses are close together &amp; Towns inclosed with Pickets, thier Lodges are 30 to 40 feet in Diamute[r] Covered with earth on Neet Poles Set end wise resting on 4 forks Supporting Beems Set in a Square form near the Center, and lower about 5 feet high    other forks all around Supt. Strong Beems, from 8 to 10 of those, with a opening at top of about 5 to 6 feet Square, on the Poles which pass to the top, Small Willow &amp; grass is put across to Support <ref target="n07101206" n="6">the earth—</ref>   The <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name> exchange, Some merchndze of Small value which they get from <name type="person" key="Cameron, Murdoch">Mr. Cameron</name>
                  <ref target="n07101207" n="7"/> of <name type="place" key="Minnesota River (St. Peters)">St. Peters</name> for Corn &amp;c and have great influence over this people    treat them roughly and keep them in contineal dread—    The <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Ricaras</name> are at war with the Crow Indians and <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>—&amp;c. &amp;—    The <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Ricaras</name>, have a custom Similar to the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name> in maney instances, they think they cannot Show a Sufficient acknowledgement without [giving?] to their guest handsom Squars and think they are despised if they are not recved</p>
               <p>
The <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name> followed us with women two days    we put them off.    the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Ricarries</name> we put off dureing the time we were near their village—    2 were Sent by a man to follow us, and overtook us this evening, we Still procisted in a refusial—<ref target="n07101208" n="8"/>    The Dress of the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Ricara</name> men is Simpally a pr. of Mockersons &amp; Legins, a flap, and a Buffalow Robe—    Their Hair is long and lais loose    their arms &amp; ears are decerated with trinkets—</p>
               <p>
The womin Dress Mockersons &amp; Legins &amp; Skirt of the Skin of the Cabre
or Antelope, long fringed &amp; [roab?] to the fringes &amp; with Sleaves, verry white, and Roabes—    all were Dressed to be without hare in the Summer</p>
               <p>
Those people make large Beeds of Diferrent colours, out of glass or Beeds of Dift colours, verry ingeniously</p>
               <p>
                  <table rows="6" cols="3">
                     <head>Course &amp; Deistance &amp;c.</head>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 45°E.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">2</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">m. To the Mouth of a Creek between the two upper <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Ricara</name>
                           <lb/>
villages</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 75 E.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">1 ½</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">m. to a Point on the L. S.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N 45° E</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">2</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">m to a pt of wood L. S.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 45° E</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">2</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">m. to a pt. of wood on the L S<ref target="n07101209" n="9"/>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 20° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">2 ½</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">m to a pt. on the L. S.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 8° W</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">1 ½</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">m to a pt. on the L S.    river narrow and large wooded points</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1804-10-12.02" n="lc.geo.1804-10-12.01">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>12th <hi rend="italic">October Friday</hi> 1804</date>
               </ab>
               <p>
I rose early    after brackfast we joined the Indians who were waiting on the bank for us to come out and go and Council, we accordingly joined them and went to the house of the 2nd Chief <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="person" key="Hay (Pocasse)">Lassil</name>
                  </hi> [<name type="person" key="Hay (Pocasse)">Pocasse</name>] where there was many Chief and warriers &amp; about 7 bushels of Corn, a pr Leagins a twist of their Tobacco &amp; Seeds of 2 Kind of Tobacco we Set Some time before the Councill Commenced    this man Spoke at Some length declareing his dispotion to believe and prosue our Councils, his intention of going to Visit his great father    acknowledged the Satisfaction 〈which he〉 in receiveing the presents &amp;c.    rais'g a Doubt as to the Safty on passing the nations below particularly the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Souex</name>.    requested us to take a Chief of their nation and make a good pact with <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandins</name> &amp; nations above.    after answering<ref target="n07101210" n="10"/> those parts of the 2d Chiefs Speech which required it, which appeared to give General Satisfaction we went to the Village of the 3rd Chief and as usial Some Serimony took place before he Could Speek to us on the Great Subject. This Chief Spoke verry much in the Stile on nearly the Same Subjects of the other Chief who Set by his Side, more Sincear &amp; pleasently, he presented us with about 10 bushels of Corn Some beens &amp; quashes all of which we acksepted with much pleasure, after we had ansd. his Speech &amp; give them Some account of the Magnitude &amp; power of our Countrey which pleased and astonished them verry much we returned to our boat, the Chiefs accompanied us on board, we gave them Some Sugar a little Salt, and a Sun Glass, &amp; Set 2 on Shore &amp; the third proceeded on with us to the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandens</name> by name _____,<ref target="n07101211" n="11"/> at 2 oClock we Set out the inhabitints of the two Villages Viewing us from the banks, we proceeded on about 9½ miles and Camped on the S. S. at Some woods passed, the evening Clear &amp; pleasent Cooler</p>
               <p>
The Nation of the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Rickerrie</name> [<hi rend="italic">NB: <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Rickaras</name>
                  </hi>] is about [<hi rend="italic">WC: 〈450 men〉 <name type="person" key="Tabeau, Pierre-Antoine">Mr. Taboe</name> says, I think 500 men</hi>] 600 men able to bear arms [<hi rend="italic">NB: <name type="person" key="Tabeau, Pierre-Antoine">Mr Tabat</name> is right</hi>]    a Great perpotion of them have fusees    they appear to be peacefull, their men tall and perpotiend, womin Small and industerous, raise great quantities of Corn Beens Simmins &amp;c. also Tobacco for the men to Smoke    they Collect all the wood and do the drugery as Common amongst Savages.</p>
               <p>
Thise 〈nation is〉 [<hi rend="italic">NB: two villages are</hi>] made up of 〈10〉 [<hi rend="italic">NB: nine</hi>] Different Tribes of the <name type="native_nation" key="Pawnee Indians">Pania</name> [<hi rend="italic">NB: <name type="native_nation" key="Pawnee Indians">Panies</name>
                  </hi>],<ref target="n07101212" n="12"/> who had formerly been Seperate, but by Commotion and war with their neighbours have Come reduced and compelled to Come together for protection,<ref target="n07101213" n="13"/> The Curruption of the language of those different Tribes has So reduced the language that the Different Villages do not understade all the words of the others.—    Those people are Durtey, Kind, pore, &amp; extravigent pursessing 〈Pride〉 national pride.    not beggarley reive what is given with great pleasure, Live in worm houses large and built in an oxigon [octagon] form forming a Cone at top which is left open for the <hi rend="italic">Smoke</hi> to pass, those houses are generally 30 or 40 foot Diamiter. Covd. with earth on poles willows &amp; grass<ref target="n07101214" n="14"/> to prevent the earths passing thro',</p>
               <p>
Those people express an inclination to be at peace with all nations—The <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Seaux</name> who trade the goods which they get of the British Traders for their corn, and great influence over the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Rickere</name>, poisen their minds and keep them in perpetial dread.</p>
               <p>
I Saw Some of the 〈<name type="native_nation" key="Cheyenne Indians">Chien</name> or Dog〉 [<hi rend="italic">NB: <name type="native_nation" key="Cheyenne Indians">Chyenne</name>
                  </hi>] Indians, also a 〈fiew〉 man of a nation under the <hi rend="italic">Court new</hi>—<ref target="n07101215" n="15"/>    This nation is at war with the <name type="native_nation" key="Crow Indians">Crow Indians</name> &amp; have 3 Children prisoners.</p>
               <p>
a curious Cuistom with the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Souix</name> as well as the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">reckeres</name> is to give handsom Squars to those whome they wish to Show Some acknowledgements to—    The <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Seauix</name> we got Clare of without taking their Squars, they followed us with Squars 13th<ref target="n07101216" n="16"/> two days. The <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Rickores</name> we put off dureing the time we were at the Towns but 2 Handsom young Squars were Sent by a man to follow us, they Came up this evening and peresisted in their Civilities.</p>
               <p>
Dress of the men of this nation is Simply a pr. mockerson, Leagins, flap in front &amp; a Buffalow roabe, with ther [their?] arms &amp; ears Deckorated</p>
               <p>
The women, wore Mockersons leagins fringed and a Shirt of Goat Skins, Some with Sleaves.    this garment is longe &amp; Genlry. White &amp; fringed, tied at the waste with a roabe, in Summer without hair.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="right">12th Octr.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <table rows="6" cols="3">
                     <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Course Distance &amp; reffurence</hi>
                     </head>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 45 E</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">2</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Miles to the mouth of a creek between the 2 upper villages<lb/>
of the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Rickere</name> L. S. (1)</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">S. 75° E.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">1 ½</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">miles the point on the L. S.    passed the Village (2)</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 45° E.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">2</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">mes. to a point of wood on the L. S.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 20° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">2 ½</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">miles to a pt. on the S. S.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">N. 8° W.</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                           <hi rend="underline">1 ½</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">miles to a pt. on L. S. passed a Sand bar.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                           <hi rend="double underline">9 ½</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1804-10-12.03" n="lc.geo.1804-10-12.01">
            <sp who="wc">
               <speaker>Clark</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date>[<hi rend="italic">undated, October 12, 1804</hi>]<ref target="n07101217" n="17"/>
                  </date>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="center">
                     <hi rend="italic">2nd Chief <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Ricaras</name>
                     </hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>
My Father, I am glad to See this is a fine Day to here the good Councils &amp; talk good talk</p>
               <p>
I am glad to See you &amp; that your intentions are to open the road for all</p>
               <p>
we See that our Grand father has Sent you to open the road    we See it</p>
               <p>
Our Grand father by Sending you means to take pity on us</p>
               <p>
Our Grand father has Sent you with tobacco to make peace with all nations, we think</p>
               <p>
The first nation who has recomended the road to be clear and open.</p>
               <p>
You Come here &amp; have Directed all nations which you have met to open &amp; clear the road.</p>
               <p>
[If?] you come to See the water &amp; roads to Clear them as Clear as possible</p>
               <p>
you just now Come to See us, &amp; we wish you to tell our Grand ftar that we wish the road to be kept Clear &amp; open.</p>
               <p>
I expect the Chief in the next Town will tell you the Same to move on &amp; open the road</p>
               <p>
I think when you Saw the nations below the[y] wish you to open the road—    (or something to that amount:</p>
               <p>
when you passd. the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Souex</name> they told you the Same I expect.    we See you here to day    we are pore our women have no Strouds &amp; Knives to Cut their meat    take pitty on us when you return.</p>
               <p>
you Come here &amp; Derect us to Stay at home &amp; not go to war, we Shall do So, we hope you will when you get to the <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandins</name>
                  </hi> you will tell them the Same &amp; Cleer the road, no one Dar to Stop you, you go when you please,—</p>
               <p>
The you tell us to go Down, we will go and See our grand father &amp; here &amp; receve his Gifts, and think fully that our nation will be covered after our return, our people will look for us with the same impatience that our Grand father looks for your return, to Give him</p>
               <p>
If I am going to See my grand father, many bad nations on the road, I am not afraid to Die for the good of my people (all Cried around him.)</p>
               <p>
The Chief By me will go to the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name> &amp; hear what they will Say.    (we agree'd.)</p>
               <p>
The verry moment we Set out to go down we will Send out my Brother to bring all the Nation in the open prarie to See me part on this Great mission to See my Great father.</p>
               <p>
our people hunting Shall be glad to here of your being here &amp; they will all Come to See, as you Cannot Stay they must wate for your return to See you, we are pore take pity on our wants</p>
               <p>
The road is for you all to go on, who do you think will injure a white man when they come to exchange for our Roabes &amp; Beaver</p>
               <p>
after you Set out many nations in the open plains may Come to make war against us, we wish you to Stop their guns &amp; provent it if possible. Finished</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="center">3d Chief of <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Ricares</name>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>
My fathers    I will see the Indians below &amp; See if they have the hart as they tell you</p>
               <p>
The nation below is the 〈<name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>〉 <name type="native_nation" key="Omaha Indians">Mahas</name> &amp; <name type="native_nation" key="Oto Indians">Ottes</name> &amp; but one nation, (the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Souix</name>[)] has not a good heart.</p>
               <p>
I always look at the 1t Chief &amp; the 2d whin they go &amp; will also follow ther example &amp; go on also</p>
               <p>
You See those 2 men they are chiefs, when I go they will take Care, they beleve your words.</p>
               <p>
Mabie we will not tell the trooth, as to the Child    perhaps they will not wish to go.</p>
               <p>
My Children the old women &amp; men whin I return I can then give them, Some a Knife Some powder &amp; others Ball &amp;c. What is the matter if we was to go for nothing    my great Chief wish to go, I wish to go also.</p>
               <p>
when I go to See my Grand father I wish to return quicke for fear of my people being uneasy.</p>
               <p>
my Children are Small &amp; perhaps will be uneasy whin I may be Safe</p>
               <p>
I must go, I also wish to go, perhaps I may when I return make my people glad</p>
               <p>
I will Stay at home &amp; not go to War even if my people are Struck</p>
               <p>
we will believ your word but I fear the Indians above will not believe your word.</p>
               <p>
I will think that ½ of the men who will return will Stay in this Village ½ below in the other villages</p>
               <p>
what did the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Seaus</name> tell you—    (we informd them) 

</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1804-10-12.04" n="lc.geo.1804-10-12.01">
            <sp who="jo">
               <speaker>Ordway</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Friday 12th Oct 1804</hi>.    a Clear &amp; pleasant morning.    the Indians assembled on the bank near us for to Trade with us.    they wanted red paint mostly, but would Give whatever they had to Spare for any kind of Goods    one of the men Gave an Indian a pin hook &amp; the Indian Gave him in return a pair of Moggisins    we Gave them Some Small articles of Goods for Buffalow Robes &amp; Moggn. &amp;.C.    the officers went to the villages in order to hear what the chiefs had to Say. They Gave us 10 or 12 bushels of corn &amp; beans &amp;.C. &amp;.C.    the officers came on board about 12 oClock    took a Good Indian with us who had been to the head of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri River</name>.    about 1 oClock we Set off the fiddle playing &amp; the horns Sounding &amp;.C.    little abo. the Towns we Saw a great nomber of Squaws employed in toteing wood across the River in their Buffalow hide cannoes    proceeded on.    passd. a timbred bottom on S. S.    also one on the N. S. where we Camped at the upper end of the Bottom on N. S. <name type="person" key="Newman, John">Newman</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Reed, Moses B.">Reed</name> confined.<ref target="n07101218" n="18"/>    3 Indians came to Camp


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1804-10-12.05" n="lc.geo.1804-10-12.01">
            <sp who="pg">
               <speaker>Gass</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Friday 12th.</hi>    We had a pleasant morning, and remained here the forenoon to hear the chief of this village speak. Last night the Indians stole an axe from our cook, which of course in some degree diminished our confidence, and lessened the amicable character we had conceived of them. At 9 o'clock <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Lewis</name>, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain Clarke</name> and myself went to the 2nd Village, and talked with its chief; then to the third Village, about half a mile beyond a small creek,<ref target="n07101219" n="19"/> and talked with the chief of that Village; and got some corn and beans<ref target="n07101220" n="20"/> from them. The third village is nearly of the same size of the second, and has in it a great number of handsome and smart women and children: the men are mostly out hunting. About 12 we left the village and proceeded on our voyage. One of the natives agreed to go with us as far as the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>. We encamped on the north side. After dark we heard some person hallooing on the opposite shore; and a periogue went over and brought an Indian and two squaws, who remained with us all night.<ref target="n07101221" n="21"/>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="entry" xml:id="lc.jrn.1804-10-12.06" n="lc.geo.1804-10-12.01">
            <sp who="jw">
               <speaker>Whitehouse</speaker>
               <ab>
                  <date/>
               </ab>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Friday 12th Oct</hi>. 1804.    about 12 oclock we Set off.    one of the natives went with us, to go as far as the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>.    we Camped on the N. S. of the River—</p>
               <p>
Friday October 12th    This morning we had pleasant weather, the Indians that had been with us, the last Evening, we found had stole one of our Axes, about 2 o'Clock P. M. we set off, one of the Indians came to the Boat &amp; embarked with us, We proceeded on till 4 oClock P. M. and encamped on the North side of the River, We had been encamped but a short time, when some Indians came to the opposite side of the River and called to us, to bring 
them over.    One of the Pettyaugers was sent, and brought them, they remain'd with us during the Night.—


</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <note xml:id="n07101201" n="1">Evidently they walked, which would mean that this village (<name type="place" key="Rhtarahe village">Rhtarahe</name>) was the nearer to their camp of the two on the larboard side of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> in <name type="place" key="Corson County, S. Dak.">Corson County</name>, <name type="place" key="South Dakota">South Dakota</name>. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 25.</note>
            <note xml:id="n07101202" n="2">For his speech and that of the next chief see below in this day's entry.</note>
            <note xml:id="n07101203" n="3">
               <hi rend="italic">Nicotiana quadrivalvis</hi> Pursh. Goodspeed, 451; Gilmore (SCAT); Cronquist et al., 72.</note>
            <note xml:id="n07101204" n="4">The other village on the larboard shore (<name type="place" key="Waho-erha village">Waho-erha</name>), just upstream from the one they had already visited. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 25.</note>
            <note xml:id="n07101205" n="5">In <name type="place" key="Campbell County, S. Dak.">Campbell County</name>, <name type="place" key="South Dakota">South Dakota</name>, in an area now inundated by the <name type="place" key="Oahe Reservoir">Oahe Reservoir</name>. <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 25; Mattison (OR), 108–9; MRC map 45.</note>
            <note xml:id="n07101206" n="6">
               <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name> gives an excellent description of an <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> earth lodge on <ref n="1804-10-10" type="related">October 10</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n07101207" n="7">
               <name type="person" key="Cameron, Murdoch">Murdoch Cameron</name>, a Scotsman, was a trader on the <name type="place" key="Minnesota River (St. Peters)">St. Peters</name>, or <name type="place" key="Minnesota River (St. Peters)">Minnesota River</name>,, whom <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> believed to have a bad influence on the Indians. They never met him, but in 1805 <name type="person" key="Pike, Zebulon Montgomery">Zebulon Montgomery Pike</name> warned him against trading liquor to the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>. <name type="person" key="Cameron, Murdoch">Cameron</name> died in 1811, reportedly from being poisoned by a <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>. See below, <ref n="1805-02-28" type="related">February 28</ref>, <ref n="1805-03-18" type="related">March 18, 1805</ref>, and <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name>
               <ref n="1804-1805.winter.part1" type="related">Summary of Rivers and Creeks</ref>. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> to <name type="person" key="Heney, Hugh">Hugh Heney</name>, July 20, 1806, Observations and Reflections of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> [August 1807], Jackson (LLC), 1:312–13 and n. 1, 2:703 and n. 8; Jackson (JP), 1:33 and n. 61, 34, 37, 39, 62 and n. 104, 120, 122. </note>
            <note xml:id="n07101208" n="8">Or perhaps the party did not refuse. See Ronda (LCAI), 62–64. Cultural explanations for this seemingly promiscuous practice are given in ibid. and in Kehoe. It was sanctioned for purposes of trade, for hospitality, and, most importantly, it was a means by which power was transferred from older or more powerful men to aspiring young men via their wives.</note>
            <note xml:id="n07101209" n="9">The line is probably a repeat of the preceding.</note>
            <note xml:id="n07101210" n="10">The text of the entry is interrupted at this point by the courses and distances; the two parts are joined together for ease of reading.</note>
            <note xml:id="n07101211" n="11">If this man was the same as <name type="person" key="Toone">Piaheto</name>, whose name was already recorded, it is hard to see why <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> left a blank, unless he had become aware that the man had a multiplicity of names and was waiting to decide which to use.</note>
            <note xml:id="n07101212" n="12">
               <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi> map 25 indicates that the village on the starboard side of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, in <name type="place" key="Campbell County, S. Dak.">Campbell County</name>, was the one composed of nine separate groups of people, and says "The other two villages are <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Ricaries</name> proper." The reference to "<name type="native_nation" key="Pawnee Indians">Panias</name>" (<name type="native_nation" key="Pawnee Indians">Pawnees</name>) refers to their being of the same Caddoan language family as the <name type="native_nation" key="Pawnee Indians">Pawnees</name>. This shows the diversity of language and culture often found among Indians classed by whites as belonging to the same "tribe." Hodge, 1:83–86; Parks (NCL).</note>
            <note xml:id="n07101213" n="13">
               <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> here ignores the predominant role played by smallpox in reducing the population of the river tribes. Elsewhere he notes the devastation wrought by the disease. White (WW), 325–27; Stearn &amp; Stearn.</note>
            <note xml:id="n07101214" n="14">Possibly <hi rend="italic">Andropogon gerardi</hi> Vitman, big bluestem, or <hi rend="italic">Spartina pectinata</hi> Link, prarie cordgrass or sloughgrass. Gilmore (UPI), 16, 14.</note>
            <note xml:id="n07101215" n="15">The <name type="native_nation" key="Cheyenne Indians">Cheyennes</name> were a small tribe of the Algonquian language family, who moved from <name type="place" key="Minnesota">Minnesota</name> into the <name type="place" key="North Dakota, South Dakota">Dakotas</name> in the eighteenth century, ahead of the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>. In the early 1800s, having adopted the nomadic hunting life of the plains, they became allies of the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>. Their role in the wars later in the nineteenth century won them a fame out of proportion to their numbers. The identity of the "nation under the <hi rend="italic">Court new</hi>"—that is, <name type="place" key="Black Hills">Cǒte Noir</name>, <name type="place" key="Black Hills">Black Hills</name>—is not readily apparent. Possibly they were <name type="native_nation" key="Kiowa Indians">Kiowas</name>, some of whom were still near the <name type="place" key="Black Hills">Black Hills</name> near the end of the eighteenth century, or possibly <name type="native_nation" key="Arapaho Indians">Arapahoes</name>. Hyde (IHP), 144, 151–52.</note>
            <note xml:id="n07101216" n="16">"13th" here may mean that the two <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> women mentioned below continued to follow them on <ref n="1804-10-13" type="related">October 13</ref> as they had on the twelfth.</note>
            <note xml:id="n07101217" n="17">This material is on loose sheets in the Voorhis Collection, Missouri Historical Society. See Indian Speeches, Miscellaneous Documents of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, <ref n="v02.appendix.c" type="related">Appendix C</ref>. The date was established from references in the regular entry.</note>
            <note xml:id="n07101218" n="18">
               <name type="person" key="Newman, John">John Newman</name> was tried the next day for "having uttered repeated expressions of a highly criminal and mutinous nature," was found guilty, and sentenced to receive seventy-five lashes on his back. He was also dismissed from the permanent party and had to return with other non-permanent members from <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name> in the spring of 1805. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> does not mention the incident until the next day and no one mentions <name type="person" key="Reed, Moses B.">Moses B. Reed's</name> connection with the incident.</note>
            <note xml:id="n07101219" n="19">The two villages are <name type="place" key="Rhtarahe village">Rhtarahe</name> and <name type="place" key="Waho-erha village">Waho-erha</name>, <name type="place" key="Corson County, S. Dak.">Corson County</name>, <name type="place" key="South Dakota">South Dakota</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n07101220" n="20">The beans were the product of the hog peanut, <hi rend="italic">Amphicarpa bracteata</hi> (L.) Fern.</note>
            <note xml:id="n07101221" n="21">
               <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name> says nothing of the mutinous conduct of <name type="person" key="Newman, John">Newman</name> this day, or the confinement of <name type="person" key="Newman, John">Newman</name> and <name type="person" key="Reed, Moses B.">Reed</name>.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1804-10-11" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="1804-10-13" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
