<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.sup.ronda.01.07">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> among the Indians</title>
            <title type="sub" level="a">7. Down the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>
            </title>
            <title type="sub"/>
            <author>James P. Ronda</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2005</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title level="m" type="main">
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> among the Indians</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">7. Down the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>
               </title>
               <author>James P. Ronda</author>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1984</date>
               <idno type="ISBN">0-8032-8990-1</idno>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Supplements</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Texts</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-11-01</date>
            <date>2005-02-01</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>File splitting Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="ch7" type="chapter" n="7">
            <quote>
               <lg type="linegroup">
                  <l>"Our Situation well calculated to defend our selves from any designs of the natives,</l>
                  <l> Should they be enclined to attack us."</l>
               </lg>
               <bibl>—<name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark</name>, 1805</bibl>
            </quote>
            <div type="section">
               <p>
When <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> pulled out of the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref>
                  <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Clearwater</name> villages in boats in early October, they were moving toward worlds wholly unlike any they had yet experienced. In the next two months the expedition left the mountains and ponderosa pines of the plateau and sailed through the awesome and seemingly desolate <name type="place" key="Great Columbian Plain">Columbia Plain</name>. Navigating hazardous rivers, the Corps of Discovery paddled the <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Clearwater</name> to the <name type="place"
                        key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Snake</name> and on at last to the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>. Driven to reach the western sea before winter and challenged by treacherous white water, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had little time to describe the dark-walled canyons and treeless plains around them. But in one memorable passage, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> tried to capture something of the strange landscape. "The face of the Countrey on both Side of the river above and about the falls," wrote the captain, "is Steep ruged and rockey open and contain but a Small preportion of herbage, no timber a fiew bushes excepted."<ref target="n0701" n="1"/> But below the <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Cascades (Great Rapids, Great Shute)">Cascades of the Columbia</name> the terrain and climate once again changed dramatically. Rain, fog, and dense ground cover all signaled that <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had at last reached a marine environment. They were in territory that received more than sixty inches of rain annually, more than six times the amount that fell on the land they had seen around <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The Dalles</name>. Days marked by high winds, terrifying storms, monotonous meals of pounded salmon, and a damp that rotted clothing and tents pointed to what lay ahead during the winter at <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name>.<ref target="n0702" n="2"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Moving through climates and landforms striking for their abrupt changes tested the expedition's endurance, as did the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> itself. But even more striking were the physical and cultural differences among the Indians down the river and toward the coast. At the confluence of the <name type="place"
                        key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Snake</name> and the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> entered an Indian world increasingly distant from the plains traditions that had been so much a part of expedition-Indian relations since those early days along the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>. On the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>, salmon was king and fishing the enterprise that gave shape to native life. Large houses with wooden frames, clothing a strange admixture of native and European fashions, graceful canoes with "curious images" at their bows, and practices like head-flattening—all pointed to a native environment dominated by <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name> ways.</p>
               <p>
To these sights were added the strange clucking sounds of the Chinookan speakers and the smells of tons of stacked salmon drying in warm winds blowing up the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> gorge. In flea-infested plank houses or at hastily made camps along the river, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> contended with Indians long accustomed to dealing with English, American, and native traders. The <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name> Sahaptians and Chinookans could outbargain the sharpest Yankee in dealing for dog meat or precious firewood. In those transactions it was the Indian middleman—whether <name type="native_nation" key="Wishram-Wasco Indians">Wishram</name> or <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinook</name>—who expected to set the price, while outsiders of whatever cultural stripe were to pay or go without. An unfamiliar material culture coupled with hard bargaining methods a bit too close to home hinted that relations with the Indians in the Pacific Northwest were going to be distant at best and troubled at worst.</p>
               <p>
But much if not all of this was unimagined during the first days of travel beyond <name type="place" key="Canoe Camp (Idaho)">Canoe Camp</name>. For nearly a week the expedition struggled with the twists, turns, and rapids of the <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Clearwater</name> and <name type="place"
                        key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Snake</name>. As <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> neared the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>-<name type="place"
                        key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Snake</name> confluence, they constantly had to deal with dangerous rocks, capsized canoes, and wet gear. Fully occupied in navigating through the many <name type="place"
                        key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Snake River</name> rapids, the explorers perhaps missed the subtle signs that they were approaching the eastern edge of the <name type="place" key="Great Columbian Plain">great Columbia Plain</name>. One indication they did record was the growing scarcity of firewood. The Indians who lived along the <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Clearwater</name> and upper <name type="place"
                        key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Snake</name> very carefully gathered and stacked whatever wood was available. On October 14, at <name type="place" key="Pine Tree (Cave) Rapids">Pinetree Rapids</name> on the <name type="place"
                        key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Snake</name> some thirty miles below the <name type="place" key="Palouse (Drouillard's) River">Palouse River</name>, the Americans were so short of wood that they asked their two <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> guides for permission to take and burn some of the Indians' wood.<ref target="n0703" n="3"/>
               </p>
               <p>
If hints of coming changes in land and climate in land and climate were overlooked, it was harder to miss the human clues pointing to a life where salmon replaced buffalo. During the six days before coming to the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>, the party passed dozens of fishing villages. Those villages, typically containing four brush lodges, were located about eight to ten miles apart at good fishing runs. In the summer, lodges were built with willows and rushes in a style that may have reminded the explorers of <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Shoshoni.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name>
                  </ref> wickiups. Winter lodges made with split pine rails wore a more permanent face. Attracting more of the expedition's attention were the graveyards prominently located in many villages. Unlike scaffold burial places seen on the plains, these cemeteries were marked by picket fences surrounding bodies interred in the earth.<ref target="n0704" n="4"/>
               </p>
               <p>
From their <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> guides <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> knew that they were quite close to the <name type="place"
                        key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Snake</name>-<name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> confluence and the territories of Indians having little contact with whites. Thus informed, the captains prepared for what proved to be the first of many meetings with Indians down the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>. <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">Twisted Hair</name> and <name type="person" key="Tetoharsky">Tetoharsky</name> were sent ahead on October 14 to announce the expedition's advance. Those Sahaptians scouted by the chiefs were known to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> as <name type="native_nation" key="Wanapam Indians">Sokulks</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Yakima Indians">Chimnapams</name>. The <name type="native_nation" key="Wanapam Indians">Sokulks</name> proved to be <name type="native_nation" key="Wanapam Indians">Wanapams</name> who lived on the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> above the <name type="place"
                        key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Snake</name>-<name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> confluence, while the <name type="native_nation" key="Yakima Indians">Chimnapams</name> were <name type="native_nation" key="Yakima Indians">Yakimas</name> whose villages dotted the great river around present-day <name type="place" key="Pasco, Wash.">Pasco</name>, <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>.<ref target="n0705" n="5"/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">Twisted Hair</name> and <name type="person" key="Tetoharsky">Tetoharsky</name> did their advance work skillfully; on October 16 near the <name type="place"
                        key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Snake</name>-<name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> junction, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> saw five Indians coming upriver "in great haste." Anxious to make a good first impression, the captains brought out tobacco and smoked with the new arrivals. Each was given additional tobacco to distribute among other Indians. The native party, either <name type="native_nation" key="Yakima Indians">Yakimas</name> from nearby villages or visiting <name type="native_nation" key="Wanapam Indians">Wanapams</name>, eagerly took the tobacco and hurried back to spread the news of an impending great event.</p>
               <p>
By midday the expedition was at the <name type="place"
                        key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Snake</name>-<name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> confluence and, as had so often happened on the Upper <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, the Americans quickly became objects of intense curiosity. Scores of <name type="native_nation" key="Yakima Indians">Yakimas</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Wanapam Indians">Wanapams</name> lined the riverbanks to stare in astonishment at the bearded strangers and all their fascinating baggage. Those Indian sightseers bold enough to approach <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> were rewarded with small twists of tobacco. As the Indians watched closely, the explorers made camp and waited for official delegations from the river peoples.</p>
               <p>
Later in the evening, the expedition was treated to a spectacle the likes of which they had not seen since their grand welcome by <name type="person" key="Cameahwait">Cameahwait's</name>
                  <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Shoshoni.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshonis</name>
                  </ref>. Led by their chief <name type="person" key="Cutssahnem">Cutssahnem</name>, two hundred <name type="native_nation" key="Wanapam Indians">Wanapam</name> men came striding into the American camp singing and beating on small drums. In the firelight the <name type="native_nation" key="Wanapam Indians">Wanapams</name> formed a half circle and continued to chant a festive greeting. After the obligatory smoke, the captains got down to serious talk with <name type="person" key="Cutssahnem">Cutssahnem</name>. But as was so often the case in the Northwest, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> were handicapped by translation difficulties. American intentions were explained in signs to <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">Twisted Hair</name> and <name type="person" key="Tetoharsky">Tetoharsky</name>, who then had to be relied upon to present a faithful summary to their fellow Sahaptian speakers. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> wanted the <name type="native_nation" key="Wanapam Indians">Wanapams</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Yakima Indians">Yakimas</name> to know "our friendly disposition to all nations, and our joy in Seeing those of our friendly Children around us." If the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> translators failed to get the message across, the explorers knew from long experience that gifts were a powerful declaration of "friendly disposition." For <name type="person" key="Cutssahnem">Cutssahnem</name> there was a large medal, a shirt, and a handkerchief. An unnamed "second chief" and a headman from one of the <name type="native_nation" key="Wanapam Indians">Wanapam</name> villages were given smaller medals. With all parties properly welcomed and in good spirits, the Americans ended the day by purchasing eight fat dogs, some dried salmon, and twenty pounds of dried horsemeat.<ref target="n0706" n="6"/>
               </p>
               <p>
The junction of the <name type="place"
                        key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Snake</name> and the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> rivers had long been a favorite place for <name type="native_nation" key="Yakima Indians">Yakimas</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Wanapam Indians">Wanapams</name> to gather for fishing, trading, and visiting. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> decided to camp for an additional day or two at the junction to repair broken equipment, dry dampened papers, and purchase additional provisions. On the morning of October 17, while <name type="person" key="Cutssahnem">Cutssahnem</name> and several of his principal men traded dogs and vocabulary phrases with <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> took two men in a small canoe for a short reconnaisance up the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>. The mat-lodge fishing villages and drying scaffolds he saw along the banks were of the sort that would be described in the expedition's records for many days to come. At one cluster of lodges, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> stopped for a closer look. In one house he found a busy crowd of men, women, and children. Seemingly unafraid of their uninvited guest, the <name type="native_nation" key="Wanapam Indians">Wanapams</name> politely offered <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> a sitting mat and some boiled salmon "on a platter of rushes neetly made." As <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> enjoyed his meal and the good company, he took careful note of his hosts' clothing, manners, and physical characteristics.</p>
               <p>
Once back at camp, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> found time to write an extended commentary on the river folk. Following the categories that were now an integral part of expedition ethnography, he described their bodies, dress, and houses. His observations on <name type="native_nation" key="Wanapam Indians">Wanapam</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Yakima Indians">Yakima</name> clothing and ornament were written with his characteristic eye for detail. What especially captured <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> attention that day were three barely related but arresting facets of native life. Following directions from <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name> and <name type="person" key="Rush, Benjamin">Rush</name> that economic relations between males and females be carefully noted, the explorers generally repeated the white wisdom proclaiming Indian women "squaw drudges" to tyrannical husbands. Along the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>, the explorers found societies in which the sharing of labor between men and women was much more in evidence. Those societies placed considerable emphasis on age and wisdom. At one mat lodge <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> met a centenarian who sat at the best place in the house, and "when She spoke great attention was paid to what she said." Mat lodges, so unlike <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> earth lodges or plains tepees, also called for written description. Later in their <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> voyage, the explorers would see large plank houses and pit dwellings, but from the <name type="place"
                        key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Snake</name>-<name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> confluence to <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The Dalles</name> mat lodges were the most common native architecture. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> noted that the houses measured from fifteen to sixty feet long and were "generally of an oblong sqare form." The whole dwelling was supported by interior poles and forks. Openings along the roof allowed smoke from cooking fires to escape. Quick to see the relationship between house design and climate, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> noted that flat roofs "proves to me that rains are not common in this open country." Perhaps thinking of the kinds of medical information so eagerly sought by <name type="person" key="Rush, Benjamin">Benjamin Rush</name>, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> recorded the eye ailments and dental peculiarities present among river people. Looking over his new-found native friends, the explorer pronounced them "of a mild disposition and friendly disposed."<ref target="n0707" n="7"/>
               </p>
               <p>
The time taken with Indians at the <name type="place"
                        key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Snake</name>-<name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> junction was well spent because it allowed for repairing equipment and gathering vital geographic information. From <name type="person" key="Cutssahnem">Cutssahnem</name> the explorers obtained a charcoal-on-skin map "of the rivers and Tribes above on the great river and its waters on which he put great numbers of villages of his nation and friends." An unnamed <name type="native_nation" key="Yakima Indians">Yakima</name> chief who joined the council on October 18 offered a second map of the same territory and its people. These maps and the numbers of people seen around the confluence made it plain to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> that daily encounters with Indians were to be expected. As the expedition left the junction and began to navigate the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>, <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">Twisted Hair</name> and <name type="person" key="Tetoharsky">Tetoharsky</name> were sent on ahead again to prepare the way. When the two <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> scouts returned later in the day and found the expedition past the <name type="place" key="Walla Walla (Waller Waller) River">Walla Walla River</name> and ready to camp in present-day <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>, they carried news of chief <name type="person" key="Yelleppit">Yelleppit</name> and the <name type="native_nation" key="Walula Indians">Walla Walla Indians</name>.<ref target="n0708" n="8"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Relayed by the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> guides, the greeting <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> got that evening from the <name type="native_nation" key="Walula Indians">Walulas or Walla Wallas</name> and their chief <name type="person" key="Yelleppit">Yelleppit</name> was as enthusiastic as that offered earlier by <name type="person" key="Cutssahnem">Cutssahnem</name> and his kin. <name type="person" key="Yelleppit">Yelleppit's</name> message of welcome included an offer of scarce firewood as an additional sign of friendship. Later that night the chief and some twenty of his men came upriver and made camp a short distance from the explorers.</p>
               <p>
Early the next morning <name type="person" key="Yelleppit">Yelleppit</name>, two other <name type="native_nation" key="Walula Indians">Walula</name> chiefs, and a chief from either a <name type="native_nation" key="Cayuse Indians">Cayuse</name> or a <name type="native_nation" key="Umatilla Indians">Umatilla</name> band appeared in camp for a grand council. <name type="person" key="Yelleppit">Yelleppit</name> was an imposing figure, described by <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> as "a bold handsom Indian, with a dignified countenance about 35 years of age, about 5 feet 8 inches high and well perpotioned." Struggling as always with translations, the explorer-diplomats did the best they could with signs to convey their "friendly intentions towards our red children perticelar those who opened their ears to our Councils." <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> words were not recorded, but the <name type="native_nation" key="Walula Indians">Walula</name> chief probably heard the usual diplomatic speech directed to Indians. Presentations of a medal, a handkerchief, some wampum for <name type="person" key="Yelleppit">Yelleppit</name>, and additional strings of wampum for the other chiefs were all part of the expedition's good-will ritual.</p>
               <p>
Fascinated by the explorers and impressed with their store of goods, <name type="person" key="Yelleppit">Yelleppit</name> asked them to remain a day longer so that all his people could see them. His request betrayed something more than just native curiosity about whites. The chief had his eye on the weapons and goods carried by the explorers. If European objects were already in <name type="native_nation" key="Walula Indians">Walula</name> hands (and no expedition diarist mentioned seeing any such until further downriver) they surely came from other Indian traders. Like the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name>
                  <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> or <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> who hoped to keep the explorers and their goods from moving on, so too did <name type="person" key="Yelleppit">Yelleppit</name> seek to persuade <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> to remain a while longer. The chief's search for European goods would continue for years after the captains politely rejected his request. When <name type="person" key="Thompson, David">David Thompson</name> visited <name type="person" key="Yelleppit">Yelleppit</name> in July 1811, the chief made the same kind of request. In addition, <name type="person" key="Yelleppit">Yelleppit</name> wanted <name type="person" key="Thompson, David">Thompson</name> to build a trading house at the <name type="place"
                        key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Snake</name>-<name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> confluence.<ref target="n0709" n="9"/>
               </p>
               <p>
As the expedition continued down the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> and neared the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Umatilla (Youmalolam) River">Umatilla River</name>, Indian reactions began to change dramatically. The welcomes offered by <name type="person" key="Cutssahnem">Cutssahnem</name> and <name type="person" key="Yelleppit">Yelleppit</name> vanished and were replaced first by fear and then by ill-concealed hostility. That fear became evident during the afternoon of October 19 as the explorers left <name type="native_nation" key="Walula Indians">Walula</name> territory and entered that occupied by <name type="native_nation" key="Umatilla Indians">Umatillas</name>. Throughout the afternoon, the men saw hastily abandoned villages and frightened Indians. "At our approach," said <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, "they hid themselves in their Lodges and not one was to be seen until we passed." Although the expedition's records offer no straightforward explanation for this sudden shift in native attitudes, an event later in that afternoon does suggest how Indians with little or no contact with whites responded to the expedition.</p>
               <p>
As <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> was walking on shore with a small party that included <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name>, <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name>, and the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> guides, he idly shot a crane. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> thought no more about the incident. A cluster of mat lodges in the distance seemed more worthy of attention. Indians from those lodges were spotted running in terror back to their village. Anxious to quiet the <name type="native_nation" key="Umatilla Indians">Umatillas'</name> fears, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> decided to take <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name> and the <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph and Reubin">Field brothers</name> on a visit. Once at the settlement, they found five mat houses with their doors firmly shut. Pipe in hand, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> pushed his way into the first lodge and found thirty-two men, women, and children "in the greatest agutation." As the Indians cried, wrung their hands, and lowered their heads in preparation for death, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> struggled to allay their fears. Handshaking, a proffered pipe, and gifts eventually soothed them. He repeated the performance at the other lodges and, with the help of the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> chiefs and the presence of <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name>, terror passed into what he claimed was "greatest friendship." Then the <name type="native_nation" key="Umatilla Indians">Umatillas</name> spilled out the reason for their fear. As <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> explained it later to <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Nicholas Biddle</name>, "The alarm was occasioned by their thinking that we were supernatural and came down from the clouds." The <name type="native_nation" key="Umatilla Indians">Umatilla</name> perception of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> as sky gods had been sparked by <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> random killing of the crane. "These shots (having never heard a gun), a few light clouds passing, the fall of the birds and our immediately landing and coming towards them convinced them we were from above."<ref target="n0710" n="10"/>
               </p>
               <p>
As the expedition moved closer to <name type="place" key="Celilo (Great) Falls">Celilo Falls</name> and <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The Dalles</name>, the Indians continued to show signs of fear and distrust. Perhaps the outsiders were identified with <name type="native_nation" key="Paiute Indians">Paiute</name> warriors who frequently raided in the region. For whatever reason, the river people traded warily with <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>. <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> recalled that these Indians acted "as if they were in fear of us."<ref target="n0711" n="11"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Noting that edginess, members of the party stayed close to their weapons, but something else increasingly captured their attention. On October 20, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> saw the first piece of European clothing, a "salors jacket," on a river Indian. Even more trade goods were in evidence when the explorers visited the <name type="place" key="Upper Memaloose Island">Upper Memaloose Islands</name>. Known as the "place of the departed," the islands contained many large burial vaults filled not only with human and equestrian remains but with all sorts of trade goods of European manufacture. That those grave offerings were part of native daily life was verified when the explorers stopped at an Indian camp to purchase fish and found "some articles which showed that white people had been here or not far distant during the summer." By the time <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> were around the <name type="place"
                        key="John Day (Lepage's) River (Sherman-Gilliam counties, Oreg.)">John Day River</name>, non-Indian clothing and implements were everywhere.<ref target="n0712" n="12"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Sailors' overalls, brass bracelets, tea kettles, and scarlet blankets all pointed to the presence of a vast trade network centered at <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The Dalles of the Columbia</name>. Although <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> did not yet know it, they were about to encounter that center and cross a fundamental cultural and linguistic boundary. Just as the Middle <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> trade network and the people involved in it had a profound impact on the expedition, so did the Pacific-Plateau system dominate Indian-explorer relations around <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The Dalles</name> and down the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>. Understanding the Pacific-Plateau economic and cultural network is essential for comprehending the often tangled and tense encounters between river Indians and the American party.</p>
               <p>
On the broadest level, the Pacific-Plateau system involved exchanging huge quantities of dried salmon for other food and trade goods. What corn and buffalo were to the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> villagers, dried fish was to the <name type="native_nation" key="Wishram-Wasco Indians">Wishram and Wasco</name> merchants at <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The Dalles</name>. Stretching from the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name> coast to <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> territories and linked to the Middle <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> system by way of the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Shoshoni.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name>
                  </ref> Rendezvous, the network joined Chinookan and Sahaptian-speaking peoples in an intricate set of personal and economic relationships. Through the trade system flowed not only fish, wappato bread, buffalo robes, and European goods but also games, songs, and stories. Preserving the system met the needs not only of <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The Dalles</name> middlemen but also their more distant Chinookan and Sahaptian trading partners.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>
Geography, in the form of a dramatic narrowing of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> at <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The Dalles</name> and the resulting creation of ideal fishing stations, conspired with weather—warm dry winds blowing up the gorge—to make the Indian villages around the <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">Long</name> and <name type="place" key="Short (Little) Narrows">Short Narrows</name>, in <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> words, "great mart[s] of trade."<ref target="n0713" n="13"/> The <name type="native_nation" key="Wishram-Wasco Indians">Wishram Indians</name> lived on the north bank at <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The Dalles</name>; the <name type="native_nation" key="Wishram-Wasco Indians">Wascos</name> occupied sites on the south side of the river. Although trading and fishing took place from <name type="place" key="Celilo (Great) Falls">Celilo Falls</name> down to <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The Dalles</name>, the most intense bargaining was done at the main <name type="native_nation" key="Wishram-Wasco Indians">Wishram</name> village of <name type="place" key="Nix-luidix village">Nix-luidix</name>. That village, whose name meant "trading place," was located at the head of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">Long Narrows</name>. When <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> visited it on October 24, they found some twenty large wooden plank houses. Each plank dwelling held three <name type="native_nation" key="Wishram-Wasco Indians">Wishram</name> families. Asked by the explorers who they were, the <name type="native_nation" key="Wishram-Wasco Indians">Wishrams</name> replied, "i'tcxluit," meaning "I am Ita'xluit." That phrase sounded like <name type="native_nation" key="Wishram-Wasco Indians">Echeloot</name> to American ears; hence the expedition's maps and journals always referred to the <name type="native_nation" key="Wishram-Wasco Indians">Wishrams</name> as <name type="native_nation" key="Wishram-Wasco Indians">Echeloots</name>.</p>
               <p>
The towering stacks of dried salmon at <name type="place" key="Nix-luidix village">Nixluidix</name>, estimated by <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> at about ten thousand pounds, pointed up the vast quantities of goods exchanged in the Pacific-Plateau network. Trading took place from spring through fall during the three major salmon runs, with most activity reserved for the fall season. During September and October dried fish and roots were freshly prepared and in abundant supply. To <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The Dalles</name> trade fair came the nearby <name type="native_nation" key="Yakima Indians">Yakimas</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Tenino Indians">Teninos</name> as well as the more distant <name type="native_nation" key="Umatilla Indians">Umatillas</name>, <name type="native_nation" key="Walula Indians">Walulas</name>, and <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perces</name>
                  </ref>. Local Sahaptians brought to <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The Dalles</name> food products, including meat, roots, and berries. At the trading places, the <name type="native_nation" key="Wishram-Wasco Indians">Wishram</name> middlemen exchanged those goods for dried salmon and European cloth and ironware. Distant Sahaptians, especially the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perces</name>
                  </ref> who had access to the plains, brought skin clothing, horses, and buffalo meat. Less interested in fish than their <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> cousins, the Sahaptians of the plateau were drawn to <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The Dalles</name> in search of European goods, especially metal and beads.</p>
               <p>
Centered at <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The Dalles</name> and with one arm stretching east, the Pacific-Plateau system also extended west down the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> to the coastal <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookans</name>. Those <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name> peoples brought to the trade system a variety of European goods obtained from fur traders, as well as indigenous crops. Among the manufactured objects carried by them and eagerly sought by <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The Dalles</name> merchants were guns, blankets, clothing, and the prized blue beads. Coming upriver in their graceful canoes, the lower <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookans</name> carried wappato roots to be pounded and made into a bread that even the explorers found tasty. Once at <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The Dalles</name>, <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookans</name> obtained dried salmon, buffalo meat, and valuable bear grass used in making cooking baskets and the distinctive Northwest Coast hats.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> observed and recorded much about the Pacific-Plateau network and the kinds of goods that passed through it, but they arrived too late in the season to witness the full flavor of a rendezvous at <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The Dalles</name>. Although the smell of dead fish still hung in the air and clouds of fleas hovered everywhere, the real trading days were over by mid-October. The explorers grasped something of the economic significance of <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The Dalles</name> because they could see physical signs of the trade. The Astorian <name type="person" key="Ross, Alexander">Alexander Ross</name>, who had extensive <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name> experience soon after <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, caught the personal side of that trading before it was swept away by the great fur companies. <name type="person" key="Ross, Alexander">Ross</name> estimated that at peak trading times three thousand Indians gathered at the <name type="native_nation" key="Wishram-Wasco Indians">Wishram</name> villages for bargaining. But <name type="person" key="Ross, Alexander">Ross</name> also understood that trading was more than a simple act of economic exchange. Here Indians met old friends, made new ones, and heard the latest news. Gambling, socializing, and sporting for the opposite sex were all essential features of the trading days. "The <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">Long Narrows</name>," said <name type="person" key="Ross, Alexander">Ross</name>, "is the great emporium or mart of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> and the general theatre of gambling and roguery."<ref target="n0714" n="14"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Escaping the analysis of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> and later whites was the political significance of upper <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookan</name> control at <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The Dalles</name>. In the Middle <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> system, it was essential for <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name>
                  <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">Sioux</ref> bands to dominate both the flow of goods up the river and access to crops produced by village farmers. Although <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> consistently misconstrued the nature of the relationship between nomads and villagers, they at least sensed that trade and politics were closely joined along the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>. The captains were much less aware of the balance of power down the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>. Upper <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookans</name> such as the <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skilloots</name> did not have the military power possessed by the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name> bands, but they were willing to resort to force in order to protect their place as middlemen in the trade system. Just how far Indians from <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The Dalles</name> to the <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Cascades (Great Rapids, Great Shute)">Cascades</name> would go do defend their place in the network would be revealed in 1812 and 1814 when the fur traders Robert Stuart, Alexander Stuart, and James Keith fought pitched battles with the river Indians for passage on the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> never drew such a violent response from the river peoples; it is worth recalling that the only real trouble the expedition had while on the river was with the <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skilloots</name>, a people very protective of their role as traders.<ref target="n0715" n="15"/>
               </p>
               <p>
On October 22 the expedition came to <name type="place" key="Celilo (Great) Falls">Celilo Falls</name>, the first physical barrier on the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>. Long a major salmon-fishing place, the falls area was filled with lodges and fish-drying scaffolds. It was plain from the flood of water over the falls that a portage of the expedition's baggage had to be organized. That portage required native help and soon the explorers enlisted a number of <name type="native_nation" key="Tenino Indians">Teninos</name> for that duty. All the hurry to prepare for the portage, as well as the outlandish appearance of the Americans, drew a large crowd of Indian onlookers. <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> pointedly wrote, "The natives are very troublesome about our camp." The trouble <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> had in mind was petty theft. Any object laid aside for a moment was bound to vanish. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> recognized the problem and claimed that when the expedition established secure camps in the <name type="place" key="Celilo (Great) Falls">Celilo Falls</name>-<name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">Dalles</name> area the greatest concern was not Indian arrows but "the protection of our stores from theft."<ref target="n0716" n="16"/>
               </p>
               <p>
The issue of theft, which reached peak proportions during the trip along the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> between <name type="place" key="Celilo (Great) Falls">Celilo Falls</name> and the <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Cascades (Great Rapids, Great Shute)">Cascades</name>, troubled the explorers as it would later students of the expedition. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> found it a growing annoyance and eventually a drain on their diminishing supply of trade goods. On the return journey up the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> they openly threatened to fire on the thieves. In an unusual outburst of anger and frustration, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> struck a <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skilloot</name> Indian caught stealing during the return portage through <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The Dalles</name>. At one point the captains had to restrain some members of the expedition who seemed "well disposed to kill a few of them."<ref target="n0717" n="17"/>
               </p>
               <p>
What <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> saw as troublesome and potentially dangerous behavior was perceived by the river Indians rather differently. Taking axes, clothing, or rifling through the expedition's luggage probably involved two patterns of behavior not understood by the captains or their men. On one level, river people saw the things they took from the expedition as proper payment for services rendered. As the Indians viewed it, the explorers had more knives and blankets than they could possibly use. What harm could there be in taking a blanket, especially when the whites had so many and the Indians had provided valuable support in portaging around dangerous places in the river? But the issue was more complex. The river peoples had a strong sense of private property. They left stacks of valuable dried fish standing unguarded without thought of loss. In pilfering small objects from the Americans, they sought <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clarks'</name> acknowledgment of their importance. Taking an axe was done to remind the white men of the need to offer respect and attention to the trading lords of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>. As a recent student of <name type="native_nation" key="Wishram-Wasco Indians">Wishram and Wasco</name> life put it, "Thefts from whites would arise not from fundamental lawlessness or from defining whites as enemies but rather from a temporary dislocation of relations which might be remedied if pressure were applied, for example, through thefts or incidents. These [pressures] would serve to reestablish, not break, relationships."<ref target="n0718" n="18"/> Theft as a means of creating mutually rewarding reciprocal relations was a notion utterly foreign to the explorers. It made far more sense in their world to see river people as crafty traders and cunning thieves.</p>
               <p>
Throughout the day on October 23, members of the expedition struggled and sweated as they manhandled goods and canoes over the <name type="place" key="Celilo (Great) Falls">Celilo Falls</name> portage. That difficult task was made even more unpleasant by swarms of fleas infesting the dried grass and by fish skins littering the ground. Tortured by the fleas, many in the party stripped off their skin shirts and breeches in an effort to rid themselves of the biting pests. The portage lasted all day and eventually provided work for a few Indians and entertainment for more who watched the whole undertaking with a mixture of amusement and wonder.</p>
               <p>
Near the end of the day, the strain of the portage effort was broken by an alarming piece of news. One of the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> chiefs appeared at the expedition's camp and with signs claimed he had heard from Indians around the falls that "the nation below intended to kill us." When the Sahaptians who had crowded around the Americans all during the day left earlier than usual, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> thought the rumor was confirmed. To prepare for the expected attack, they carefully checked weapons and issued each man a sufficient number of rounds. With a bravado born of unfamiliar surroundings and some real fear, <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse</name> boasted, "We were not afraid of them for we think we can drive three times our number." The arms and ammunition may have reassured men like <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse</name>, but the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> chiefs remained visibly worried throughout the night.<ref target="n0719" n="19"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Although the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name>
                  <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> and <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> threats against the expedition had some real intention behind them, talk relayed thirdhand about the supposed plans of "the nation below" appears in retrospect to be less reliable. The Indians referred to as "the nation below" were certainly upper <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookans</name>, perhaps <name type="native_nation" key="Wishram-Wasco Indians">Wishrams</name> or <name type="native_nation" key="Cascade Indians">Cascades</name>. Those Indians and their neighbors did show considerable hostility toward fur traders whose activities challenged <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The Dalles</name> trade fair system. The rumor reveals not so much the planned actions of the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookans</name> around <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The Dalles</name> as the relations between the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perces</name>
                  </ref> and the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookans</name>. <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">Twisted Hair</name> and <name type="person" key="Tetoharsky">Tetoharsky</name> admitted to the captains on October 24 that they feared for their lives if they remained with the expedition once it passed <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The Dalles</name>. During trading times the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perces</name>
                  </ref> and <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookans</name> maintained the same sort of partnership as did the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Mandan.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>
                  </ref> and <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Assinniboine.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Assiniboine Indians">Assiniboins</name>
                  </ref>. But for most of the year there was considerably more tension and occasional raiding between the two peoples. The alleged preparations for an attack on <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> may have been rumormongering or an effort to justify the desire of the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> guides to leave the party.<ref target="n0720" n="20"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Whatever the cause of the alarm, the expedition's plans for combat did not go unnoticed; as the Americans ventured through the dangerous <name type="place" key="Short (Little) Narrows">Short</name> and <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">Long Narrows</name>, Indians approached them with much caution. Some <name type="native_nation" key="Tenino Indians">Eneeshur</name> Sahaptians who lived around the <name type="place" key="Short (Little) Narrows">Short Narrows</name> watched in amazement as <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> sent their canoes and best watermen to shoot the <name type="place" key="Short (Little) Narrows">Narrows</name>. As this daring venture in whitewater navigation was unfolding, <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">Twisted Hair</name> and Tetoharsky announced that they were ready to leave the expedition. The <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> interpreters correctly reported that <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The Dalles</name> was the boundary between Sahaptian and Chinookan speakers. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> recognized that the chiefs could do no interpreting past <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The Dalles</name>, but because they hoped to effect a peace treaty between the Sahaptians and the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookans</name>, they persuaded the chiefs to remain for two more days.</p>
               <p>
Once safely past the <name type="place" key="Short (Little) Narrows">Short Narrows</name> and into <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookan</name> territory, the expedition made camp near <name type="place" key="Nix-luidix village">Nixluidix</name>, the principal <name type="native_nation" key="Wishram-Wasco Indians">Wishram</name> village. Attracted by the large plank houses in the town, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> paid the <name type="native_nation" key="Wishram-Wasco Indians">Wishrams</name> a visit. He was welcomed warmly and invited into one of the houses. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> journal entry for the day contains a careful description of the house and details of its construction. But it remained for the practical carpenter <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Patrick Gass</name> to pronounce <name type="place" key="Nix-luidix Indians">Nixluidix</name> as a town filled with "tolerably comfortable houses."</p>
               <p>
Still bothered by flea bites and short of fuel for their fires, the explorers settled in at their <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">Dalles</name> camp. Later that evening an Indian whom <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> vaguely described as "the principal chief from the nation below" presented himself and several of his men at the American camp. It remains unclear who this chief was and what group he represented. Whoever he was, the explorer-diplomats seized on his arrival as an opportunity to promote one more of their intertribal peace schemes. The expedition's records do not reveal the course of the negotiations, but <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> clamed they had engineered lasting peace and friendship between the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perces</name>
                  </ref> and the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookans</name>. That claim had as much validity as did earlier optimistic reports of a <name type="native_nation" key="Missouri Indians">Missouri</name> villager alliance against the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name>
                  <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">Sioux</ref>. In both cases, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> simply did not understand the nature of tribal and band politics. But none of those unpleasant facts intruded on pleasant illusions. Medals and gifts heightened the illusion of lasting peace, and the evening slipped away to the sounds of dancing and of <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Pierre Cruzatte's</name> fiddle.<ref target="n0721" n="21"/>
               </p>
               <p>
With the hazards of <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The Dalles</name> behind them, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> continued their sweep down the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>. Reassured by the friendly <name type="place" key="Nix-luidix village">Nixluidix</name> reception and by an apparently successful piece of diplomacy, the explorers did not expect much Indian trouble beyond the now-familiar incidents of theft. But just as the physical and cultural landscape was persistently unsettling, so too did rumors of danger persist. No sooner had the boats gotten through the <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">Long Narrows</name> than the <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name> guides again began to talk about threats posed to the Americans by unnamed "nations below." But when <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> landed at a <name type="native_nation" key="Wishram-Wasco Indians">Wishram</name> village past the <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">Long Narrows</name>, they found no hostility but only a war chief and a number of warriors on their way to attack <name type="native_nation" key="Paiute Indians">Paiute</name> bands. When the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> chiefs finally left the expedition, each was given a medal. There was no sense of impending trouble as <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">Twisted Hair</name> and <name type="person" key="Tetoharsky">Tetoharsky</name> went back upriver.<ref target="n0722" n="22"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Without <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> guides and among people whose language was unknown to them, the Americans' safety now depended on the attitudes of the river people. At the same time, much rested on the ability of the captains to restrain a growing belligerence in the ranks directed against the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookans</name>. From October 25 to the first days of November, the explorers had almost daily contact with a large number of <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookans</name>. Those encounters usually involved stopping at villages to purchase dogs and dried fish to replenish the expedition's larder. Because these stops never lasted long and communication was very difficult, pursuit of the usual diplomatic and ethnographic goals proved nearly impossible. Nevertheless, the explorers did manage to distribute medals and gifts to a number of village leaders. Years later, during the complex Anglo-American negotiations surrounding the <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name> Question, those actions of the expedition were used to bolster United States claims to the Northwest. Despite language and time limitations, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> journal entries contain an amazing amount of information about the river peoples and their ways. Vivid descriptions of clothing, canoes, house construction, trade, and burial practices can be found in expeditionary records for this period. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> even found time to piece together laboriously several <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookan</name> vocabularies, although how this was accomplished without interpreters remains unclear. Throughout the last days of October and into November, relations between the explorers and the Indians remained peaceful. Accustomed to the presence of European goods and the indirect influence of white traders, most <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookans</name> were not startled by the Americans. Many enjoyed the fiddle music and dancing. <name type="person" key="York">York</name> remained the attraction he had always been. The days contained the usual trials of wilderness travel, but there was little expectation that the Indians on the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> would add to the trials.</p>
               <p>
Once the expedition passed <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The Dalles</name>, travel was rapid and relations with the river <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookans</name> were reasonably good. Although theft was an ever present irritation, the expedition's need for food and information made the captains unwilling to make good on the sorts of threats that would surface on the return journey. For their part, the river Indians viewed <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> as curiosities and potential trading partners, certainly not as a possible challenge to native domination in the region.</p>
               <p>
But much of that apparent good will evaporated on November 4 when the expedition encountered a large <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skilloot</name> village near the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Willamette (Multnomah) River">Willamette River</name>. The Chinookan-speaking <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skilloots</name> occupied both sides of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> between the <name type="place" key="Washougal (Seal) River">Washougal</name> and <name type="place" key="Cowlitz (Coweliskee) River">Cowlitz</name> rivers. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> met <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skilloot</name> traders all along the river and on the return journey found a <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skilloot</name> settlement as far east as <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The Dalles</name>. During the early days of November, as the explorers entered <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skilloot</name> territories—near present-day <name type="place" key="Portland, Oreg.">Portland</name>, <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>, and <name type="place" key="Vancouver, Wash.">Vancouver</name>, <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>—they noted an ever increasing stock of European goods. That supply of guns, swords, clothing, and assorted copper and brassware suggested the economic role of the <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skilloots</name>. Ranging from the coast to <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The Dalles</name>, they acted as secondary middlemen along the western arm of the Pacific-Plateau system.<ref target="n0723" n="23"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Landing at a large <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skilloot</name> village of twenty-five houses, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> were impressed by the many well-armed warriors as well as by the number of canoes drawn up in front of the settlement. Invited into one of the lodges by a <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skilloot</name> who had been hired earlier to pilot the expedition over this stretch of river, the captains enjoyed roasted wappato roots and apparent good company. After purchasing four bushels of wappato, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> party moved several more miles downriver, hoping to locate a suitable place for the noon meal. As the explorers prepared their usual river diet of dried fish, dog meat, and roots, several canoes of <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skilloots</name> appeared. Dressed in garb that was a colorful mixture of native dress and European clothing, the Indians seemed bent on a festival or council. Anxious to accommodate them, the captains promptly invited the <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skilloots</name> to join them. It would be the last time <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> ever allowed such a large number of heavily armed Indians into camp. What the explorers expected would be a friendly meeting soon turned unpleasant. For reasons that may have had something to do with a fear of losing their economic position to unknown newcomers, the <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skilloot</name> warriors became "assumeing and disagreeable." Adding injury to insult, one of the <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skilloots</name> managed to steal <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> prized ceremonial pipe tomahawk. As the captains searched the Indians and their canoes, another <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skilloot</name> made off with a capote belonging to either <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name> or <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name>. All this confusion and trouble added up to a thoroughly nasty afternoon. The expedition kept to the river for an hour after dark "with a view to get clear of the natives who [were] constantly about us, and troublesom." Now more than ever, the expedition looked upon the people of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> with a wary eye. As the explorers prepared to spend their last weeks on the river, they were in no mood to accept Indians as anything other than necessary trading partners.<ref target="n0724" n="24"/>
               </p>
               <p>
For several days after the unhappy <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skilloot</name> encounter, the explorers kept up their guard as they floated past <name type="native_nation" key="Mult-no-mah Indians">Multnomah</name>, <name type="native_nation" key="Cathlamet Indians">Kathlamet</name>, and <name type="native_nation" key="Wahkiakum Indians">Wahkiakum</name> villages. As with other river <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookans</name>, contacts with these villagers were brief and usually for trade in food stores. Now and again there was time for some ethnographic observations, as when <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> wrote an especially detailed description of <name type="native_nation" key="Wahkiakum Indians">Wahkiakum</name> houses. But what continued to occupy <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> attention was the sizable number of European objects held by river people. In fact, European influence now went beyond material goods and could be heard in the language. It is not clear when <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> first heard the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinook</name> trade jargon. English words and curse phrases were noted among the <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skilloots</name> and their neighbors early in November. The explorers also heard about the English trader, Mr. Haley. And it was on November 7 that <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark</name> wrote his memorable phrase "Ocian in view O! the joy." Although the ocean proper was not quite yet in view, all attention was now focused on reaching the coast and finding winter quarters as quickly as possible.<ref target="n0725" n="25"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Information from the river Indians led <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> to believe that there were permanent trade establishments along the coast. Hoping to find traders and locate a suitable place for wintering over, the captains attempted to quicken the pace of travel. Thwarted by the rolling currents of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> and the steadily deteriorating weather, they found themselves stalled at <name type="place" key="Grays Point (Cape Swells)">Gray's Point</name> in <name type="place" key="Grays (Shallow) Bay">Gray's Bay</name>. From November 10 to November 15, the expedition camped on the east side of <name type="place" key="Point Ellice (Point Distress)">Point Ellice</name>. Those were miserable, wet days that dampened spirits and rotted clothing already in tatters. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> summed up the misery everyone felt when he wrote, "We are all wet as usual—and our Situation is Truly a disagreeable one; and our selves and party Scattered on floating logs and Such dry Spots as can be found on the hill sides and crivicies of the rocks."<ref target="n0726" n="26"/> Borrowing from native practice, the explorers made hasty shelters from poles and mat. Later those temporary lean-tos gave way to huts made from boards scavenged from an abandoned <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinook</name> village. Getting their first taste of a coastal winter, the whole expedition may well have started to feel nostalgic for the cold but bracing days on the northern plains.</p>
               <p>
On November 15, after reconnoitering by <name type="person" key="Colter, John">John Colter</name> and other members of the expedition, the Americans moved down the coast four miles to a sandy beach just below <name type="place" key="Chinook Point">Chinook Point</name>. Here, at an abandoned <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinook</name> village, they spent the next nine days until November 24. With the weather now clearing, they could see <name type="place" key="Point Adams">Point Adams</name> and <name type="place" key="Cape Disappointment">Cape Disappointment</name>. There in front of the weary explorers were the rollers of the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>—the goal <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had once described as "this great <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific Octean</name> which we been so long anxious to see."<ref target="n0727" n="27"/> The days spent at the <name type="place" key="Chinook Point">Chinook Point</name> camp were filled with visits from many neighboring <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinooks</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsops</name>. Although the explorers allowed only small numbers of Indians into camp and treated all natives "with great distance," there was a chance to meet <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinook</name> chiefs like <name type="person" key="Comcomly">Comcomly</name> and <name type="person" key="Shelathwell">Chillarlawil</name>. Besides trade in fish, there were the more personal exchanges between the men in the expedition and the young women offered by <name type="person" key="Delashelwilt">Delashelwilt's</name> wife.</p>
               <p>
The camp at <name type="place" key="Chinook Point">Chinook Point</name> provided a temporary respite from the demands of constant travel. But the need to find a reliable food supply and a sheltered place for winter quarters required the expedition to move once again. The Indians told <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> that lands along the south side of the river offered the best game and roots. After taking a vote on November 24, the expedition moved back upriver and crossed over to the south side of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>. Early in December, following a search by a small party under <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> command, the site for <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name> was selected. Surrounded by marshes and towering fir trees, and invaded by a pervasive dampness, the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> expedition prepared to spend a second winter in the land of <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name> imagination.</p>
               <p>
Indian visitors to the rain-soaked camps at <name type="place" key="Point Ellice (Point Distress)">Point Ellice</name> and <name type="place" key="Chinook Point">Chinook Point</name> could not have missed the tough talk and threats. The <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinooks</name>, <name type="native_nation" key="Cathlamet Indians">Kathlamets</name>, and <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsops</name> were repeatedly warned that any false moves would be met with maximum force by the expedition. Sentries were ordered to fire on Indians suspected of theft if it appeared that firearms were being taken. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> claimed that all these threats and verbal onslaughts produced the desired result. "We find the Indians easy ruled and kept in order by stricter indifference towards them." Symbolic of all that suspicion was the password "no <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinook</name>" already in use by men of the expedition even before the construction of <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name>.<ref target="n0728" n="28"/>
               </p>
               <p>
The ill-concealed tensions between the expedition and coastal Indians was the legacy of experiences and misunderstandings on the journey down the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>. After the nasty encounter with the <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skilloots</name>, the explorers began to build a negative image of river and coastal peoples that colored relations throughout the winter. That powerful image was a composite of several related attitudes about Pacific Northwest people and their lifeways. A principal element was the perception of <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookan</name> peoples as incorrigible thieves. The theft of expedition goods and the fear of losing weapons was behind much of the provocative language directed at the Indians. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> would have found substantial agreement in his ranks when he branded the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookans</name> as "thievishly inclined."<ref target="n0729" n="29"/>
               </p>
               <p>
But it was more than a belief in their criminality that led the explorers to view their Indian neighbors with suspicion and sometimes open hostility. During the days at <name type="place" key="Point Ellice (Point Distress)">Point Ellice</name> and <name type="place" key="Chinook Point">Chinook Point</name>, the expedition often depended on nearby Indians for food. The <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinooks</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsops</name>, accustomed to hard bargaining with whites in the sea otter trade, expected to drive equally hard bargains with the hungry explorers. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> clearly resented paying "immoderate prices" for essential foodstuffs. When some <name type="native_nation" key="Cathlamet Indians">Kathlamets</name> came offering roots, skins, and woven mats, "they asked such high prices that we were unable to purchase anything of them."<ref target="n0730" n="30"/> What Indians saw as simply good business and the Yankee law of supply and demand looked quite different to hungry and wet Americans. The <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookans</name>, so it appeared to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, were not only thieves but sharp traders bent on gouging the needy. There was no trace of admiration in <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> voice when he declared that the <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsops</name> were "great higlers in trade and if they conceive you anxious to purchase [they] will be a whole day bargaining for a handfull of roots." It did not take many days of fruitless trading for green fish and roots in a pouring rain to convince the explorers that coastal Indians were possessed of an "avarcious all grasping disposition."<ref target="n0731" n="31"/>
               </p>
               <p>
To the image of thievish and grasping Indians <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> added a third element. They found many <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookan</name> customs and practices both incomprehensible and reprehensible. Although the expedition always viewed Indian life through the filter of its own Euro-American values, there were native ways, especially on the northern plains, that the explorers found praiseworthy. No such praise was offered to coastal peoples. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> repeatedly described the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookans</name> as dirty, poorly clad people who engaged in such barbarous customs as head flattening and ankle binding. Coastal sexual practices also came in for much pointed comment. During the <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name> winter, sexual relations between village women and men in the expedition had been commonplace. Although concerned about the spread of veneral complaints in the ranks, the captains had been muted in their criticism of those Indian women. There was no such reluctance to vilify the coastal women. From the time of the first sexual encounters with <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinook</name> women in November, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> blasted them as promiscuous sellers of their own bodies for trinkets and bits of ribbon.<ref target="n0732" n="32"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Finally, and perhaps most important, there was the matter of the physical appearance of coastal Indians. Every culture promotes its own image of an attractive body. The Indians of the northern plains came quite close to the somatic norm held by the explorers. But the Indians <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> found on the lower <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> and on the coast did not fit the Euro-American image. Shorter in stature and possessing facial features quite unlike those of the plains natives, the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookans</name> appeared to the explorers as "low and ill-shaped." The fact that these Indians were superb canoe navigators, masterful traders, and skillful fishermen was often overlooked as the expedition stressed what it saw as the negative aspects of a "badly clad and illy made" people.<ref target="n0733" n="33"/>
               </p>
               <p>
In many ways, reaching the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Great Western Sea</name> was an anticlimax. Certainly all members of the expedition were exhilarated by the sight of the ocean. There was a sense of achievement in knowing that they had passed the tests of a hazardous land. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> own enthusiasm emerged when, taking a cue from <name type="person" key="Mackenzie, Alexander">Alexander Mackenzie</name>, he carved on a big pine tree: "<name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark</name> December 3rd 1805. By land from the U. States in 1804 &amp; 1805." As <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> recalled, his men appeared" much Satisfied with their trip beholding with estonishment the high waves dashing against the rocks &amp; this emence Ocian."<ref target="n0734" n="34"/> But those feelings of excitement and accomplishment were tempered by relations with new neighbors that were already less than cordial. Throughout November, as the explorers suffered in the rain and cold, they were increasingly willing to use threats against the <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookans</name>. Given their experiences with other river bands and the constant problem of theft, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> surely felt justified in telling the Indians that they would be summarily shot if caught stealing guns or other weapons. Short on provisions and confronted by native traders who demanded high prices for their goods, the explorers felt trapped. Resorting to threats satisfied their desire to be in control of a difficult situation, but it spread fear and suspicion among the very people the Americans needed as winter allies and friends. Hemmed in by an inhospitable climate, an uncertain and monotonous food supply, and a language foreign to all expedition ears, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> faced a winter whose hazards were no less real than they had been at <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name>. Whether their Indian neighbors would exacerbate those dangers was still unknown.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="section">
            <head rend="center">Abbreviations</head>
            <p>
B A E       Bureau of American Ethnology</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">Field Notes.</hi>        Osgood, Ernest, S., ed. <hi rend="italic">The Field Notes of <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain William Clark</name>, 1803–1805.</hi> New Haven: Yale University Press, 1964.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal.</hi>        <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass, Patrick</name>. <hi rend="italic">A Journal of the Voyages and Travels of a Corps of Discovery.</hi> Edited by <name type="person" key="McKeehan, David">David McKeehan</name>. 1807. Reprint, with preface by Earle R. Forrest. Minneapolis: Ross and Haines, 1958.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal.</hi>        Quaife, Milo M., ed. <hi rend="italic">The Journals of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Meriwether Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Sergeant John Ordway</name>.</hi> Madison: Historical Society of Wisconsin, 1916.</p>
            <p>
Thw.       Thwaites, Reuben G., ed. <hi rend="italic">The Original Journals of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition.</hi> 8 vols. New York: Dodd, Mead &amp; Co., 1904–1905.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal.</hi>        "The Journal of <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Private Joseph Whitehouse</name>." In Thw. 7:29–190.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="notes" type="notes">
            <head rend="center">Notes</head>
            <note xml:id="n0701" n="1">Thw. 3:159.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0702" n="2">Donald W. Meinig, <hi rend="italic">The <name type="place" key="Great Columbian Plain">Great Columbia Plain</name>: A Historical Geography, 1805–1910</hi> (Seattle: University of Washington Press, 1968), pp. 3–20.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0703" n="3">Thw. 3:113–16.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0704" n="4">Ibid. 3:109.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0705" n="5">Verne F. Ray, "Native Villages and Groupings of the <name type="place" key="Columbia Basin">Columbia Basin</name>," <hi rend="italic">Pacific Northwest Quarterly</hi> 27 (1936):119; Robert H. Ruby and John A. Brown, <hi rend="italic">Indians of the Pacific Northwest: A History</hi> (Norman: University of Oklahoma Press, 1981), p. 17; Thw. 3:116.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0706" n="6">
               <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> p. 181; <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> p. 299; Thw. 3:119–20.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0707" n="7">Thw. 3:124–27. Photographs of mat houses can be found in Ruby and Brown, <hi rend="italic">Indians of the Pacific Northwest,</hi> p. 18.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0708" n="8">
               <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> p. 182; Thw. 3:128–32; <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> p. 175.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0709" n="9">Thomas R. Garth, "Early Nineteenth Century Tribal Relations in the <name type="place" key="Columbia Plateau">Columbia Plateau</name>," <hi rend="italic">Southwestern Journal of Anthropology</hi> 20 (1964):45–48; Glover, ed., <hi rend="italic">Thompson's Narrative,</hi> pp. 350–51; Thw. 3:134–35. Because the <name type="native_nation" key="Walula Indians">Walulas</name> were dependent on <name type="native_nation" key="Cayuse Indians">Cayuse</name> traders for their manufactured goods, it is possible that <name type="person" key="Yelleppit">Yelleppit</name> was searching for a source of supply that would make his people less dependent on the <name type="native_nation" key="Cayuse Indians">Cayuses</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0710" n="10">"<name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name> Notes," 2:529; Thw. 3:136–37.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0711" n="11">
               <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> p. 301; Thw. 3:145.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0712" n="12">
               <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> p. 183; Thw. 3:138, 140.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0713" n="13">"<name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name> Notes," 2:527.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0714" n="14">
               <name type="person" key="Ross, Alexander">Alexander Ross</name>, <hi rend="italic">Adventures of the First Settlers on the <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name> or <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia River</name>,</hi> ed. Milo M. Quaife (1849; reprint, Chicago: The Lakeside Press, 1923), pp. 127–28.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0715" n="15">
               <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>-Coues, <hi rend="italic">History,</hi> 2:785–90; "<name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name> Notes," 2:499–500; <name type="person" key="Ross, Alexander">Ross</name>, <hi rend="italic">Adventures on the <name type="place" key="Oregon">Oregon</name>,</hi> pp. 127–29; Thw. 4:289. For recent studies see David French, "<name type="native_nation" key="Wishram-Wasco Indians">Wasco-Wishram</name>," Spicer, ed., <hi rend="italic">Perspectives in American Indian Culture Change,</hi> pp. 343–52; Leslie Spier and Edward Sapir, <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Wishram-Wasco Indians">Wishram</name> Ethnography,</hi> University of Washington Publications in Anthropology, vol. 3 (Seattle, 1930), pp. 224–28; Wood, "Contrastive Features," pp. 153–66.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0716" n="16">
               <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> p. 302; Thw. 3:148.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0717" n="17">Ibid. 4:267–69, 302–9.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0718" n="18">French, "<name type="native_nation" key="Wishram-Wasco Indians">Wasco-Wishram</name>," pp. 352–53.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0719" n="19">
               <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> p. 303; Thw. 3:150–51. <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> p. 179.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0720" n="20">Garth, "Tribal Relations," pp. 51–55.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0721" n="21">
               <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> p. 186; <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> p. 180. For additional information on the <name type="place" key="Nix-luidix village">Nixluidix</name> site, see W. Duncan Strong, <hi rend="italic">Archaeology of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">Dalles</name>-<name type="place" key="Deschutes (Clark's, Towanahiook's) River">Deschutes</name> Region,</hi> University of California Publications in American Archaeology and Ethnology, vol. 29 (Berkeley, 1930), pp. 1–16. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> detailed map of Indian villages in <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The Dalles</name> region is in Thw. 3:158.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0722" n="22">
               <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> p. 187; <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> p. 304; Thw. 3: 158.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0723" n="23">Joel V. Berreman, <hi rend="italic">Tribal Distributions in Oregon,</hi> Memoirs of the American Anthropological Association, vol. 47 (Menasha, Wisconsin, 1937), p. 16; Thw. 6:117.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0724" n="24">Ibid. 3:197–98.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0725" n="25">
               <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> p. 308; Thw. 3:205, 207.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0726" n="26">Thw. 3:216.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0727" n="27">Ibid. 3:210.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0728" n="28">"<name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name> Notes," 2:541; Thw. 3:224–26, 243–44.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0729" n="29">Ibid. 3:199.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0730" n="30">Ibid. 3:253. See also 3:186, 244–45, 251.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0731" n="31">Ibid. 3:311.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0732" n="32">Ibid. 3:186, 239.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0733" n="33">Ibid. 3:209, 217.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0734" n="34">Ibid. 3:234.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.ronda.01.06" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.ronda.01.00" type="contents"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.ronda.01.08" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
