<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.sup.ronda.01.09">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> among the Indians</title>
            <title type="sub" level="a">9. The Way Home</title>
            <title type="sub"/>
            <author>James P. Ronda</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2005</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>jfaust2@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title level="m" type="main">
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> &amp; <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> among the Indians</title>
               <title level="m" type="sub">9. The Way Home</title>
               <author>James P. Ronda</author>
               <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Lincoln and London</pubPlace>
               <date>1984</date>
               <idno type="ISBN">0-8032-8990-1</idno>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Supplements</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Texts</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-11-01</date>
            <date>2005-02-01</date>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>
            <name>Laura Weakly</name>File splitting Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="ch9" type="chapter" n="9">
            <quote>
               <lg type="linegroup">
                  <l>"Last evening the indians entertained us with seting the fir trees on fire. They have</l>
                  <l>a great number of dry lims near their bodies which when set on fire creates a very</l>
                  <l>suddon and immence blaze from bottom to top of those tall trees. They are a</l>
                  <l>beatifull object in this situation at night. This exhibition reminded me of a display</l>
                  <l>of fireworks. The natives told us that their object in seting those trees on fire was</l>
                  <l>to bring fair weather for our journey."</l>
               </lg>
               <bibl>—<name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name>, 1806</bibl>
            </quote>
            <div type="section">
               <p>
When <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> left <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name> late in March 1806, their exploring duties were far from over. Ahead loomed responsibilities every bit as challenging as those that had driven the explorers up the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> and across the mountains nearly two years before. During the winter, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had heard from Indian sources about a river that struck south from the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> and reached the "<name type="place" key="Gulf of California">gulph of California</name>." Finding that river, known to both Indians and explorers as the <name type="native_nation" key="Willamette (Multnomah) River">Multinomah</name>, raised the expedition's hopes for a trade connection into the Southwest. Equally important were charting the northern course of the <name type="place" key="Marias River">Marias River</name> and exploring the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone</name>. Finally, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> needed to verify Indian information concerning a shorter route between <name type="place" key="Lolo (Travelers' Rest) Creek (Mont.)">Travelers' Rest</name> and the <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Great Falls of the">Great Falls</name> of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>. All that exploring would demand skill and coordination in field operations beyond anything yet attempted by the Corps of Discovery.</p>
               <p>
But in all these intricate maneuvers, Indian matters were not forgotten. Promoting and encouraging intertribal peace as a requisite for trade was a goal from the earliest days of the journey. On the return, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> needed to foster such notions, often in the face of long-standing tradition. Equally important was the complex matter of organizing delegations of Indians to visit federal officials in <name type="place" key="Washington D.C.">Washington</name>. Like intertribal peace, this accomplishment hinged on neutralizing "the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> menace." Finally, there were ethnographic tasks yet undone. In their hurry to reach the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had not carefully studied the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> people. Time spent with those Indians would allow the American ethnographers to record aspects of their life and culture.</p>
               <p>
Speed, timing, and survival were essential for success in all these efforts. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> were determined to reach <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> in one season of travel, with careful planning and good fortune. The explorers had to work their way back up a floodstage <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> even more hazardous than before, avoid Indian complications at the <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Cascades (Great Rapids, Great Shute)">Cascades</name> and <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The Dalles</name>, and reach their horses at the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> villages before those Indians left for summer hunts. Delays caused by snow on the <name type="place" key="Lolo Trail">Lolo Trail</name> could throw their schedules seriously off track. Finally, and no small matter, several field parties had to be coordinated to reach the Upper <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> before freeze-up. All told, the return journey presented challenges and opportunities as great as any the expedition had yet faced.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>
The cold, wet days of spring on the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> did nothing to boost the men's spirits as they struggled back upriver. And struggle they did, since the river ran higher and faster than in the fall of 1805. Although <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> found friendly treatment at several <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookan</name> villages along the lower <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>, there were already unsettling signs. The expedition was intent on finding the <name type="place" key="Willamette (Multnomah) River">Multnomah River</name>, but information from the Indians on the short, shallow character of the <name type="place" key="Quicksand (Sandy) River">Quicksand (Sandy)</name> and <name type="place" key="Washougal (Seal) River">Seal (Washougal)</name> rivers was troubling. A brief reconnaissance of those rivers by <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Sergeant Pryor</name> verified those disappointing reports.</p>
               <p>
But that disappointment could not match the real concern produced by news from Indians coming downriver from <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The Dalles</name>. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had expected to supplement the expedition's food stores with pounded salmon purchased from <name type="native_nation" key="Wishram-Wasco Indians">Wishram and Wasco</name> traders. Now that plan was in doubt as party after party told of scarcities of food and even starvation upriver. "This information," said <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> with considerable understatement, "gave us much uneasiness with rispect to our future means of subsistence." Quickly rejecting a time-consuming wait at <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The Dalles</name> for the first salmon run, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> decided to remain at their camp on the north side of the river while laying in a supply of dried meat sufficient for the journey to the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perces</name>
                  </ref>. Such a halt would also afford <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> time to extend his search for the elusive <name type="place" key="Willamette (Multnomah) River">Multnomah River</name>.<ref target="n0901" n="01"/>
               </p>
               <p>
On April 2, with expeditionary hunters out on resupply missions, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> resumed his quest for the <name type="place" key="Willamette (Multnomah) River">Multnomah</name>. That effort was materially advanced when several <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Watlala Indians</name> came to camp to trade. With them were two young men from one of the bands living on the <name type="place" key="Willamette (Multnomah) River">Willamette</name>, the river <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> would eventually select as his <name type="place" key="Willamette (Multnomah) River">Multnomah</name>. From these men he obtained a sketch of the river and directions to find its mouth. Convinced this was the true object of his search, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> hired an Indian pilot and took seven men to reconnoiter the <name type="place" key="Willamette (Multnomah) River">Willamette</name>. Before reaching the entrance of the river, blocked from earlier view by <name type="place" key="Sauvie (Wapato) Island">Sauvies Island</name>, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> landed at the large <name type="place" key="Ne-er-cho-ki-oo village">Neerchekioo village</name>. As was so often the case with <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> ethnography, it is not clear whether this name refers to a location, a village, or a band. The captains further confused things by describing town residents as the <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Neerchkioo</name> tribe of the <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Shahhala (Watlala)</name> nation. The village site was dominated by a large plank house, with more than one hundred cutwater canoes "piled up and scattered in different directions about in the woods."</p>
               <p>
Exploring the <name type="place" key="Willamette (Multnomah) River">Willamette</name> was <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> principal objective, but seeing so imposing a plank house piqued his curiosity. That there might be some wappato for exchange could not have been far from his mind as well. Plank houses of this size were usually partitioned into several "apartments." <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> entered one of the rooms and offered goods in trade for wappato. He met stony silence, "sulkey" faces, and a firm rejection of his offer. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> mood is hard to guess. What he did next may have been practical joking or the reflection of more hostile feelings. Taking a piece of cannon fuse from his pocket, the explorer tossed it into the fire. As the fuse sputtered and the fire changed color, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> used a magnet on his inkstand to make a compass needle spin around the rose. "Astonished and alarmed," the Indian women pleaded for him to restore their "healthy" fire. They hastily put several parcels of wappato at his feet. Throughout this display of technological wizardry, an old blind shaman had been "speaking with great vehemunce," calling on spirit forces to protect the village. The drama ended when <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> belatedly paid the women for the wappato.<ref target="n0902" n="02"/>
               </p>
               <p>
For all its color and comic overtones, this incident at <name type="place" key="Ne-er-cho-ki-oo village">Neerchekioo</name> does have a grimmer side. In light of the canoe-stealing episode in the last days at <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name>, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> actions in the plank house suggest an increasing willingness to bend the rules whenever it suited the expedition's needs. Frightening and intimidating women and an elderly blind man did little to enhance the honor or the reputation of men who had set a high standard of conduct for themselves and others.</p>
               <p>
By the second week of April, the expedition had moved farther up the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> and was now in position for its first major river challenge—the <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Cascades (Great Rapids, Great Shute)">Cascades</name> portage. That long and difficult carry was more than a dangerous trek around boiling rapids. As <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> knew, the <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Watlala Indians</name> of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Cascades (Great Rapids, Great Shute)">Cascades</name> resented the presence of any outsiders who even appeared to threaten their control at this place on the river trade system. Harrassment, hostility, and petty theft were all part of the toll <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Cascades (Great Rapids, Great Shute)">Cascades</name> folk extracted from all travelers. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> were not exempt from that tariff. As the Americans labored up the north shore, against swift current and over high boulders, they met Indians increasingly "sulky and illy disposed." Everything pointed to a portage physically taxing and emotionally trying. One false step could mean canoes and goods irretrievably lost; an overreaction to Indian provocation could have fatal results.<ref target="n0903" n="03"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Friday, April 11, proved the crucial day for the <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Cascades (Great Rapids, Great Shute)">Cascades</name> portage. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> was in charge of the actual portaging operation while <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> remained at a base camp at the lower end of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Cascades (Great Rapids, Great Shute)">Cascades</name>. The captains elected to guide empty canoes through the rapids by means of ropes from the shore. Goods had to be transported over a narrow, rough, and slippery path nearly three thousand yards long. Even without Indian troubles, it was a demanding and nerve-racking task. No sooner had the portage begun than the <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Watlalas</name> commenced their delaying tactics. So many Indians crowded around the base camp that several extra men had to be assigned to guard duty. The harrassment increased when one particularly bold Indian began throwing stones down on two men in the portage party. <name type="person" key="Shields, John">John Shields</name>, who had taken some extra time at the head of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Cascades (Great Rapids, Great Shute)">Cascades</name> to buy a dog, suddenly found himself the object of the <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Watlalas'</name> attention. When several Indians attempted to take his future meal and push him off the portage path, <name type="person" key="Shields, John">Shields</name> drew his knife in readiness for something more than a polite scuffle. Seeing his determined resistence, the native highwaymen fled. Even <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> did not escape his share of trouble. Three <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Watlalas</name> slipped into his camp at dusk, and before he could stop them, they had absconded with the dog <name type="person" key="Seaman">Scannon</name>. Absolutely furious, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> ordered three men to give chase and use all necessary force to rescue <name type="person" key="Seaman">Scannon</name>. Gunplay was fortunately avoided as the Indians released the dog when they saw armed explorers in hot pursuit. Not even the reassurances of a <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Watlala</name> chief that these were the unsanctioned exploits of "two very bad men" and "not the wish of the nation" could mollify the Americans. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> ordered the sentries to shoot any Indian who dared steal the expedition's property. The <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Watlalas</name> may have seen this all as a baiting game, but an edgy <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> did not share that view. "I am convinced," he wrote, betraying both worry and belligerence, "that no other consideration but our number at this moment protects us."<ref target="n0904" n="04"/>
               </p>
               <p>
The following day there was less tension with <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Cascades (Great Rapids, Great Shute)">Cascades</name> natives. Guards armed with short rifles perhaps convinced them that their toll price was simply too high. But the rapids demanded its own fee as one American craft was caught in the current, slammed against a large rock, and sank. At the end of another cold, rainy day the expedition had passed the <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Cascades (Great Rapids, Great Shute)">Cascades</name>. Considering his anger earlier in the day, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> completed the portage quietly, taking a <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Watlala</name> vocabulary and carefully noting some of the differences between upper and lower <name type="native_nation" key="Chinook Indians">Chinookan</name> dialects.<ref target="n0905" n="05"/>
               </p>
               <p>
In many ways the <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Cascades (Great Rapids, Great Shute)">Cascades</name> portage was a dress rehearsal for the tensions and troubles that lay ahead at <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The Dalles</name>. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> knew from their westward journey that Indians at <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The Dalles</name> might prove difficult. When last at the <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">Narrows</name>, the expedition had attracted relatively few curious Indians. Now in mid-April, with the first salmon run not far off, <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The Dalles</name> was crowded with people. On April 15, after establishing <name type="place" key="Fort Rock Camp (Oreg.)">Rock Fort Camp</name> at the lower end of <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">Long Narrows</name>, the explorers settled in to pursue portage and trade duties. Convinced that an overland route to the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> villages would save considerable time, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> prepared to do some horse swapping. To speed that trade, it was decided that <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> would set up a temporary trading post on the north side of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> would remain to oversee packing and portaging operations from <name type="place" key="Fort Rock Camp (Oreg.)">Rock Fort Camp</name>.<ref target="n0906" n="06"/>
               </p>
               <p>
With those decisions made, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> took <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name>, <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name>, and nine other men across to the north shore. Horse trading had never been one of the expedition's strengths. Despite the fact that the frontiersmen knew good horseflesh when they saw it, they were usually at the mercy of native sellers who could set price and supply at will. The Indians who watched <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> party make camp showed little or no interest in trade. Concerned at how poorly business was faring, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> detailed <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name> and <name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">Frazer</name> to visit the <name type="native_nation" key="Wishram-Wasco Indians">Chilluckquittequaw</name> village while <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name> and <name type="person" key="Goodrich, Silas">Goodrich</name> went to the <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skilloots</name> to drum up business.<ref target="n0907" n="07"/> These ventures produced scant results. Only <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name> returned with any prospects, bringing a lame <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skilloot</name> chief who promised some trade. The chief's presence produced a few nibbles at <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> merchandise, but the high price placed on horses made setting the hook nearly impossible. Faced with discouraging news, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> cautiously accepted the <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skilloot</name> chief's invitation to visit his village. That night <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> party was at the <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skilloot</name> camp. The explorers may have been pleased by the sight of so many fine horses. The whine of <name type="person" key="Cruzatte, Pierre">Cruzatte's</name> fiddle and the stomp of dancing feet perhaps fostered hopes that <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The Dalles</name> passage might not be so trying after all. But <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> experienced other and less favorable omens that night: he was bitten and chewed by "the mice and vermin with which this house abounded."<ref target="n0908" n="08"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Anticipation overcame the weariness of a restless night, and the next morning <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> eagerly laid out his goods on a nearby rock. They had been carefully packaged into individual parcels, one bundle offered for each horse. But his best efforts at creative merchandising went awry. Making and then promptly breaking agreements, the Indians "tenterlised" a frustrated <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark</name>. By the end of the day, he was worn out and ready to quit the <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skilloots</name>. Only word that more horses might be brought in convinced him to stay another day. And there was a second and more heartening piece of news. As the <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skilloot</name> trade languished during the afternoon, a chief and twenty people from the Sahaptian-speaking <name type="native_nation" key="Tenino Indians">Eneeshur</name> village appeared and promised good horses at low prices. For a man who had struggled all day to buy three horses, of which only one was a fit animal, the <name type="native_nation" key="Tenino Indians">Eneeshurs'</name> word was indeed welcome. Encouraged or not, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> was willing to stay at the <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skilloot</name> village one more day in the hope that the winds of trade might shift.<ref target="n0909" n="09"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Horse trading on April 18 proved no better than on earlier days. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had pinned his hopes on the <name type="native_nation" key="Tenino Indians">Eneeshurs</name> now that <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skilloot</name> sellers persisted in demanding high prices. Those hopes received a sharp check early in the day when an <name type="native_nation" key="Tenino Indians">Eneeshur</name> party arrived and, to <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> great "estonishment," announced that all trade understandings were off. Not about to give up, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> fell back on his doctoring talents to change the market climate. He offered salve for the chief's sores, gave "some small things" to his children, and ministered camphor and warm flannel to the ailing back of the "sulky Bitch" who was the chief's wife. Just as medical skills had proved a powerful force in dealing with other Indians, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> found the <name type="native_nation" key="Tenino Indians">Eneershurs'</name> sales resistance lessening. But only two more horses were forthcoming. At prices double what <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Shoshoni.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name>
                  </ref> and <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Flathead.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Flathead</name>
                  </ref> traders had asked, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> must have wondered if the expedition's corral would ever hold enough horses for the journey to the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perces</name>
                  </ref>. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had not slept in two days; when he collapsed in exhaustion at <name type="place" key="Fort Rock Camp (Oreg.)">Rock Fort Camp</name>, his timetables were falling steadily behind.<ref target="n0910" n="10"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Throughout the next three days, expedition hands labored to drive packhorses and haul goods over <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The Dalles</name> portage. Although that effort moved slowly, it was at least successful. The same could not be said for the continuing effort to swell the horse herd. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> moved his trading post to the <name type="native_nation" key="Tenino Indians">Eneeshur</name> village above the <name type="place" key="Short (Little) Narrows">Short Narrows</name> and admitted that he used "every artifice decent and even false statements to enduce those pore devils to sell me horses." He unsuccessfully offered for each horse the full range of remaining trade items, including blankets, face paint, ribbon, beads, and brass. For a sweetener, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> threw in his own large blue blanket, military coat, sword, and hat plume. All of that was to no avail because the canny <name type="native_nation" key="Tenino Indians">Eneeshurs</name> demanded cooking kettles for horses. In an outburst that revealed mounting frustration and worry, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> bitterly described the people of <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The Dalles</name> as "poor, dirty, proud, haughty, inhospitable, parsimonious, and faithless in every rispect."<ref target="n0911" n="11"/>
               </p>
               <p>
As incidents of petty theft and harrassment increased, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> struggled to escape the grip of <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The Dalles</name>. The last two days at the <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">Narrows</name>, April 21 and 22, held more unpleasantness with Indians than any comparable time in the history of the expedition. Determined to deny the Indians even castoff items, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> ordered canoes, poles, and paddles burned. When <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> spotted an Indian taking one of the iron sockets from a canoe pole, the captain dealt him several blows and ordered the offender kicked out of camp. All the pent-up rage bred by days of trouble boiled over. "I now informed the Indians that I would shoot the first of them that attempted to steal an article from us; that we were not afraid to fight them, that I had it in my power at that moment to kill them all and set fire to their houses, but it was not my wish to treat them with severity provided they would let my property alone. That I would take their horses if I could find out the persons who had stolen the tommahawks but that I had rather lose the property altogether than take the horse of an innocent person." Just how much of this speech was understood is not clear. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> exercise in spleen was perhaps more an index of the expedition's anxiety over homeward schedules than an overeager desire to burn and kill Indians. Punching one thief and shouting some ill-considered threats was not especially noble behavior, but there was sufficient provocation and confusion on both sides to make <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> words and deeds at least understandable.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> fared no better. Stuck at the <name type="native_nation" key="Tenino Indians">Eneeshur</name> village until <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> main party came up, he was surrounded by Indians who showed little regard for either his mission or his comfort. The captain's day was miserable as the <name type="native_nation" key="Tenino Indians">Eneeshurs</name> crowded around him, demanded tobacco, and made uncharitable remarks about his person. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> sole achievement was a chance meeting with a <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> man who lent him a horse and promised to guide the party on their overland route to the <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Clearwater River</name>.<ref target="n0912" n="12"/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> could not break free from <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The Dalles</name> without one last incident. On April 22, as the expedition prepared to leave its camp at the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Deschutes (Clark's, Towanahiook's) River">Deschutes River</name> and begin an overland trek, <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name> was caught in a final entanglement. The Frenchman's horse bolted, threw its rider, and ran off toward one of <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The Dalles</name> villages. As the horse neared the village, <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau's</name> saddle and pad slid from the animal's back. The pad was evidently picked up by an Indian who then denied having it. This seemed the final insult, and <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> quickly renewed his promise to put the torch to nearby mat lodges unless the robe was returned. On the ragged edge of exasperation and fatigue, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> declared, "They have vexed me in such a manner by such repeated acts of villany that I am quite disposed to treat them with every severyty, their defenseless state pleads forgiveness so far as respects their lives."<ref target="n0913" n="13"/> But once again the storm blew over and the captain's rhetoric was not translated into reality.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>
Finally beyond the reach of <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The Dalles</name>, the expedition marched along the north side of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> through rocky, sandy country. Guided by the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> who had earlier offered his services to <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> and aided by the presence of an additional <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> family, the expedition headed toward the <name type="native_nation" key="Walula Indians">Walulas</name> and their friendly chief <name type="person" key="Yelleppit">Yelleppit</name>. Progress was slowed by too few packhorses and, inevitably, the travelers' sore feet and twisted ankles. Such now-familiar hazards were soothed when they reached the camps of the convivial <name type="native_nation" key="Klickitat Indians">Klikitats</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Yakima Indians">Pishquitpahs</name>.<ref target="n0914" n="14"/> Those evenings with them were filled with fiddling, dancing, and the sort of good times the explorers had not experienced for a long time.</p>
               <p>
Four days after slipping free from <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The Dalles</name>, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> finally met <name type="person" key="Yelleppit">Yelleppit</name>. Encountering the <name type="native_nation" key="Walula Indians">Walulas</name> symbolized the end of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> passage. It also meant that the mountains were ahead, and a time with the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perces</name>
                  </ref>. <name type="person" key="Yelleppit">Yelleppit's</name> village of fifteen large mat lodges was currently on the north side of the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> some twelve miles below the <name type="place"
                        key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Snake</name>-<name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> confluence. Eager to show his pleasure at seeing the Americans, <name type="person" key="Yelleppit">Yelleppit</name> delivered a long speech enjoining his people to welcome the strangers. The chief then went about gathering food and fuel to set an example of hospitality. Firewood and roasted fish were valuable but even more precious was information offered by the <name type="native_nation" key="Walula Indians">Walulas</name> on the best way to reach the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> camps on the <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Clearwater</name>.<ref target="n0915" n="15"/>
               </p>
               <p>
On the westbound journey, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had not been able to spend much time with <name type="person" key="Yelleppit">Yelleppit's</name> folk but had promised to be more neighborly on the return. The chief, interested in gaining a prominent place in the American trade system, was not about to let that promise go unfulfilled. Early on the morning of April 28, he arrived at the expedition's camp with "a very eligant white horse" as a gift for <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>. Like <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The Dalles</name> traders, the chief had his eye on acquiring some kettles. Since the expedition was dangerously short on cooking pots, the Indian was offered instead <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> sword, one hundred rounds of ammunition, and some trade goods. If the captains thought this exchange would satisfy <name type="person" key="Yelleppit">Yelleppit</name> and the expedition might then cross the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name>, they were mistaken.</p>
               <p>
The <name type="native_nation" key="Walula Indians">Walula</name> chief was not ready to let <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> slip so easily from his grasp. He was willing to provide horses, food, canoes, and information but his price called for the Americans to stay in camp for at least an extra day. <name type="person" key="Yelleppit">Yelleppit</name> artfully recalled the promise made a year ago. An extra day spent with him would hardly make any difference in travel plans. Just how much the presence of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> meant to <name type="native_nation" key="Walula Indians">Walula</name> prestige became plain when <name type="person" key="Yelleppit">Yelleppit</name> revealed that he had invited a large party of <name type="native_nation" key="Yakima Indians">Yakimams</name> for a grand feast and dance. Once again, the explorers proved the greatest tourist attraction in western America. Sensing that it would be both impolitic and impolite to disappoint <name type="person" key="Yelleppit">Yelleppit</name>, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> agreed to spend a day before attempting a river crossing. Talks with the <name type="native_nation" key="Walula Indians">Walulas</name> were simplified by the presence of a female <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Shoshoni.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name>
                  </ref> prisoner who provided the necessary translation link between <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name> and the Sahaptian-speaking <name type="native_nation" key="Walula Indians">Walulas</name>. "We conversed with them," wrote <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, "for several hours and fully satisfyed all their enquiries with rispect to ourselves and the objects of our pursuit." Throughout the day, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> practiced medicine, "a great wonder" to the <name type="native_nation" key="Walula Indians">Walulas</name>, as <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> noted. The day ended as a group of one hundred <name type="native_nation" key="Yakima Indians">Yakimas</name> came for an evening of dancing and singing, much of it led by a <name type="native_nation" key="Walula Indians">Walula</name> shaman who declared that communication with the moon spirit had enabled him to predict the arrival of the Americans. In the firelight and shadow of that festive night, the entire expedition may have set aside their knowledge that the <name type="place" key="Lolo Trail">Lolo Trail</name> and the <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Snow) Mountains">Bitterroots</name> loomed ahead.<ref target="n0916" n="16"/>
               </p>
               <p>
In the last days of April, the explorers crossed the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> and began a northeastern trek toward the <name type="place"
                        key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Snake</name>-<name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Clearwater</name> junction. They were now blessed with twenty-three "excellent young horses," most of them from the <name type="native_nation" key="Walula Indians">Walulas</name>. By the first of May, they were along the <name type="place" key="Touchet River">Touchet River</name> near present-day <name type="place" key="Waitsburg, Wash.">Waitsburg</name>, <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>. Two days later, up <name type="place" key="Pataha Creek">Pataha Creek</name> east of present-day <name type="place" key="Pomeroy, Wash.">Pomeroy</name>, <name type="place" key="Washington">Washington</name>, the expedition met a <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> known to them as <name type="person" key="Apash Wyakaikt">Wearkkoomt</name>. More properly named <name type="person" key="Apash Wyakaikt">Apash Wyakaikt</name> or <name type="person" key="Apash Wyakaikt">Flint Necklace</name>, he had heard that <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> were on the way and was eager to greet them. Although their journals did not mention it at the time, <name type="person" key="Apash Wyakaikt">Apash Wyakaikt</name> had evidently gone by land ahead of the expedition in October 1805 to announce their arrival at the <name type="place"
                        key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Snake</name>-<name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> confluence. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> was convinced that those efforts were "very instrumental in procuring us a hospitable and friendly reception among those natives." Not even rain, snow, hail, and scanty rations could diminish what must have been the expedition's pleasure at knowing they would soon be with the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perces</name>
                  </ref> on the <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Clearwater</name>.<ref target="n0917" n="17"/>
               </p>
               <p>
The weather and the dog-meat rations did not improve as the explorers slowly made their way toward the <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Clearwater</name>. In the hard going of steep and narrow paths, men and animals slipped and stumbled. One packhorse loaded with irreplaceable ammunition fell into a creek, but that mysterious <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> luck held and neither horse nor load was damaged. In the afternoon of May 4, the party arrived at the lodges of another <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> familiar from a year before. <name type="person" key="Tetoharsky">Tetoharsky</name>, along with <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">Twisted Hair</name>, had provided invaluable help on the westward voyage. From <name type="person" key="Tetoharsky">Tetoharsky's</name> kin, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> now learned that they should cross the <name type="place"
                        key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Snake</name> at this point and then follow the <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Clearwater</name> on the northeast side to where <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">Twisted Hair</name> had pastured the expedition's herd of horses. Knowing that more horses were close by may have improved morale, dampened by a night so cold and disagreeable that the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perces</name>
                  </ref> huddled around <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> fire "in great numbers insomuch that we could scarcely cook or keep ourselves warm."<ref target="n0918" n="18"/>
               </p>
               <p>
On the following day, May 5, the explorers plodded along the <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Clearwater</name>. Their enquiries at <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> mat lodges for food found the larders nearly bare. And many <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perces</name>
                  </ref> resented the way the strangers crowded into the lodges, disregarding both etiquette and their obvious poverty. But at one of the lodges <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> found an unexpected ally. On the westbound journey, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had done a good deal of doctoring among the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perces</name>
                  </ref>. One of those he had medicated had "never ceased to extol the virtues of our medicines and the skill of my friend <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain Clark</name> as a phisician." Ointments and salves now proved powerful agents as dozens of ailing <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perces</name>
                  </ref> began to line up for consultations with "their favorite phisician." <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> doubted the efficacy of <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> medicine chest but justified "this deception for they will not give us any provision without compensation in merchandize and our stock is now reduced to a mere handfull."</p>
               <p>
Provisions, especially dog meat, were what the expedition desperately needed. The <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perces</name>
                  </ref> did not usually eat dog and found it amusing that the explorers relished it. That amusement very nearly sparked a serious argument when a <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> prankster "very impertinently" threw a scrawny puppy toward <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>. Angered by the act and the general laughter it provoked, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> caught the dog and threw it back at the Indian "with great violence." At the same time, the explorer brandished his tomahawk and made signs that if another dog grew wings the Indian would suffer for it. With undisguised arrogance, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> recorded that he then continued lunch "<hi rend="italic">on dog</hi>" without further interruption.</p>
               <p>
Later that afternoon, the expedition reached a large mat lodge measuring 15 by 156 feet. Holding thirty families, this <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> long house was home to many in the band of <name type="person" key="Cut Nose">Neeshneparkkeook, or Cutnose</name>, who had gotten his name as the result of a wound suffered in combat with the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Shoshoni.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshonis</name>
                  </ref>. Although not especially impressed with either his physique or his intelligence, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> gave <name type="person" key="Cut Nose">Cutnose</name> a small medal. Perhaps more important, the explorers met a <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Shoshoni.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name>
                  </ref> taken prisoner by the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perces</name>
                  </ref>. With this man as translator, it was now possible to have direct talks with the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perces</name>
                  </ref> without relying on signs. The first piece of information that came from the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Shoshoni.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name>
                  </ref> translator was worrisome. He indicated that at least one <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> elder believed <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> were "bad men and had come to kill them." Knowing that such rumors had to be squelched, the captains were pleased when <name type="person" key="Apash Wyakaikt">Flint Necklace</name> rejoined the party.<ref target="n0919" n="19"/>
               </p>
               <p>
For the next two days, the expedition traveled east along the <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Clearwater</name>. As before, those were days of slim rations. Horses traded for <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> eyewash were quickly butchered. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> also had time to record accurate descriptions of <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> clothing, burial practices, and hunting techniques. But just beneath that travel routine was some very disturbing news, something beyond horses or diplomacy. Everyone in the party could now see that the <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Snow) Mountains">Bitterroots</name> were covered with snow, an observation confirmed by several <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perces</name>
                  </ref> who reported, "The snow is yet so deep on the mountains that we shall not be able to pass them until after the next full moon or about the first of June." Describing this as "unwelcome intiligence," <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> admitted that the diet of horsemeat and roots already had most of the expedition dreaming of those "fat plains of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>" and home.<ref target="n0920" n="20"/>
               </p>
               <p>
It was not until the afternoon of May 8, some miles south of the <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Clearwater</name>, that <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> found lodges belonging to <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">Twisted Hair</name>. The captains expected to see not only him but horses as well. What greeted them instead was a long-simmering quarrel between <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">Twisted Hair</name> and <name type="person" key="Cut Nose">Cutnose</name>. No sooner had the explorers met <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">Twisted Hair</name> than he began to speak in a loud and angry voice. <name type="person" key="Cut Nose">Cutnose's</name> reply was equally heated. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> did not immediately understand the cause of the dispute but quickly realized that any delay in finding their horses might be serious. Moving to cut off the argument, the captains announced that they were going to march on to the first good water and bed down for the night. Hoping to reconcile them, they invited both <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">Twisted Hair</name> and <name type="person" key="Cut Nose">Cutnose</name> to come along.</p>
               <p>
Once at their evening camp, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> acted to mediate between the two quarrelling Indians. During the past several days, the explorers had heard rumors that their horses were scattered and the saddle and tack cache damaged. Putting <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">Twisted Hair</name> and <name type="person" key="Cut Nose">Cutnose</name> on good terms might clear the air and make rounding up the horses much easier. Because the young <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Shoshoni.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name>
                  </ref> interpreter refused to take part in what he said was not his affair, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had to rely on signs to mollify both parties. After <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name> found <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">Twisted Hair</name>, the explorers listened first to his explanation. <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">Twisted Hair</name> claimed that no sooner had he taken possession of the expedition's horses than <name type="person" key="Cut Nose">Cutnose</name> and <name type="person" key="Broken Arm">Tunnachemootoolt (Broken Arm)</name> returned from a raid against the <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshinis</name>. Angry and jealous of the prestige <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">Twisted Hair</name> had gained by his association with the Americans, <name type="person" key="Cut Nose">Cutnose</name> and <name type="person" key="Broken Arm">Broken Arm</name> evidently had begun a long and wearing argument with the elderly Indian. Tired and upset by their complaints, <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">Twisted Hair</name> now admitted he had neglected the horses. Unsure how close to the truth his words were but unwilling to worsen a complex situation, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> reminded the Indian that his reward of two guns and ammunition was still available if he would locate the missing horses. The captains then sent <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name> to fetch <name type="person" key="Cut Nose">Cutnose</name>. His story was predictably different. <name type="person" key="Cut Nose">Cutnose</name> charged that <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">Twisted Hair</name> was "a bad old man" who "woar two faces." According to <name type="person" key="Cut Nose">Cutnose</name>, <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">Twisted Hair</name> had allowed several young men to ride expedition horses hard enough to injure them. <name type="person" key="Cut Nose">Cutnose</name> insisted that he and <name type="person" key="Broken Arm">Broken Arm</name> had tried to protect the horses, but to no avail. Denied the services of their translator, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> could neither ascertain the full truth nor resolve the quarrel. Prudence suggested staying with <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">Twisted Hair</name> one day to allow him time to bring in the horses and then moving on to <name type="person" key="Broken Arm">Broken Arm's</name> lodge to pay him proper due.<ref target="n0921" n="21"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Letting each man tell his tale and giving at least surface credence to both was a happy compromise. On the following day, <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">Twisted Hair</name> sent two young men to bring in the expedition's horses. Although most were healthy, at least three showed signs of hard use. In the afternoon, <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">Twisted Hair</name> and <name type="person" key="Willard, Alexander">Alexander Willard</name> went out to recover saddles, tack, powder, and lead from a cache built the previous year. Happily, there were signs that the row between <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">Twisted Hair</name> and <name type="person" key="Cut Nose">Cutnose</name> had become a thing of the past. But against these good omens was the growing awareness that the expedition would be spending more time with the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perces</name>
                  </ref> than first anticipated. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> location on May 9 was unsuitable for a more permanent camp. Access to water, good pasture, and protection against weather and theft all required finding another site.</p>
               <p>
That the expedition had left <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name> too soon became painfully evident when the explorers set out on May 10 for <name type="person" key="Broken Arm">Broken Arm's</name> village. With eight inches of snow on the ground, horses slipped repeatedly along the hazardous trail. It was not until late in the afternoon that <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> finally came down to <name type="place" key="Lawyer (Commearp) Creek">Lawyer's Canon Creek</name> and straggled into the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> settlement. Greeting them were an impressive <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> chief and his people, framed by a large mat lodge and an American flag left behind the previous year. Cold and hungry, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> asked <name type="person" key="Broken Arm">Broken Arm's</name> help to restock the expedition's supplies. The chief responded by bringing roots and dried salmon, food that stirred memoires of agonizing indigestion and dysentery. He then graciously promised as many horses as needed for fresh meat.</p>
               <p>
While all this menu-planning was going on, the stage was being set for preliminary talks with the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perces</name>
                  </ref>. Those councils moved a step closer when an important chief <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> called <name type="person" key="Hohots Ilppilp">Hohastillpilp</name> arrived at <name type="person" key="Broken Arm">Broken Arm's</name> village with a party of fifty mounted warriors. More properly known as <name type="person" key="Hohots Ilppilp">Hohots Ilppilp</name> or the <name type="person" key="Hohots Ilppilp">Bloody Chief</name>, his village was some six miles away near the <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Clearwater</name>. With <name type="person" key="Broken Arm">Broken Arm</name>, <name type="person" key="Cut Nose">Cutnose</name>, and <name type="person" key="Hohots Ilppilp">Hohots Ilppilp</name> present, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> decided to begin serious talks. <name type="person" key="Broken Arm">Broken Arm</name> and <name type="person" key="Hohots Ilppilp">Hohots Ilppilp</name> were first given medals. Using their <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Shoshoni.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name>
                  </ref> interpreter, the explorers explained "the design and the importance of medals in the estimation of the whites as well as the red men who had been taught their value." Impressed by all this, and with his eye on gaining things more precious than medals, <name type="person" key="Broken Arm">Broken Arm</name> led the explorers to a council tepee. With a crowd of Indians packed into the lodge, everyone spent the rest of the evening eating prime horsemeat, smoking friendly pipes, and talking in a mixture of phrases and signs that were hastily translated. This council seemed to promise the kind of diplomatic success that had so often eluded <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>.<ref target="n0922" n="22"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Early talks with <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> chiefs prepared the way for two days of serious diplomatic exchange on May 11 and 12. If <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> were unsure of their agenda at <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name>, they were more certain of their negotiating priorities with the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perces</name>
                  </ref> and other plateau peoples. Participation in the American trade system, intertribal peace, and delegations of notables destined for the president's reception room were all on the list of subjects to be broached with the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perces</name>
                  </ref>. It was an agenda that <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> believed applicable to every native group. That such diplomacy—especially the dangerous practice of promising arms to traditional enemies—might have unforeseen and unpleasant consequences had not yet become plain to the Corps of Discovery diplomats.</p>
               <p>
With the arrival of <name type="person" key="Yoom-park-kar-tim">Yoomparkkartim (Five Big Hearts)</name>, "a chief of great note," all major <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> headmen in the immediate area were present. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> never lacked a flair for the dramatic, no matter how understated their journal entries. Borrowing from native cartographic techniques, the captains began the grand council by drawing a map of the country with charcoal on a stretched hide. Smoking, gift-giving, and the mapping revealed just how much the explorers had learned of Indian protocol. If past experience proved any guide, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> was responsible for making the formal presentation. Although his remarks were short and uncomplicated, translations proved "tedious" as every word passed through English, French, <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name>, <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Shoshoni.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name>
                  </ref>, and <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> speakers. Half the day was taken up getting <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> message across to the patient chiefs. The American officer presented four closely related points. Establishing trading posts, instituting intertribal peace, and preparing delegations were a trio of themes that had been repeated since the earliest days on the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>. The issue of American sovereignty was an unspoken part of the talks, although what had been said the previous day about the design and meaning of medals suggests that thoughts of sovereignty were not far from the Americans' minds. But there was a final point in <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> presentation that was both spoken and demonstrated. Throughout their long voyage <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> were always at pains to show as forcefully as possible the military prowess and technological strength of the new republic. Parades, keelboat curiosities, telescopes, mirrors, and the omnipresent airgun were all for that purpose. "After the council was over," wrote <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, "we amused ourselves with showing them the power of magnatism, the spy glass, compass, watch, air gun and sundry other articles equally novel and incomprehensible to them." When one young and important warrior told the captains that he had "opened his ears to our councils and that our words had made his heart glad," <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> must have believed that a major diplomatic victory was in the offing.<ref target="n0923" n="23"/>
               </p>
               <p>
The captains understood enough Indian political and diplomatic practice to realize that no immediate answer to the American plans could be expected. There had to be time for talk and a ceremonial acceptance of a consensus that was ultimately binding on none. Throughout the morning of Monday, May 12, chiefs and elders spoke their minds in a council that eventually proved to have far-reaching consequences for the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> people. The <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> leaders assembled at <name type="person" key="Broken Arm">Broken Arm's</name> village certainly understood what was at stake. By 1806 there were about four thousand <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perces</name>
                  </ref> living in several autonomous bands. The predictable rhythms of their lives were increasingly challenged by the flood of firearms falling into the hands of <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Atsina Indians">Atsina</name> warriors. The <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> situation was similar to that of <name type="person" key="Cameahwait">Cameahwait's</name>
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians, Lemhi">Lemhi</name>
                  <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Shoshoni.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshonis</name>
                  </ref>. Both peoples desperately needed a place in the American trade system, if only to obtain guns and ammunition. In a plains and plateau world undergoing profound change, links to American traders promised what must have seemed cheap security. Several hours of talk behind him, <name type="person" key="Broken Arm">Broken Arm</name> emerged and set in motion one of the most dramatic moments in expedition history. Taking flour made from cous roots, the chief made a thick mush and then ladled it into "the kettles and baskets of all his people." After a long speech in which he explained the decisions reached in council, <name type="person" key="Broken Arm">Broken Arm</name> called on all who accepted those decisions to eat the mush. In a colorful line, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> observed, "All swallowed their objections if any they had very cheerfully with their mush." This was done to a background of women crying and tearing their hair, perhaps sensing that links with the strangers might bring unequal measures of safety and danger.</p>
               <p>
With ritual acceptance of the council's decisions, it was time for the Indians to present formally their views to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>. Because so many <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perces</name>
                  </ref> required medical attention, the captains decided that <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> would spend the rest of the day doctoring while <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> pursued his diplomacy. The official orator for the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perces</name>
                  </ref> was the elderly father of <name type="person" key="Hohots Ilppilp">Hohots Ilppilp</name>, a man of considerable prestige and political skill. Declaring that the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perces</name>
                  </ref> now spoke with one heart and one mind, the old speaker presented a perceptive, critical evaluation of American proposals and native needs. He agreed that peace with neighboring tribes had real advantages. As if to underscore the unity of American and <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> policies, he reported that in the summer of 1805 a <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> delegation had gone to parley with <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Shoshoni.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshonis</name>
                  </ref> along the <name type="place"
                        key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Snake River</name>. But those emissaries had been killed by <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Shoshoni.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name>
                  </ref> warriors and the resulting raid against the <name type="place"
                        key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Snake River</name> people had counted forty-two <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Shoshoni.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshonis</name>
                  </ref> dead and only three <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> casualties. The blood of the slain peacemakers had been properly revenged and peace was now possible. But whether the old man meant peace as <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> understood it or a temporary truce remained unclear. As they had along the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, the explorer-diplomats unthinkingly assumed that "peace" meant the same thing on both sides of the cultural divide.</p>
               <p>
As the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> leadership understood it, the real issue was trade and security. Access to guns symbolized their concern. Speaking to that complex matter, the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> orator declared that his people were willing to travel on to the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> plains for trade. However, no <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> was prepared to make such a trading journey unless there were solid assurances that <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Atsina Indians">Atsina</name> warriors were not lying in ambush along the trail. All of this meant arming the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perces</name>
                  </ref> and making peace with those plains warriors already well armed by Canadian traders. That these two objectives were mutually exclusive may have been evident to some <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perces</name>
                  </ref> but not to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>. The old speaker pledged everlasting friendship to the Americans, saying that although the bands were poor, "their hearts were good." There may have been plenty of "good hearts" in evidence, but what the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perces</name>
                  </ref> really wanted were guns. As for a delegation to the Federal City, that issue was unresolved. If the Americans could deliver weapons, then perhaps a long journey to see the chief of the seventeen fires would be worth the trouble and danger.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> fullest day of diplomacy since talks with <name type="person" key="Cameahwait">Cameahwait</name> ended with a flurry of eating, singing, dancing, and gambling. Pipes were passed, more gifts-exchanged, and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> continued his medical ministrations. But in all this play and good feeling, there was one activity that especially fascinated many <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> warriors. Firing rifles at targets drew their attention. The presence of native visitors on the weapons range was a clear indication of what lay behind so much of the talk during that day. When <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> struck the mark twice from a range of 220 yards, those warriors could not help but be impressed with the weapons that might soon be in their hands.<ref target="n0924" n="24"/>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> believed that their major diplomatic objectives with the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perces</name>
                  </ref> had been accomplished. After the talks, they were increasingly concerned with the problem of deep snows in the <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Snow) Mountains">Bitterroots</name>. During the grand council, there were further reports that the <name type="place" key="Lolo Trail">Lolo Trail</name> would not be passable for at least another month. Any hope of a quick passage over the mountains was now gone. A site had to be found for a camp among the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perces</name>
                  </ref>, and arrangements had to be made for guides once the trail was open. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> hoped that by inviting <name type="person" key="Twisted Hair (Walamotinin)">Twisted Hair's</name> family to live nearby, guides from his household might be hired. Following suggestions from several chiefs, they located a camping place along the north bank of the <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Clearwater River</name> near modern-day <name type="place" key="Kamiah, Idaho">Kamiah</name>, <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>. This was an especially favorable site, providing access to good hunting grounds, fine pasture for horses, and the river when the salmon finally ran. The expedition's baggage was stored in the center of a depression made by an abandoned winter pit lodge. Although the expedition spent nearly a month (May 14–June 10, 1806) at this spot, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> never gave the camp a formal name. Tradition has called it <name type="place" key="Camp Chopunnish (Idaho)">Camp Chopunnish, Long Camp, or Camp Kamiah</name>. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> placed his seal of approval on the location by declaring himself "perfectly satisfied with our position."<ref target="n0925" n="25"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Although <name type="place" key="Camp Chopunnish (Idaho)">Camp Chopunnish</name> was never much more than a collection of leaky brush wickiups, luggage pens, and a makeshift horse corral, it was the center of busy activity. Day by day there were more Indians who found a welcome at <name type="place" key="Camp Chopunnish (Idaho)">Camp Chopunnish</name> than at <name type="place" key="Fort Clatsop (Oreg.)">Fort Clatsop</name>. Contacts with the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perces</name>
                  </ref> ranged from trade and medicine to sport and sex. As they waited for snows to melt up in the <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Snow) Mountains">Bitterroots</name>, members of the expedition developed close ties with these Indians.</p>
               <p>
Despite the best efforts of expeditionary hunters led by <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">George Drouillard</name>, it was plain by early May that a reliable trade in foodstuffs had to be established with the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> villages. It was this trade that most often provided common ground for explorer and Indian. What to offer for stocks of camas and cous roots and the much-sought-after cous bread proved a serious problem. <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> tastes in trade goods did not run to "baubles," as <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> called them. Beads, armbands, and other luxury items failed to attract much attention. The practical <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perces</name>
                  </ref> sought knives, kettles, blankets, and moccasin awls. But the expedition's supplies of those tools and utensils were short, and if <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> hoped to foster a dependable trade, canny substitutions had to be found.<ref target="n0926" n="26"/>
               </p>
               <p>
By mid-May, as the expedition's hunting fortunes further declined, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> organized trading parties to visit the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> villages. Typical of those ventures was the first mission to <name type="person" key="Broken Arm">Broken Arm's</name> village. <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Toussaint Charbonneau</name>, <name type="person" key="Thompson, John B.">John Thompson</name>, <name type="person" key="Weiser, Peter">Peter Wiser</name>, <name type="person" key="Potts, John">John Potts</name>, and <name type="person" key="Hall, Hugh">Hugh Hall</name> were given moccasin awls, knitting pins, and brass armbands to exchange for cous roots and bread. After a day of haggling, "our marketers" returned near dark with six bushels of roots and bread. On May 20, <name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">Frazer</name> was sent on the second trade foray. He reported that the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perces</name>
                  </ref> were apparently ready to depart from their usual utilitarian demands and might be wooed with brass uniform buttons. Buttons promptly vanished from the expedition's clothing as each man gathered what he could to make trade bargains. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> evidently feared that such a scramble might produce economic chaos and reduced morale. On May 21, the captains collected all the remaining goods and carefully parceled them out to each man. Every member of the Corps of Discovery was given one awl, one knitting pin, half an ounce of vermilion paint, two needles, a few skeins of thread, and one yard of ribbon. With this "slender stock," each man was to make any agreements he could to obtain the food necessary for the <name type="place" key="Lolo Trail">Lolo Trail</name> passage.<ref target="n0927" n="27"/>
               </p>
               <p>
In the last days of May, small expedition parties made regular trips to Indian camps along the <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Clearwater</name>. Trading was often difficult as <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> folk soon learned that the laws of supply and demand favored them. <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name> admitted that roots and bread could only be bought "at a very dear rate." Hardpressed to meet <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> business demands, some men ingeniously fashioned moccasin awls from small links of a discarded chain. The <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> trade was not only difficult but dangerous as well. When <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name> and <name type="person" key="Lepage, Jean Baptiste">Jean Baptiste Lepage</name> went up the <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Clearwater</name> to trade at a village some eight miles away, they experienced, in <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> words, "a broken voyage." Things began to go wrong for the two French traders when their packhorse slipped and fell into the <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Clearwater</name>. Terrified, the horse bolted and swam across the river. An Indian on the opposite shore helpfully tried to drive the horse back toward the traders, but the pack cinches broke and precious cargo was lost. And to compound troubles, a raft loaded with roots destined for <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name> and <name type="person" key="Lepage, Jean Baptiste">Lapage</name> struck a rock and capsized. "The river having fallen heir to both merchandize and roots," wrote <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> laconically, "our traders returned with empty hands." The troubles experienced by <name type="person" key="Potts, John">Potts</name>, <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name>, and <name type="person" key="Collins, John">John Collins</name> were far more serious. While attempting to cross the <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Clearwater</name>, their canoe caught the full force of the current and slammed into a tree. <name type="person" key="Potts, John">Potts</name> was "an indifferent swimmer"; as he floundered in the river, the canoe quickly filled with water and sank. In the confusion three blankets, one blanket coat, and a supply of trade goods were lost. Efforts by <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Pryor</name> and his men to raise the canoe and recover the goods failed. The loss of the blankets was indeed serious. As <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name> explained, "The loss of these blankets is the greatest which hath happened to any individual since we began our voyage, as there are only three men in the party who have more than one blanket apiece."<ref target="n0928" n="28"/>
               </p>
               <p>
By the first days of June, the expedition's stocks of trade items were nearly gone. High prices, accidents, and continued poor hunting made business with the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perces</name>
                  </ref> increasingly difficult and jeopardized the explorers along the <name type="place" key="Lolo Trail">Lolo Trail</name>. "Having exhausted all our merchandize," wrote <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, "we are obliged to have recourse to every subterfuge in order to prepare in the most ample manner in our power to meet that wretched portion of our journey, the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky Mountains</name>, where hungar and cold in their most rigorous forms assail the wearied traveller." Whether those "subterfuges" were the same as the tricks of trade employed by <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> along the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> is not plain in the journals. What is recorded is a desperate effort to find any objects that might attract the Indians' attention. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> cut the buttons from their own coats and made up measures of several medications. Those goods, along with some unused phials and tin boxes, were given to <name type="person" key="McNeal, Hugh">McNeal</name> and <name type="person" key="York">York</name>. When the two men returned bringing three bushels of roots and some cous bread, their success was "not much less pleasing to us than the return of a good cargo to an East India Merchant."<ref target="n0929" n="29"/> Less successful was a long trip undertaken by <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, <name type="person" key="Frazer, Robert">Frazer</name>, and <name type="person" key="Weiser, Peter">Wiser</name> to an Indian fishery at <name type="place" key="Wild Goose Rapids">Wild Goose Rapids</name> on the <name type="place"
                        key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Snake River</name> to trade for salmon. After a journey that lasted a week and covered some one hundred miles, <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway's</name> party returned with seventeen spoiled fish and a few cous roots.<ref target="n0930" n="30"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Throughout the first week of June, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> continued to pursue the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> trade. Believing that snows would be sufficiently melted within the next two weeks, the explorers redoubled their efforts to stockpile food for the mountain passage. But these efforts were hampered by few goods for trade and the failure of salmon to run on the <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Clearwater</name>. Nothing could be done about the tardy fish, but many men in the party used considerable imagination to create "little notions" from bits and pieces of worn files, spare bullets, and tattered fish nets. These ventures in product design evidently paid off, much to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> surprise. The captains, who had been so pessimistic a few days before, found that by June 6 the Corps had enough rations to dare the <name type="place" key="Lolo Trail">Lolo Trail</name>.<ref target="n0931" n="31"/> The remaining trade centered on obtaining ropes for packsaddles, skin bags to hold provisions, and animal hair for saddle pads.</p>
               <p>
That the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perces</name>
                  </ref> continued to have "good hearts" toward their <name type="place" key="Camp Chopunnish (Idaho)">Camp Chopunnish</name> neighbors was the result of two expectations. Hope that ties to the Americans might bring a steady supply of trade goods, especially guns and ammunition, and some lessening of tensions with plains raiders clearly shaped the Indians' behavior. Only slightly less important for expedition–<ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> relations were the medical services <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> provided to countless Indian men, women, and children. Just how interested the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perces</name>
                  </ref> were in his doctoring was evident even before <name type="place" key="Camp Chopunnish (Idaho)">Camp Chopunnish</name> was established. As <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> explained it, cures accomplished during the westbound journey "raised my reputation and gives those nativs an exolted oppinion of my skill a a phisician." Quickly realizing that much of their future comfort and security depended on <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> good will, the explorers were willing to continue the "deception" of <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> as the great healer. But <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> was not without scruples, and he maintained: "We take care to give them no article which can possibly injure them, and in many cases can administer and give such medicine and sirgical aid as will effectually restore them in simple cases."<ref target="n0932" n="32"/>
               </p>
               <p>
As the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perces</name>
                  </ref>' "favorite phisician," <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had a waiting room filled with eager patients. Throughout the days at <name type="place" key="Camp Chopunnish (Idaho)">Camp Chopunnish</name>, he saw a wide variety of diseases and disorders. Most common were sore eyes, rheumatism, strained muscles, and abrasions. But there were also more demanding medical problems, including serious abscesses, mental depression, and "disorders intirely out of the power of Medison." Determined to do what he could for those "poor afflicted wretches," <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> utilized simple medications and common-sense therapies. Those included various salves, elixirs, pills, and large quantities of eyewash. Laudanum (tincture of opium) was the most potent drug in the expedition's medicine chest. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> also administered back rubs and on at least one occasion performed minor surgery on festering abscess. The fact that a party of <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perces</name>
                  </ref> once spent two days in the saddle to obtain some of <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> famous eyewash is a reminder of how important his medical services were at <name type="place" key="Camp Chopunnish (Idaho)">Camp Chopunnish</name>.<ref target="n0933" n="33"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Of all the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> cases seen by <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, none was more dramatic or as well-documented as that of a paralyzed chief. This unnamed "chief of considerable note" first appeared at camp on May 11. With Clinical precision, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> described the Indian's symptoms and speculated on the cause of his apparent paralysis. "This man is incapable of moveing a single limb but lies like a corps in whatever position he is placed, yet he eats hartily, dejests his food perfectly, enjoys his understanding. His pulse are good, and has retained his flesh almost perfectly; in short were it not that he appears a little pale from having been so long in the shade, he might well be taken for a man in good health. I suspect that their confinement to a diet of roots may give rise to all the disorders of the nativs of this quarter except the Rhumitsism and Sore eyes, and to the latter of those, the state of debility incident to a vegitable diet may measureable contribute." Although betraying a cultural preference for red meat in the diet, in every other way the diagnosis represents a skillful piece of physiological observation.<ref target="n0934" n="34"/>
               </p>
               <p>
With this case <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> learned the difference between successful diagnosis and effective therapy. The explorers were especially eager to provide good care for the chief. Success in treatment would further insure <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> hospitality and support. But in a case as complex as this, they were quite unsure how to proceed. Notions about diet as the root cause of the man's immobility offered slight guidance for a condition that had already lasted five years. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> first prescribed "simple cooling medicenes" for the chief. When these failed and the chief's relatives persisted in hoping for a cure, he gave several doses of sulphur and cream of tartar and proposed a regimen of daily cold baths. But in all of this <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> admitted that he was at a loss to deturmine what to do for this unfortunate man." In desperation, he suggested a few drops of laudanum and the expedition's version of chicken soup, a watery broth made from portable soup.<ref target="n0935" n="35"/>
               </p>
               <p>
A breakthrough of sorts came on May 24. After giving a powerful sweat bath to chronically ill <name type="person" key="Bratton, William E.">William Bratton</name> and seeing its positive results, the captains decided to try the treatment on the chief. But the sweating hole dug for <name type="person" key="Bratton, William E.">Bratton</name> proved too small for the chief. Stymied but not ready to admit defeat, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> urged relatives to take the chief to their larger sweat lodges. And reflecting current medical interest in the possible healing effects of electricity, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> declared that the chief "would be an excellent subject for electricity" and regretted that "I have it not in my power to supply it."<ref target="n0936" n="36"/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> may have thought that, after his failure to sweat the chief, his advice to the anxious family might end the expedition's involvement. But <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> reputation was too powerful for that, and when both patient and family lingered in camp, he was compelled to once again prescribe sulphur and cream of tartar and urge that the stricken chief be be taken home. When the latter suggestion was strongly resisted, it was agreed to attempt a second sweat. On the following day, May 27, the chief's father carefully enlarged the sweat pit. The man was then lowered into the pit with ropes and, despite considerable pain, the therapy seemed promising.</p>
               <p>
In the days that followed, the heat treatments were repeated. To the surprise of all, the chief gradually recovered use of his arms and hands. By the end of May, the man was washing his face and was able to move his toes and legs. As the expedition prepared to leave <name type="place" key="Camp Chopunnish (Idaho)">Camp Chopunnish</name> in early June, the chief continued to report progress. Whether his improvement was sustained is not known, but the efforts of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> in this difficult case reenforced the positive image of the explorers in the minds of many <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perces</name>
                  </ref>.<ref target="n0937" n="37"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Busy with trade, medicine, and the demands of daily life, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> still found time to record something about the lives of their Indian hosts. As had become the rule in their ethnography, the explorers paid most attention to <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> material culture. In references scattered throughout the <name type="place" key="Camp Chopunnish (Idaho)">Camp Chopunnish</name> entries, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> commented on a variety of topics. Eating habits, domestic architecture, hunting techniques, and the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> passion for fine horses all found a place in their records. Clothing, saddles, and weapons were duly noted and described. Attitudes about old age, the protocol of diplomacy, and the custom of sacrificing horses at the death of a prominent person made the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perces</name>
                  </ref> come alive in the journals. And the explorers took time to set down one vivid aural impression of native life. "The noise of their women pounding roots reminds me of a nail factory," wrote <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>.<ref target="n0938" n="38"/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <name type="place" key="Camp Chopunnish (Idaho)">Camp Chopunnish</name> was second only to <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name> as a place where Indians and explorers could enjoy each other's company. Although records for this period are neither as full nor as explicit as those kept at <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name>, there is evidence strongly suggesting that the Americans stood "at ease" among the <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Clearwater</name> people. Finding much to admire in <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> customs, hospitality, and physique, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> felt comfortable enough to relax and enjoy some breathing time before assaulting the dreaded <name type="place" key="Lolo Trail">Lolo Trail</name>. There were times for fiddling, dancing, and singing. On several occasions, the expedition's hunters shared meat with hungry Indians. In return, the natives showed the Americans a remarkably infection-free method for gelding horses. Even at <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name> there had been bumps and scrapes in Indian-expedition relations. But if such troubles drifted into <name type="place" key="Camp Chopunnish (Idaho)">Camp Chopunnish</name>, they were so minor as to elude all journal keepers.<ref target="n0939" n="39"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Even more elusive are the facts about sexual relations between men in the expedition and <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> women. Among the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perces</name>
                  </ref>, there were no strong sanctions for or against sex with whites. These plateau people used sex neither to seal trade bargains nor to gain spiritual power. The expedition's records during the winters with the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Mandan.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>
                  </ref> and the <name type="native_nation" key="Clatsop Indians">Clatsops</name> are filled with the pleasures and troubles of native affairs. But the <name type="place" key="Camp Chopunnish (Idaho)">Camp Chopunnish</name> entries in all journals are oddly silent on what was from the beginning an accepted part of the life of the expedition. There seems little doubt that contacts more intimate than trading for roots took place during those early spring days. Sex usually made for good copy in the journals when it involved disease, personal trouble, or cultural misunderstanding. Since relations with the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perces</name>
                  </ref> were amiable, whatever personal encounters took place may well have been mutually satisfactory.</p>
               <p>
Perhaps the most intriguing piece of evidence to suggest the presence of such liaisons is a photograph taken by the noted western cameraman William H. Jackson. Before the 1877 <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> War, Jackson encountered a <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> band and was introduced to a blue-eyed, sandy-haired man claiming to be <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark's</name> son. Sufficiently impressed, Jackson photographed the man. The assertion that <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> left a son behind along the <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Clearwater</name> persisted, and when Chief Joseph's band surrendered to General Nelson Miles in 1877, one of the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> prisoners was pointed out as <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> son. Although in no way conclusive, the story does reveal the continued positive reputation of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> among the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perces</name>
                  </ref> well into the nineteenth century. Whether this particular man was indeed <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> son or the child of another white explorer is beyond the power of existing historical evidence either to verify or deny. At the same time, the persistence of the tale hints at one more part of the physical life at <name type="place" key="Camp Chopunnish (Idaho)">Camp Chopunnish</name>.<ref target="n0940" n="40"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Far less difficult to document were times of boisterous fun and athletic competition in what might be aptly described as the <name type="place" key="Camp Chopunnish (Idaho)">Camp Chopunnish</name> Olympics. The men of the expedition had been selected, at least in part, for their sound constitutions. Despite long months of travel and often irregular diets, most remained in good condition. Their frontier and military backgrounds were filled with demanding physical conditioning as well as a tradition of competitive sports. The <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> men equally admired strong bodies and tests of skill and strength. Early in June, as the expedition prepared to leave camp, the explorers and Indians staged an impromptu series of athletic contests. There had already been some target shooting, and now foot races were added to the schedule. Matched against a <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> team that <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> admitted was "very active" were sprinters <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">George Drouillard</name> and <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">Reuben Field</name>. But Indian runners proved very swift, and at least one was as fast as the best the Corps of Discovery had to offer. Following the races was a game <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> described as "prison base," an activity much like "keep away" or "running bases." These good-natured competitions provided yet another chance for all in camp to enjoy simple pleasures. For the captains there was an additional benefit. As <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> explained it, with the mountain crossing drawing near, those men who had become "rather lazy and slouthfull" needed some rigorous exercise.<ref target="n0941" n="41"/>
               </p>
               <p>
As May slipped into June and the time grew closer to leave <name type="place" key="Camp Chopunnish (Idaho)">Camp Chopunnish</name>, there were several diplomatic questions still unanswered. Although <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> certainly believed that most of the American proposals had been accepted, some issues had not yet received formal <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> replies. Those included the expedition's requests for guides beyond the mountains, a <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> group to accompany <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> at least partway in his journey to negotiate with <name type="native_nation" key="Atsina Indians">Atsina</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name> bands, and a delegation to visit President <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson</name>.</p>
               <p>
On June 4, as <name type="person" key="Broken Arm">Broken Arm</name> and several other chiefs prepared to leave for their own villages, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> reminded them of earlier promises to aid the expedition. The chiefs' reply revealed not so much second thoughts about an American trade and military alliance as some caution about the powers and abilities of untested new friends. <name type="person" key="Broken Arm">Broken Arm</name> carefully declined the invitation for some young warriors to accompany <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> beyond <name type="place" key="Lolo (Travelers' Rest) Creek (Mont.)">Travelers' Rest</name>, declaring that his hunters would not venture beyond the <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Snow) Mountains">Bitterroots</name> until late in the summer. He hinted that there was little hope for a <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> delegation to go with <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>. Although none of the chief's replies spelled defeat for American diplomacy, they did reveal a certain prudent wariness. The <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perces</name>
                  </ref> wanted American guns and the security they promised, but there were always those cries of fearful women to counsel caution.<ref target="n0942" n="42"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Not about to accept <name type="person" key="Broken Arm">Broken Arm's</name> words as a final answer, the captains decided to send <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> and a small party to parley once again with the chief. Receiving the Americans with unfailing hospitality, <name type="person" key="Broken Arm">Broken Arm</name> told <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> of the presence of many headmen from small and more distant villages who had not been at the grand council in early May. <name type="person" key="Broken Arm">Broken Arm</name> had thoughtfully invited them and now asked <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> to repeat to them the American plans. If <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> hoped that a larger audience and a second chance to explain federal policy might change some minds, he was wrong. <name type="person" key="Broken Arm">Broken Arm</name> repeated what he had said two days before: no large number of <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perces</name>
                  </ref> were about to accompany the expedition. The request for some warrior-diplomats to foster intertribal peace on the <name type="place" key="Marias River">Marias</name> could not be decided until a larger council met.</p>
               <p>
But <name type="person" key="Broken Arm">Broken Arm</name> did not want <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> to think the whole notion of peace with neighbors was now in doubt. The chief explained that, as a result of recent contacts with <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Shoshoni.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshonis</name>
                  </ref> who desired peace with <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> and <name type="native_nation" key="Cayuse Indians">Cayuse</name> bands, a <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> delegation had been sent toward the <name type="place"
                        key="Snake (Ki-moo-e-nim, Lewis's, Southeast Branch of Columbia) River">Snake River</name> to negotiate such an agreement. <name type="person" key="Broken Arm">Broken Arm</name> promised he would never break that peace and to emphasize his good intentions presented <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> two ceremonial pipes—one a traditional <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> pipe for the explorers and the other a fancy plains pipe with silver inlays for the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Shoshoni.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshonis</name>
                  </ref>. Knowing the significance of those pipes, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> decorated the one destined for the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Shoshoni.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshonis</name>
                  </ref> with blue ribbon and white wampum to symbolize a mutual desire for peace. As he made his way back to camp, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> may well have noted that, although American policy now seemed on firmer ground, the immediate need for guides over the treacherous <name type="place" key="Lolo Trail">Lolo Trail</name> was yet unmet.<ref target="n0943" n="43"/>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>
From the first days at <name type="place" key="Camp Chopunnish (Idaho)">Camp Chopunnish</name>, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had maintained a close watch on snow conditions in the <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Snow) Mountains">Bitterroots</name>. The expedition's timetables called for a quick journey over the mountains. A long stay with the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perces</name>
                  </ref>, no matter how pleasant, seriously endangered the homeward voyage. By the middle of May, both captains were looking for any sign to prove that the <name type="place" key="Lolo Trail">Lolo Trail</name> would soon be passable. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> reported: "I frequently consult the nativs on the subject of passing this tremendious barrier whic now present themselves to our view." <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> anxiously eyed the level of the <name type="place" key="Clearwater (Flathead, Kooskooskee) River">Clearwater River</name> for some hint that snows were melting. In a moment of frustration, he lashed out at "that icy barrier which seperates me from my friends and Country, from all which makes life esteemable—patience, patience." <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> might well have counseled patience for himself and the whole party. Both <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> and expedition hunters reported deep snows that might not melt until at least mid-June.<ref target="n0944" n="44"/>
               </p>
               <p>
As mid-June approached, the entire expedition busied itself preparing for the <name type="place" key="Lolo Trail">Lolo</name> assault. By June 6, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> felt certain that their food stocks were sufficient to meet any challenge on the trail. But two days later, all those hopes and plans suffered an unexpected setback. A <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> reported that the trail beyond <name type="place" key="Weippe Prairie (Camas Flats, Quawmash Flats)">Weippe Prairie</name> was still so deep with snow that any passage during June was courting disaster. As the Indian explained, "If we attempted it sooner our horses would be at least three days travel without food on the top of the mountain." <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> admitted, "This information is disagreeable inasmuch as it causes some doubt as to the time at which it will be proper for us to set out." A hurried and anguished meeting to discuss tactics must have followed that unwelcome <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> road report. When <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had held a similar talk in early June 1805 to decide whether the <name type="place" key="Marias River">Marias River</name> was the true <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> channel, they had made the right choice. But in a rush to get home, and increasingly fearful of delay, the captains now blundered into the wrong decision. "As we have no time to loose we will wrisk the chanches and set out as early as the Indians generally think practicable or the middle of this month." Risking the chances was dangerous enough; without Indian guides, the expedition was moving toward a rendezvous with the Lolo that not even the old <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> luck could overcome.<ref target="n0945" n="45"/>
               </p>
               <p>
The decision to leave <name type="place" key="Camp Chopunnish (Idaho)">Camp Chopunnish</name> against Indian advice and without guides was dead wrong, but it was very popular with the rank and file in the Corps of Discovery. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> insisted that "our party seem much elated with the idea of moving on towards their friends and Country, they all seem alirt in their movements today." But as the day of departure approached, both captains began to have second thoughts. "Even now," said <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, "I shudder with the expectation [of] great difficuelties in passing those Mountains." <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> was typically more explicit in his appraisal of the situation.
<quote>
	I am still apprehensive that the snow and the want of food for
	our horses will prove a serious imbarrassment to us as at
	least four days journey of our rout in these mountains lies
	over hights and along a ledge of mountains never intirely
	distititue of snow. Every body seems anxious to be in motion,
	convinced that we have not now any time to delay if the
	calculation is to reach the United States this season; this I
	am detirmined to accomplish if within the compass of human
	power.<ref target="n0946" n="46"/>
                  </quote>
That determination now brought <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> to risk their chances on what all remembered as a harsh, unforgiving trail.</p>
               <p>
On June 15, the explorers rode from <name type="place" key="Camp Chopunnish (Idaho)">Camp Chopunnish</name> to <name type="place" key="Weippe Prairie (Camas Flats, Quawmash Flats)">Weippe Prairie</name>. Even that reasonably easy path proved hazardous as spring rains made the ground slippery. Fallen timber blocked much of the route and <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> was forced to concede that "our march [was] slow and extreemly laborious." On the following day, as the expedition moved to higher elevations, the full impact of snowy conditions on the trail became plain. Although the <name type="place" key="Lolo Trail">Lolo</name> vanished in deep snow, the expedition was determined to press on. But even <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> began to question such foolhardy valor, and at the end of an exhausting day wrote that the <name type="place" key="Bitterroot (Snow) Mountains">Bitterroot</name> snow "augers but unfavorably with rispect to the practicability of passing the mountains."<ref target="n0947" n="47"/>
               </p>
               <p>
June 17 proved a day of decision and defeat. Floundering in drifts sometimes twelve to fifteen feet deep, each member of the party musth have recalled those terrible days of September 1805 when it seemed the <name type="place" key="Lolo Trail">Lolo</name> would be a cold grave. With men near exhaustion and horses unable to breast the drifts, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> held another hurried conference. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> made the choices and chances painfully clear. "If we proceeded and should get bewildered in these mountains the certainty was that we should loose all our horses and consequently our baggage, instruments perhaps our papers and thus eminently wrisk the loss of the discoveries which we had already made if we should be so fortunate as to escape with life." The needed on the compass of human power had swung about and now counseled retreat. Bested by the bitter snows, the expedition "a good deel dejected" turned around and headed back toward <name type="place" key="Weippe Prairie (Camas Flats, Quawmash Flats)">Weippe Prairie</name>, there to wait for Indian guides hired by <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name> and <name type="person" key="Shannon, George">Shannon</name>. <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Patrick Gass</name> caught the mood at the end of the day when he wrote that most in the party were "melancholy and disappointed." Camping that night in a chill rain that edged toward sleet, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> could only recall, "This is the first time since we have been on this long tour that we have ever been compelled to retreat or make a retrograde march."<ref target="n0948" n="48"/>
               </p>
               <p>
After the difficult and depressing trek back to <name type="place" key="Weippe Prairie (Camas Flats, Quawmash Flats)">Weippe Prairie</name>, the expedition's fortunes took an upward turn. <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name> brought three <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> guides into camp. In return for guns and ammunition, these men promised to direct the explorers at least as far as <name type="place" key="Lolo (Travelers' Rest) Creek (Mont.)">Travelers' Rest</name>. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> were told that a peace had been arranged between <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref>, <name type="native_nation" key="Walula Indians">Walula</name>, and <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Shoshoni.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshoni</name>
                  </ref> bands. But news about fresh engagements with <name type="native_nation" key="Atsina Indians">Atsina</name> warriors was troubling. The <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> guides claimed that hostile raiders had recently killed many <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Shoshoni.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshonis</name>
                  </ref> and <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Flathead.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Flatheads</name>
                  </ref>. Those deaths added both danger and urgency to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> diplomacy on the <name type="place" key="Marias River">Marias</name>.<ref target="n0949" n="49"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Led by experienced <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perces</name>
                  </ref>, the expedition made a safe and swift passage over those tremendous mountains. By June 29 the explorers were at the <name type="place" key="Lolo Hot Springs">Lolo Hot Springs</name> enjoying the recuperative powers of steaming water on aching muscles and bruised feet. Once at <name type="place" key="Lolo (Travelers' Rest) Creek (Mont.)">Travelers' Rest</name> on July 1, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> put the final touches on an intricate plan that promised to fulfill many of their objectives and test their field skills.</p>
               <p>
The captains "consurted" the following strategy. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> would take a small party overland to the <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Great Falls of the">Great Falls</name> of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> "by the most direct route." Privates <name type="person" key="Thompson, John B.">Thompson</name>, <name type="person" key="Goodrich, Silas">Goodrich</name>, and McNeal would remain at the falls to retrieve and refurbish equipment cached in 1805. In the meantime, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> would take a handful of volunteers up the <name type="place" key="Marias River">Marias River</name> to chart its northern course, explore the country, and contact the Blackfeet and Atsina Indians. After that dangerous reconnaissance, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> hoped to rejoin the <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Great Falls of the">Great Falls</name> detachment on the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> for a grand reunion with <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> party at the mouth of the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone</name>.</p>
               <p>
Although <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> Blackfeet adventure on the <name type="place"
                        key="Two Medicine River (Main or South Branch Marias River)">Two Medicine River</name> was more dramatic than anything <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> undertook, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> assignment was every bit as important. He was to proceed south from <name type="place" key="Lolo (Travelers' Rest) Creek (Mont.)">Travelers' Rest</name> through the <name type="place" key="Bitterroot Valley">Bitterroot Valley</name> and eventually cross the <name type="place" key="Continental Divide">Great Divide</name> to <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Three Forks of the">Three Forks</name>. At the forks, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> planned to take his party overland to find the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone</name> and explore its course to the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>. At the same time, a group under <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name> would travel by canoe from <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Three Forks of the">Three Forks</name> to <name type="place" key="Columbia River, Great Falls of the">Great Falls</name> for a linkup with the men left by <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>. Eventually the whole Corps of Discovery would reassemble at the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone</name>-<name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> confluence.<ref target="n0950" n="50"/>
               </p>
               <p>
One last detail remained to be done that day at <name type="place" key="Lolo (Travelers' Rest) Creek (Mont.)">Travelers' Rest</name>. Thinking about the complex diplomacy ahead with <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri River</name> villagers and <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> bands, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> decided that the Nor'Wester <name type="person" key="Heney, Hugh">Hugh Heney</name> might prove a valuable ally in the struggle either to win or to cow the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref>. In a long letter to <name type="person" key="Heney, Hugh">Heney</name>, the explorers offered him the office of Indian agent. More specifically, the captains wanted the trader to use his influence to wean <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> chiefs away from British merchants like Murdoch Cameron and bring them into the <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> trade system. At the same time, they hoped <name type="person" key="Heney, Hugh">Heney</name> could organize a delegation of chiefs and elders for a journey to <name type="place" key="Washington D.C.">Washington</name>. Reflecting <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> ideas on American trade along the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, the letter urged <name type="person" key="Heney, Hugh">Heney</name> to employ every means to pacify or at least neutralize <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name> power. So long as the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> choked traffic from <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>, the American fur trade would slowly die. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> explained to <name type="person" key="Heney, Hugh">Heney</name> that American Indian policy was based on peace and reconciliation. But the iron fist of coercion was undisguised in the letter. If the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> did not allow passage of American trade goods, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> were "positive that she [the United States] will not long suffer her citizens to be deprived of the free navigation of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> by a fiew comparatively feeble bands of Savages who be so illy advised as to refuse her profered friendship and continue their depridation on her citizens who may in future assend or decend the river." The captains' claims that <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> warriors amounted to "comparatively feeble bands of Savages" would have surprised men like <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo</name> and the <name type="person" key="Partisan">Partisan</name> who had effectively derailed American policy two years before. The letter suggests that when it came to understanding plains Indian politics, the explorers had still not learned the lessons of the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name> confrontation.<ref target="n0951" n="51"/>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>
One day after leaving <name type="place" key="Lolo (Travelers' Rest) Creek (Mont.)">Travelers' Rest</name>, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and his party were reminded of the dangers that lay ahead. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> knew that entering <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Atsina Indians">Atsina</name> territories was risky, but when his <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>
                  </ref> guides left him and warned that the "Pahkees" would "cut us off," the full weight of that danger came home. Two days later, when <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and his men were at the <name type="place" key="Blackfoot (East Fork Clark's) River">Big Blackfoot River</name>, they saw so many abandoned lodges as to become "much on our guard both day and night." <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> concern was justified, but by the time his detachment reached the <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">Great Falls of the Missouri</name> on July 15, they still had seen no Indians. Once at the falls, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> selected <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">Reuben</name> and <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Joseph Field</name> and <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">George Drouillard</name> to take part in what was to be the most violent Indian encounter in expedition history.<ref target="n0952" n="52"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Leaving <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Great Falls of the">Great Falls</name> on July 17, the explorers rode northwest, believing this route would bring them to the <name type="place" key="Teton (Rose, Tansy) River">Teton</name> or <name type="place" key="Teton (Rose, Tansy) River">Rose River</name> and then on to the <name type="place" key="Marias River">Marias</name>. On <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name> shortgrass plains as flat as "a well shaved bowling green," <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and his men maintained a "strict lookout" for any Indians. By July 21 a disappointed <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> realized that the course of the <name type="place" key="Marias River">Marias</name> was not as northward as he had hoped. That unhappy discovery was overshadowed on the following days as the explorers found more signs that Indians were nearby. When the ever-watchful <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name> located a cluster of eleven recently abandoned skin lodges, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> assumed that these were made by <name type="native_nation" key="Atsina Indians">Atsina</name> buffalo hunters camped along the main branch of the <name type="place" key="Marias River">Marias</name>. At <name type="place" key="Camp Disappointment (Mont.)">Camp Disappointment</name> on July 25, there were even more traces of recent native presence. As he had once before, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> wrote that he was "extreemly fortunate in not having met with these people."<ref target="n0953" n="53"/>
               </p>
               <p>
The captain's good fortune ran out the next day, July 27. Leaving <name type="place" key="Camp Disappointment (Mont.)">Camp Disappointment</name>, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> rode with the <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph and Reubin">Field brothers</name> while <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name> scouted the <name type="place"
                        key="Two Medicine River (Main or South Branch Marias River)">Two Medicine River</name> valley. At midafternoon, as <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> forded <name type="place" key="Badger Creek (Mont.)">Badger Creek</name> and came up a sharp rise, he spotted to his far left some thirty horses, about half having saddles. The captain quickly drew out his small telescope for a closer look. He saw "a very unpleasant sight." Standing out against the afternoon sky were several Indians looking intently down toward the <name type="place"
                        key="Two Medicine River (Main or South Branch Marias River)">Two Medicine River</name> valley and its cottonwood fringe. These Indians were so fixed on watching <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name> that they did not appear to notice <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and his companions. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> immediately decided to make the best of an uncertain situation and proceeded to "approach them in a friendly way."<ref target="n0954" n="54"/>
               </p>
               <p>
To signal their intention, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> sent <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Joseph Field</name> riding on ahead with an American flag. At that moment, the Indians saw the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> forces and became frightened. As <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> later explained, they "appeared to run about in a very confused manner as if much allarmed." Plainly fearing an attack, several Indians came down toward the horses and drove them back up to the summit. If the Indians were fearful of hostilities, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> was equally concerned. He believed that there might be at least as many warriors as there were horses—surely a daunting thought. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> was also convinced that any attempt to escape from such a large, well-armed war party would invite disaster. Riding on, the Americans came to within a quarter of a mile of the warriors before the Indians made any move toward them.</p>
               <p>
Some hint of what was going on in the minds of the <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians, Piegan">Piegan</name> warriors comes from an interview conducted in the early 1900s by the ethnologist George Bird Grinnell with an elderly <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians, Piegan">Piegan</name> named Wolf Calf. Wolf Calf was the youngest member of the war party, and his recollections of that meeting with <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> were still vivid and remarkably accurate. The Indian admitted that his companions were both surprised and frightened when they saw <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> men but decided to act in "a friendly fashion" for at least a short time. That decision was made plain when one Indian galloped toward <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> at full tilt. Seeing this and understanding it was not a general charge, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> dismounted and extended his hand to the <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians, Piegan">Piegan</name>. The warrior eyed <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and then cantered his horse back to the main <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name> group. Whatever this scout said to his fellows was not recorded by Wolf Calf, but the fact that all eight soon came riding to meet the Americans perhaps suggests that the Indians were now confident of their own security.</p>
               <p>
As the <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name> neared <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and the <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph and Reubin">Field brothers</name>, the captain remained certain that additional warriors were still hiding close at hand. Claiming an expertise that was not really his, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> told <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Joseph</name> and <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">Reuben</name> that these Indians were <name type="native_nation" key="Atsina Indians">"Minnetarees of Fort de Prairie" or Atsinas</name>. Using language filled with more swagger than wisdom, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> pronounced his willingness to "resist to the last extremity prefering death to that of being deprived of my papers instruments and gun." <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, once again on his horse, advanced slowly and met the one Indian who was ahead of the rest. Both men cautiously shook hands and then moved on to use the same welcome with those behind. This accomplished, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> dismounted. Perhaps thinking this signaled the beginning of a parley, the Indians asked for pipes and tobacco. Those supplies were with <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name> who was still down along the <name type="place"
                        key="Two Medicine River (Main or South Branch Marias River)">Two Medicine</name>. While one Indian joined <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">Reuben Field</name> to find <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name>, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> tried his hand at some sign language. Inquiring as to what tribe these men belonged, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> understood their answer to be that they were <name type="native_nation" key="Atsina Indians">Atsinas</name>. Although unquestionably they were <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians, Piegan">Piegans</name>, there are two possible explanations for <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> faulty identification. Because the expedition's most skilled sign language interpreter was still down in the river valley, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> may have simply misunderstood what was being signed. It is equally possible that the <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians, Piegan">Piegans</name>, already thinking about stealing guns and horses, hoped to shift the blame on other Indians. Whatever the case, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> attempt at conversation as well as his handing out of medals, flags, and handkerchiefs did little to calm the edgy <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians, Piegan">Piegans</name>. They seemed "more allarmed at this accedental interview than we were." Still worried about more warriors, and with evening approaching, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> suggested leaving high ground for a camp nearer the river. Guiding their horses down steep bluffs made more dangerous by loose, slippery gravel, the explorers and their nervous <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name> hosts made their way to three solitary cottonwood trees near the <name type="place"
                        key="Two Medicine River (Main or South Branch Marias River)">Two Medicine River</name>.</p>
               <p>
At those trees which still stand near the river, the <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name> put up a makeshift shelter of buffalo skins. Then the Indians invited <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> party to join them. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> was anxious to learn as much as possible from the <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians, Piegan">Piegans</name>. Using <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard's</name> signs, he conducted "much conversation" inside the hide wickiup that night. The <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name> said that they were part of a large band camped along the <name type="place" key="Marias River">Marias</name>. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> must have perked up when he heard that this band had a white trader in camp. He may well have urged <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name> to press the <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians, Piegan">Piegans</name> for more details about <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name>-Canadian trade. What <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> learned simply reenforced <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Jefferson's</name> worst fears. Agents of the Hudson's Bay Company and the North West Company were firmly entrenched on the northern plains and were rapidly extending their influence throughout the region. The <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name> made regular visits to posts like <name type="place" key="Buckingham House">Buckingham House</name> and <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountain House">Rocky Mountain House</name> along the <name type="place" key="Saskatchewan River">North Saskatchewan River</name>. Those Indians brought to the "Northern White Men" wolf and beaver pelts for guns, ammunition, and alcohol. Their loyalty to the Canadians made it clear that American fur traders would find this part of the northern plains a hard market to crack.<ref target="n0955" n="55"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Although what <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> heard form the <name type="person" key="Blackfeet Indians, Piegan">Piegans</name> worried him, what he said frightened them. Explaining that he came from the east and had been beyond the mountains to the great ocean, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> unwittingly dropped a geo-political bombshell by declaring that the <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet's</name> traditional enemies—the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_NezPerce.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perces</name>
                  </ref>, <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Shoshoni.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshonis</name>
                  </ref>, and <name type="native_nation" key="Kutenai Indians">Kutenais</name>—were now united by an American-inspired peace. Even more shocking to <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians, Piegan">Piegan</name> ears was word that these united tribes would be getting guns and supplies from Yankee traders. If <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> thought the <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name> would receive such news with glad hearts and then join an American alliance, he gravely misjudged western realities. That night along the <name type="place"
                        key="Two Medicine River (Main or South Branch Marias River)">Two Medicine</name> the explorer, in effect, announced the clash of empires had come to the <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name>. After more than twenty years of unchallenged power on the plains made possible by Canadian guns, the <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name> now faced a profound threat to their power and survival. Unaware that this was a frontal assault on <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name> influence, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> invited the warriors to help form a delegation of chiefs and elders for additional talks in <name type="place" key="Washington D.C.">Washington</name>. To make that offer more attractive, he promised ten horses and much tobacco to those who ventured east to see the great chief of the seventeen fires. But all this naive talk did not hide the fact that <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and his men were among well-armed <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians, Piegan">Piegans</name> whose intentions were unclear. Had the captain known what young Wolf Calf knew that night—that a decision had been made to steal the expedition's guns—the explorer might have doubled the watch.<ref target="n0956" n="56"/>
               </p>
               <p>
In the chill dawn hours of July 27, <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Joseph Field</name> struggled to fight back sleep and keep his watch. As soon as it was light, the <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians, Piegan">Piegans</name> were up and crowding around the fire. Intent on watching them, <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Field</name> carelessly laid his gun behind him and close to his sleeping brother <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">Reuben</name>. One of the Indians, seeing the gun unguarded, slipped behind <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Joseph</name> and quietly took the weapon. That act was a signal for other Indians to take guns belonging to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name>. Still unnoticed, the <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians, Piegan">Piegans</name> then attempted to make good their escape with valuable booty. It was only then that <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Joseph Field</name> saw what was happening and shouted to rouse his sleeping brother. <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">Reuben</name>, armed only with a broad-blade knife, gave angry chase. He proved a faster runner than a <name type="person" key="Blackfeet Indians, Piegan">Piegan</name> named <name type="person" key="Sidehill Calf">Side Hill Calf</name>. <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph">Field</name> caught the Indian, pulled the guns away, and in a moment of fury thrust his knife into the man's chest. When an excited <name type="person" key="Field, Reubin">Reuben Field</name> told <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">John Ordway</name> late the next day about the deed, he said that <name type="person" key="Sidehill Calf">Side Hill Calf</name> "drew but one breath [and] the wind of his breath followed the knife and he fell dead."</p>
               <p>
But <name type="person" key="Sidehill Calf">Side Hill Calf's</name> violent end was only the beginning of confusion and bloodletting around the lonely cottonwoods. Awakened by all the shouting, <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name> saw an Indian making off with his rifle and shot pouch. Springing up, the Frenchman yelled, "Damn you let go my gun," and wrested it from the <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians, Piegan">Piegan's</name> hands. That shout awakened <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, who by his own admission had been in "a profound sleep." Still groggy, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> demanded to know what was going on. What he saw was explanation enough as <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name> scuffled with the Indian. Going to aid the interpreter, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> reached for his rifle only to find it missing. He then drew his horse pistol and began to run after one of the fleeing <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians, Piegan">Piegans</name>. Quickly overtaking him, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> leveled his pistol at the Indian and demanded return of the rifle. The hapless thief was about to do as ordered when the <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph and Reubin">Field brothers</name>, still boiling with anger, came up and asked permission to shoot the Indian. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> wisely refused a similar request from <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name>, who had now captured the would-be robber of his weapon.</p>
               <p>
It now appeared that the <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians, Piegan">Piegan</name> plan had been thwarted and the <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name> might quietly retire. If <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> believed that, he was soon jolted back to a harsher reality. Once the Indians saw that the Americans had all their guns back, the <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name> turned their attention to the expedition's horses. Losing guns was serious enough, but without horses <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and his men would be stranded in a difficult country. For the <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians, Piegan">Piegans</name>, it seemed a last chance to rescue some honor and bring home valuable prizes. Now they threatened the survival of the American detachment and the ultimate success of the whole western venture. Understanding the stakes, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> ordered his men to open fire on any Indians trying to make off with horses. Whie the <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph and Reubin">Field brothers</name> and <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name> pursued some <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name>, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> ran after two <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians, Piegan">Piegans</name> doing just that. Nearly out of breath from the long dash, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> called on the Indians to release the stolen horses or he would fire. One Indian hid behind some mushroom-shaped rocks and called to his friend, standing about thirty paces from <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>. That armed Indian suddenly turned around and squarely faced <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>. Certain he was about to be attacked, the captain shot his adversary through the stomach. Stunned by what was plainly a mortal wound, the warrior fell to his knees. Then suddenly he raised himself up on one elbow and fired a desperate shot at <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>. But from his awkward position the dying man could not take clean aim and the ball went whistling just over the captain's head. "Being bearheaded," recalled <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, "I felt the wind of his bullet very distinctly."</p>
               <p>
As quickly as the <name type="place"
                        key="Two Medicine River (Main or South Branch Marias River)">Two Medicine</name> fight had exploded in two deaths, it was over. Whatever the combatants on both sides felt about each other, all were united by a common desire—to escape as quickly as possible. Fleeing north, the six surviving <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians, Piegan">Piegans</name> must have feared that more armed whites were on the way. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> was equally fearful of <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name> revenge. He ordered the horses rounded up and decided to use the stronger Indian ones to make good a speedy escape. While <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name> and the <name type="person" key="Field, Joseph and Reubin">Field brothers</name> prepared the horses, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> gathered up shields, bows, and arrows abandoned by the <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians, Piegan">Piegans</name>. He burned the weapons and in a final act of defiance put a peace medal around <name type="person" key="Sidehill Calf">Side Hill Calf's</name> neck so that "they might be informed who we were." As if to count coup on the <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name>, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> cut off the amulets from the shields and took them along as spoils of war.<ref target="n0957" n="57"/>
               </p>
               <p>
What remained now was to escape the <name type="place"
                        key="Two Medicine River (Main or South Branch Marias River)">Two Medicine</name> killing ground. Ahead lay two full days of hard riding over broken ground to reach <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway's</name> party on the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>. When <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and his men finally reached the great river on the afternoon of July 28, they had "the unspeakable satisfaction to see our canoes coming down." <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and his tired companions left behind at the <name type="place"
                        key="Two Medicine River (Main or South Branch Marias River)">Two Medicine</name> the seed of a myth that has long shaped popular understanding of the <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name> fight. That myth links the <name type="place"
                        key="Two Medicine River (Main or South Branch Marias River)">Two Medicine</name> encounter with later <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name>-American hostilities. As the story goes, the violence directed against American fur traders in the years after <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> was the result of <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians, Piegan">Piegan</name> revenge wreaked on the killers of <name type="person" key="Sidehill Calf">Side Hill Calf</name> and his unnamed fellow warrior. The death of <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">George Drouillard</name> at <name type="place" key="Missouri River, Three Forks of the">Three Forks</name> in 1810 at the hands of a <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name> war party has been used to strengthen the claim for an undying Indian vengeance.</p>
               <p>
The <name type="native_nation"
                        key="Two Medicine River (Main or South Branch Marias River)">Two Medicine</name> myth was not the product of anything either the explorers or their contemporaries wrote about the fight or about later trapper troubles. Rather, the tale appears to have its genesis in the fertile imagination of Washington Irving. In his <hi rend="italic">Astoria,</hi> Irving claimed that the <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name> had "conceived an implacable hostility to the white men, in consequence of one of their warriors having been killed by <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Lewis</name>, while attempting to steal horses." When David H. Coyner published his <hi rend="italic">The Lost Trappers</hi> in 1847, he repeated Irving's claim and added, "The act created an implacable hatred for the whites from that day till this." By the time Elliott Coues produced his edition of <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Nicholas Biddle's</name>
                  <hi rend="italic">History</hi> in 1893, the legend was in full bloom. Coues gave his stamp of approval to the tale in a footnote citing the Irving account and stories he heard on the northern <name type="place" key="Montana">Montana</name> frontier in 1874. Although historians from Hiram Chittenden to more recent scholars have discredited this interpretation of native behavior and have suggested more persuasive explanations, the myth continues to be repeated in popular accounts of the expedition as well as in an occasional serious study.<ref target="n0958" n="58"/>
               </p>
               <p>
As Alvin Josephy, Jr., pointed out in 1965, the key to understanding <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name> actions toward American traders comes from something <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> himself said that July night around the fire along the <name type="place"
                        key="Two Medicine River (Main or South Branch Marias River)">Two Medicine</name>. After telling the <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians, Piegan">Piegans</name> that their traditional enemies had been united in a peace promoted by American diplomats, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> dropped the other shoe. Traders from <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> were going to sell guns to those united tribes, thus challenging the place of the <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians, Piegan">Piegan</name>, <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians, Blood">Blood</name>, and <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians, Proper">Siksika</name> peoples. All of that seemed to come terribly true in subsequent years. By 1807–1808, men working for <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> entrepreneurs were busy trading with <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name> rivals. When a former member of the expedition, <name type="native_nation" key="Colter, John">John Colter</name>, joined in an 1808 battle with <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Crow.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Crow Indians">Crow</name>
                  </ref> and <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Flathead.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Flathead Indians">Flathead</name>
                  </ref> warriors against the <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name>, the message was not lost on anyone. It may well have been that those merchants in places like <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountain House">Rocky Mountain House</name> saw to it that the import of that message was fully understood. In the face of a massive assault on their plains empire, <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name> warriors hardly had time to think of avenging Side Hill Calf and his unfortunate companion. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> was unwittingly the prophet of events like the 1821 Immell-Jones massacre; he was not their cause. The bloody fray on the morning of July 27 provides a window into the ever-unstable balance of plains power. Although <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name> revenge against Americans for the deeds of Reuben Field and <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Meriwether Lewis</name> may satisfy the modern writer's sense of historical symmetry, it was the more potent forces of guns and international trade that made the <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name> feared by a generation of American mountain men.<ref target="n0959" n="59"/>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>
It was not until noon on August 12, 1806, that the Corps of Discovery reassembled. Much had happened since those days at <name type="place" key="Lolo (Travelers' Rest) Creek (Mont.)">Travelers' Rest</name>. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> party had explored the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone</name>, the plan for <name type="person" key="Pryor, Nathaniel Hale">Pryor</name> to carry a letter to <name type="person" key="Heney, Hugh">Hugh Heney</name> had misfired when <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Crow.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Crow Indians">Crow</name>
                  </ref> Indians stole expedition horses, and <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> had been wounded in a freak hunting accident. But now on the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> below the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River">Yellowstone</name>, the company was whole again. What remained of its Indian business was the same thorny problem that had occupied so much time during the winter with the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Mandan.html"
                       rend="box">Mandans</ref>. Establishing peace among <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>, <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name>, and <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> villagers and the consequences of that peace were at the heart of that problem. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had not abandoned their commitment to a villager alliance aimed at eliminating or reducing <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> influence. The explorers thought they had successfully planted the seeds of that policy during their first winter. In truth, the alliance and the tactics to execute it were no more realistic in 1806 than they had been in 1804. But realism had never been part of the expedition's Indian policy. As the explorer-diplomats began their final talks with the Indians, there was no reason to think that they might suddenly understand the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> facts of life.<ref target="n0960" n="60"/>
               </p>
               <p>
For three days beginning on August 14, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark</name> carried on constant and sometimes difficult negotiations with <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> leaders. Neither cast nor lines had changed much since the explorers and the Indians had met during the winter of 1804–1805. The issues—trade, sovereignty, and the villager alliance—were the same. <name type="person" key="Black Cat (Posecopsahe)">Black Cat</name>, <name type="person" key="Big White (Sheheke)">Sheheke</name>, <name type="person" key="Black Moccasin (Omp-se-ha-ra)">Black Moccasin</name>, <name type="person" key="Little Crow (Ka-goh-ha-me)">Little Raven</name>, and <name type="person" key="Le Borgne (One Eye)">Le Borgne</name> were familiar faces from the earlier scene. Believing that the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> chief <name type="person" key="Black Cat (Posecopsahe)">Black Cat</name> was the key to American success, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> quickly sought him out after paying brief calls at the villages of <name type="place" key="Metaharta (Metehartar) village">Metaharta</name> and <name type="place" key="Mahawha (Marharha) village">Mahawha</name>. <name type="person" key="Black Cat (Posecopsahe)">Black Cat</name> greeted <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> with customary warmth, and together the two men shared a summer squash and smoked a friendly pipe.</p>
               <p>
Anxious to begin talks on the delegation issue as soon as possible, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> detailed <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name> to call on <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> chiefs while <name type="person" key="Drouillard, George">Drouillard</name> was sent to <name type="person" key="Big White (Sheheke)">Sheheke's</name> village to hire <name type="person" key="Jusseaume, René">René Jusseaume</name> as council interpreter. When <name type="person" key="Jusseaume, René">Jusseaume</name> arrived at the expedition's camp just above <name type="place" key="Mitutanka (Matootonha) village">Matootonha</name> village, the talks began. Following a familiar agenda, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> first renewed the invitation to visit <name type="place" key="Washington D.C.">Washington</name> and speak with the president. <name type="person" key="Black Cat (Posecopsahe)">Black Cat</name> agreed with such a journey would be important but insisted that the price in danger exacted by <name type="person" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name>
                  <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> warriors was too high. It was just those kinds of fears that <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> sought to allay. Claiming more power than either the expedition or the United States actually had, he told <name type="person" key="Black Cat (Posecopsahe)">Black Cat</name> that the Americans "would not suffer those Indians [the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref>] to hurt any of our red children who should think proper to accompany us." Bent on making promises even more difficult to keep, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> offered continued federal military protection against hostile raiders after the chiefs returned home. To make American proposals more palatable, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> reminded <name type="person" key="Black Cat (Posecopsahe)">Black Cat</name> that there would be lavish gifts for all who ventured so far from home.</p>
               <p>
This exchange was interrupted by the arrival of <name type="person" key="Le Borgne (One Eye)">Le Borgne</name>. If there was one man the explorers had failed to impress during the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> winter, it was this powerful and astute <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> chief. That <name type="person" key="Le Borgne (One Eye)">Le Borgne</name> now came without much coaxing illustrated his recognition that some accommodation might be necessary with the persistent strangers from downriver. Knowing how important this moment was, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> rounded up whatever other chiefs he could find and assembled them along the riverbank. With <name type="person" key="Jusseaume, René">Jusseaume</name> as interpreter, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> once again repeated the familiar litany of American proposals. Delegations could see for themselves the wealth and power of the American nation. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> encouraged quick action on the invitation, hinting that a prompt decision would hasten the arrival of quality trade goods at reasonable prices.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Le Borgne (One Eye)">Le Borgne's</name> reply was characterized by the kind of political acumen that marked so much of his diplomacy with both Indians and whites. He showed some passing interest in making the long trip to <name type="place" key="Washington D.C.">Washington</name> but insisted that dangers posed by the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> made the journey far too harzardous. "The <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> were in the road," he said, "and would most certainly kill him or any others who should go down." Suddenly turning the negotiating tables, the chief observed that the American claim to have brought peace to the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> was not true. <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> warriors had recently killed eight <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name> and taken some horses. And there had been renewed tension with the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name>. If <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> were peacemakers of dubious repute, <name type="person" key="Le Borgne (One Eye)">Le Borgne</name> boasted that he had done much better. The chief had recently negotiated a complex trade agreement with the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Cheyenne.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Cheyenne Indians">Cheyennes</name>
                  </ref>. When the Americans pacified the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name>
                  <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref>, then <name type="person" key="Le Borgne (One Eye)">Le Borgne</name> might consider a visit to the federal father.<ref target="n0961" n="61"/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> must have finally realized that <name type="person" key="Le Borgne (One Eye)">Le Borgne</name> was not a likely prospect for conversion to client-chief status. But there was always <name type="person" key="Black Cat (Posecopsahe)">Black Cat</name>. When he asked <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> to make a second visit to <name type="place" key="Ruptáre (Rooptahee) village">Rooptahee</name>, the captain may have taken new hope that the delegation problem was nearing some solution. As the two men again shared a pipe, <name type="person" key="Black Cat (Posecopsahe)">Black Cat</name> broke the news <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> most feared. Because "the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> were still very troublesom," not a single prominent man was willing to risk a <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> voyage. <name type="person" key="Black Cat (Posecopsahe)">Black Cat</name> tried to soften the blow by offering twelve bushels of corn from what had been a slim harvest. But that well-meaning gesture could not hide a serious failure of the expedition. Plainly disappointed, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> urged the chief and his elders to "pitch on some man which they could rely and send him to see their great father." After more objections were aired, one young man stepped forward and agreed to go. But when <name type="person" key="Gibson, George">George Gibson</name> reported that the man had taken his knife, all fury broke loose. For all the comic overtones in a process that seemed to move two steps back for every one forward, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> was justifiable angry. Tongue-lashed by <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, the chief and elders hung their heads. <name type="person" key="Black Cat (Posecopsahe)">Black Cat</name> broke the painful silence and admitted that fear of <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> ambushes and reprisal made it impossible for anyone to accompany the expedition. At last <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> seemed to grasp the depth of <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> concern. To his credit, he gracefully accepted the inevitable and quietly spent more time smoking with <name type="person" key="Black Cat (Posecopsahe)">Black Cat</name>.</p>
               <p>
Later the same day, August 15, <name type="person" key="Jusseaume, René">Jusseaume</name> brought some startling news. The Frenchman claimed that <name type="person" key="Little Crow (Ka-goh-ha-me)">Little Raven</name>, second chief at <name type="place" key="Mitutanka (Matootonha) village">Matootonha</name>, had expressed a desire to go with the expedition. After so many false starts and setbacks, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> was determined not to let this opportunity slip away. Taking <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name> with him, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> hurried to the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> village for a talk with <name type="person" key="Little Crow (Ka-goh-ha-me)">Little Raven</name>. The chief acknowledged his interest in the journey but wanted to talk with friends and family before setting out on so dangerous a course. A pipe of tobacco moved that intention along and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> returned to his camp thinking the delegation issue settled at last.</p>
               <p>
What <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> heard late that night made the need for any diplomatic success even more urgent. Since returning to the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> villages, <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name> had spent some time at <name type="place" key="Metaharta (Metehartar) village">Metaharta</name>, where he and <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea</name> had lived before joining the expedition. From those contacts he had learned that several <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> war parties had gone out against <name type="person" key="Cameahwait">Camehwait's</name>
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians, Lemhi">Lemhi</name>
                  <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Shoshoni.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshonis</name>
                  </ref> and the <name type="place"
                        key="Grand (We-tar-hoo and similar spellings) River (S. Dak.)">Grand River</name>
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name>. Such news plainly demonstrated the fragile character of any villager alliance. Even more worrisome, continued <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> forays against the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Shoshoni.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshonis</name>
                  </ref> and other potential American allies could only subvert and discredit diplomatic efforts made over the past two years. A symbolic gesture in the form of a <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>-<name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> delegation could not change old patterns of warfare, but it might rescue the expedition's diplomatic reputation.<ref target="n0962" n="62"/>
               </p>
               <p>
On August 16, compelled by a sense of desperation, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> made one last effort to fashion a respectable delegation. When <name type="person" key="Le Borgne (One Eye)">Le Borgne</name> and several other <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> chiefs appeared uninvited at the American camp, he was given a rare opportunity. Here was a final chance to impress <name type="person" key="Le Borgne (One Eye)">Le Borgne</name> and perhaps bring him into the federal fold. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> may have even dared to hope that at least one <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> might join <name type="person" key="Little Crow (Ka-goh-ha-me)">Little Raven</name> to form a genuinely representative delegation. Pulling out all the ceremonial stops, the captains decided to give <name type="person" key="Le Borgne (One Eye)">Le Borgne</name> one of the swivel guns that had originally been on the keelboat. As <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had the cannon loaded, he offered a double-barreled message. Raids against the "pore defenceless <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Snake Indians</name>" had to stop, and such a potent weapon could always be used to defend American friends.</p>
               <p>
Although <name type="person" key="Le Borgne (One Eye)">Le Borgne</name> was plainly pleased with the gift, it was the elderly chief <name type="person" key="Cherry Grows on a Bush (Caltarcota)">Caltarcota</name> who now replied to <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>. The <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> orator, who had so effectively challenged the expedition's diplomacy two years before, now repeated what must have been painfully familiar to all the explorers. The <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name> wanted to see the great father, but so long as the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> stood in the way such a trip was impossible. But <name type="person" key="Cherry Grows on a Bush (Caltarcota)">Caltarcota</name> had more to say and more than <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> wanted to hear. The <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> chief had been opposed to an <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> peace and lessening of tensions with the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name>
                  <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> in 1804, and nothing he had heard since had changed his mind. Raids against enemies were both strategically wise and culturally necessary. The <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name> were not about to alter old ways and endanger village security simply to please the seemingly odd whims of unpredictable strangers. There would be no <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> representatives, nor would there be any promises of peace and cooperation. <name type="person" key="Le Borgne (One Eye)">Le Borgne</name> proudly took the cannon back to his village, but as was so often the case, the American diplomats were left with empty hands and empty promises.</p>
               <p>
For all the disappointment with the <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name>, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> felt certain that he still had <name type="person" key="Little Crow (Ka-goh-ha-me)">Little Raven</name> as a token delegate. Later on the evening of August 16, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> walked to <name type="place" key="Mitutanka (Matootonha) village">Matootonha</name> to keep up the chief's resolve. To his astonishment, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> was bluntly told that <name type="person" key="Little Crow (Ka-goh-ha-me)">Little Raven</name> had changed his mind and would not accompany the expedition downriver. Not even a gift of a flag could change the Indian's mind. When <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> pressed <name type="person" key="Jusseaume, René">Jusseaume</name> to find reasons for this unwelcome change of heart, the interpreter reported that there had been a serious argument between <name type="person" key="Big White (Sheheke)">Sheheke</name> and <name type="person" key="Little Crow (Ka-goh-ha-me)">Little Raven</name>. <name type="person" key="Big White (Sheheke)">Sheheke</name> was evidently jealous of the prestige offered to <name type="person" key="Little Crow (Ka-goh-ha-me)">Little Raven</name>. At this point a frustrated <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> simply did not care who the delegate was so long as he was of sufficient rank and influence. Turning again to <name type="person" key="Jusseaume, René">Jusseaume</name>, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> asked him to use his influence to enlist <name type="person" key="Big White (Sheheke)">Sheheke</name> in the expedition's ranks. The trader, a man always in search of the main chance, drove a hard bargain. He promised to deliver <name type="person" key="Big White (Sheheke)">Sheheke</name> if the Americans agreed to provide transportation and rations for the <name type="person" key="Big White (Sheheke)">Sheheke</name> and <name type="person" key="Jusseaume, René">Jusseaume</name> families. Worn down by days of fruitless talk and seeing no alternatives, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> grudgingly agreed.<ref target="n0963" n="63"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Saturday, August 17, was a day to tie up loose ends. There were brief but inconclusive talks with some <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> chiefs, financial settlements with <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name> and a fur trade-bound <name type="person" key="Colter, John">John Colter</name>, and some poignant words from <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> about the future of <name type="person" key="Sacagawea">Sacagawea's</name> young <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Jean Baptiste">Jean Baptiste Charbonneau</name>, "a butifull promising child." By midmorning the expedition was at <name type="place" key="Mitutanka (Matootonha) village">Matootonha</name> to pick up the <name type="person" key="Big White (Sheheke)">Sheheke</name> and <name type="person" key="Jusseaume, René">Jusseaume</name> entourages. The explorers were already anticipating the joys of a festive homecoming, but when <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> came to <name type="person" key="Big White (Sheheke)">Sheheke's</name> lodge he saw what it meant for the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> chief to leave for an uncertain future. Grim-faced elders sat smoking farewell pipes while women wept. Despite <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> efforts to reassure the villagers with gifts of powder and bullets, "maney of them cried out aloud" as <name type="person" key="Big White (Sheheke)">Sheheke</name> and his family went to the canoes. Tears and gunpowder were not the sort of legacy <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> wanted to leave behind.<ref target="n0964" n="64"/>
               </p>
               <p>
Only one piece of Indian diplomacy was left before reaching <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>. The role of the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> in Middle <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> trade and politics had always eluded <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>. The explorers simply could not comprehend the intricate relationship between <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> farmers and <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> hunters. In the eyes of the explorers, the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> should have been willing recruits in the struggle against <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name> power. That <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> and Arikara warriors continued to carry out joint raids against <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> towns was bewildering. How could the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> pursue a policy that further bound them to their <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> oppressors? <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> hoped that the earlier delegation sent under <name type="person" key="Gravelines, Joseph">Joseph Gravelines</name>, and now the presence of <name type="person" key="Big White (Sheheke)">Sheheke</name>, might at last end the raids that fueled endless hostilities.</p>
               <p>
By the morning of August 21, the expedition was at the <name type="person"
                        key="Grand (We-tar-hoo and similar spellings) River (S. Dak.)">Grand River</name> and the Arikara villages. After exchanging volleys of shots in greeting, the Americans landed opposite the upper village of <name type="place" key="Waho-erha village">Waho-erha</name>. While securing their canoes, the explorers could not miss the white skin lodges that dotted the hillsides above the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> towns. Those tepees belonged to <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Cheyenne.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Cheyenne Indians">Cheyennes</name>
                  </ref> who regularly traded for <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> corn. <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> had met individual <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Cheyenne.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Cheyenne Indians">Cheyennes</name>
                  </ref> during the <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan (N. Dak.)">Fort Mandan</name> winter, but now there was a chance for serious talks with these important plains people. Once on shore, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> was greeted by a crowd of friendly and inquisitive <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> and <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Cheyenne.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Cheyenne Indians">Cheyennes</name>
                  </ref>.</p>
               <p>
Without further ceremony, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> decided to hold a council. Putting <name type="person" key="Big White (Sheheke)">Sheheke</name> to his left, he faced a semicircle of eager Indians. To symbolize the hoped-for peace between villages, <name type="person" key="Big White (Sheheke)">Sheheke</name> offered <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> tobacco for all to smoke. Encouraged by the acceptance of that gift, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> launched into a capsule history of the expedition, relating "where we had been, what we had done and said to the different nations." He was aided in that narrative by the presence of the trader and translator <name type="person" key="Garreau, Joseph">Joseph Garreau</name>. As <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> surveyed the assembled dignitaries, he may have noticed a man of substantial importance who had not been seen in October 1804. That man was <name type="person" key="Grey Eyes">Grey Eyes</name>, who had taken the place of <name type="person" key="Lighting Crow (Kakawissassa)">Kakawissassa</name> as principal chief and would lead defiance against American forces in 1823. After being introduced to <name type="person" key="Grey Eyes">Grey Eyes</name>, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> again emphasized the need for peace with neighbors and unity against the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref>. The <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> chief than delivered a "very animated" speech, filled with rhetorical sound and fury denouncing the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> as "bad people." But the sharp words were intended to please <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> and did not signify any change in <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> policy. <name type="person" key="Grey Eyes">Grey Eyes</name> certainly wished that the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> might be less troublesome at market times, but he was not about to alienate so strong and important a customer in order to please untested whites.</p>
               <p>
As the day grew hotter and the diplomacy less successful, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> was grateful when a <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Cheyenne.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Cheyenne Indians">Cheyenne</name>
                  </ref> chief invited him to enjoy the shade of a tepee. Making little progress with the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name>, the captain hoped for better with the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Cheyenne.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Cheyenne Indians">Cheyennes</name>
                  </ref>. After smoking with the chief, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> offered him a small peace medal. It was an awkward moment when the frightened chief firmly rejected the gift. "He knew that the white people were all medecine," explained <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, "and was afraid of the medal or anything that white people gave them." It was only with the greatest difficulty that <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> convinced the chief that flags and medals were signs of status and prestige, not carriers of disease and death. As things fell out, American diplomacy proved more successful with the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Cheyenne.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Cheyenne Indians">Cheyennes</name>
                  </ref> than the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name>. Just before leaving the villages on August 22, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> was approached by several <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Cheyenne.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Cheyenne Indians">Cheyenne</name>
                  </ref> chiefs who asked that American traders be sent among them to teach proper trapping techniques. That was the kind of request to gladden the heart of any <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> merchant.<ref target="n0965" n="65"/>
               </p>
               <p>
But <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Cheyenne.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Cheyenne Indians">Cheyenne</name>
                  </ref> requests were still in the future as <name type="person" key="Big White (Sheheke)">Sheheke</name>, who had accompanied <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> to the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Cheyenne.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Cheyenne Indians">Cheyenne</name>
                  </ref> camp, offered a long discourse on villager tensions—a diatribe that contained more self-justification than serius analysis. The <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan's</name> torrent of invective was finally checked when the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Cheyenne.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Cheyenne Indians">Cheyenne</name>
                  </ref> chief caustically observed that all the village folk shared a measure of blame. Never one to miss a chance to press the fundamentals of American Indian policy, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> again insisted that "if they wished to be happy they must shake off all intimecy with the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> and unite themselves in a strong alliance and attend to what he had told them." But, as before, American proposals got no more than token assent.</p>
               <p>
Unnoticed throughout the day was the growing tension caused by the presence of <name type="person" key="Big White (Sheheke)">Sheheke</name> and his family. They were constant reminders of all the blows and strikes the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> and the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Mandan.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>
                  </ref> had exchanged over the years. Resentment finally exploded late in the evening. <name type="person" key="Big White (Sheheke)">Sheheke</name> found himself embroiled in an acrimonious shouting match with an <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> chief named <name type="person" key="One Arm">One Arm</name>. Fearful that <name type="person" key="One Arm">One Arm's</name> "loud and thretening tone" might lead to violence, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> stepped in and reminded the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> that <name type="person" key="Big White (Sheheke)">Sheheke</name> was under American protection. Any harm done to him would bring a strong response from the expedition. That threat evidently worked since <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> finished the evening hearing <name type="person" key="One Arm">One Arm</name> and the other chiefs swear peace toward the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Mandan.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>
                  </ref> and loyalty to the United States.<ref target="n0966" n="66"/>
               </p>
               <p>
But their solemn oaths meant little. The next morning, as the expedition prepared to make the final pull for <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>, <name type="person" key="Garreau, Joseph">Garreau</name> reported that the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> chiefs had decided not to form another delegation until the first party had safely returned. And the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikara</name> leaders themselves again told <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> how dependent they were on the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name>
                  </ref> for guns and ammunition. Those were facts that not even the most adept diplomat could shape to fit an American mold. Except for the interest in the fur trade shown by the <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Cheyenne.html"
                       rend="box">
                     <name type="native_nation" key="Cheyenne Indians">Cheyennes</name>
                  </ref>, the expedition left the <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name> with little to call success.<ref target="n0967" n="67"/>
               </p>
               <p>
The next month saw <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> sprint for home. Moving quickly with the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> current, the expedition often covered fifty or sixty miles in a day. Despite unending mosquito attacks, sudden rain squalls, and sore eyes from river glare, the men "ply'd their orers very well." But <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo</name> and the Brulé <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Teton">Teton</name>
                  <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">Sioux</ref>, those most redoubtable of expedition adversaries, were not about to allow <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> to leave the river without one last set-to. At the end of August, as the Americans neared present-day <name type="place" key="Yankton, S. Dak.">Yankton</name>, <name type="place" key="South Dakota">South Dakota</name>, they spotted <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo</name> and a large band of well-armed men along the river bank. What ensued was a nasty verbal exchange that pitted <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> and <name type="person" key="Jusseaume, René">Jusseaume</name> against <name type="person" key="Black Buffalo (Un-tongar-Sar-bar)">Black Buffalo</name>. The jeering and hooting so unnerved the explorers that when they came upon some friendly <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians, Yankton">Yankton</name>
                  <ref target="http://lewisandclarkjournals.unl.edu/images_Sioux.html"
                       rend="box">Sioux</ref> two days later there was nearly fatal gunfire.</p>
               <p>
But raw nerves were soothed in the days that followed. Edginess was replaced by excitement. Every day brought fresh signs that the great venture—what <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> had once called "a darling project of mine"—was nearly done. New clothes, tobacco, and alcohol obtained from trader <name type="person" key="Aird, James">James Aird</name> brought the men of the expedition one step closer to home and further from the life they had shared for so long. And then in the third week of September there were the familiar sights and faces of <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name> and what had been the Corps of Discovery was about to escape into national history and myth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>
The final scene in a drama that had so long bound together the lives of Indians and explorers was played out on September 23 at <name type="place" key="Fort Bellefontaine (Mo.)">Fort Bellefontaine</name> along the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> above <name type="place" key="Saint Louis, Mo.">St. Louis</name>. Sentries on duty that cold, wet morning were perhaps the only audience as <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> escorted <name type="person" key="Big White (Sheheke)">Sheheke</name> to the "publick store" so that the Mandan chief could outfit himself and his family in the latest fashion.<ref target="n0968" n="68"/> As the Indian searched through stacks of calico shirts, fancy handkerchiefs, and colored beads, he symbolized the first fruits of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> expedition. The explorers brought Indian America face to face with the Industrial Revolution and a rising American empire. Still ahead for people from the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> to the <name type="place" key="Columbia River">Columbia</name> were more delegations, more talks, and more troubles. The calloused hands of the explorers had delivered the Indians into the finer fingers of agents, merchants, and bureaucrats. But, for now, none of that was clear to grizzled veterans or to an anxious Indians. For <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, there was only the homecoming reserved to those once feared lost and now found. Men of the expedition were about to reenter a familiar world; <name type="person" key="Big White (Sheheke)">Sheheke</name> and his kin could not say the same. The <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> chief, dressed in the best the young Republic could afford, did not know how much those explorers had forever changed his world.

</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="section">
            <head rend="center">Abbreviations</head>
            <p>
B A E       Bureau of American Ethnology</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">Field Notes.</hi>        Osgood, Ernest, S., ed. <hi rend="italic">The Field Notes of <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Captain William Clark</name>, 1803–1805.</hi> New Haven: Yale University Press, 1964.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal.</hi>        <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass, Patrick</name>. <hi rend="italic">A Journal of the Voyages and Travels of a Corps of Discovery.</hi> Edited by <name type="person" key="McKeehan, David">David McKeehan</name>. 1807. Reprint, with preface by Earle R. Forrest. Minneapolis: Ross and Haines, 1958.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal.</hi>        Quaife, Milo M., ed. <hi rend="italic">The Journals of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Captain Meriwether Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Sergeant John Ordway</name>.</hi> Madison: Historical Society of Wisconsin, 1916.</p>
            <p>
Thw.       Thwaites, Reuben G., ed. <hi rend="italic">The Original Journals of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition.</hi> 8 vols. New York: Dodd, Mead &amp; Co., 1904–1905.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Whitehouse</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal.</hi>        "The Journal of <name type="person" key="Whitehouse, Joseph">Private Joseph Whitehouse</name>." In Thw. 7:29–190.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="notes" type="notes">
            <head rend="center">Notes</head>
            <note xml:id="n0901" n="1">Thw. 4:227–28.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0902" n="2">Ibid. 4:235–39.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0903" n="3">Ibid. 4:259–60.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0904" n="4">Ibid. 4:266–68.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0905" n="5">Ibid. 4:273.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0906" n="6">Ibid. 4:284.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0907" n="7">Although the <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skilloot</name> villages were usually clustered around the <name type="place" key="Cowlitz (Coweliskee) River">Cowlitz River</name>, during the spring salmon runs many <name type="native_nation" key="Watlala Indians">Skilloots</name> buit temporary mat lodges at <name type="place" key="Columbia River, The Dalles of the (Great Narrows)">The Dalles</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0908" n="8">Thw. 4:288–90.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0909" n="9">Ibid. 4:292–94.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0910" n="10">Ibid. 4:296, 298–300.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0911" n="11">Ibid. 4:306–7.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0912" n="12">Ibid. 4:308–12.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0913" n="13">Ibid. 4:313.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0914" n="14">
               <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> p. 347; Thw. 4:317, 319, 321. The identity of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name>
               <name type="native_nation" key="Yakima Indians">Pishquitpahs</name> remains unclear. They were certainly not Salish-speaking <name type="native_nation" key="Pisquow Indians">Pishquows</name> as Thwaites claimed, Thw. 3:137. It seems more likely that they were Sahaptin speakers and a band of either <name type="native_nation" key="Cayuse Indians">Cayuses</name> or <name type="native_nation" key="Umatilla Indians">Umatillas</name>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0915" n="15">Thw. 4:328–29.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0916" n="16">"<name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name> Notes," 2:532; <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> p. 348; Thw. 4:331–32.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0917" n="17">Josephy, <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>,</hi> p. 11; Thw. 4:351–52.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0918" n="18">Thw. 4:354–55.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0919" n="19">Ibid. 4:357–60.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0920" n="20">Ibid. 4:371.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0921" n="21">Ibid. 5:4–9.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0922" n="22">Ibid. 5:14–16.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0923" n="23">
               <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> p. 356; Thw. 5:18–20.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0924" n="24">Josephy, <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>,</hi> pp. 11–14; Verne F. Ray, <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> and the <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name> Indians</hi> (Washington, D.C.: The Westerners, 1971), pp. 11–14; Thw. 5:23–27.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0925" n="25">Appleman, <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>,</hi> pp. 272–73; Peebles, <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> in <name type="place" key="Idaho">Idaho</name>,</hi> p. 30; Thw. 5:33–35.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0926" n="26">Thw. 5:30.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0927" n="27">Ibid. 5:52–53. What remains unclear in this arrangement is whether all food obtained by trade was put in a common stockpile or if each mess or individual was responsible for his own rations.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0928" n="28">
               <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> pp. 265–66; Thw. 5:86, 95.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0929" n="29">Thw. 5:98.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0930" n="30">
               <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> pp. 360–63; Thw. 5:99–100.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0931" n="31">Thw. 5:113.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0932" n="32">Ibid. 5:360–61.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0933" n="33">Thw. 4:359, 365, 5:27, 48, 50.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0934" n="34">Thw. 5:22. Modern medical opinion suggests that the chief was suffering from a variety of polymyositis. C. L. Thomas, ed., <hi rend="italic">Taber's Cyclopedic Medical Dictionary,</hi> 13th ed. (<name type="place" key="Philadelphia, Pa.">Philadelphia</name>: F. A. Davis Co., 1977), Ibid. 112, and personal communication with Charles McGowen, MD.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0935" n="35">Thw. 5:27, 62–63.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0936" n="36">Ibid. 5:63.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0937" n="37">Ibid. 5:67, 72.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0938" n="38">Ibid. 5:4, 11, 16, 29–31, 72.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0939" n="39">Ibid. 5:35, 49, 58, 68.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0940" n="40">Josephy, <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>,</hi> p. 14.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0941" n="41">Thw. 5:117.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0942" n="42">Ibid. 5:105–6.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0943" n="43">Ibid. 5:112–13.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0944" n="44">Ibid. 5:43, 46, 51, 53.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0945" n="45">Ibid. 5:95, 103, 113–14, 118. Although the journals do not offer a clear explanation for the lack of <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name> guides, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> told <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Nicholas Biddle</name>, "The reason of our having no guide was that the Indians had declared that the hills were impassable. One of them had attempted and returned we met him." "<name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name> Notes," 2:544.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0946" n="46">Thw. 5:134–35.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0947" n="47">Ibid. 5:135, 137.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0948" n="48">
               <name type="person" key="Gass, Patrick">Gass</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> p. 273; Thw. 5:141–42.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0949" n="49">Thw. 5:153, 156–58.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0950" n="50">Ibid. 5:175–80.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0951" n="51">
               <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> to <name type="person" key="Heney, Hugh">Heney</name>, July 20, 1806, Jackson, ed., <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 1:309–13. Donald Jackson's view that the July 20 draft is <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark's</name> copy of a document composed by <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>, probably on July 1, fits what is known about <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis'a</name> Indian policy.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0952" n="52">Thw. 5:188, 192, 203. The word "Pahkee" specifically referred to the <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians, Proper">Siksikas or Blackfeet-proper</name> but was often used by <name type="native_nation" key="Shoshone Indians">Shoshonis</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perces</name> to mean any plains enemy.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0953" n="53">Ibid. 5:207–208, 212, 215–17.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0954" n="54">The Indians that <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> saw were <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians, Piegan">Piegans</name>. <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians, Blood">Bloods</name>, <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians, Piegan">Piegans</name>, and <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians, Proper">Siksikas or Blackfeet-proper</name> were the three constituent tribes of the <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name> confederacy. The tribes were politely independent but united by a common language, common customs, and common enemies. See John C. Ewers, <hi rend="italic">The <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name>: Raiders on the Northwestern Plains</hi> (Norman: University of Oklahoma Press, 1958), pp. 3–18.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0955" n="55">For the rise and growth of the <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name> trade, see Ewers, <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name>,</hi> pp. 19–44 and E. E. Rich, <hi rend="italic">The Fur Trade and the Northwest to 1857</hi> (Toronto: McClelland and Stewart, 1967), pp. 122–29.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0956" n="56">Thw. 5:219–23. Wolf Calf's talk with Grinnell is recorded in Wheeler, <hi rend="italic">Trail of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>,</hi> 2:311-12. A second and less accurate account from <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name> tradition can be found in James H. Bradley, "The Bradley Manuscript," Montana Historical Society <hi rend="italic">Contributions</hi> 8 (1917):135.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0957" n="57">
               <name type="person" key="Ordway, John">Ordway</name>, <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> p. 383; Thw. 5:223–27; "Peale's Memorandum of Specimens and Artifacts," Jackson, ed., <hi rend="italic">Letters,</hi> 2:477. My understanding of both <name type="place" key="Camp Disappointment (Mont.)">Camp Disappointment</name> and the <name type="place"
                     key="Two Medicine River (Main or South Branch Marias River)">Two Medicine River</name> fight site was greatly enhanced by Wilbur Werner, who guided me over both locations in the summer of 1981.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0958" n="58">
               <name type="person" key="Biddle, Nicholas">Biddle</name>-Coues, <hi rend="italic">History,</hi> 3:1105n; David H. Coyner, <hi rend="italic">The Lost Trapper,</hi> ed. David J. Weber (1847; reprint, Albuquerque: University of <name type="place" key="New Mexico">New Mexico</name> Press, 1970), p. 55; Washington Irving, <hi rend="italic">Astoria; or, Anecdotes of an Enterprise Beyond the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky Mountains</name>,</hi> ed. Edgeley W. Todd (1836; reprint, Norman: University of Oklahoma Press, 1964), p. 147.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0959" n="59">Josephy, <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Nez Perce Indians">Nez Perce</name>,</hi> pp. 651–53. Josephy's conclusions were somewhat anticipated by Ewers, <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="native_nation" key="Blackfeet Indians">Blackfeet</name>,</hi> p. 48, and Dale L. Morgan, <hi rend="italic">The West of William H. Ashley, 1822–1838</hi> (Denver: The Old West Pulishing Co., 1964), p. xxxv.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0960" n="60">The councils with <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> Indians in 1806 were conducted by <name type="person" key="Clark, William">William Clark</name> since <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis's</name> painful wound limited his active participation in expedition affairs.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0961" n="61">
               <name type="person" key="Le Borgne (One Eye)">Le Borgne's</name> diplomatic achievements are recorded in Coues, ed., <hi rend="italic">New Light,</hi> 1:367–97.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0962" n="62">Thw. 5:337–42.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0963" n="63">Ibid. 5:342–43.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0964" n="64">Ibid. 5:344–46.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0965" n="65">Ibid. 5:347.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0966" n="66">Ibid. 5:350–53.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0967" n="67">Ibid. 5:355–56.</note>
            <note xml:id="n0968" n="68">Ibid. 5:393–94.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="file_references">
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.ronda.01.08" type="prev"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.ronda.01.00" type="contents"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr n="lc.ronda.01.afterword" type="next"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
