<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lc.sup.alwin.01">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition Online</title>
            <title type="sub">
               <hi rend="italic">Montana</hi> 29:3 [1979]: 16–27.</title>
            <title type="sub">Pelts, Provisions, &amp; Perceptions: The Hudson's Bay Company
Mandan Indian Trade, 1795–1812</title>
            <author>John A. Alwin</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska Press and University of Nebraska Libraries–Electronic Text Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>?</addrLine>
               <addrLine>eburke3@unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="ISBN"/>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
               <term>Supplements</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
               <term>Texts</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-02-24</date>
            <name>Beth Burke</name>Initial creation</change>
         <change>
            <date>2016-010-06</date>
            <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
            Converted from P4 to P5. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="main">Pelts, Provisions, &amp; Perceptions: The Hudson's Bay Company <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> Indian Trade, 1795–1812</head>
         <p>
            <name type="person" key="Alwin, John">by <ref target="https://www.cwu.edu/~geograph/alwin.html">John A. Alwin</ref>
            </name>
         </p>
         <div type="Article">
            <p>(This article first appeared in <hi rend="italic">
                  <ref target="http://www.his.state.mt.us/pub/magazine/default.asp">Montana [The Magazine of Western History]</ref>
               </hi> 29:3 [1979]: 16–27.)</p>
            <p>On November 12, 1795, two Hudson's Bay Company employees left their <name type="place" key="Assiniboine River">Assiniboine River</name> post, <name type="place" key="Brandon House">Brandon House</name>, with rival North West Company traders traveling to the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> villages along the banks of the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri River</name>. Although the <name type="place" key="Montreal">Montreal</name>-based North West Company had an established trade with the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>, this was the British company's first venture to the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>. Over the next fifteen-odd years, Hudson's Bay Company traded regularly with the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name>, receiving pelts, provisions, horses, and, incidentally, some interesting perceptions of first Spanish and then American efforts to discover a water passage through the continent. One of those efforts, the Lewis and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition, drew more than just curious attention from Hudson's Bay and North West Company traders. Worried that Lewis and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>'s discoveries might trigger a rush of American traders to the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> area and beyond, Hudson's Bay men tried to maintain their ties with the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>s by discrediting the Americans. There is even a hint that North West Company men tried to sabotage the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition. Their worries were not groundless. Within a few years of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>'s return, American traders came up the <name type="person" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> with trade goods in hand eager to extract the finest pelts they could from the region. Faced with increased competition from the Americans, conflicts with Indian tribes along their trade routes, and then the disastrous intrusion of war between the United States and Great Britain, Hudson's Bay Company traders finally had to turn their backs on the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> trade in 1812. It was a brief chapter in Hudson's Bay Company's history, but through it we can see perhaps more clearly the web of international relationships operating in the fur trade on the upper <name type="person" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> in the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> period.</p>
            <p>International Rivalries</p>
            <p>The quest for a Northwest Passage, or waterway to the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>, had brought the first European contact with the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> Indians in 1738 when French explorer <name type="person" key="Varennes, Pierre Gaultier de">Pierre Gaultier de Varennes</name>, Sieur de la Verendrye reached the villages after traveling southwest from the middle <name type="place" key="Assiniboine River">Assiniboine River</name>.<ref target="nlc.alwin.0101" n="1"/> Neither his journey nor the more extensive 1742 expedition by sons Louis and Francois, which also passed through the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> villages, discovered a route to the <name type="place" key="Western Sea">Western Sea </name>or an especially rich fur region. During the remainder of their tenure in the mid-continent, the French concentrated their western efforts further to the north in the <name type="place" key="Lake Winnipeg">Lake Winnipeg</name> drainage.</p>
            <p>In accord with the 1763 Treaty of Paris, which ended the Seven Years War, the French withdrew from interior <name type="place" key="North America">North America</name>. Within a few years the vacuum left by the retreat of French fur traders from the western interior of <name type="place" key="Canada">Canada</name> had been filled by a new breed of <name type="place" key="Montreal">Montreal</name>-based traders, commonly referred to as the Pedlars. They adopted many of the techniques of their predecessors, even occupying some of their posts. As the British Hudson's Bay Company (HBC) was soon to discover, they were even more aggressive competitors than those they had replaced.</p>
            <p>The Pedlars, like the French before them, pursued an expansionist policy geared to carrying the trade to the natives in the continental interior, while the rival HBC continued to restrict its fur trading to several strategically located estuary posts on the shore of <name type="place" key="Hudson Bay">Hudson Bay</name>. Since receiving its charter in 1670, the Bay Company, through its tidewater approach to the trade, had succeeded in attracting sufficient numbers of trading Indians, some of whom traveled great distances to trade at the Company's posts. But by the late 1760s and early 1770s it was obvious to HBC officers involved in the trade that the Company's traditional approach was inadequate. In the interior rival Pedlars intercepted trading Indians before they could get to HBC posts. Hudson's Bay men knew they had to change their operations to meet the competition.</p>
            <p>HBC Posts</p>
            <p>Finally in the early 1770s the HBC <name type="place" key="London">London</name> headquarters decided that it also would have to operate inland posts. In 1774 the HBC built its first full-fledged inland trading establishment, and in the decades that followed, several major Bayside posts thrust arms of settlement and trade into the continental interior in an effort to counter the formidable opposition, soon unified as the North West Company (NWC). The swiftness and spatial dimension of this expansion is distinctive in the annals of <name type="place" key="North America">North America</name>.<ref target="nlc.alwin.0102" n="2"/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <name type="place" key="Albany Fort">Albany Fort</name> was one of the Bayside posts to thrust a tentacle of trade inland. By 1790 <name type="place" key="Albany">Albany</name> men had extended trade to the upper <name type="place" key="Albany River">Albany River</name> and in 1793 leapfrogged far to the west where they built <name type="place" key="Brandon House">Brandon House</name> on the middle <name type="place" key="Assiniboine River">Assiniboine River</name> near its junction with the Souris. The post immediately became operations center for its own trading network which soon included outposts farther upstream on the <name type="place" key="Assiniboine River">Assiniboine</name>, on the southern shore of <name type="place" key="Lake Manitoba">Lake Manitoba</name>, downstream on the <name type="place" key="Assiniboine River">Assiniboine</name>, as well as on the <name type="place" key="Red River">Red River</name>.</p>
            <p>A seasonal transport routine quickly developed. Each spring fur returns from <name type="place" key="Brandon House">Brandon House</name> and its outposts were transported in twenty-odd foot bateaux more than 1300 miles to <name type="place" key="Albany Fort">Albany Fort</name>, or the somewhat shorter distance to <name type="place" key="Martin's Falls Depot">Martin's Falls Depot</name> on the <name type="place" key="Albany River">Albany River</name>. Trade goods and other essentials for the forthcoming trading season, that year's "outfit," were shuttled up from the Bayside each summer on a return trip in the same craft. This, then, was the situation in 1795 when the <name type="person" key="Brandon House">Brandon House</name> traders inaugurated a distinctive new branch of their trade—one which reached beyond the Company's chartered lands and across the Hudson Bay drainage divide to the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> villages in the central portion of present-day North Dakota.</p>
            <p>HBC traders at <name type="person" key="Brandon House">Brandon House</name> had seen first-hand evidence of the fruits of the NWC <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> trade since the post's first season. On December 22, 1793, founding Post Master <name type="person" key="MacKay, Donald">Donald MacKay</name> recorded the arrival of Canadian traders at the nearby Nor'Wester post with a large quantity of buffalo robes acquired at the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> villages. Two years later <name type="person" key="Goodwin, Robert">Robert Goodwin</name>, his successor, decided the HBC should check into the potential of developing its own <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> trade. He understood that buffalo robes, which were used as cariole coverings in Montreal, were the Canadians' single most important trade item, although the agricultural <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>s also had "Indn Maize, Kidney beans, Pumkins and grows many other things.. ."<ref target="nlc.alwin.0103" n="3"/>
            </p>
            <p>It was only with difficulty and the inducements of liquor and ammunition that <name type="person" key="Goodwin, Robert">Goodwin</name> could convince the Canadians to allow the pair of HBC employees to tag along that November 1795 "to see the country &amp; what it produces."<ref target="nlc.alwin.0104" n="4"/> The Company judged this initial trip a success when the pair of HBC employees returned on December 26 with 142 Made Beaver (MB)<ref target="nlc.alwin.0105" n="5"/> worth of furs and two <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> horses. The Company promptly sent three more men back to the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>s with a new supply of trade goods. Thereafter, HBC and NWC trading parties raced each other to the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> villages.<ref target="nlc.alwin.0106" n="6"/>
            </p>
            <p>The <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> Trade</p>
            <p>For more than a decade after the initial ventures of 1795–96, HBC employees or their representatives were routinely sent to the villages of the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>s, which they then usually referred to as the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandals</name> or <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandalls</name>, as well as to those of <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>  neighbors and allies, the <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsas</name>.<ref target="nlc.alwin.0107" n="7"/> Although the Company's routine varied somewhat from year to year, the usual practice was to make two trips. The first party normally set out from <name type="person" key="Brandon House">Brandon House</name> in late September or early October, soon after the new outfit of trade goods and supplies arrived at the post. All, or part, of this initial group usually arrived back at <name type="person" key="Brandon House">Brandon House</name> by Christmas. Shortly after recuperating from New Year's celebrations, they commenced preparations for the departure of the second trading expedition, which returned to <name type="person" key="Brandon House">Brandon House</name> during March or April.</p>
            <p>Both Company employees and "freemen" conducted the HBC's <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>  trade. As their name suggests, freemen were not in the employ of any company. Equipped with up to 200 MB worth of HBC trade goods on credit, they commonly traveled to and from the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>s with the parties of one to six Company employees.</p>
            <p>The route between <name type="person" key="Brandon House">Brandon House</name> and the <name type="person" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> followed the <name type="place" key="Souris River">Souris River</name> as much as possible to take advantage of firewood and protection of the river valley. To avoid a broad westerly bend in the river's course, traders left the <name type="place" key="Souris River">Souris</name> and struck out overland, passing along the west side of the forested <name type="place" key="Turtle Mountain">Turtle Mountain</name>, before rejoining the <name type="place" key="Souris River">Souris</name>. Farther downstream, east of present-day <name type="place" key="Minot, North Dakota">Minot, North Dakota</name>, the river's course bends sharply to the northwest. Here, the route left the river for the last time and ran south to the <name type="person" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> and the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> villages. The one-way trip, estimated to be 150 to 200 miles depending on the exact route, generally required around ten days to travel. Depending on snow conditions, the mode of transport was horse and/or dog sled.</p>
            <p>It is not possible to determine the complete variety and quantity of trade goods sent to the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>s or the value of furs obtained there each year. But HBC men traveling to the villages evidently had a range of trade goods that included items as varied as tobacco, vermilion, beads, rings, looking glasses powder, shot, and guns. The last item may have been traded exclusively for horses.</p>
            <p>Determining the value of pelts obtained at the villages is also difficult because returns from <name type="person" key="Brandon House">Brandon House</name> and its outposts, including the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> trade, were routinely combined for accounting purposes. In some years, however, <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> returns can be calculated from daily entries in the <name type="person" key="Brandon House">Brandon House</name> Post Journal. Entries in the 1795–96 journal show a <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> trade of 262 MB and four horses.<ref target="nlc.alwin.0108" n="8"/> That season the combined <name type="person" key="Brandon House">Brandon House</name> trade totaled 4,207 MB; the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> contribution was smaller that year than in most succeeding seasons.<ref target="nlc.alwin.0109" n="9"/>
               <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> trade contributed approximately 1,100 MB (and five horses) to <name type="person" key="Brandon House">Brandon House</name> and outpost trade in 1800–01.<ref target="nlc.alwin.0110" n="10"/> Two years later this trade contributed ten per cent of the combined Assiniboine River trade of 5,486 MB.<ref target="nlc.alwin.0111" n="11"/>
            </p>
            <p>Although a regular and expected source of pelts for <name type="person" key="Brandon House">Brandon House</name>, the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> returns did not usually produce a significant addition to trade. In at least one year, however, the <name type="person" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> River returns were critical to <name type="person" key="Brandon House">Brandon House</name>. The mild temperatures and lack of snow during the winter of 1799–1800 allowed buffalo to winter in the more open plains far away from their usual wintering grounds in the more forested Parkland belt where <name type="person" key="Brandon House">Brandon House</name> was located. Without ready access to this important source of provisions, natives, who normally trapped at <name type="person" key="Brandon House">Brandon House</name>, worked almost full time in trying to stave off starvation and were not able to trap their normal supply of beaver. Rather than hunting and trapping beaver that winter, Indians frequented the post begging handouts of food. That season the <name type="person" key="Brandon House">Brandon House</name> and outpost trade totaled only 5,559 MB compared to the previous season's 8,023 MB.<ref target="nlc.alwin.0112" n="12"/> After packing that season's disappointing returns for shipment down to Hudson Bay, Post Master <name type="person" key="Goodwin, Robert">Robert Goodwin</name> commented in the post journal on April 23, 1800, "my trade would have been very little had it not been for my men going two trips to the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>s."<ref target="nlc.alwin.0113" n="13"/>
            </p>
            <p>Several years earlier both HBC and NWC trade with the upper <name type="person" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> tribes were threatened. NWC traders arriving back at the <name type="place" key="Assiniboine River">Assiniboine</name> in October of 1796 carried with them a proclamation forbidding "all forigners [sic] whatever (especially all British subjects)"<ref target="nlc.alwin.0114" n="14"/> from entering the newly-chartered lands of the Spanish Missouri Company.</p>
            <p>Spanish Competition</p>
            <p>Just as 1763 had marked the formal retreat of the French from <name type="place" key="Western Canada">Western Canada</name>, it also marked the French withdrawal from <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name>, when <name type="place" key="France">France</name> ceded that territory to <name type="place" key="Spain">Spain</name>. By the early 1790s reports of British encroachments on the northern frontier of this Spanish territory reached <name type="place" key="St. Louis">St. Louis</name>. It was, in part, to counter this HBC and NWC intrusion from the north that <name type="place" key="St. Louis">St. Louis</name> merchants organized the Missouri Company in 1794. After earlier Missouri Company failures to reach the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> villages, a party under <name type="person" key="Evans, John">John Evans</name> finally succeeded in late September of 1796.<ref target="nlc.alwin.0115" n="15"/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Evans, John">Evans</name> wasted little time in trying to rout the British traders. He took possession of the NWC post at the villages and dispatched the proclamation to the British traders on the middle <name type="place" key="Assiniboine River">Assiniboine</name>. The manifesto was not his own, but was that of his superior, <name type="person" key="MacKay, James">James MacKay</name>, who remained behind at <name type="place" key="Fort Charles">Fort Charles</name> downstream on the <name type="person" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> in present-day <name type="place" key="Nebraska">Nebraska</name>. Other correspondence followed between Evans and both James Sutherland at <name type="person" key="Brandon House">Brandon House</name> and his counterpart <name type="person" key="McDonnell, John">John McDonnell</name> at the nearby NWC post. Despite the proclamation forbidding British trade, it proved difficult to halt the well-established and mutually beneficial commerce between the village Indians and the British.</p>
            <p>The tenuity of <name type="person" key="Evans, John">Evans</name>' control was demonstrated in February 1797 when two HBC traders arrived back with four fur-laden sleds. Although <name type="person" key="Evans, John">Evans</name> barred the HBC men from trading directly with the Indians he personally accepted HBC trade goods in exchange for furs. Back at <name type="person" key="Brandon House">Brandon House</name> the pair of HBC men reported they had been greeted at the villages by "300 Indians who carried their Sleds on their Shoulders into the vilage [sic], so fond were they of the English. . ." In contrast the natives reportedly were "highly displeased with Evans," whose only recourse was to raise the Spanish flag in an effort to assert his authority.<ref target="nlc.alwin.0116" n="16"/>
            </p>
            <p>Word reached <name type="person" key="Brandon House">Brandon House</name> in spring that <name type="person" key="Evans, John">Evans</name> had been forced to withdraw down the <name type="person" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> to <name type="place" key="Fort Charles">Fort Charles</name>. Prior to his retreat he almost came to "fisticuffs in attempting to prevent them [NWC men] from Trading with the natives. . ." By attempting to cut off trade with the British without an adequate supply of his own trade goods to offer in their place, <name type="person" key="Evans, John">Evans</name> so angered the Indians that they threatened to kill him and his men if they refused to leave, "being greatly exasparated [sic] against them for preventing the Subjects of G. Britain from comming to Trade with them. .."<ref target="nlc.alwin.0117" n="17"/>
            </p>
            <p>The Spanish claim to the territory and trade of the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name> especially distressed the NWC. To check out the location of the villages and to verify the Spanish claim they called on the services of their newly-acquired surveyor and geographer, <name type="person" key="Thompson, David">David Thompson</name>. An employee of the HBC since 1784, <name type="person" key="Thompson, David">Thompson </name>had deserted the Company for the NWC only six months prior to his late November 1797 arrival at the NWC post at the <name type="place" key="Souris River">Souris</name> mouth.</p>
            <p>HBC Post Master <name type="person" key="MacKay, John">John MacKay</name> extended the courtesy of inviting <name type="person" key="Thompson, David">Thompson</name> to <name type="person" key="Brandon House">Brandon House</name> for some hospitality, a usual practice among the fur traders. Disgruntled after the former HBC employee failed to show up, <name type="person" key="MacKay, John">MacKay</name> wrote, "I did myself the honour to stay at home if that Astronomer wished to see me, I know no place he could find me sooner, than in my own House."<ref target="nlc.alwin.0118" n="18"/> With only four days to prepare for his <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> expedition, <name type="person" key="Thompson, David">Thompson</name> probably had little time or inclination to socialize, especially with an officer of his former employer. He headed south for the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandans</name> on November 28 and was back at McDonnell's (Assiniboine) House on February 3, having determined the latitude and longitude of two villages.<ref target="nlc.alwin.0119" n="19"/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>
            </p>
            <p>Six years later, entries in the <name type="person" key="Brandon House">Brandon House</name> journal record the arrival at the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> village of two other celebrated explorers—Meriwether <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and William <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>. Since <name type="person" key="Thompson, David">Thompson</name>'s trip, <name type="place" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</name> had been retroceded to <name type="place" key="France">France</name>, and in 1803 had become American territory. <name type="person" key="Jefferson, Thomas">Thomas Jefferson</name>, eager for an expedition into the trans-<name type="place" key="Mississippi River">Mississippi</name> region and on to the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>, had begun planning for the expedition even before Louisiana became American soil. When the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition finally started up the <name type="person" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> River in 1804, its aims were several. Two primary objectives were to explore the <name type="person" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> River and the possibility of a commercial communication with the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>, and to note the potential for an American fur trade in the regions traversed.<ref target="nlc.alwin.0120" n="20"/>
            </p>
            <p>Thus, when <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> arrived at the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> villages in late October of 1804, it was, in part, a quest for furs and a Northwest passage which had brought them; the same objectives which had earlier lured French and Spanish explorers and traders. Because of their regular link with the village Indians, British traders on the Assiniboine received occasional intelligence on this celebrated expedition.</p>
            <p>Even before starting construction of <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan">Fort Mandan</name>, the expedition's wintering place near the villages, the American explorers encountered Assisiboine-based British traders in the vicinity. On November 1, 1804, shortly after their arrival at the villages, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> dispatched a letter to the officer in charge of the NWC's Department of Assiniboia, stationed at a post several days travel upriver from <name type="person" key="Brandon House">Brandon House</name>.<ref target="nlc.alwin.0121" n="21"/> In the letter, they informed him of the expedition and its purpose and asked for any geographic information he might provide on the country into which the expedition was headed.</p>
            <p>Word of the expedition's arrival at the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> villages may not have reached <name type="person" key="Brandon House">Brandon House</name> until November 13, 1804. That day two Canadians arrived back from the <name type="person" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> villages where they reported seeing 150 Americans, an exaggeration of the actual forty-five in the expedition. More correctly, they reported that the entourage had arrived in three large boats—<name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>'s keelboat and two large pirogues. Under the command of "Captn. Clerk &amp; Captn <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name>" the group was reportedly bound for the <name type="place" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky Mountains</name>, but had to winter at the "Mandals."<ref target="nlc.alwin.0122" n="22"/>
            </p>
            <p>Post Master <name type="person" key="MacKay, John">MacKay</name> was surprised that the two Canadians who brought word of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition had not seen the three HBC men sent to the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>s on October 19—<name type="person" key="Budge, George">George Budge</name>, <name type="person" key="Henderson, George">George Henderson</name>, and <name type="person" key="Anderson, Tom">Tom Anderson</name>. <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, however, noted their safe arrival at the villages in a November 8 entry in his journal. Writing at <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan">Fort Mandan</name>, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> mentioned that the expedition's <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> interpreter had arrived back from the village and "informed us that three English men had arrived from the Hudson Bay Company. . ,"<ref target="nlc.alwin.0123" n="23"/> Although it was expected the HBC men would visit Fort <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> the next day, it was not until December 1 that <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> referred to <name type="person" key="Henderson, George">George Henderson</name>'s arrival at the fort. Fifteen days later <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> recorded the arrival of <name type="person" key="Budge, George">George Budge</name>, incorrectly referred to as "George Bunch" in his journal, along with two NWC clerks.<ref target="nlc.alwin.0124" n="24"/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Henderson, George">George Henderson</name> left both <name type="person" key="Budge, George">George Budge</name> and <name type="person" key="Anderson, Tom">Tom Anderson</name> at the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>s that December when he started back for the <name type="person" key="Brandon House">Brandon House</name> with their take of 208 MB. At <name type="person" key="Brandon House">Brandon House</name> he delivered a letter from <name type="person" key="Budge, George">George Budge</name> which indicated that there was really little prospect for additional trade with the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>s, for they were "so much taken with the Americans . . .” <ref target="nlc.alwin.0125" n="25"/> Nonetheless, when <name type="person" key="Budge, George">Budge</name> and <name type="person" key="Henderson, George">Henderson</name> finally arrived back at <name type="person" key="Brandon House">Brandon House</name> on March 15, they brought an additional 424 MB with them. How much more information on <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> they brought back is unknown; Post Master <name type="person" key="MacKay, John">MacKay</name> failed to mention the Americans in his journal on this occasion.</p>
            <p>On April 2, 1805, five days prior to the expedition's departure for the <name type="plave" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>, another mention is made of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>. That day, unidentified Indians arrived directly from the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> villages and expressed their displeasure with the Americans who had wintered near the villages. After talking with them <name type="person" key="MacKay, John">MacKay</name> wrote, "they are not well pleased with them [the Americans]. Captn <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> told them the Ground he walked on was his own, and next year he would take possetion [sic] of the whole River."<ref target="nlc.alwin.0126" n="26"/>
            </p>
            <p>There appears to have been very little friction between HBC men and the expedition during <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>'s winter layover at <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan">Fort Mandan</name>. The two incidents we know of, however, both involved <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Toussaint Charbonneau</name>, <name type="person" key="Sacajawea">Sacajawea</name>'s husband and a former Nor'Wester resident at the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> villages who was hired by the expedition as an interpreter for the westward journey to the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>.</p>
            <p>Arriving back at <name type="place" key="Fort Mandan">Fort Mandan</name> from a short trading foray on January 13, 1805, <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name> informed his superiors that an HBC employee had been speaking against the Americans. That day <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> recorded "that the Clerk of the Hudson Bay Co. with the <hi rend="italic">Me ne tar res</hi> [Minatarees or <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name>] has been Speaking Some fiew expressns unfavourable towards us..."<ref target="nlc.alwin.0127" n="27"/> According to the <name type="person" key="Coues, Elliott">Coues</name> edition of the history of the expedition, on January 13, 1805, <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name> arrived back from a trip to the lodges of some <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Minatarees</name> and informed <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>,</p>
            <p>that the agents of the Hudson's Bay Company at that place had been endeavoring to make unfavorable impressions with regard to us on the mind of the great chief, and the Northwest Company intended building a fort there. The great chief had in consequence spoken slightly of the Americans, but said that if we would give him our great flag he would come and see us.<ref target="nlc.alwin.0128" n="28"/>
            </p>
            <p>The other point of friction between the expedition leaders and the HBC traders is less definite. This involved the possibility that HBC employees tried to dissuade <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name> from continuing on with the expedition when it left the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>s. On March 11, 1805, as the expedition's departure date from Fort <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> approached, <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> entered in his journal, "We have every reason to believe that our <hi rend="italic">Menetarre</hi> interpreter (whome we intended to take with his wife, as an interpreter through his wife to the <name type="native_nation" key="Snake Indians">Snake Indians</name> of which nation She is) has been Corrupted by the [blank in MS] Company &amp;c." <ref target="nlc.alwin.0129" n="29"/>
               <name type="person" key="Chuinard, E. G.">E. G. Chuinard</name>, an authority on <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>, believes that the blank, which could not be deciphered in the original journal, "no doubt refers to the Hudson's Bay Company. . ."<ref target="nlc.alwin.0130" n="30"/> In the <name type="person" key="Coues, Elliott">Coues</name> history of the expedition there are additional details. The entry for March 17, 1805, includes the following passage:</p>
            <p>Our Minnetaree interpreter <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Chaboneau</name>, whom we intended taking with us to the <name type="place" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name>, had some days ago been worked upon by the British traders, and appeared unwilling to accompany us, except on certain terms—such as his not being subject to our orders, and his doing duty or returning whenever he chose.<ref target="nlc.alwin.0131" n="31"/>
            </p>
            <p>It may be inaccurate to interpret the blank in the <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> quote and the "British traders" in the <name type="person" key="Coues, Elliott">Coues</name> text as HBC traders. For one thing, the term "British" in the original journals of the expedition and the <name type="person" key="Coues, Elliott">Coues</name> history is used to refer to both the NWC and HBC or to either company and its men. And there were other circumstances suggesting that it was probably the NWC men, rather than the HBC employees, who tried to handicap the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition by convincing <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name>, and thus <name type="person" key="Sacajawea">Sacajawea</name>, to withdraw from the expedition.</p>
            <p>Three months after <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>'s reference to others' attempts to talk <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name> into staying behind, Nor'Wester Francois <name type="person" key="Larocque, Antoine">Antoine Larocque</name> started west from the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> villages with a party of <name type="native_nation" key="Crow Indians">Crow Indians</name> to explore the <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River Valley">Yellowstone River Valley</name>.<ref target="nlc.alwin.0132" n="32"/>On the previous winter's trip to the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>s he and other NWC traders had learned from <name type="native_nation" key="Crow Indians">Crows</name> trading at the villages that “beavers were as numerous in their rivers as buffaloes and other large animals were in their plains or meadows..."<ref target="nlc.alwin.0133" n="33"/>
               <name type="person" key="Larocque, Antoine">Larocque</name>’s job was to verify these reports and to inaugurate trade with the <name type="native_nation" key="Crow Indians">Crow</name>.</p>
            <p>When NWC first planned this <name type="place" key="Yellowstone River Valley">Yellowstone</name> expedition is not known, but if there was even an inkling of such a trip by March 1805, the North West Company traders' concern over the continued westward passage of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition right through the heart of this promising fur trapping region is understandable. Hoping to handicap the Americans, it may have been the NWC men who tried to convince <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name> to withdraw his services. It seems unlikely that HBC employees at the villages would be in a position to influence the ex-Nor'Wester, <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name>. Irrespective of who was responsible, the effort failed and <name type="person" key="Charbonneau, Toussaint">Charbonneau</name> along with <name type="person" key="Sacajawea">Sacajawea</name> accompanied the expedition after all.</p>
            <p>When <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> returned from the <name type="placee" key="Pacific Ocean">Pacific</name> in 1806, they passed by the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> Villages during the summer when HBC traders were busy conveying goods to and from the shore of <name type="place" key="Hudson Bay">Hudson Bay</name>. As a result, it may not have been until December 20, 1806, when HBC traders returned from the first <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> trip of the 1806–07 season, that the men at <name type="person" key="Brandon House">Brandon House</name> learned of the homeward passage of the expedition. The five men who returned that day reported that "Captn <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> with his Party passed the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandal</name> Village on their return to the <name type="place" key="United States">United States</name> last Summer &amp; that the Americans Intend to settle the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Mississouri</name> [sic] River at least as high up as the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandals</name>[.]"<ref target="nlc.alwin.0134" n="34"/>
            </p>
            <p>HBC Retreat</p>
            <p>Although the Americans did not push settlement up the <name type="person" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> the next year, <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>'s triumphant return and their reports of plentiful furs in the upper <name type="person" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> country helped to encourage American traders. The traders wasted little time in exploring the new territory, but there was a more immediate threat to HBC trade with the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>—ambushes by <name type="native_nation" key="Assiniboine Indians">Assiniboine Indians</name>. Conflict with the <name type="native_nation" key="Assiniboine Indians">Assiniboine</name> nearly terminated HBC trade in 1807 due to a particularly serious encounter, but contrary to what some historians have assumed trade continued after 1807.</p>
            <p>On the return of their second trip to the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>s in April 1807, HBC traders fell into the grasp of an <name type="native_nation" key="Assiniboine Indians">Assiniboine</name> party. <name type="person" key="Budge, George">George Budge</name> communicated the "Unfortunate Intelligince" on April 11 when he arrived back at <name type="person" key="Brandon House">Brandon House</name>. Later that day, Post Master <name type="person" key="Vincent, Thomas">Thomas Vincent</name> described the incident in the House Journal:</p>
            <p>the <name type="native_nation" key="Assiniboine Indians">Assinaboils</name> had Robbed them of four of their Horses and stabbed two others one of them died on the Spot, the other he left unable to get up, three of the above Horses were bought during the winter at the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandals</name>[.] he has left <name type="person" key="Slater, James">James Slater</name> and <name type="person" key="Corrigale, Jacob">Jacob Corrigale</name> With the furrs 3 days Journey from the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandal</name> Village the other 3 men with 3 horses are coming home with part of the Furrs, they likewise Robbed him of all his Provisions Ammunition, 2 new Guns, a part of his Furr &amp;c, in the Scuffle he himself and <name type="person" key="Corrigale, Jacob">Jacob Corrigale</name> were Nearly Stabbed by two of the Rascals whilst near 40 others Surrounded them with their Bows drawn, had they made further Resistance Inevitable Death must have been Ye Consequence[.]<ref target="nlc.alwin.0135" n="35"/>
            </p>
            <p>A week later <name type="person" key="Budge, George">Budge</name> and four other men went back with six horses to fetch home the remaining furs, and by April 27 all men from the ill-fated party had safely made it back to <name type="person" key="Brandon House">Brandon House</name>.</p>
            <p>This was not the first time the <name type="native_nation" key="Assiniboine Indians">Assiniboine</name> had interfered with the Company's Missouri trade. Just three years earlier they had waylaid a party of HBC men en route to the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>s. Detained for several days by the hostiles, the traders were released only after paying dearly for their freedom with stocks intended for the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> trade.<ref target="nlc.alwin.0136" n="36"/>
            </p>
            <p>The <name type="native_nation" key="Assiniboine Indians">Assiniboine</name> tried to obstruct the Company's <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> trade for very good reasons. When peace prevailed between the <name type="native_nation" key="Assiniboine Indians">Assiniboine</name> and their sometime enemies, the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>s, the <name type="native_nation" key="Assiniboine Indians">Assiniboine</name> served as middlemen, supplying the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>s with goods obtained at the British posts. This was a lucrative business for them and they obviously did not wish to see the HBC or any other traders interfere by carrying goods directly to the <name type="person" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> villages. When at war with the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>s, the <name type="native_nation" key="Assiniboine Indians">Assiniboine</name> understandably tried to stop the British Missouri trade which provided their enemies with guns, powder, and shot. For similar reasons, the <name type="native_nation" key="Sioux Indians">Sioux</name> also occasionally threatened the British-<name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> trade.</p>
            <p>At times there was great hostility between the <name type="native_nation" key="Assiniboine Indians">Assiniboine</name> and <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> as was indicated in an account of HBC traders who arrived back from the villages in December 1801. The day prior to their departure for <name type="person" key="Brandon House">Brandon House</name> the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>s killed eleven <name type="native_nation" key="Assiniboine Indians">Assiniboines</name> within half a mile of the village, and brought their heads and several other parts of their bodies back to the village to feed to the dogs.<ref target="nlc.alwin.0137" n="37"/>
            </p>
            <p>Because of the possibility of further Indian attacks, Post Master <name type="person" key="MacKay, John">John MacKay</name> decided in 1807 not to send HBC employees to the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>s. He did, however, outfit a French Canadian and an Irish freeman for that trade, and they departed <name type="person" key="Brandon House">Brandon House</name> in October 1807. The following spring <name type="person" key="MacKay, John">MacKay</name> received news that both freemen had been killed by the <name type="native_nation" key="Assiniboine Indians">Assiniboines</name>. This was contradicted by a later report which indicated that one, <name type="person" key="La France">La France</name>, had died of consumption and the other, <name type="person" key="McCrachan, Hugh">Hugh McCrachan</name>, was still at the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> villages, afraid to come home by himself. The second report proved the more truthful, and even though the Irishman did not return that trading season, he showed up empty-handed the next October. Outfitting him again with trade goods on credit, HBC promptly sent <name type="person" key="McCrachan, Hugh">McCrachan</name> back to the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>s in company with two Canadian traders. The party of three were back with five loaded horses by mid-December 1808.</p>
            <p>In the fall of 1809 three Canadians arrived at <name type="person" key="Brandon House">Brandon House</name> with two <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> Indians from the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> with word that "above 2 Hundred American Hunters gone up the Miss Sourie ..." Although <name type="person" key="MacKay, John">John MacKay</name> evidently knew little about the large American party, he quickly realized their trade potential. Within ten days all preparations had been made and four men left with the two <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> Indians for the <name type="place" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> "to trade with the Americans on the return . . ."<ref target="nlc.alwin.0138" n="38"/> That party of Americans was the initial expedition of the newly-formed Missouri Fur Company, organized the previous winter by <name type="person" key="Lisa, Manuel">Manuel Lisa</name> and prominent St. Louis businessmen.<ref target="nlc.alwin.0139" n="39"/>
            </p>
            <p>The Missouri Fur Company's first venture to the upper <name type="person" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> not only inaugurated the company's trade, but it also escorted <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>
               <name type="person" key="Chief Shahaka"> Chief Shahaka</name> to his village. On arrival in the fall of 1809, the company built a fort near the villages. There it was decided that <name type="person" key="Lisa, Manuel">Manuel Lisa</name> and expedition military commander <name type="person" key="Chouteau, Pierre">Pierre Chouteau</name> would return to <name type="place" key="St. Louis">St. Louis</name>. Then, two expedition parties were directed to <name type="place" key="Fort Raymond">Fort Raymond</name>, the fort Lisa had built the previous year at the mouth of the Big Horn River. One group went via the <name type="person" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>, while the other traveled overland to Fort Raymond. Members of these two parties were evidently the "above 2 Hundred American Hunters" reported at <name type="person" key="Brandon House">Brandon House</name> to have ascended the <name type="person" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>.</p>
            <p>Not all in the expedition proceeded to <name type="place" key="Fort Raymond">Fort Raymond</name> or returned to <name type="place" key="St. Louis">St. Louis</name> that fall. Some remained behind to winter in the vicinity of the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> villages. These were the men who HBC traders referred to when they arrived back at <name type="person" key="Brandon House">Brandon House</name> on December 6, 1809. The post journal entry for that day records that they had ,,found a Compound of Mallatoes, Negroes Creoles and Canadians from the Illinois under a Mr Choteau who after settling his son at the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>es returned to the Illinois[.]"<ref target="nlc.alwin.0140" n="40"/> The "Mr. Choteau" referred to was undoubtedly <name type="person" key="Chouteau, Pierre  Sr.">Pierre Chouteau, Sr.</name>, who had returned to <name type="place" key="St. Louis">St. Louis</name> with <name type="person" key="Lisa, Manuel">Lisa</name>. Confronted with this situation at the villages, the HBC traders were for "carrying back immediately," but on their return to <name type="person" key="Brandon House">Brandon House</name> a group of Indians threatened to plunder them if they did not accept their "offer" of a trade—700 poor quality wolves for the HBC trade goods.<ref target="nlc.alwin.0141" n="41"/>
            </p>
            <p>No attempt was made by the HBC to send even freemen to the <name type="person" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> villages in 1810. But during the 1811–12 season the HBC combined outfits with the NWC in a joint trading expedition for "mutual security, and to protect ourselves against the natives.. ."<ref target="nlc.alwin.0142" n="42"/> Evidently there had been no plans to send men that season, but on December 23, 1811, an American and an old Canadian trader arrived at <name type="person" key="Brandon House">Brandon House</name> from the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> villages to report that there were few Americans wintering on the <name type="person" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>. The pair suggested that the <name type="native_nation" key="Missouri Indians">Missouri Indians</name> there would be glad to trade with the British if they would send goods, as the villagers were discontented with the present traders. After some hesitation, both companies agreed to supply a portion of the goods, and to divide returns equally.</p>
            <p>By January 2 <name type="person" key="Yorston, William">William Yorston</name> and three other Company men had begun preparations for their trip to the <name type="person" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>. But three days later a skirmish between <name type="person" key="Yorston, William">Yorston</name> and his commanding officer at <name type="place" key="Brandon House">Brandon</name> almost aborted the planned <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> trip. That day <name type="person" key="Yorston, William">Yorston</name>, who evidently had been attempting to "throw obstacles in the way" of the venture used "insulting language" with his superior, who promptly slapped him in the face. This led to a scuffle between the two, a rare occurrence at Company posts. <name type="person" key="Yorston, William">Yorston</name> wrestled down his opponent, who later that day wrote of the incident in the post journal: "[he] pounded away for eight or ten minutes twisting the hankerchief round my neck at the same time till I was almost strangled." Other details of the fight were not recorded, but <name type="person" key="Yorston, William">Yorston</name> finally did agree to accompany the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> expedition. His participation was essential since he was the only HBC employee at the post who knew both the route to the villages and the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> language.<ref target="nlc.alwin.0143" n="43"/>
            </p>
            <p>The joint entourage left for the villages on January 8, with the HBC men taking four horses with sleds and four dog sleds to transport the returns. On March 14, 1812, the combined <name type="person" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name> River party returned with a "grand" total of 120 beaver skins, 4 buffalo robes, 14 wolves, and 2 bear skins.</p>
            <p>At the villages the British found trading difficult, for the Americans could offer the Indians "better encouragement." The Americans had become entrenched, despite the report to the contrary, and the British traders thought themselves lucky to escape with their meager take of furs. In less than three months the two nations would be at war; a war that disrupted fur trading from the <name type="place" key="Great Lakes">Great Lakes</name> to the <name type="place" key="Pacific Coast">Pacific Coast</name>. This 1812 expedition ended HBC attempts to maintain a regular trade link between <name type="person" key="Brandon House">Brandon House</name> and the village Indians of the upper <name type="person" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>. The war cut off trade and effectively severed Company ties with this distinctive area which, for more than a decade, had proved to be a valuable source for pelts, provisions and perceptions.</p>
            <p>Hudson’s Bay Company Incorporated 2nd May 1670</p>
            <p>AUTHOR'S NOTE ON SOURCES</p>
            <p>On May 2, 1670, the charter granting Rupert's Land to the Governor and Company of Adventurers of England trading into Hudson's Bay, more commonly referred to as the Hudson's Bay Company (HBC), received the Great Seal of England. This charter granted the Company "sole Trade and Commerce" within the drainage basin of Hudson Bay and Strait, a vast domain of more than one million square miles. During succeeding decades Company fur trading activity expanded beyond the limits of Rupert's Land on many fronts to include almost all of mainland <name type="place" key="Canada">Canada</name> and reached south into northern and western sections of the <name type="place" key="United States">United States</name>.</p>
            <p>Archives of the Hudson's Bay Company were the principal source of information for this article. The archives deal mainly with Company transactions in <name type="place" key="North America">North America</name> and include documents such as post journals, post account books, various types of correspondence, individuals' journals, district reports, maps and sketches. Canadian and British scholars have used these corporate archives for decades—American scholars can almost certainly make greater use of this important source for historical research.</p>
            <p>Company records from 1670 to 1870 were made available to scholars at <name type="place" key="Beaver House">Beaver House</name>, the Company headquarters in <name type="place" key="London, England">London, England</name>, beginning in the early 1930s. Since 1966 researchers in <name type="place" key="North America">North America</name> have had access to the positive microfilm copies of the archives, up to 1870, in the Public Archives of Canada, Ottawa. In 1974, following the move of the head office of the HBC from <name type="place" key="London">London</name> to <name type="place" key="Winnipeg, Manitoba">Winnipeg, Manitoba</name>, four years earlier, the 4200-plus linear feet of the archives were moved to their new quarters in the Manitoba Provincial Archives and Library in <name type="place" key="Winnipeg">Winnipeg</name>. All post journals to 1940, as well as other selected post-1900 documents, are now open to researchers. Additional 20th century documents are made available as they are classified.</p>
            <p>I was introduced to the archives in the summer of 1973 when I started my dissertation research on the historical geography of HBC transportation between 1670 and 1821. I relied on the microfilms of the archives in <name type="person" key="Ottawa, Ontario">Ottawa, Ontario</name>, and the next year, even before their official opening date, I became one of the first researchers to use the archives at their new home in <name type="place" key="Winnipeg">Winnipeg</name>.</p>
            <p>I want to thank Drs. <name type="person" key="Ewers, John">John Ewers</name> of the Smithsonian Institution, <name type="person" key="Kaye, Barry">Barry Kaye</name> with the Department of Geography at the University of Manitoba, and <name type="person" key="Malone, Michael">Michael Malone</name> of the Department of History at Montana State University for commenting on an earlier draft of this paper. I also acknowledge the Hudson's Bay Company for permission to consult, and quote from, its archives. Special thanks are extended to Mrs. <name type="person" key="Smith, Shirlee">Shirlee Smith</name>, HBC archivist, for granting an eager graduate student access to the archives even in advance of their official opening date in Winnipeg.</p>
            <note xml:id="nlc.alwin.0101" n="1">For the early history of the white man's contact with the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>s see <name type="person" key="Nasatir, A. P.">A. P. Nasatir</name>, ed., <hi rend="italic">Before <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>: Documents Illustrating the History of the <name type="person" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>. 1785–1804</hi> (2 vols. St. Louis: St. Louis Historical Documents Foundation, 1952).</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.alwin.0102" n="2">For the most definitive history of the Hudson's Bay Company see <name type="person" key="Rich, E. E.">E. E. Rich</name>, <hi rend="italic">Hudson's Bay Company. 1670–1870</hi> (3 vols., Toronto: McClelland and Stewart Limited. 1960). A more compact history of the Western Canadian fur trade is <name type="person" key="Rich, E. E.">E. E. Rich</name>, <hi rend="italic">The Fur Trade and the Northwest to 1857</hi> (Toronto: McClelland and Stewart Limited, 1967).</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.alwin.0103" n="3">Hudson's Bay Company Archives (HBC Archives), B. 22/a/3, fo. 8, <name type="person" key="Brandon House">Brandon House</name> Post journal, 1795–96.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.alwin.0104" n="4">
               <hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.alwin.0105" n="5">"Made Beaver" (MB) was the HBC's basic unit of exchange. Since beaver was the chief fur dealt with by the Company, it was made the standard to regulate the value of all other types of pelts and trade goods.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.alwin.0106" n="6">The HBC's direct trade with the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> s dated back to the early 1700s when, for a brief period, they traded at the Hudson Bay Post of York Factory. <name type="person" key="Ray, Arthur J.">Arthur J. Ray</name>, <hi rend="italic">Indians in the Fur Trade</hi> (Toronto: University of Toronto Press, 1974), 55–59.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.alwin.0107" n="7">For additional general information on these tribes see <name type="person" key="Meyer, Roy W.">Roy W. Meyer</name>, T<hi rend="italic">he Village Indians of the Upper <name type="person" key="Missouri River">Missouri</name>: The <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name>s, <name type="native_nation" key="Hidatsa Indians">Hidatsa</name>s, and <name type="native_nation" key="Arikara Indians">Arikaras</name>
               </hi> (Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1977).</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.alwin.0108" n="8">HBC Archives, B. 22/1/3, <hi rend="italic">passim</hi>, <name type="person" key="Brandon House">Brandon House</name> Post Journal 1795–96.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.alwin.0109" n="9">HBC Archives, B. 3/d/106, Albany Fort Account Book, 1795–96.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.alwin.0110" n="10">HBC Archives, B. 22/a/8, fos. 6d and 12d, <name type="person" key="Brandon House">Brandon House</name> Post Journal, 1800–01.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.alwin.0111" n="11">HBC Archives, B. 22/a/10, <hi rend="italic">passim</hi>, <name type="person" key="Brandon House">Brandon House</name> Post Journal, 1802–03.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.alwin.0112" n="12">HBC Archives, B. 3/d/110 and 112, Albany Fort Account Book, 1799 to 1800.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.alwin.0113" n="13">HBC Archives, B. 22/a/7, fo. 26, Brandon House Post Journal, 1799–1800.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.alwin.0114" n="14">At <name type="person" key="Brandon House">Brandon House</name>
               <name type="person" key="Sutherland, James"> James Sutherland</name> copied the letter in the post Journal, HBC Archives, B. 22/a/4, fo. 16–16d, <name type="person" key="Brandon House">Brandon House</name> Post Journal, 1796–97. Extracts from this journal, including the letter, appear in <name type="person" key="Nasatir, A. P.">Nasatir</name>, <hi rend="italic">Before <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>
               </hi> II: 461–464.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.alwin.0115" n="15">For the story of <name type="person" key="Evans, John">John Evans</name> and this expedition see <name type="person" key="Nasatir, A. P.">A. P. Nasatir</name>, ed., "<name type="person" key="Evans, John">John Evans</name>, Explorer and Surveyor," <hi rend="italic">Missouri Historical Review</hi> XXV (October 1930–July 1931): 219–239, 432–460, 585–608.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.alwin.0116" n="16">HBC Archives, B. 22/a/4, fo. 31, <name type="person" key="Brandon House">Brandon House</name> Post Journal, 1796–97.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.alwin.0117" n="17">Ibid., f. 35d.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.alwin.0118" n="18">HBC Archives, B. 22/a/5, fo. 20d, <name type="person" key="Brandon House">Brandon House</name> Post Journal, 1797–98.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.alwin.0119" n="19">For <name type="person" key="Thompson, David">Thompson</name>'s account of his <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> journey see <name type="person" key="Glover, Richard">Richard Glover</name>, ed., <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="person" key="Thompson, David">David Thompson</name>'s Narrative: 1784–1812</hi> (Toronto: The Champlain Society, 1962), 160–181.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.alwin.0120" n="20">For an interesting and unique account of the events and perceptions leading up to the expedition see <name type="person" key="Allen, John Logan">John Logan Allen</name>, <hi rend="italic">Passage Through the Garden: <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> and the Images of the American Northwest</hi> (Urbana: University of Illinois Press, 1975), 1–126.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.alwin.0121" n="21">A copy of this letter can be found in <name type="person" key="Coues, Elliott">Elliott Coues</name>, ed., <hi rend="italic">History of the Expedition under Command of <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>
               </hi> (4 vols., New York: Francis P. Harper, 1893), I, 187n–188n.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.alwin.0122" n="22">HBC Archives, B. 22/a/12, fo. 7d, <name type="person" key="Brandon House">Brandon House</name> Post Journal, 1804–05.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.alwin.0123" n="23">
               <name type="person" key="Thwaites, Reuben Gold">Reuben Gold Thwaites</name>, ed., <hi rend="italic">Original Journals of the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition, 1804–1806</hi> (8 vols., New York: Dodd, Mead, and Company, 1904–05), I, 218.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.alwin.0124" n="24">
               <hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>., I, p. 238. The dominant role of the NWC in the <name type="native_nation" key="Mandan Indians">Mandan</name> trade is obvious from a passage in the <name type="person" key="Brandon House">Brandon House</name> Post Journal for this season. On February 27, 1805, Post Master <name type="person" key="MacKay, John">MacKay</name> referred to the discrepancy in numbers between his 3 men involved in the trade that season and the NWC's 3 clerks and 15 "foremost Hands" at the villages. Whereas the HBC traders had only collected 200-odd MB by late February, the NWC men already had 900 MB. HBC Archives, B. 22/a/12, fo. 9d, <name type="person" key="Brandon House">Brandon House</name> Journal, 1804–05.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.alwin.0125" n="25">HBC Archives, B. 22/a/12, fo. 8d, <name type="person" key="Brandon House">Brandon House</name> Post journal, 1804–05. For a study of previously published reactions of natives to the <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name> Expedition see <name type="person" key="Ewers, John C.">John C. Ewers</name>, "Plains Indian Reactions to <name type="person" key="Lewis, Meriwether">Lewis</name> and <name type="person" key="Clark, William">Clark</name>." <hi rend="italic">Montana, The Magazine of Western History</hi> XVI (Winter 1966): 2–12.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.alwin.0126" n="26">HBC Archives, B. 22/a/12, fo. 11d, <name type="person" key="Brandon House">Brandon House</name> Post Journal, 1804–05.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.alwin.0127" n="27">
               <name type="person" key="Thwaites, Reuben Gold">Thwaites</name>, <hi rend="italic">Original Journals</hi> I: 248.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.alwin.0128" n="28">
               <name type="person" key="Coues, Elliott">Coues</name>, <hi rend="italic">History of the Expedition</hi> I: 225.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.alwin.0129" n="29">
               <name type="person" key="Thwaites, Reuben Gold">Thwaites</name>, <hi rend="italic">Original Journals</hi> I:  271.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.alwin.0130" n="30">
               <name type="person" key="Chuinard, E. G.">E. G. Chuinard</name>, "The Actual Role of The Bird Woman," <hi rend="italic">Montana, The Magazine of Western History</hi> XXVI (Summer 1976): 25.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.alwin.0131" n="31">
               <name type="person" key="Coues, Elliott">Coues</name>, <hi rend="italic">History of the Expedition</hi> I: 246–247.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.alwin.0132" n="32">This expedition was briefly considered in <name type="person" key="Murray, Robert A.">Robert A. Murray</name>, "First Tracks in the Big Horns", <hi rend="italic">Montana, The Magazine of Western History</hi> XXVI (Winter 1976): 7–11.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.alwin.0133" n="33">
               <name type="person" key="MacKenzie, Charles">Charles MacKenzie</name>, "The Missouri Indians, 1804–05" in <hi rend="italic">Les Bourgeois De La Compagnie Du Nord-Ouest</hi>, ed. by <name type="person" key="Masson, L. R.">L. R. Masson</name> (2 vols., Quebec, 1889–1890) I: 341.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.alwin.0134" n="34">HBC Archives, B. 22/a/14, fo. 8d, <name type="person" key="Brandon House">Brandon House</name> Post Journal. 1806–07.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.alwin.0135" n="35">
               <hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>., fos. 14d–15.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.alwin.0136" n="36">
               <name type="person" key="MacKenzie, Charles">MacKenzie</name>, "The Missouri Indians, 1804–05," I: 329.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.alwin.0137" n="37">HBC Archives, B. 22/a/9, fo. 13, <name type="person" key="Brandon House">Brandon House</name> Post journal, 1801–02.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.alwin.0138" n="38">HBC Archives, B. 22/a/17, fo. 8d, <name type="person" key="Brandon House">Brandon House</name> Post journal, 1809–10.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.alwin.0139" n="39">For information on <name type="person" key="Lisa, Manuel">Manuel Lisa</name> and The Missouri Fur Company see <name type="person" key="Oglesby, Richard Edward">Richard Edward Oglesby</name>, <hi rend="italic">
                  <name type="person" key="Lisa, Manuel">Manuel Lisa</name> and The Opening of the Missouri Fur Trade</hi> (Norman: University of Oklahoma Press, 1983).</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.alwin.0140" n="40">HBC Archives. B. 22/a/17, fo. 12d, <name type="person" key="Brandon House">Brandon House</name> Post Journal 1809–10.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.alwin.0141" n="41">
               <hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.alwin.0142" n="42">HBC Archives, B. 22/a/18b, fo. 7, <name type="person" key="Brandon House">Brandon House</name> Post Journal' 1811–12.</note>
            <note xml:id="nlc.alwin.0143" n="43">
               <hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>., fo. 7d–8.</note>
            <p>
               <name type="person" key="Alwin, John A.">
                  <ref target="https://www.cwu.edu/~geograph/alwin.html">John A. Alwin</ref>
               </name>, professor of Earth Sciences at <name type="place" key="Montana State University">Montana State University</name>, is a specialist in historical geography, especially the geography of the Great Plains. A native of Michigan, Dr. Alwin received an M.A. from University of Montana before going on to receive his Ph.D. from University of Manitoba in Winnipeg. He is the author of several articles on Hudson Bay Company history, early day river transportation in Canada, and the geography of town development in Montana.</p>
            <p> This article has been reproduced with the permission of <ref target="https://www.cwu.edu/~geograph/alwin.html">John A. Alwin</ref>, Prof. of Geography, Dept. of Geography, Central Washington University.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
